<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cloud-hands on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/cloud-hands/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in cloud-hands on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/cloud-hands/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Cloud Hands Fall Workshop</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 17:31:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</guid>
      <description>We are in the process of finalizing the details of a Tai Chi Cloud Hands workshop with Robert Tangora this fall in Boston, from October 26-28.
As preparation for the workshop, I will be teaching a fall course at Brookline Tai Chi, covering the basic mechanics of Cloud Hands, as well as the prep exercises from Robert&#39;s newly published book.
I&#39;m really looking forward to taking everyone at Brookline Tai Chi through these exercises and at the same time, working with members of the Inner Form coaching program to improve their Cloud Hands practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exercises from The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/09/exercises-from-the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 07:03:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/09/exercises-from-the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands/</guid>
      <description>One of the toughest parts of learning movement exercises from a book is knowing what goes in between each still photo.
That&#39;s why I&#39;m very excited that Robert Tangora has put out an overview video of all the exercises that he teaches in the Internal Structure of Cloud Hands.


You can use this video as a companion guide to the book.
I think this book is such an excellent resource, that I&#39;m urging every serious Tai Chi and qigong practitioner that I know to find a way to work it into theirs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands by Robert Tangora</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 07:00:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/</guid>
      <description>Robert Tangora&#39;s new book, The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands, has just been published.
Last October, I spoke to Robert about why he chose this topic for a Tai Chi book and what he hoped to communicate to people.
Based on that interview, working with him live doing his Cloud Hands training, and the meticulous way he approaches learning, teaching, and Tai Chi, I have no doubt that this book is going to the top of my recommended reading list next to Energy Gates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Hands for Rhythm and Flow</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/04/02/cloud-hands-for-rhythm-and-flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 08:58:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/04/02/cloud-hands-for-rhythm-and-flow/</guid>
      <description>Cloud Hands is one of the best containers for developing better rhythm and flow in your practice, but you&#39;ve got to work on rhythm and flow separately. The reason is that you develop two very different qualities of mind when you work on these two seemingly related skills.
Better Rhythm
Better rhythm comes from &#34;harmonizing&#34; more and more moving parts over time in your practice. At first, we all face the challenge of not being able to feel into the body well.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>