<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cloud-hands on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/cloud-hands/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in cloud-hands on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/cloud-hands/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Cloud Hands Fall Workshop</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 17:31:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4081&#34; title=&#34;Robert Tangora Tai Chi Cloud Hands&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/07/DSC_0067-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are in the process of finalizing the details of a Tai Chi Cloud Hands workshop with Robert Tangora this fall in Boston, from October 26-28.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As preparation for the workshop, I will be teaching a fall course at Brookline Tai Chi, covering the basic mechanics of Cloud Hands, as well as the prep exercises from Robert&#39;s newly published book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m really looking forward to taking everyone at Brookline Tai Chi through these exercises and at the same time, working with members of the Inner Form coaching program to improve their Cloud Hands practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4080&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, I just shared a 25-minute follow-along practice mp3 with the Inner Form members, guiding them through a set of Cloud Hands prep exercises. This is the same kind of coaching I give people in live classes each week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more it amazes me just how many different ways we are able to refine and improve qigong and Tai Chi practice. Of course, people have been teaching themselves the basics from books for years, but I think we&#39;ve entered age where getting feedback and guidance remotely is getting much more sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, there are elements of the practice that will only be transmitted in person, but think of how much more we are able to share this way, through video, audio, email, and written discussion -- across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It amazes me that people continue to find this site, reach out, and connect with each other about something so personal, so individual, and so fundamental to their sense of well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And I&#39;m grateful that I get to share in that with all of you!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, ok, so back to the workshop announcement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&#39;re in Boston and you want to prep for Tai Chi Cloud Hands with Robert Tangora in October, be sure you&#39;re on &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/contact-us/chi-mail&#34;&gt;the Brookline Tai Chi mailing list&lt;/a&gt; when we announce the new course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you plan to come to Boston for the workshop, you should probably join &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/contact-us/chi-mail&#34;&gt;the BTC email list too&lt;/a&gt;, so you&#39;ll get all the details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&#39;re already a member of the Inner Form section of this site, be sure to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/forum/cloud-hands-challenge/prep-exercises-mp3/&#34;&gt;download your practice mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a Tai Chi practice (budding or established) and you&#39;re looking for other dedicated practitioners who will share ideas with you, give you feedback and motivate you to keep up your practice, you should join us in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/&#34;&gt;the Inner Form section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exercises from The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/09/exercises-from-the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 07:03:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/09/exercises-from-the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the toughest parts of learning movement exercises from a book is knowing what goes in between each still photo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s why I&#39;m very excited that Robert Tangora has put out an overview video of all the exercises that he teaches in the &lt;a title=&#34;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands by Robert Tangora&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/&#34;&gt;Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4030&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/rbxbLQIjpYI?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use this video as a companion guide to the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this book is such an excellent resource, that I&#39;m urging every serious Tai Chi and qigong practitioner that I know to find a way to work it into theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the months of July, August, and September, I&#39;m dedicating a portion of my daily practice time to the material in Robert&#39;s book. I&#39;m calling it the 90-Day Cloud Hands Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why I&#39;m Excited about The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve studied with Robert for several years, mainly when he comes to Boston to teach seminars, and we&#39;ve worked on several different pieces of his system -- this book ties them all together. I wish I had had this from the beginning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is also a road map for infusing your Tai Chi practice will all of the main principles found in the complete Energy Arts curriculum &lt;strong&gt;(see below, I want to share my notes on this with you)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He&#39;s collected simple (but profound, and not necessarily easy) exercises that lay out all the building blocks for your Cloud Hands practice and described them in the book. And now we have the video reference to go with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re looking for a way to boost your personal practice, no matter where you&#39;re coming from with it, setting a 90-day goal of honing one skill, or repeatedly delving into one set of exercises can be a great way to do it. 90 days is enough time to really immerse yourself, but also short enough so it doesn&#39;t feel endless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book and video just coming out is the perfect trigger to set you off on a 90-day challenge of your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Personal Practice Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Since I&#39;m in the process of weaving the Cloud Hands material together with my normal Energy Arts practice, I started mapping out the links I was seeing between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just rough outlines I&#39;ve put together. Think &#34;work in progress&#34;, &#34;musings&#34;, or &#34;scratchpad.&#34; I&#39;m not claiming anything definitive!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, if you&#39;d like to check them out, drop your email in the form below and I&#39;ll send you my notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&#34;width: 100%;&#34; src=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/embed/m7p7s5/&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;261&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands by Robert Tangora</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 07:00:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3991&#34; title=&#34;Robert Tangora Cloud Hands&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/06/DSC_0074-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands by Robert Tangora&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi Instructor Robert Tangora&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; new book, &lt;strong&gt;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/strong&gt;, has just been published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last October, &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;I spoke to Robert about why he chose this topic for a Tai Chi book&lt;/a&gt; and what he hoped to communicate to people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on that interview, working with him live doing his Cloud Hands training, and the meticulous way he approaches learning, teaching, and Tai Chi, I have no doubt that this book is going to the top of my recommended reading list next to &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;Energy Gates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3990&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://tangora-cloud-hands.kickofflabs.com/?kid=BXEF&#34;&gt;Robert is offering up a free sample chapter from the book as a preview.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&#39;ve downloaded the chapter, he&#39;ll send you a link to the book on Amazon and while you&#39;re waiting for it in the mail, do what I did: &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora Tai Chi Cloud Hands Interview&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi-cloud-hands-interview/&#34;&gt;re-watch the whole interview I did with him.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inner Form members:&lt;/strong&gt; this is going to be a juicy topic for us to discuss more. While you&#39;re waiting for the &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;, the material in this book could easily fill all your free hours with rich, rewarding practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Hands for Rhythm and Flow</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/02/cloud-hands-for-rhythm-and-flow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 08:58:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/02/cloud-hands-for-rhythm-and-flow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-2361&#34; title=&#34;Cloud Hands&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/11/Cloud-Hands-205x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Gates Qigong Cloud Hands&#34; width=&#34;205&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud Hands is one of the best containers for developing better rhythm and flow in your practice, but you&#39;ve got to work on rhythm and flow separately. The reason is that you develop two very different qualities of mind when you work on these two seemingly related skills.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3742&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Better Rhythm&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Better rhythm comes from &#34;harmonizing&#34; more and more moving parts over time in your practice. At first, we all face the challenge of not being able to feel into the body well. When you can&#39;t feel, you can&#39;t actually move different parts under conscious control (which is why I always recommend isolation work, &lt;a title=&#34;Recommended Products&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/products/&#34;&gt;like Z Health mobility drills&lt;/a&gt;). The more you can feel, the more connections you can make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, training rhythm isn&#39;t just about having more and more connections, though. It&#39;s about bringing them together in a coordinated way that doesn&#39;t take a lot of thought, or &#34;harmonizing&#34; all your moving parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More Flow&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Flow in qigong, tai chi, and ba gua is having a clear sense of what&#39;s moving through the body, not just how the body itself moves. At first, you need to build the physical container, then you begin to sense other, related movement, mainly fluids in this case, and then more subtle energy flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, as the body feels saturated by fluids, the nerves feel flushed with chi, and the tissues feel permeable and heavy, you pay attention to the wave-like sensations going on inside the body, more than the external, mechanical movements of the arms and legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud Hands is one of the best places to play with this balance of internal movement versus stable external shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a title=&#34;Practice Bonus&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/practice-bonus/&#34;&gt;April Practice Bonus&lt;/a&gt;, we go through the details of exactly how this is done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>