<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>practice-people on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/categories/practice-people/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in practice-people on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/categories/practice-people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Your Answers to &#34;What Does It Feel Like to Meditate?&#34;</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/06/07/your-answers-to-what-does-it-feel-like-to-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2013 08:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/06/07/your-answers-to-what-does-it-feel-like-to-meditate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to thank everyone who took the time to answer &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/&#34;&gt;this poll about meditation practice&lt;/a&gt;. You shared some really nice insights into what you experience and why you practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I want to share some of the common themes and the particular language people used to express what happens in a typical meditation practice session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Body-Centered Meditation Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first big theme was how physically oriented many people are in their practice. Here&#39;s one description that captured the body-centered practice well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first process is of physically settling in, sitting or standing . After a few minutes, mental calm will follow, then more or less in order physical releasing and smoothing out, then emotional smoothing, lastly nervous smoothing.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And other description of the process, again anchored by a connection to the physical body:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The way it goes is more or less always the same: it begins easily, then when I start to really get into some spot that needs attention, things can become quite painful, or unnerving. Then there&#39;s often the part when things seem to take hours to resolve, and I have to stick to it and really discipline myself not to let my attention jump around. Then I get some sort of release, and it starts feeling good. By the end of the session, once the body has been completely scanned and I&#39;ve gone through the moving parts of the set, my body feels all light and fluid.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overall, there seemed to be an assumption that body-centered practice was not the same as &#34;higher-level&#34; esoteric practice. At the same time, many people recognized the immediacy of addressing the physical body in their practice. At the top of the list for many people was a clear benefit for the body:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I almost always get is physical relaxation and a better sleep.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the past, we&#39;ve explored &lt;a title=&#34;Common Sensations That Arise When You Are Developing Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/&#34;&gt;the energetic continuum from the physical body out to more subtle frequencies&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps the way that this continuum is organized gives us some clues. You can&#39;t address the more ethereal aspects of your self and your relationships to other people without being grounded in a healthy physical body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Meditation for Being in the World&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, some of the descriptions of meditation practice blended the physical and relational dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unwinding the work day is like softening a tight muscle.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Or having a clear dual purpose:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think the feeling I start with is one of looking for a practical way to recharge and be able to bring it into my daily life. When the session is over I usually feel mentally flexible and physically accepting of my bodily discomfort.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And even when the goal is more along the lines of emotional or mental, like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began to practice because I wanted to be a calmer person,&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
there is still a sense of bringing the body back into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Striving for Perfect Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, many people also wrestled with how well their practice was going. Perhaps the clearest articulation of the dilemma of progress in meditation was expressed here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This almost seems like a trick question because I believe that the mediation sessions that are the most frustrating, annoying, painful, etc, are the better sessions for me. If I have what I think is a &#34;good&#34; session, that&#39;s usually a dead end. I&#39;m happy with myself and that&#39;s it for the day. If I have a &#34;bad&#34; session, that seems to be more helpful in moving me in the direction of greater consciousness, mentally, physically and emotionally. Putting that aside, the result my ego likes most and considers a good session, is a reduction in tension. My body becomes more relaxed and as a result I can feel more. My thought becomes more relaxed and the repetitive chatter slows down and stops for longer periods of time. As a result I can think much clearer and work much better. Emotionally, I don&#39;t react to negativity around me as quickly and can avoid getting caught up in it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And sometimes, you go through a process of working on one dimension or another of your practice, and get to a place where the practice is just an essential, but everyday part of your life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34; id=&#34;docs-internal-guid-36aad5fa-1eae-6247-cab7-7512c26258cf&#34;&gt;Originally I started meditating when becoming aware of the racing thoughts in my mind and wanting to eliminate them. Of course, it did not take too long to realize there is no eliminating those thoughts as they arise but that the real benefit was to become the observer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Over time and the practice of different Qigong, the experience deepened and now becomes a way to realize a type of wholeness or unity or synergy with everything, that transcends the focus on what to get done today, body awareness of hunger/pain/etc, and the other things we associate with being human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, now the emotional attachments to what I considered a &#34;good meditation&#34; have left as well. Where before I might have considered having a meditation where I transcended the universe of matter and anti-matter and found the crack between realities some kind of big deal, I now can just accept that it happened (or didn&#39;t) without any judgement, joy, elation, etc.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Do these experiences line up for you? What did I miss in trying to capture the language around meditation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/07/the-transformational-power-of-tai-chi-body-mechanics/&#34;&gt;Wu Jianquan&#39;s advice on practicing Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt; also applies to much of the meditation practice that people reported on here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. CHARACTER TRANSFORMATION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When emptiness becomes a habit, it causes you to have a milder temperament and can eliminate arrogant behaviors. When calmness becomes a habit, it causes you to have a clearer mental state, increasing your ability to deal with problems. When naturalness becomes a habit and your body has a smooth coordination, it causes you to have a more robust build, which gives you a more leisurely attitude. When softness becomes a habit, it causes you to have a friendlier disposition, giving you more confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. INCREASED INSPIRATION&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because every part of the Taiji boxing art contains scientific principles [This seems an airy claim since there is no specific scientific analysis in this book, but becomes more reasonable when taken in the context of the larger body of Taiji literature: for example, Xu Zhiyi&#39;s 1927 book contains three chapters exploring Taiji&#39;s relation to psychology, physiology, and physics.], and also due to its alternations of emptiness and fullness, it is a method that is inexhaustible. When practicing the solo set, the whole body feels comfortable, and when practicing the pushing hands, the whole body feels enlivened. Therefore after practicing for a while, not only will one not feel tired, but one&#39;s spirit will also feel awakened, a clear demonstration of one&#39;s sense of interest being boosted. However, for beginners, because they have not yet become familiar with the map that will lead them to their destinations, they easily begin to get bored, and they must be patient for a period, after which they naturally will gradually come to find the more scenic vistas of sensation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Yin and Yang of Learning and Teaching the Internal Arts</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/07/the-yin-and-yang-of-learning-and-teaching-the-internal-arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2012 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/07/the-yin-and-yang-of-learning-and-teaching-the-internal-arts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a guest post from my friend and fellow instructor, Paul Cavel. I asked Paul to talk a little bit about his experience teaching all over Europe and what he&#39;s learned after nearly 20 years doing it. There are some great insights here about the internal energy arts that you can apply to your own practice, whether you teach or not. Take note when he talks about practice mindset!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3549&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1537&#34; title=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been traveling around Europe teaching internal arts in England, France, Germany and Greece since 1995, as well as training with my teacher almost every year in the United States since 1994. Through these experiences, I&#39;ve had the opportunity to meet people of many different backgrounds and observe how cultural influences can give them unique perspectives on most any subject, including their neigong training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, more than any cultural differences, I see that the real challenges come from the Western mindset being so radically different to the Eastern approach. I know for me, as a Westerner learning ancient Eastern arts, the initial hurdle was to figure out the methodology underlying the great content I was training, so I could see the bigger picture--the proverbial light at the end of the tunnel. There are 16 neigong, each with many, many layers of complexity, and dozens of forms to learn in any one system, so understanding how each can be integrated into the whole within the linear Western model for learning can be a bit tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students who achieve real and sustainable results from their practice are those who approach their training with patience, dedication and consistency. Perhaps most importantly, they have the willingness to work towards balance in all aspects of their being, rooting out weaknesses rather than only playing to their strengths--tenants consistent with an Eastern learning strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;East Meets West&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some people approach their practice as though they have &#34;been there, done that,&#34; but from an Eastern perspective, that would be completely missing the point. Instead, it&#39;s about the depth and range of your skill set and how you can apply it in every conceivable way--not just in your practice, but in life. The students who catch onto this style will, over time, automatically weave in mechanics that create flowing forms and circulate blood and chi more profoundly. These are the factors that influence health and well-being, and give the most experienced practitioners the ability to achieve seemingly superhuman results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find a tai chi class in almost every major city across the Western world, but few schools teach the deep internal content that underlies and powers up these forms as originally propagated in the East. Many schools have resorted to a linear teaching style to suit the average Westerner, but the Eastern approach has always been a circular progression: that is you learn a technique and practise it for awhile, developing your skill to the extent you can over several weeks to months. When you reach a plateau and your practice seems to stop evolving, you move on to other techniques, integrating everything you&#39;ve learned within your forms (qigong sets, tai chi styles or bagua palm changes). Later, you return to the original technique, once again singling out that thread and further refining it. Although, upon revisiting the technique, your increased awareness--in body, mind and chi--contributes to an upgrade in your overall understanding and execution of the technique. This circular learning process creates a multiplying, self-sustaining positive feedback loop in your practice and the results you can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Structure-Flow Continuum&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Most students approach their practice from one of two ends of the spectrum: either from the perspective of flow or structure. That is there are those who gravitate towards the integrity of the movement form (i.e. successful execution of component pieces that combine to create a physical form) and others who focus on the flow, or the overall quality of motion within any given form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the point of view of teaching the internal arts, it is helpful to know where a student&#39;s talent lies--either in flow or structure. Initially, using their natural ability, you can focus on that stream of information to help them gain some momentum. Once they gain some skill in that which comes easier for them, then a good teacher will use this momentum to redress the balance by focusing on exercises that will develop the opposite end of the continuum. This approach allows students to see the bigger picture with their talent being the driver of their success. As anyone who trains with an emphasis on internal power development knows, it is the balance between form and flow that is at the crux of all matters relating to how much benefit any one person will get from their practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life as a Traveling Teacher&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Teaching in different cultures for nearly two decades tuned me into the fact that, as a teacher, I cannot be attached to one style or method of presenting material as each culture, city, class, group or individual will have a slightly unique disposition. Although any given culture might be predisposed to start from a particular perspective, the magic of the internal arts is in the details and how they seamlessly integrate with all others. So there really is no starting line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circular progression of learning is about building up and breaking down component pieces in endless weaves and patterns, essentially looking at every possible angle to create a well-integrated, balanced form. This kind of assimilation is what allows students to overcome obstacles and achieve their goals, regardless of where they begin. From the perspective of teaching, I&#39;ve not found anything more rewarding than helping students come to this realization and take on a long-term outlook towards their training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1529&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/strong&gt; is a certified sports massage therapist, personal trainer and senior instructor of internal arts and Taoist meditation master Bruce Frantzis. Since 1987, Paul has studied the Energy Arts System in-depth, including qigong, tai chi, bagua zhang, Longevity Breathing therapy, qigong tui na energy healing and meditation. In 1995, with the encouragement of his teacher, he began offering an integrated health, fitness and stress-management solution to exercise and strengthen the body while releasing blockages -- in mind-body-energy -- that help people realize their true human potential. Find Paul blogging at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/&#34;&gt;www.CircleWalking.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Dr. Mark Cheng is Bringing Tai Chi to the Fitness Community, Part 2</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/25/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2012 08:11:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/25/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a title=&#34;How Dr. Mark Cheng is Bringing Tai Chi to the Fitness Community, Part 1&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/18/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-1/&#34;&gt;part 1 of this interview&lt;/a&gt;, we talked to Dr. Mark Cheng about how his background as an acupuncturist, martial artist, strength coach and PhD in Chinese Medicine has shaped his point of view about the broader subject of fitness and wellness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now he&#39;s going to explain his thinking behind developing a project, called Tai Cheng, which aims to introduce Tai Chi to a much larger fitness audience.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3225&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is Dr. Cheng&#39;s introduction to Tai Cheng:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/tCPrrsyP1-0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/tCPrrsyP1-0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Cheng aims to synthesize his various perspectives and present Tai Chi in an accessible way to an American audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally the CEO of Beachbody had the idea to call the program Tai Cheng, as in Cheng of my last name &amp;eacute;&amp;bdquo;&amp;shy;. That didn&#39;t make sense to me, so I kept the spelling but changed the character &amp;amp; the concept. So, if you look at the pinyin C-H-E-N-G, and if you look at the logo, and if you understand Chinese, you&#39;ll be able to understand that the &amp;aelig;&amp;circ;character actually means &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;achievement&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; &amp;aelig;&amp;circ;&amp;aring;&amp;Scaron;&amp;Yuml; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;evolution&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;change&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; &amp;egrave;&amp;reg;&amp;Scaron;&amp;aelig;&amp;circ;. You know how Tai Chi &amp;aring;&amp;curren;&amp;ordf;&amp;aelig;&amp;yen;&amp;micro; literally means &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;supreme ultimate?&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Tai Cheng means &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the supreme change&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the supreme evolution.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not reinventing the wheel, as much as going back to what Tai Chi was supposed to be originally. From what one of my teachers said, Tai Chi at its inception was taught so that you understand that all the basics, all the fundamentals of movement, all of the baseline of skill that we&#39;re supposed to be laying is actually the secret to high performance. If you want to perform well, if you want to build skill, but you don&#39;t have that solid foundation, in Chinese, they say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;lian wu bu lian gong, dao lao yi chang kong&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; which means, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;if you train martial arts, but you don&#39;t establish a foundation of functional movement, as you get older you&#39;re left with nothing.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi is like a really well-cut diamond. I mean, to look at it from only one perspective, you&#39;re really robbing yourself of the richness of the experience. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m not saying that you have to fight or that you have to be into combative martial arts or that you have to be into some esoteric meditation or anything like that. If you don&#39;t come into Tai Chi with health issues you may not appreciate the restoratives that you&#39;re getting, and in that case instead of rehab, it&#39;s prehab. If you&#39;re coming to Tai Chi and you just enjoy this as a rejuvenative exercise, you may never care about the self-defense aspect of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what Tai Chi can be. It can improve how your body functions. It can re-center your spine. It can improve your posture. It can dramatically lower your stress levels by virtue of teaching you how to control probably the most necessary vital process and probably the only vital process that you can control volitionally, your breathing. It can heighten your awareness of tension in your own body. It can point out to you how your body reacts to stressors both physical as well as mental. Those things are very important for anyone wanting to get the most out of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lives are full of factors and stressors that can compromise optimum functionality. So I made sure that Tai Cheng began with a &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;neural reboot&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. Because neurologically or neuromuscularly, there&#39;s so many people who have neuromuscular systems that have gone afoul from hours and hours of sitting in spinal flexion or from funny exercise patterns or what have you. Let&#39;s take that whole system and reboot it and say, &#34;instead of trying to debug every little thing, let&#39;s just reboot the whole system and then give you a fresh start in movement.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the thing is that most Tai Chi products are taught out there in a monkey-see-monkey-do fashion. Emulate these movements. There&#39;s not a whole lot of explanation why and if you teach Tai Chi using the language of, &#34;Stroke Peacock&#39;s Tail&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;White Crane Cools Wings&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or whatever, the average American is going to look at that with a certain degree of cynicism and go, &#34;Yeah, okay, do you want me to get crystals and incense too?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Tai Cheng, I wanted to be able to show people that this ancient training method holds a lot of relevance to their modern lives. You just need to be able to see it in a way that makes sense in terms of sports medicine, in terms of self defense, in terms of restoring the body, in terms of preparing you for high impact, interval training. And that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s my forte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I talk about in Tai Cheng is how you would be taught Tai Chi in its most traditional fashion. When you first roll in to find an old school Tai Chi master, the last thing that he has you do is the form. He or she I should say. The most essential part of Tai Chi training, as I&#39;ve been taught, are the ji ben gong or the basic training exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re taught from the most traditional standpoint of the basics, of the ji ben gong, what are you doing essentially? You&#39;re doing exactly what we&#39;re taught to do in terms of sports medicine, in terms of functional movement by people like Gray Cook, who say that you need to lay a huge platform of fundamental movement, a baseline of mobility and stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s the essence of what Tai Chi should be. What a lot of people are confusing for Tai Chi these days is just like, &#34;Okay, come follow me as I do this pre-choreographed form. This sequence of movements is all of Tai Chi.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; That&#39;s not Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, Tai Chi is a principle. As long as you understand the fundamentals of movement, you optimize your body for movement. And then, you understand ways of training those principles. Anything that you put in the machine comes out as Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Cheng project is designed to get these core concepts about what Tai Chi is, out to the widest possible audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted something that would not just be for the octogenarian, not just be for the young kid, not just be for the martial art insider, and not just for injury rehab people. I wanted something that no matter who you are, you&#39;ll be able to look at this and go like, &#34;Oh geez! This stuff is valuable to me!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the way in which I taught it, I think, is probably is going to be challenging for some people. Instead of trying to dump tons of movements and sequences on them at a time, which is how many are conditioned to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;learning&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;, I actually dial them back a lot. I wanted people to see that I&#39;m having them focus on the prerequisites movement rather than on advanced skillsets first. A lot of people think they&#39;ll buy an instructional DVD or DVD series because they want to just learn like a form or something cool and learn a lot at once. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m dialing people back, and saying, &#34;Look, you got tons of movements already. Let&#39;s see how solid your platform of movement is.&#34; So, that really was the big revolution in thinking that I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m hoping catches on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the points that I tried to convey to the CEO of Beachbody (the company that produces Tai Cheng) was that, let&#39;s say you got someone doing P90X, something pretty vigorous like that and they&#39;re doing maybe like a cardio kickboxing classes or Turbo Kick or what have you, or someone that&#39;s an MMA competitor. If your body&#39;s only used to exercising one way all the time, your muscular system adapts to that. So, it stops experiencing maximum benefit after a certain point. If all your workouts are pretty intense in terms of like high speed, high load, high intensity, you will burn yourself out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like the soil, if you farm only one crop on a plot of land all year round, you will strip that soil dead. It won&#39;t be able to support any another crops. With the field, when you rotate crops intelligently, you ensure the longevity of the soil. With your body, if you rotate different workouts schemes or if rotate different ways of training, you ensure the longevity of your body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in the first test group, we had one guy that was scheduled for a bilateral knee replacement, total knee replacement surgery. We had one woman who was drop-dead gorgeous, in rockstar shape who had been doing a lot of working out. We really had the whole gamut, and everybody reported improvement. We had one guy who was morbidly obese, and just walking from one side to the other side of the room, he would pant and start sweating. That guy that came in morbidly obese just ran his first marathon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gentleman who was scheduled for bilateral knee replacement, I think less than or maybe about half-way through the program pulled me aside to show me that he could climb up and down a flight of steps without limping along painfully step-by-step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, the woman who is in rockstar shape yet couldn&#39;t even do one proper pushup started cranking out strict pushups with higher &amp;amp; higher reps. The thing is regardless of what you come to the table with, Tai Cheng will make you perform better.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There is a valuable lesson here for all movement instructors. If you get a roomful of people with a huge range of abilities and you&#39;re going to get them started doing some Tai Chi practice, how do you frame it? How do you set the expectation for what people are going to experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I guess part of it comes back to being a medical professional. My bottom line is do no harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So more than anything else, I want people to be able to push the envelope but not tear it. So I want them to push the envelope with their movement. I want them to push the envelope of their capacity. I want them to push the envelope of their ability and both their mobility and their stability, but I also want them to do so in a way that they will feel worked but still have more energy in the tank if they need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t want anyone to ever feel like, &#34;I&#39;m so thrashed that all I can do is just lie here in a quivering heap.&#34; And conversely, I don&#39;t want anyone to feel like, &#34;I&#39;m bored out of my ass. I need to go do something mindless and fast and hyper.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&#39;ve got people that are expecting high volumes of movement and high intensity, the key is to instruct them and say, &#34;Look, I understand your expectations and your habits, but what I&#39;m trying to teach you to do is to pay attention to yourselves, to your body, to your movements, and to your performance in a far more attentive and productive manner. We have a society &amp;amp; a lifestyle that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s mostly based on distraction over concentration. If you look at children these days, their parents never taught them to focus in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have kids that are classified as this, that, and the other, or diagnosed as having different learning disorders or cognitive/developmental disorders. While there are certainly some disorders or diseases that are genuinely medical in their nature, a lot of them are really social in nature. That kid won&#39;t make eye contact? Okay. Well, as a parent, did you consistently reinforce the necessity for eye contact from a very young age or did you just kind of ignore that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a situation like the one I just described, that&#39;s not a medical thing. That&#39;s a social thing. So, to be able to teach people or re-socialize people in a way to say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I&#39;d like you to slow down. I&#39;d like you to concentrate on your breath. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d like you to realize where the little bugs in your motor programming are and learn how to overcome them.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a deeper level of understanding that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s coming in Tai Cheng. I&#39;m not saying you&#39;re not good enough, I&#39;m not saying that your output is not good enough, and I&#39;m not saying that your effort isn&#39;t good enough, but learn to refine. Learn to appreciate. Learn to drop the defensiveness, so you can continually and truly improve, truly move better, truly feel better, and truly train harder, longer, and more safely!&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you can see, the Tai Cheng project is at an interesting crossroads, bringing the traditional values of high performance martial training into a conversation with modern sports science and rehabilitative medicine. At the same time, Dr. Cheng is giving Tai Chi practitioners and other martial artists license to go out and test their training methods and practice principles in new arenas. It&#39;s going to be fun to see how Tai Cheng takes hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more about Dr. Cheng&#39;s work and this upcoming project, visit: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/taichengworkout&#34;&gt;www.facebook.com/taichengworkout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Dr. Mark Cheng is Bringing Tai Chi to the Fitness Community, Part 1</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/18/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2012 09:35:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/18/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/01/DrCheng.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3250&#34; title=&#34;DrCheng&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/01/DrCheng-179x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dr Mark Cheng performing Tai Chi&#34; width=&#34;179&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Dr. Mark Cheng compares learning Tai Chi to studying a well-cut diamond, and as you&#39;ll see in the following conversation, his background as an acupuncturist, martial artist, strength coach and PhD in Chinese Medicine actually allows him to look at the broader subject of fitness and wellness in the same multi-faceted way. With the depth and range he brings to teaching movement, it&#39;s no wonder that he&#39;s leading the way to introducing Tai Chi to a much larger fitness audience and in the process, asking all Tai Chi people to step back and take a fresh look at their art.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3179&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked about his upcoming project, called Tai Cheng, an introduction to Tai Chi and healthy movement coming out in 2012, as well as his journey through movement and martial arts, going all the way back to his first experience with Tai Chi at age 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Cheng&#39;s message is clear and ambitious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My deepest wish for Tai Cheng is that this takes off. Whether using Tai Chi as the vehicle or whether using functional movement as the vehicle, we need to be able to show the world and be able to teach the world to see that effective exercise is not just about sets and reps. It&#39;s not just about how much weight did you move. The focus of Tai Cheng is on the quality of your movement and how you feel at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, a good exercise program considers how you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re going to be in the long run. If you&#39;re training really hard now, you may look great after doing 90 days of high intensity training, but then your body may be so trashed from repetitive motion injury. Because of the pain, there could be so much cortisol going through your body that you&#39;re really fighting a losing battle against weight gain. So obviously situations like this aren&#39;t productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to show people that you&#39;ve got to be able to regulate stress. You&#39;ve got to be able to eat well and eat healthy, but also live healthy and make healthy choices as far as your own exercise. Seeing people make the leap in understanding that takes them just from sets &amp;amp; reps to seeing that quality of movement comes first would thrill me to no end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you read about his initial exposure to Tai Chi and his growing movement education, you&#39;ll see how several different intertwined threads have brought him to this project.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On his early training background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My first love has always been Chinese martial arts. I was fortunate enough to start before adulthood. My first exposure to Chinese martial arts was with my father, who studied Tai Chi with one of Cheng Man Ching&#39;s students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember the first time I saw my father practicing Tai Chi. It looked like the funniest thing to me. When you&#39;re a little kid and you watch someone moving in slow motion like that, you&#39;re just struggling to suppress the snickering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, my father heard me giggling and was like, &#34;Hey, you think this is funny, but this is really martial arts!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that thought sounded even funnier to me. So, then I totally lost it... You can imagine a little kid rolling around on the floor laughing his head off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my father goes, &#34;Okay, you don&#39;t realize that. Well, throw a punch right at me.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I was like, &#34;Oh, really? Okay!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just teed off and with Shou Hui Pipa (Play the Pipa), he launched me and I remember it&#39;s like I didn&#39;t really feel anything. It wasn&#39;t like a hard joint lock, no pain. It&#39;s just that I threw a punch and next thing I knew, I was sailing through the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember thinking, &#34;Wow! This is sweet. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve got to learn this!&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; That was 30 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I came out to California to pursue my undergraduate degree, I was fortunate enough to study martial arts under several outstanding masters, from Prof. Daniel Lee to Shotokan Karate pioneer Tsutomu Ohshima. At a certain point, my interests in Chinese martial arts led right into Chinese medicine. I remember seeing my Shaolin teacher, Hong Li-rong, occasionally seeing patients on evenings that we had training classes. We would bow to start class, and then he&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d turn the class over to one of the senior students for warmup while he would use his manual medicine skills to heal people. And as you know, a lot of the higher-level sifu are also, in addition to their martial skills, very renowned for their medical or healing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing my undergrad degree in East Asian Studies at UCLA, I did a short stint in import-export, realized I wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t doing what made me happy, and then went on to study acupuncture here in California. After graduation &amp;amp; earning board licensure, I apprenticed with one of Dr. Yu Da-Fang&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s disciples to study tui na (Chinese manual medicine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been specializing in Chinese manual medicine since then, which allowed me to meet the legendary Sifu Dan Inosanto, and he in turn introduced me to Pavel Tsatsouline, who is the founder of the RKC Kettlebell method. Pavel introduced me to Gray Cook, the founder of the FMS, or Functional Movement Systems. So Chinese medicine really brought me to three of my most important mentors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gray has been responsible for really revolutionizing my whole view of medicine and of patient care. Working with Gray has really given me a new motivation for going back and reviewing Tai Chi and reviewing traditional Chinese martial arts in general to see what gems are in the training.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you can see, this is a very traditional upbringing in the Chinese martial arts. At the same time, Dr. Cheng has also connected to people in the fitness world who also have a very complete paradigm for understanding movement and understanding the body. Now, he is holding these two paradigms and treating them in their own right, but also seeing differences and seeing crossover points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the ways I talk about it when my patients ask me or when my colleagues ask me, &#34;What&#39;s your direction? What are you all about? Why can&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t you define yourself professionally as one thing or the other?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My explanation is that it really goes back to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;What is Asian-American?&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have the luxury of coming from a culture that&#39;s very old with a lot of traditional, old, and powerful knowledge. But being that we are American, we have the freedom to look at what we have, what we come to the table with, in terms of our own culture, with a critical eye. We can look at the things that we bring to the table, and say that certain things may not stand the test of time in terms of laboratory validation. That freedom allows us to change, to evolve, and to improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we&#39;re also here in the States, we have access to so much information and so much openness, breadth of thought, and discovery. I think it would be a bigger travesty to not take advantage of that freedom to learn from the people that we have surrounding us who are just brilliant minds.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you look at the history of Tai Chi too, of course there were innovators and there was ongoing research. And people would come along and say, &#34;Let&#39;s take it one way or take it the other way.&#34; People err on the side of thinking that tradition is a static thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think one of the biggest mistakes is when you hear from people who say tradition is static. It&#39;s not, because if you look at the term &#34;mixed martial art&#34; you look at systems like Choy Lee Fut. By definition, that&#39;s an amalgam of three systems already. That&#39;s a mixed martial art. So, what&#39;s mixed? What&#39;s not mixed? I mean, these things have been mixed, and synthesized, and rethought, and reworked since time immemorial. It wasn&#39;t until we got dogmatic in saying that, &#34;No, no. It has to be this way.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In Part 2, Dr. Cheng will go into detail about how he chose a focus for his new project and how it aims to bring Tai Chi to a wide audience, especially people who have had little or no exposure to genuine Tai Chi. For more about Dr. Cheng&#39;s work and his upcoming Tai Cheng project, visit: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/taichengworkout&#34;&gt;www.facebook.com/taichengworkout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living between the Lab and the Classroom with Dr. Peter Wayne</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2012 09:50:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-3237&#34; title=&#34;PW Correction&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/01/PW-Correction.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;215&#34; height=&#34;197&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trained in Evolutionary Biology, Peter Wayne, Ph.D., has spent the last 12 years in medical research and more than 35 years studying and teaching Tai Chi. He now serves as Research Director for the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine jointly based at the Harvard Medical School and Brigham and Women&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Hospital, where a primary focus of his research is studying the clinical and physiological impacts of Tai Chi on health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to Peter about the unique opportunities and challenges of being both a Tai Chi teacher and a researcher and how these two different roles inform each other. He is currently working on a book about the same topic. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3233&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little about your book&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book summarizes what the medical research community knows about the clinical health benefits of Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;for example, Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s impact on heart disease, balance, psychological well being, and overall quality of life. But it also tries to go a little further, exploring the biological mechanisms that may underlie why Tai Chi is effective for so many conditions. To do this, I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve organized the book around what I call &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the eight active ingredients of Tai Chi.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; The grouping of these ingredients reflect both what I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve learned is essential in Tai Chi from my many Tai Chi and qigong teachers, and also what I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve learned from our Tai Chi research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The concept of isolating active ingredients is common in other medical research. But does it really make sense to think of Tai Chi within this framework?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great question&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;..and I think absolutely so. Part of why I chose this language is to bend the ear of my medical colleagues&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;to try to communicate in their language. Even if we see positive clinical effects in Tai Chi trials, without plausible mechanisms&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; that is, being able to attribute clinical health effects to specific &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;active ingredients&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;, research results often have little traction in the medical community. Mechanisms are part of what we call the totality of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, by using this language, we&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve been able to emphasize Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s richness&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;that it includes not just one active ingredient&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;but many&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;including those related to neuromuscular control, breathing, cognitive processes, etc. This may explain why it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s helpful for so diverse a set of health issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a teacher, thinking in terms of active ingredients has helped me shape a curriculum that tries to maximize the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;dosage&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; of essential tai chi principles in as short a period of time as is possible. This is key for teaching in clinical trials which are often constrained in length due to funding limitations; but also relevant to community-based classes where we want people to get a real taste of deep Tai Chi as quickly and efficiently as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living in the research world and the Tai Chi world at the same time allows Peter to apply lessons from one to the other. Here he explains how his scientific education influences the way he understands teaching Tai Chi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My formal academic training was in evolutionary biology and ecological modeling, and my research for the first 15 years was with plants. So shifting to medical research 12 years ago was a big change for me. Consequently, I bring a somewhat unique perspective to the teams of medical researchers I work with. My training to think ecologically, in terms of systems, is more like Chinese Medicine in that it focuses on ecological interactions within the body&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;how systems interact to create a complex whole that is greater than the sum of its parts. In contrast, Western medicine has traditionally emphasized reductionist thinking, focusing on smaller and smaller parts, often at the cost of not seeing the whole person. Interestingly, systems biology is being increasingly appreciated in medicine, and Tai Chi research fits beautifully into this more ecological framework of health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you give an example?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;,breathing is a really important element in our tai chi and qigong training. But there&#39;s no way you can substantially change your breathing without changing your posture and how you hold your structure. And your breathing deeply affects you nervous and cardiovascular system, and many aspects of your mood; it can be a great tool for focusing the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;monkey mind&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; and becoming more sensitive to the inner landscape of our body. And of course changes in all these processes feedback on how we move and socially respond and interact with others. All these processes are ecologically intertwined with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also still think it&#39;s useful to unpack the interconnected components&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;for example to teach breathing exercises on their own and to study the physiological impacts of breathing exercises, in isolation of the larger package of Tai Chi. As a teacher, focusing on individual components helps brings awareness to finer scale processes, and it helps make a clearer teaching intention. Also talking about the physiology of breathing in classes helps some students appreciate the work, and for the students, there can be a lot of power in knowing. Most of us like to be told why we are doing a given practice in a given way. It really helps if students are informed. It creates buy in. I really love building bridges between traditional practices and modern science for this reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, what&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s it like for you teaching in a clinical trial compared to your community-based classes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In clinical trials, we are asking individuals to volunteer their time as a study participant so we can learn more about the health effects of Tai Chi. Often, these individuals have serious health conditions, and may not have chosen Tai Chi, or even heard of it, were it not for their doctor telling them about the trial. So many come to class not because they especially want to do tai chi, but because it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s a &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;new therapy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; they are hopeful it might improve their health. So there is sometimes a bit more time devoted to easing them into the work and making them feel comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think in your classes, in my classes, everyday someone walks in, and it&#39;s like an energetic push-hands. How do you meet that person exactly where they are and make them feel comfortable. And sometimes it has to be with a joke, sometimes it has to be with empathic solemnness, sometimes it&#39;s with a little distance&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;some do not initially care for intimacy. And you just have to feel that out. The real challenge, of course, is when you try to feel it out with 30 different people at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoying the challenge of connecting with diverse populations, and find humor and science help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite moments in teaching new Tai Chi students, both in clinical trials and community-based classes, is introducing them to a qigong warm-up exercise called &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Washing yourself with qi from nature.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; This very simple exercise, done either standing or seated, is designed to gather in healing, rejuvenating, peaceful energy from nature and guide this energy through every cell of the body, starting at the crown of the head and down through the chest, shoulders, spine, all the internal organs, through the legs and feet. I ask participants&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;not uncommonly older housewives and retired blue collar workers with little or no exposure to New Age practices --to imagine doing this while standing on a mountaintop, a beach, or wherever they feel they would be surrounded by nourishing energy. As they do the movement, I invite them to trust the energy to permeate and revitalize every cell of their body, while at the same time, tired sick energy is filter out and washed out through the soles of their feet into the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll abruptly stop, smile, and acknowledge with them how odd or weird this all sounds. They typically agree and we all laugh together. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll then share with them some of the research my colleagues and I have done related to the placebo effect, that sheds light on the exercise we are learning, and more generally supports the Tai Chi principle that what you think and believe impacts your physiology and how you feel. Typically, I draw on the well-documented placebo effect in asthma patients. Briefly, asthma patients in placebo studies were recruited to participate under the guise of evaluating new asthma drugs. Wearing an air-tight breathing mask, first they were told they would be challenged with an airborne insult, for example, ragweed, but actually they were simply given saline sprayed into the air they inhaled. Just the suggestion of ragweed induced physiologically measurable asthmatic attacks in the majority of participants. Following this insult, they were then told they were being given a new asthma &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;rescue&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; medication, which again was saline, and most of those who had had the asthma attacks quickly recovered. A huge body of research now shows that this so-called placebo effect -- that is, that placebos can have a real therapeutic effect -- is true for nearly all medical interventions, including sugar pills, mock injections, even surgery, and for nearly all medical conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this brief interlude, I return back to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;washing yourself with qi from heavens&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and jokingly say &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;so as we wash with qi from heavens, you can go to your special place and imagine breathing in and bathing every cell in your body with healing energy, or you can breath in ragweed or other toxic substances. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s your choice!&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Learn more about Peter&#39;s school here at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.treeoflifetaichi.com/&#34;&gt;Tree of Life Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Man Who Did His Tai Chi Form 19,100 Times</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2011 07:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;I got an email the other day that was a little bit different than the usual requests for lessons. It read:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I learned the Short Form at Brookline Tai Chi under the tutelage of Bill Ryan back about 1996-1997. For seven years, I continued to do the short form three times every morning. Then for the past eight years or so, I have done the short form four times every morning.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;I keep a log of my centering practices, and have documentation that over the past 15 years, I have only missed doing my tai chi on three days, two when I was strapped down in hospital beds and unable to get up, and one day when I simply forgot to practice. (I practiced twice the next day.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Thus, I have done the short form now over 17,800 times.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;There were so many things that fascinated me about getting this email. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2966&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;First of all, it reinforced my belief that there&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s no such thing as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34;&gt;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;former student&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/a&gt;. As a teacher, this was a powerful reminder that you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t know the full extent of what you are giving your students and just how far they will take what they learn.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Then, consider this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He practices tai chi every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He practices several repetitions of the short form every time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He logs his practice every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;As you know from reading this blog, I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m a little obsessed with the idea of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;practice.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Clearly this man knew something about cultivating a practice. I wanted to know more about what motivated him to practice daily and record it with such diligence. So I asked him, but I wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t ready for the depth and thoughtfulness of his answer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3105&#34; title=&#34;Sandy Davis&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/12/IMG_0518-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sandy Davis runs Resilience Works&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;It turns out, I was talking to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;The Resilience Guy.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Sandy Davis runs a company called &lt;a href=&#34;http://resilienceworks.com/&#34;&gt;ResilienceWorks&lt;/a&gt;, dedicated to teaching people how to become more resilient, or as he puts it:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;CENTER&#34;&gt;&amp;Acirc; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: small;&#34;&gt;The more you invest wisely in your own vitality,&lt;br /&gt;
The more resilient you become, and&lt;br /&gt;
The easier it is to thrive.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Many of us come to movement arts like tai chi or qigong because of an innate desire to thrive, but Sandy has gone into great depth explaining the structures that make this process possible. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He advocates for &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Seven Simple Self-Care Structures&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; that make this possible:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Keep all your agreements.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Eat well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Sleep well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Have a daily centering practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Exercise aerobically on a regular basis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Have a daily creative practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Log your self-care results every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Now, when we talk about &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;practice&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; here, we often talk about 3 or 4 of these structures (mainly centering, exercise, and sleep). We often imply that a lot of what grabs you about something like tai chi is the creative expression you derive from continually refining it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;And certainly we talk about tracking your practice -- although I haven&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t yet met anyone else who has taken this habit to quite the same degree as Sandy -- he&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s missed three days of practice in the last 14 years, and he can prove it!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;So what is it about &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;keeping all your agreements&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; that adds to your store of energy? When I heard Sandy describe this particular structure, it broadened my sense of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what builds your energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what uses up your energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; in a way I had never considered. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.resilienceworks.com/resiliencemanual&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Resilience Manual&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s guide to developing these structures, he writes:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;There is much satisfaction to be had in knowing that you are someone who can be relied upon to keep your word. By consistently walking your talk, &lt;strong&gt;you can acquire a deep-seated self-confidence in your ability to successfully follow through&lt;/strong&gt; on whatever you agree to undertake. This includes faithfully attending to your own foundational self-care habits, as well as to faithfully doing your chosen daily self-care practices.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Alternatively, there is much disappointment to be had in knowing that you are someone who routinely fails to follow through on your commitments. Whenever you fail to keep your word, whenever you fail to do what you promised, whenever you do 95% of what you said you would do and leave the last 5% unfinished, in all these instances, you experience a loss of self-respect. Each of these failures, whether obvious and public, or miniscule and private, generates a measure of personal disappointment and/or discouragement. &lt;strong&gt;Such breakdowns cost you valuable energy. They undermine your self-confidence. And they get in the way of deepening your resilience-readiness. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;What I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve highlighted in bold above should be familiar language when you think about your movement practice. You are either moving in a way that builds and integrates your coordination and your energy, or in a way that saps both and leads to dis-integration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Many of us have a gut feeling that how we cultivate a movement practice spills over into other dimensions of life, but I think Sandy has clearly articulated exactly how that works in the above passage. The lesson is that doing your movement practice won&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t make you a better person, but &lt;em&gt;it is a template for how to move toward more wholeness in other areas of your life&lt;/em&gt;. In Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s language, both structures feed your resilience-readiness and the store of resilience that you naturally draw energy from, no matter what situation you are facing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;The linchpin to all of this, from Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s point of view, is the seventh structure, or the meta-structure of logging the results of the other six structures on a daily basis. In &lt;em&gt;The Resilience Manual,&lt;/em&gt; he makes several compelling arguments for keeping a daily practice log both to gain perspective and to sustain accountability to yourself. For me, the most compelling reason is the deep satisfaction this seventh structure generates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;A week or so after our lesson, Sandy e-mailed me to make a correction to the number of times he has done the short form (hence the title of this post):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;FYI, I re-checked the numbers, and it turns out that I have actually done the short form more than 19,100 times. It will be a treat to pass the 20,000 mark. At my current rate of four times each day, that will take me another seven-plus months. But who&#39;s counting?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Think about how great that must feel to realize that you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re actually a little closer to 20,000? And not because you can brag about a number, but because you know you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve made a serious ongoing investment in your own well-being.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Big thanks to Sandy for sharing his method with so much clarity and simplicity! His website has more information, including some useful free resources and more in-depth explanations of the daily self-care structures. Check them out here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://resilienceworks.com/download.asp&#34;&gt;ResilienceWorks.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oh, and we also agreed that Sandy should come in for a tune-up every 3,000 forms, not every 10,000 or 15,000!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 09:22:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I sat down with Robert Tangora to talk about his upcoming book on Tai Chi Cloud Hands when he was in Boston in October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he discusses Tai Chi Cloud Hands, almost reverently, Robert explains it as a paradigm for understanding the complete art of Tai Chi, and also as a way to bring each practitioner closer to integration. The basic problem is that you have a spectrum of practices, from sitting, to standing, to moving, to fighting, that all feel very different and all develop different attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked Robert to talk about this integration problem and explain why he sees Cloud Hands as an essential part of well developed Tai Chi practice. Here are some highlights from the interview, with a link at the end to the entire video and full transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of this interview will also appear in the &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi: State of the Art&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-state-of-the-art/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi State of the Art 2012 ebook&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven&#39;t had a chance to weigh in on that topic yet, complete the survey &lt;a title=&#34;2012 Survey&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-state-of-the-art/2012-survey/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2376&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fsAN3HlNvrc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fsAN3HlNvrc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the introduction to &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/span&gt; from his website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://tangorataichi.com/Book%20Intro.pdf&#34;&gt;TangoraTaiChi.com&lt;/a&gt; (right click and &#34;save as&#34;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Cloud Hands?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you talk to a lot of people who have done Tai Chi a long time, they&#39;ll all say, &#34;Oh yeah, Cloud Hands.&#34; They may not have any idea why Cloud Hands seems really kind of special, but almost universally they go, &#34;Yeah, there&#39;s something there that&#39;s going on that I can&#39;t quite put my finger on it but I know it&#39;s there.&#34; And well, what&#39;s going on is it&#39;s this hidden relationship between the symmetries in what you&#39;re doing externally and internally.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On the relationship between health and meditation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;From a health standpoint, meditation is very important because it develops a lot of sensitivity to what&#39;s going on inside you. And if you want to be able to kind of fix something, you&#39;ve got to be able to feel it. If you can&#39;t feel it, you can&#39;t fix it. Well, most of us feel things because we have pain reactions rather than feeling things that aren&#39;t painful. Well, through meditation you actually learn to feel a lot of things that aren&#39;t pain reactions and you learn how those things end up being interrelated with pain reactions. And if you want to become really efficient at kind of healing yourself, or for that matter if you&#39;re doing some sort of healing of somebody else, you&#39;ve got to be able to distinguish those two.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On maximizing the health benefits by doing martial arts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The people I&#39;ve met who really have the health stuff of Tai Chi really well-developed were all very respectable martial arts... Those are the people who have that most developed.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On having a spectrum of different practices:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You have to have something that allows you to go from what you develop energetically while you&#39;re sitting and standing and take that into motion. Otherwise you tend to just jump into the form and the things you&#39;re doing internally in meditation practice are gone.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How Cloud Hands develops physical and energetic alignments:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeah there is physical aspects to it, like there is certain alignments you really need to kind of put in place, but there&#39;s also kind of some more energetic things that don&#39;t really necessarily have a real good physical counterpart. And it&#39;s kind of the first place where you really start kind of encountering that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, if I&#39;m like doing something on the left side of my body and it creates like a twist in a spiral like down to the ground. And I can reverse that, bring it up. Well, eventually this starts actually stimulating the Chi in my body. Just kind of start doing the same type of thing, but it does it actually probably at a different pace than my physical tissue because I can&#39;t actually make my physical tissue twist like this. But it helps induce it. So at some point it&#39;s physical, but it also has these other components energetically that it&#39;s starting to really develop.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What 90% of Tai Chi practitioners might be missing:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately everything kind of moves in these oblique ellipses and circles from your abdominal cavity...Well if you&#39;re doing both simultaneously, you start developing these kind of pulls and compression&#39;s that massage and loosen up your organs, and it begins to develop that. It&#39;s not that if you just relax and you stay really loose and you turn, you get some of that. You just don&#39;t get as much. And the place where, from a martial standpoint what happens is, you tend to be able to project power from certain angles, pretty efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s fairly efficient, it actually can be quite efficient at handling forces basically working more or less in a horizontal plane. But if I want to handle forces working in other dimensions, like vertically and stuff, I really have to have the capacity for my body to move in that direction and it&#39;d be integrated with what&#39;s happening in my legs and waist. So that&#39;s the other component, that&#39;s very important in the cross body training that probably 90% of the people doing Tai Chi they don&#39;t do it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;My favorite quote from the interview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you just practice form, there are so many things that distract you from listening to yourself.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora Tai Chi Cloud Hands Interview&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi-cloud-hands-interview/&#34;&gt;Check out the complete interview here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow and Stabilizing the Mind with Craig Barnes</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 08:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2203&#34; title=&#34;Craig Barnes doing Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-3-199x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Craig Barnes doing Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; width=&#34;199&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;Stability and flow seem to be at odds with each other. Stability can mean rigidity, or at least, it seems to conjure up something fixed, sturdy, and unmoving. Flow isn&#39;t any of those things. It&#39;s fluid and changing. So how does Energy Arts Senior Instructor Craig Barnes blend the two so seamlessly?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2191&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Recently, Craig taught a workshop about awakening energetic sensitivity, drawn from principles of Dragon and Tiger Qigong. We worked a lot on the opening of the set. The goal was to &#34;fill up your chi&#34; before you start doing the movements, so that the body is awake and engaged and each movement is more alive and more connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specific method for waking up your energetic sensitivity begins with refining awareness of your physical body. How do you move each part under conscious control, in a smooth circular way? Craig is very skilled at leading a group through a gradual progression that brings each new piece online and then weaves it together with the previous pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What impressed me more, though, was the way he included &#34;stability points&#34;, while maintaining the flow of the teaching, which was also what he was teaching people to do in their practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps &#34;stability point&#34; is the wrong term. Certainly this was a &#34;point&#34; in time in the flow of practice, but what Craig teaches, as far as stabilizing the mind, has a more diffuse quality than &#34;point&#34; conveys. You miss it if you focus on all the little details of body mechanics. If you treat the components of your practice like a checklist, you never become internally connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stability of the mind, when Craig expresses it, becomes the ground for your practice. A stable mind is like a table, set for a great meal. The specific exercises are the plates and bowls and cups that get filled up with delicious food, but you need to set the table for the meal to come together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-medium wp-image-2204&#34; title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Sword Fingers&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-2-224x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Sword Fingers&#34; width=&#34;224&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Internalizing the paradox of stability and flow goes a step or two beyond &#34;setting the table&#34;, though. Dragon and Tiger is a great place to learn how to stabilize the mind in the flow of movements because, between each distinct movement pattern, there are transitional moves that you can repeat as much as you need to. In these transitions, it&#39;s much easier to return to stability, but you don&#39;t have to break the flow. You do something simple, like circle the arms back and forth around the waist, or pulse the hands in and out, which keeps up a smooth flow. Through the simple repetition, your mind can settle down again at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Dragon and Tiger is made for this kind of work, you can still go through this process in any qigong set, if you follow these rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start your practice with simple, repetitive movements that allow you to tune into the background or underlying stability of your mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tease out gradually bigger and bigger movements, without losing the stable ground feeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work up into larger flow patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take soft landings throughout the set that return you to something simple and repetitive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For tai chi people: this is why a phrase like Grasp Sparrow&#39;s Tail is repeated a dozen times in a long form.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kilimanjaro Made Easy</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 10:05:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2151&#34; title=&#34;Jen on Kilimanjaro&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/09/P1010499-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;Z-Health Master Trainer Jen Waak is a self-described &#34;recovering management consultant&#34;. These days, she helps other &#34;Keyboard Athletes&#34; improve and maintain their bodies and stay healthy even when they&#39;re stuck behind a desk all day. What surprised me about reading Jen&#39;s advice on &#34;what you should do at your desk&#34;, was that it sounded a lot like what she did last year to get ready for a climb up Mount Kilimanjaro.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1999&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here&#39;s what Jen had to say about her prep and training:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It was a year ago today that I left to climb Kilimanjaro. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m not a climber, I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t camp, and I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t like the cold. So why I thought this was a good idea I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll never know. I just knew it was something I needed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I got over the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what have I done?&#34; stage, it was time to start figuring out what it would take to summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I started researching the trip, and here is what I learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;40% of climbers don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t make the summit, and the vast majority of the succumb to hypoxia (altitude sickness) since a summit of 19,340 feet means there is about half of the oxygen at the summit than there is at sea level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was going to be traveling ~60 very hilly miles on foot over 9 days. No one day was going to be the gotcha &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; instead it was going to be the accumulated miles that would wear down my body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being comfortable in your gear is critically important since what you have with you is, well, what you have with you. And there&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s nothing like getting blisters and only 59 more miles to go.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In a situation like this, it would be really easy to get freaked out and not know where to start. But, using a framework I call the Energy Bank, I was able to fairly easily come up with a extremely doable training plan that made summiting downright easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Energy Bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Energy Bank is this idea that we all have a finite amount of energy to get through the day, and everything we do during the day &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; everything &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; either adds to or depletes our bank balance: the lighting in the room, your breathing patterns, the horrible morning commute, your uncomfortable desk chair, and that grande burrito you had for lunch. It all has an impact. And just like a bank balance the higher the average balance, the larger the margin of error before going bankrupt. As you can imagine, a large margin of error will serve someone well when attempting one of the Seven Summits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my goal in preparing for Kilimanjaro was to get my Energy Bank Balance high enough so that the trip wouldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t run the balance down to zero &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; focusing specifically on what I would encounter on the trip that would be more likely to result in large withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training for the Climb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Breathing:&lt;/strong&gt; I knew this was already a weak link for me - and given that it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s also the downfall of most climbers, this became my #1 priority. My first goal was to fix my breathing patterns at sea level during everyday activities. Once I had that mastered, I went on to practicing my breathing while in oxygen debt (as ultimately that was what I would encounter on Kilimanjaro). Since I live at sea level, I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t truly replicate the conditions on Kilimanjaro, but instead would sprint or run stairs and focus on my breathing during and after those activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision:&lt;/strong&gt; Another one of my weak links, I spent a great deal of time working on my visual skills. My depth perception isn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t great, which translates into me being tentative going down stairs. Since I had to travel 60 miles over hilly terrain, not being comfortable going up and down was going to be a BIG problem. So, I incorporated some basic convergence drills into my training so my eyes could re-learn to focus and my brain would re-learn depth perception. Like my breathing, first I worked on this during everyday activities, and then I moved on to working it into my running stairs, long hikes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Endurance:&lt;/strong&gt; Going and going over 9 days on rough terrain was something I didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have any experience in. Using the Energy Bank concept, I realized that if my body was already somewhat adapted to that it would be a lot easier. But, with a hectic schedule and living in the city, I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t exactly take off for 9 days to climb in the Cascades. Instead, I got the idea that if fatigued my legs the night before a long hike with either a run or stair session, that I would begin the adaptation process of going long distances on tired legs. So, I would either do a long stair session or a run one night and then the next morning go and hike 10+ miles with a 3,000 foot elevation gain (since that would most replicate the conditions I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d find on Kilimanjaro). I got in probably 3 or 4 of these back-to-back training sessions prior to Kilimanjaro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gear:&lt;/strong&gt; Remember that part where I said I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t climb or camp? Yeah, that meant that I had a buy and test a TON of gear for the trip. In the weeks leading up to the climb my week would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on a hike, discover I didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have the right gear (either through blisters, sweating sunscreen into my eyes, or dealing with lots of bugs. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d come home and take notes on what worked and what didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to REI and pick up what I was missing (and just cover my eyes while signing the credit card receipt)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on another hike and re-assess. Lather, rinse, repeat until I knew I had what I needed.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overkill? Maybe. But I had no blisters, no chafing, and at no point did I say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I wish I would have brought&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;Acirc;  Everything got tested on at least one 10+ mile hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery:&lt;/strong&gt; Early on in my physical training I got a bit ambitious and decided to run 4 miles down a mountain. That turned out to be one of the less bright things I could have done, as I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t go up and down stairs for several days after that. But it also highlighted something I hadn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t considered &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; that I could get sore. A phone call to fellow Master Trainer and endurance athlete Shannon Mauck revealed the world of recovery drinks to me. Yet another thing for me to test &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I needed to find something that I both liked the taste of and that would agree with my system. (Turns out I really like Accelerade.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did it Work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d have to give the entire experiment an unqualified, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;hell, yeah.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;Acirc;  My training wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t extreme &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I did 6 long hikes and then a couple of hours of running, sprinting, and stairs per week. I worked on my breathing and vision for a few minutes a day, and made a point of incorporating that practice while on my long hikes. And the entire trip up the mountain was a piece of cake for me &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d get into camp each night with extra energy to burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The biggest surprise:&lt;/strong&gt; The mental shift in who I am. I grew up a really sick little kid, and had never considered myself an athlete. And now I had accomplished that thousands of people cannot each year. I had to redefine who I am, and now think of myself as an athlete. Because everything is a skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you liked the way she managed her mountain climbing training, you&#39;ll definitely be interested in her insight into bringing more energy into your daily life: &lt;a href=&#34;http://keyboardathletes.com/yourenergybank/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Increase Your Energy Bank Balance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Breathing, Qigong, and Meditation Improve Quality of Life</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/20/how-breathing-qigong-and-meditation-improve-quality-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 08:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/20/how-breathing-qigong-and-meditation-improve-quality-of-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I asked my friend and fellow qigong practitioner Catherine Chenoweth to talk a little bit about her experience using qigong to manage a chronic health condition. Here&#39;s what she had to say:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1782&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/07/5349FC1E-3A30-461B-9D4C-EC402891879A0.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;margin: 5px;&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/07/5349FC1E-3A30-461B-9D4C-EC402891879A0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;160&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I was released from the hospital in 1996, it was after three months, and with a diagnosis of LAM (Lymphangioleiomyomatosis), a rare, progressive, untreatable and often fatal lung disease. I asked a friend who was well versed in alternative treatments what I should do for my health, and his response, immediate and emphatic, was &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;You need to do qigong!&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I did. What started as an effort to do something proactive for my health turned into a life long passion and became an irreplaceable part of my life. I think one of the smartest things I ever did was to take an entire week course of breathing with Bruce Frantzis. One thing that is very clear when one really starts to lose their ability to breathe is how much we take breathing for granted. It may even seem like a silly thing to spend money on &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; an entire week learning how to breathe! But it is a subject that has a surprising amount of depth, and you learn quickly that many people have very poor breathing habits. To learn to breathe with the entirety of your lungs, not just the lower half of the lung as opposed to the chest, but with the sides and back of the lung as well, is something that can increase overall efficiency, something that is a must for people with progressive lung disease who want to maintain the best quality of life that they can. Not only will proper technique and practice affect your breathing, but it will spill over into areas such as stress reduction, pain reduction, and overall well being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, a balance of breathing, meditation, and qigong has been the key to maximizing my quality of life with a lung disease. The slow, gentle movements of qigong give me a way to exercise when my body is unable to do any type of western exercise, for example when faced with chronic lung collapses or after a surgery. To progress in qigong means to go deeper into layers of your body, learning to become sensitive to and to manipulate soft tissue, fluids, joints and energy. To progress in certain other forms of exercise often means doing more physically demanding, more aerobic, bigger, faster movements &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; all aspects that can be impossible goals for someone who is sick or disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I applaud anyone who takes the first steps toward taking charge of their health. In an increasingly busy and distracted society, it can seem like the last thing on anyone&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s list is to be healthy and take care of their bodies. Whether you have an illness, disease, or injury, or whether you are healthy and wish to maintain your health into old age, find some time in your life to learn some of these ancient practices, and find some time in your day to practice them. A simple breathing or qigong practice will allow you to connect with your body again, and the rewards are well worth the effort. Being through what I have been through has given me a unique perspective and a deep appreciation of the limits and possibilities of the human body. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s the only vessel you have to get you through this life. Care for it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Quiet Awareness with Lee Burkins</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1656&#34; title=&#34;Lee Burkins Ba Gua&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/ABG1-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lee Burkins Ba Gua&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In June, between sessions at Brookline Tai Chi and during master classes with Bruce Frantzis, a small group of students got a special treat. Energy Arts Senior Instructor Lee Burkins was in town to train with Bruce, and on one of the nights off, he offered a special evening course on a topic he calls &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/blog/special-evening-mini-topic-lee-burkins&#34;&gt;&#34;Investing in Loss&#34;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I love about studying with someone like Lee is that he&#39;s a  practitioner whose art has soaked so deeply into his bones, that it  practically oozes out of his DNA. Everything he teaches seems so  obviously and natural when he explains it, but you&#39;ve never thought about  it before and never accessed it so effortlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second time he&#39;s taught at Brookline Tai Chi. The first  time, a couple of years ago, he did the same thing with the&amp;Acirc;  Ba Gua  Single Palm Change. Lee took a group of people, most of whom had never  done Ba Gua, and got them gliding around the room, finding the Ba Gua  step, and eventually even spontaneously twisting and turning into the  Single Palm Change. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1651&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our topic this year seemed more esoteric at first, so I was wondering if he&#39;d be able to do the same thing. What  the heck is &#34;Quiet Awareness&#34; and how do you let that run your physical  body? You could see that with many other teachers, this could have been a  2-hour theoretical lecture. Not with Lee. He snuck up on us with really  clear and simple physical exercises, just letting go of tension and  posture through movements. We let ourselves swirl around and find a  sloshing, fluid, sense of internal space. Once people had settled down  into deeper internal awareness, he showed us how to shape an internal  sense of letting go into a solid physical structure and full, alive, and  responsive physical movement. Obviously this is all a little hard to  explain in writing....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funniest moment though, was after everyone began to really get  what he was driving at, he said, &#34;ok, ok, you&#39;re doing it, so let me  give you something to feed your thinking mind too.&#34; See, the bigger  point he was driving at was that Quiet Awareness is a different mode for  your mind to be in, and you need that to understand your body, your  mind, and your energy. The internal arts are all about accessing this  mode and manifesting it. The problem is, most of us are trained to use a  different mode of awareness, i.e. the thinking mind. As a masterful  teacher, he recognized that, and with the gentle humor he always uses in  teaching, he graciously gave our thinking minds something to chew on  too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Here&#39;s the model he shared:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Leaves on river by rstrawser, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/14696088@N04/1544960560/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2395/1544960560_9e4ba9f9f8_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Leaves on river&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lee took the classic Chinese medicine phrase, &#34;the mind moves the chi  and the chi moves the blood&#34; and formulated it as &#34;the Quiet Awareness  moves the chi and the chi moves the fluids inside the body and therefore  the body as well&#34;. To really get this concept, he explained it like the  current in a river. Think of a leaf floating along in the river. That&#39;s  your body. When the current changes, that&#39;s like the chi shifting. It  shifts direction (inward to outward, up to down), because your Quiet  Awareness shifts first. The interesting part is the lag time between  the change of the current and movement of the leaf. Your Quiet Awareness  turns over, the chi follows, and so does the leaf, but as you are learning  to tune into this process, you can feel the leaf moving along the old  current pattern, even as the current is going a different direction.  Those are the circular transitions you feel in your form.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don&#39;t know if I quite captured what we did or what Lee was  aiming to teach, but if you ever do get a chance to work with him, take  it. He&#39;s a kind and generous teacher and the naturalness of his art form  that pours out is a real treasure. &lt;a href=&#34;http://coloradointernalarts.com/practitioners.htm&#34;&gt;Lee lives and teaches in Colorado&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In his own words: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I followed up with Lee to see if this recap came close to capturing what he was teaching. Here&#39;s how he describes the process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the mind&#39;s frequency to smoothly transition from  the&amp;Acirc; vibration&amp;Acirc; of the intellectual aspect to approach and begin to  connect with the vibration/frequency of the intuitive mind. Once you  &#39;experience&#39; this shift in frequency and are able to stay in this mode  (a posture of the mind), &#39;what is hidden will be revealed&#39;, ie, the  connection of the quiet awareness to the chi to the body (nerves,  fluids, and tissues).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 12:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1529&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Paul Cavel is an Energy Arts Senior Instructor based in London. He teaches regular weekly classes there, but he&#39;s also been traveling all over the UK and Europe for years teaching workshops, including annual week-long retreats in Crete. I talked to Paul a little bit about his background in Tai Chi, neigong, and Ba Gua and asked him for some practice advice for a group of students who just completed a series at BTC on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little bit about how you got started studying these arts. Who were some of your first influential teachers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After a motorcycle accident in 1986, I started studying Yang style tai chi to heal my injuries. When the teacher left, the class naturally gravitated towards the Water method neigong practices as taught by my main teacher, Bruce Frantzis. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve been hooked ever since.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1528&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over the last 30 years, Bruce has taught in so many different places and formats. When and how did you first start studying with him?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first encounter with Bruce was in a London seminar on the spiraling energy body. Of course, that material really opened my eyes to what qigong could do! When I subsequently lived with Bruce some years later in 1994-1995, my passion for bagua was ignited in his weekly classes. I got in by the skin of my teeth as one of the last students he let into the class&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Since you&#39;ve studied with Bruce, have you had other influential teachers? Have you studied complementary arts that you bring into your teaching?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve attended the odd seminar with a reputable Chinese master or two, including a couple of months of early morning training in the park with a master in California. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve also attended events hosted by the Tai Chi Union of Great Britain where several teachers offer workshops. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve picked up the odd tidbit here and there from these courses. However, my direction is a product of Bruce&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s mentoring and the desire to follow the tenants of the genuine Water tradition as passed down by him. Bruce is my one and only teacher.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-1537  alignright&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel_SPC&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little bit about your teaching. Do you run regular classes? Workshops? Who are your students?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I teach full-time and offer various teaching formats, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Weekly classes and seminars in Kentish Town, London&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weekend seminars in England and Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weeklong retreats in Greece and Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corporate training and executive coaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private and small group lessons&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have students from all walks of life who practise for a wide variety of reasons. Some are looking for a system to maintain health and wellness while others are professionals who want an edge and/or a means for releasing stress. I also see many Energy Arts instructors who want to prepare for certification trainings or upgrade their practice and understanding of the material.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the three most important points that you would like other instructors to know about regarding your practice or your teaching or your business?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; My practice and my teaching are neigong-based. That is I focus on the strands of neigong that develop the body, chi and mind, and then integrate that material into Circle Walking, bagua, tai chi and meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m based in North London where I offer my full programme. The seminar series and retreats I teach in Europe are designed with a particular focus in mind to help students develop that particular aspect of practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I offer a lot of hands-on personal corrections, partner exercises and component practice sets with a systematic, progressive focus. My aim is to help students solidify their foundation and integrate the deeper aspects of neigong that ultimately intertwine to create the more complex movement forms of bagua and tai chi.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Some of my students have just finished a series on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth, where they learned to open and close the joints of the arms and legs. How should they continue to work on this practice on their own?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have opened up the pulse, the next step is to balance your  system. This is normally done through Circling Hands Qigong, an easy,  repetitive motion that allows the mind to focus on the content rather  that the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through practice of Circling Hands Qigong, the process is simple:  compare the pulse in the joint on the left side to the corresponding  joint on the right side of your body, and make them the same. This is  done by reducing the joint with the larger range to that of the joint  with the smaller range. Go through all the pairs, e.g. hands, feet,  elbows and knees. Next, compare each pair to all other pairs, e.g. hands  to feet, elbows to knees, shoulders to hips, and equalise any  imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reducing your range of motion to the joint with the smallest range, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dramatically soften the pulse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Release the nervous system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deepen the pulse in the joints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link the pulsing of the joints into one unified lattice, thereby amplifying the positive effects of the pulse.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more from Paul on the art of pulsing, check out this two-part series,&amp;Acirc;  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/1469/pulsing-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/1501/pulsing-bagua-zhang/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>