<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>meditation on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/categories/meditation/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in meditation on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/categories/meditation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Easing into Taoist Sitting Meditation</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/05/29/easing-into-taoist-sitting-meditation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 11:57:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/05/29/easing-into-taoist-sitting-meditation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignright&#34; alt=&#34;sitting meditition&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/05/sittin-meditition.jpg&#34; width=&#34;148&#34; height=&#34;224&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taoist sitting meditation is a powerful practice, but many people have &lt;a title=&#34;Meditation for People Who Can&#39;t Sit Still&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/24/meditation-for-people-who-cant-sit-still-2/&#34;&gt;a hard time sitting still&lt;/a&gt; or focusing on their bodies long enough to develop sensitivity to the energies of sitting meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when you explore related practices, like Tai Chi, you develop &lt;a title=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;the skills you need to ease into sitting meditation practices&lt;/a&gt;.  One of the most important skills taught in Tai Chi is the ability to focus. It is only through structured focus that we can access our Chi, or internal energies. Focus allows us to travel around our body, seeing it in a whole new way and teaching us how to heal ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taoist sitting meditation works hand in hand with movement sets. The process is actually quite easy to carry out. Simply follow the steps below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should begin with &lt;a title=&#34;5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/&#34;&gt;gentle movement exercises like qigong&lt;/a&gt; or Tai Chi.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once you are loose and feel refreshed you should sit in a straight backed chair, feet flat and thighs parallel with the floor and hands flat on the thighs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relax the shoulders and allow the chest to sink inwards in a relaxed manner. The spine itself should be straight but not held in a tense manner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Close your eyes and begin to focus on keeping your breathing slow and steady. The breath should be drawn into the abdomen from the nose and expelled slowly from slightly open lips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When your breathing is smooth you can begin to relax your entire body. Beginning with the face, begin to imagine the muscles relaxing, sagging. Move your attention to the neck, the shoulders, arms and chest, all the way down the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When your attention begins moving down your body you should pay close attention to any areas that feel tense. When these areas are located, again using your focused attention, relax them.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also do the reverse: use your sitting meditation and preparation for moving practices.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two essential reasons for using Taoist meditation before beginning Tai Chi sets, or any exercise routine. The mediation relaxes both the body and the mind, which will make the movement sets a great deal more meaningful. Secondly the mental journey through your body gives you a much deeper mental connection with your body and a greater sense of what is going on inside. These deeper connections are vital for establishing the best relationship with Tai Chi. You will find after a 15 minute meditation session that you will find yourself sinking deeper and deeper into the movements.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mc_embed_signup&#34;&gt;
&lt;form class=&#34;validate&#34; id=&#34;mc-embedded-subscribe-form&#34; action=&#34;http://dankleiman.us1.list-manage1.com/subscribe/post?u=0e4a1aa488d23c693881caeec&amp;amp;id=43c92dacfa&#34; method=&#34;post&#34; name=&#34;mc-embedded-subscribe-form&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More Energy in the Next 30 Days...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Take our free, email-based course and you will have more energy in the next 30 days than you&#39;ve had in the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;http://cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/slim-081711.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
	#mc_embed_signup{background:#fff; clear:left; font:14px Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif; }&lt;br /&gt;
	/* Add your own MailChimp form style overrides in your site stylesheet or in this style block.&lt;br /&gt;
	   We recommend moving this block and the preceding CSS link to the HEAD of your HTML file. */&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mc_embed_signup&#34;&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;http://dankleiman.us1.list-manage1.com/subscribe/post?u=0e4a1aa488d23c693881caeec&amp;id=43c92dacfa&#34; method=&#34;post&#34; id=&#34;mc-embedded-subscribe-form&#34; name=&#34;mc-embedded-subscribe-form&#34; class=&#34;validate&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; novalidate&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;More Energy in the Next 30 Days...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take our free, email-based course and you will have more energy in the next 30 days than you&#39;ve had in the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How the course works:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll take an in-depth look at moving your body, your energy, and your mind, all with the goal of smoothing out your nervous system and boosting your energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the month, you&#39;ll receive these 8 lessons via email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Break through the Daily Noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Connect to a Natural Power Source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Structure Your Practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a Ph.D. in Tai Chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to Weave Together Tai Chi&#39;s 3 Branches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take Tai Chi out into the World&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come in for a Tune-up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boost Your Practice, Week after Week&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These emails include audio practice downloads, tutorials, essays, and practice tips designed to get you deeper into the Energy Arts and expand your awareness of what&#39;s possible with a personal movement practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sign up and enjoy!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/label&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;input type=&#34;email&#34; value=&#34;&#34; name=&#34;EMAIL&#34; class=&#34;email&#34; id=&#34;mce-EMAIL&#34; placeholder=&#34;email address&#34; required&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;clear&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;submit&#34; value=&#34;Subscribe&#34; name=&#34;subscribe&#34; id=&#34;mc-embedded-subscribe&#34; class=&#34;button&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--End mc_embed_signup--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>