<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>qigong-practice on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/qigong-practice/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in qigong-practice on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/qigong-practice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing Qigong Breathing Exercises -- Mp3</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 08:38:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4412&#34; alt=&#34;Better Breathing&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/11/032-300x225.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest question people ask me about standing qigong, especially when they hear about &lt;a title=&#34;Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/&#34;&gt;the 2-hour project&lt;/a&gt;, is &#34;what do you do, just stand there?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is actually a really delicate balance between &#34;doing&#34; and &#34;feeling&#34; when you stand. You learn lots of different techniques, like breathing, sinking, dissolving, and pulsing, but how you apply them internally when you are holding a static posture is a tricky topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you rev your engine too much -- activating &lt;a title=&#34;My Favorite Breathing Hack&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/30/my-favorite-breathing-hack/&#34;&gt;strong diaphragmatic breathing&lt;/a&gt; the entire time, for example -- then you miss the potential stillness in the posture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you zone out, and don&#39;t connect to internal sensations, you&#39;ll miss the potential for integration and you won&#39;t build any chi or walk away with the sense of organization that your standing qigong can provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you strike the balance between &#34;do&#34; and &#34;feel&#34; in your standing qigong practice? I&#39;ve put together two breathing exercise mp3 for you to listen to while you practice standing qigong to help you find that balance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/[Standing]%20Breathing%20to%20Activate%20the%20Back.mp3&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong -- Breathing to Activate the Back&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/[Standing]%20Breathing%20to%20Activate%20the%20Feet.mp3&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong -- Breathing to Activate the Feet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These are short, easy practice sessions that focus in on one skill each: you will learn how to use the breath as a guide for your awareness, activating sensation, without overriding the potential for stillness. As you practice, you will be able to apply this same skill to longer and longer standing qigong practice sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One more thing:&lt;/strong&gt; if you enjoy these workouts and find them useful, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr?cmd=_s-xclick&amp;amp;hosted_button_id=QQC5GSTJLQRUW&#34;&gt;considering making a small contribution here&lt;/a&gt;. Think of it as a drop-in class fee. If I know that a lot of people are finding these helpful as practice aides, I will create more of them in the future. Thanks for your feedback and support!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update on Quantity vs. Quality and the Struggle for Perfect Practice</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/06/19/update-on-quantity-vs-quality-and-the-struggle-for-perfect-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 07:32:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/06/19/update-on-quantity-vs-quality-and-the-struggle-for-perfect-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few months ago we talked about &lt;a title=&#34;Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/&#34;&gt;the signs of progress in your qigong practice&lt;/a&gt;. For so many of us, the issue of &#34;progress&#34; is central to qigong or Tai Chi practice, since we are driven by the desire to get it right, to solve a problem like a health issue, or to reach an amorphous and elusive spiritual goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we completely abandoned the idea of outcomes and perfection in practice? Instead, what if you started each day with a &#34;doing&#34; mindset in your qigong practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take this example of a ceramics teacher from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Art-Fear-Observations-Rewards-Artmaking/dp/0961454733&#34;&gt;Art and Fear by David Bayles and Ted Orland&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://kk.org/cooltools/archives/000216&#34;&gt;In his review of the book&lt;/a&gt;, Kevin Kelly pulls this and many more excellent excerpts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The ceramics teacher announced on opening day that he was dividing the class into two groups. All those on the left side of the studio, he said, would be graded solely on the quantity of work they produced, all those on the right solely on its quality. His procedure was simple: on the final day of class he would bring in his bathroom scales and weigh the work of the &#34;quantity&#34; group: fifty pound of pots rated an &#34;A&#34;, forty pounds a &#34;B&#34;, and so on. Those being graded on &#34;quality&#34;, however, needed to produce only one pot -albeit a perfect one - to get an &#34;A&#34;. Well, came grading time and a curious fact emerged: the works of highest quality were all produced by the group being graded for quantity. It seems that while the &#34;quantity&#34; group was busily churning out piles of work - and learning from their mistakes - the &#34;quality&#34; group had sat theorizing about perfection, and in the end had little more to show for their efforts than grandiose theories and a pile of dead clay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What does your Tai Chi practice look like if you focus on building quantity? One of my favorite examples is from Chinese Wrestling expert John Wang. In this short documentary, he demonstrates Tree Hanging for building martial power (and maybe other important attributes?):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://youtu.be/wqnQj1Lx02Y&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Master Wang discusses technique and gives his student pointers, but when asked when the practice gets easier, he says, &#34;second year.&#34; That&#39;s a quantity mindset, to measure the progress of a daily practice by  year-over-year changes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you don&#39;t need to go out and tear the flesh from your arm for a full year to build a foundation for your practice (and he doesn&#39;t think many people will do it anymore anyway), but is there an element of your practice that can be measured in quantity, not quality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of whatever &#34;semester&#34; you are currently in, what component of your practice would you place on the bathroom scale? Where can you focus your time and effort to amass some serious practice skill?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, what high quality fruits will you be surprised with at the end of a quantity-driven period of practice?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Shift Your Sense of Time in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/05/02/how-to-shift-your-sense-of-time-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 08:40:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/05/02/how-to-shift-your-sense-of-time-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4584&#34; alt=&#34;Tai Chi on the Beach Fan&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/05/Tai-Chi-on-the-Beach-Fan-300x225.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last month, we discussed &lt;a title=&#34;Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/&#34;&gt;the sense of progress&lt;/a&gt; you can sometimes struggle with in your practice. At the time, I mentioned that I&#39;ve been working up to a two-hour standing session, which is a very structured practice goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I wanted to report back about what I&#39;ve been experiencing in standing qigong and show you how to shift your sense of the time that passes when you stand. The structure of adding one minute to the length of the stand each day is seems like it should make for a very linear sense of time when you practice. So far, though, that&#39;s not what&#39;s happening at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Linear Time and Work&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you set your sights on a single two-hour qigong stand, it might sound blissful and energizing or it might sound grueling, especially when you think about inching closer to the goal by adding only one minute a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when the qigong practice is not going well, it is grueling. When the posture is &#34;off,&#34; you experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;isolated muscle pulls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;joint discomfort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tension, pain, and contraction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;energetic blockages&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Your reaction is often to fight these sensations directly, trying to stretch a contracted muscles or shift away from a compressed joint. When you&#39;re fighting a thousand little battles all over your body, time ticks by one second at a time, becoming slow, linear, painful work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cycles of Flow&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When your qigong posture is &#34;on,&#34; it&#39;s completely different. Everything feels continuous and flowing, but at the same time still without becoming stagnant. For example, you might experience your back expanding outward for several minutes or your front releasing inward or your legs sinking downward. You haven&#39;t moved, but the expansive/releasing/sinking quality goes on and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is where time shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same way that you feel movement and flow without actually moving, time passes without a sense of the minutes ticking by. In this &#34;on state,&#34; the posture feels easy and comfortable. Time doesn&#39;t feel as pressing because you don&#39;t feel like you&#39;re working on the posture. You lose a sense of sustained work, endurance, and duration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this state doesn&#39;t last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can sustain it for a while, but it falls apart. I used to find that very frustrating, until I discovered that it wasn&#39;t all or nothing for keeping the &#34;on state.&#34; The posture comes together and falls apart in cycles. In longer standing qigong sessions you will go through several cycles of flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how you can find these cycles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find your &#34;natural stand&#34; time: get a clock, close your eyes and just stand for as long as it feels easy and comfortable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat step 1 three times, seeing if the time for your natural stand is consistent (or repeat into you establish and natural baseline).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The next time you practice, add 5 minutes to your natural stand time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice what happens to your body, mind, and energy when you go into the extra time, past your natural stand time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep adding time into you find your second natural phase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over time, work up to standing for 2 or 3 natural cycles.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When your standing posture comes together, the body will be relaxed and integrated, your energy will be flowing, the mind will be expanded and enveloping, and your mood will be calm. As you shift into an &#34;off&#34; phase, you may notice that your body gets stiff and isolated, your energy feels stuck, your mind starts to contract, and you feel impatient. The more you can tune into these sensations at all levels, the more you will be able to recognize the natural cycles of flow in your practice and the &#34;time&#34; you stand for will shift to more circular and integrated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>