<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>small-business-marketing on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/small-business-marketing/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in small-business-marketing on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/small-business-marketing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Cycles</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 14:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m coming to another big teaching cycle in Trainerfly and I think this short clip of David Heinemeier Hansson speaking at Stanford&#39;s Entrepreneurship Corner is really useful to frame the mindset:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-574&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;single&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;302&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;config=http://ecorner.stanford.edu/embeded_config.xml%3Fmid%3D2361&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://ecorner.stanford.edu/swf/player-ec.swf&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;single&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;302&#34; src=&#34;http://ecorner.stanford.edu/swf/player-ec.swf&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; flashvars=&#34;config=http://ecorner.stanford.edu/embeded_config.xml%3Fmid%3D2361&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the point in the clip above is more about a strategy to take when you look at the &#34;big guys&#34;, but I really feel like the alternating cycles of &#34;spending&#34; and &#34;teaching&#34; are relevant here. We just went through a &#34;spending&#34; period where we were building out the technology behind Trainerfly. That was only possible because we went through a &#34;teaching&#34; period initially, where I learned what problems I wanted to solve with a software application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I&#39;m entering another &#34;teaching&#34; cycle as I share the fruits of the &#34;spending&#34; cycle, a viable software solution, with other peers in movement education. It gets even more interesting if you chart the smaller cycles within each of the major cycles.....hmmmm, where have I encountered that kind of thinking before??&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with the Old....Business Model</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 16:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Exit&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2245/2089485151_17f142a726_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s the end of the year and it&#39;s time to get out of old habits and mindsets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here&#39;s my prediction for the best business model for independent fitness and wellness pros, for the next DECADE. Yeah, I think it&#39;s going to take a few years to unfold, but the groundwork has been laid:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-514&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more brick-and-mortar businesses&lt;/strong&gt;. Trust me, I know what it&#39;s like to cut a $10,000 rent check each month. That&#39;s over with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more separation between in-person and on-line.&lt;/strong&gt; I read an article the other day that referred to &#39;90&#39;s style &#34;clicks-and-mortar&#34; business, e.g. Walmart.com for Walmart. You&#39;ve got to move past your website as a calling card for your services, even if you &#34;have really good content&#34;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more big barriers to scaling up your business.&lt;/strong&gt; This is great news. It&#39;s so easy to manage all the clients in your universe in a systematic way, through crm, email marketing, and interactive training apps like Trainerfly (ahem!), that the little guy or independent gal, can make it all by themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more one-size fits all products.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the same kind of dinosaur as a physical location. You might have some good reasons to put out video products (like standardizing a curriculum, for example), but you better have a way to tailor it to your clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more professional athlete fantasy.&lt;/strong&gt; You don&#39;t have to go pro or get sponsored or anything like that to make a decent living.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Welcome to the professional educator reality.&amp;Acirc;  I believe that the movement educator who is committed to honing a craft can make a real living. We all work really, really hard in our practice and now it&#39;s going to be possible to build a business around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at any public health statistics. Do you see a lack of movement in our society? Are we aging? Unhealthy? Totally divorced from the inherent human joys of movement? Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So those of us out there carrying the flag for better life through movement need to speak up. But we need to adapt too. We need to meet people where they are at, offer them chunks of wellness they can digest, and slowly change the conversation. And while we&#39;re at it, we need to make a living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is within reach in the next year or five years or ten years. You just need to start today with a little mental shift. Step into 2011 with some fresh perspective. You will be well rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exit photo courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/heathbrandon/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;heathbrandon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find Your True Fans</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/21/find-your-true-fans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2010 09:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/21/find-your-true-fans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.static.flickr.com/30/54812349_b12966dcf7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;1,000 True Fans&#34; width=&#34;350&#34; height=&#34;256&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; If you&#39;ve never read Kevin Kelly&#39;s piece called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kk.org/thetechnium/archives/2008/03/1000_true_fans.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;1,000 True Fans&lt;/a&gt;, I suggest you hop on that link and read it. When you come back, you can read some of my thoughts on the issue, but I probably won&#39;t blow your mind the way Kelly will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, are you back? Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what I think stands out in his article for the aspiring &#34;Movement Education Professional&#34; (more on that term below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I don&#39;t know about you, but the long tail map is incredibly reassuring to me. I think whenever anyone is trying to run a small business, you look around and see &#34;the big guys&#34; and try to copy them. That&#39;s a totally unrealistic approach and going that route is totally disheartening. You can&#39;t behave like a big business at all: you don&#39;t have the same division of labor, you can&#39;t spend on advertising to build brand recognition, you can&#39;t fire an under-performing employee (what? cut off your left arm when sales tank???). You have to operate in a totally different way, but where is the model for how that&#39;s supposed to be done? Most of the people that would model for you, other successful small businesses, are too busy running their businesses!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So back to the long tail, Kelly says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am suggesting there is a home for creatives in between poverty and  stardom. Somewhere lower than stratospheric bestsellerdom, but higher  than the obscurity of the long tail. I don&#39;t know the actual true  number, but I think a dedicated artist could cultivate 1,000 True Fans,  and by their direct support using new technology, make an honest  living.&amp;Acirc;  I&#39;d love to hear from anyone who might have settled on such a  path.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As soon as you start looking at that in-between space, so many things open up. I like to think about this space when I&#39;m out in public. Sit on a busy street corner for 10 minutes and watch how many people go by. Do they all make a living? Do plenty of them make a comfortable living? Do you know them all? Yes. Yes. No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does that mean? &lt;strong&gt;It means that there is so much room in between for you to serve the needs of people who can pay for your service. &lt;/strong&gt;At Brookline Tai Chi, our database has over 10,000 names of people who have taken classes or inquired about classes at some point. You know what&#39;s amazing about that? Every 8 weeks, 30-50 &lt;em&gt;brand new&lt;/em&gt; people come through our door to start classes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the boring conclusion to all this is: &#34;there is a market out there for your services&#34;, but Kelly raises the stakes. It&#39;s not just a &#34;market&#34;. There are potentially raving, hard-core fans of what you do out there. You have to go find them and you have to find ways to engage them. I wrote in more detail about the &#34;universe&#34; of your fans &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/06/your-marketing-universe/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but on the Trainerfly blog, I just published &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2010/12/20/the-movement-education-professionals-manifesto/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&#34;The Movement Education Professional&#39;s Manifesto&#34;&lt;/a&gt;. The Manifesto is much more in line with the idea that passion driving a craft (in this case, your movement practice), should lead to engaging other people who get similarly excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think if you agree with premise of the Manifesto, about what movement means in your own life, and you&#39;ve taken the leap to teach professionally, then you&#39;ll see how important it is to take another big step and start finding your 1,000 True Fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/yourlocaldave/&#34;&gt;YourLocalDave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Systems? No Raise for You This Year!</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/10/no-systems-no-raise-for-you-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 09:50:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/10/no-systems-no-raise-for-you-this-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You probably don&#39;t realize it, but there is a good chance you are letting a lot of extra money in your business slip right out of your hands. In fact, if you don&#39;t have good systems in place, I can almost guarantee it. In this post I&#39;ll pull  back the curtain and show you some of the systems I use to keep things running tighter. Specifically, I&#39;m going to tell you about an end of year/new year&#39;s marketing  campaign, targeting my private clients from 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But first, think about this problem in a system-less business.&amp;Acirc;  Coming up on the end of the year, I would think,  &#34;Shit, I better start training some more people next year...where can I  turn to find new clients? Should I advertise? Should I call some old clients? Do you think my current clients will pay me twice as much??? Oh my god, what am I going  to do!!!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so maybe you don&#39;t spiral out of control right  away, but if you have good tracking and good systems going all  along, it&#39;s so much easier. For an independent  movement educator to have simple systems in place (that are really cheap and not that hard to implement), it&#39;s like finding money between the cushions of your couch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sat down earlier this week and &#34;looked through the cushions&#34; in my business.&amp;Acirc;  My simple end-of-year audit turned up 5 different  strategies for picking up money around the edges of my&lt;em&gt; existing&lt;/em&gt; business -- no crazy new ventures either. You know what I forecast I could get from a little extra  effort? &lt;strong&gt;$10,000 in the coming year.&lt;/strong&gt; Who wouldn&#39;t give themselves a  $10,000 raise with found money? But you know what? You can only do it  with the right systems in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Putting Systems to Work&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are three systems that I use on a regular basis, that make launching a follow-up marketing campaign a piece of cake: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.students.dankleiman.com/login/index.php&#34;&gt;Online Training Notes for Each Client&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://highrisehq.com/&#34;&gt;Contact Management Database&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mailchimp.com/&#34;&gt;Email Marketing Software&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a part of live training, I always give my clients access to an online resources to supplement their training. I&#39;ll share notes about complicated exercises or a technique video. In this case, I&#39;m going to leverage the online resources to remind them about the training we did earlier in the year. Even if they haven&#39;t checked the resources in a while, they still have access to the material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 1: EXPORT 2010 CLIENT LIST FROM TRAINING DATABASE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I use Highrise for keeping track of all the people in my business universe. It&#39;s super easy to navigate -- both inside the application and in conjunction with other programs. Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://highrisehq.com/extras&#34;&gt;all the different applications&lt;/a&gt; that integrate with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 2: UPLOAD CONTACTS AND TAG THEM TO YOUR CAMPAIGN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My exported list from the training software is identified inside Highrise with a &#34;tag&#34; specific to this campaign. Every contact can have many tags. You get a picture of the different relationships with each client when you look at the tags they collect over time. The real beauty of the tag, though, comes when I use an integrated email marketing application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 3: PULL CAMPAIGN TAG FROM HIGHRISE AND CREATE EMAIL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is the smoothest part by far. No need to download a list from one program and upload it to a new program, worrying about formatting. The email application and contact management application talk to each other through an API (the programs share how they each map data, so the information can flow back and forth). From inside the email application, I can select Highrise contacts, filtered by tag, and create a new mailing list just for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I&#39;ve got my list, crafting an email, or several (haven&#39;t decided yet) is easy in MailChimp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And there you have it, a quick and nerdy explanation of how to use your business systems to create better marketing and pick up the spare change lying around your business!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your Marketing Universe</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/06/your-marketing-universe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2010 10:34:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/06/your-marketing-universe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For movement education professionals, understanding your marketing universe is so important. When I studied the history of astronomy and physics in college, it was fascinating to see how people had tried to better understand the natural world through conceptual models (by the way, the ancient Greeks knew the world was round because of the way their ships came into view on the horizon and Newton developed calculus to explain the motion of the planets). It seems like a fundamental human drive and the value is that it helps organize something that can seem chaotic. That&#39;s the value for you, trying to run a small business, too: turn marketing chaos into order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two models of my marketing universe. I&#39;m not sure which one I like better, but I think they tell you different things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;First, the Funnel model (this is typical of what we see at Brookline Tai Chi):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-404&#34; title=&#34;Student_Funnel&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2010/12/Student_Funnel.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;515&#34; height=&#34;433&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;The value of the funnel model is that you can see how our students&#39; needs change as they progress through the BTC curriculum. To me, the most fascinating branch is the post-intro split between &#34;regulars&#34; and &#34;less regulars&#34;. &#34;Less regulars&#34; (as opposed to &#34;Les Regulars&#34;?) don&#39;t come to the school week-in and week-out, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;as I&#39;ve argued before&lt;/a&gt;, you still should think of them as part of the BTC universe. Here you see that you need to feed them different information to keep them an engaged part of that universe. Whenever we offer a slightly different workshop, for example, these folks come in from the far reaches of the universe to participate. They&#39;re just tuned in to a different radio frequency and we have to find the right signal to send out. Ok, you get the idea ;-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Contrast the Funnel model to the Bull&#39;s-Eye:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-409&#34; title=&#34;Student_Bullseye&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2010/12/Student_Bullseye2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;664&#34; height=&#34;661&#34; /&gt;When I put numbers or names and faces to the Bull&#39;s-Eye, I get a feel for the &#34;weight&#34; of my universe. It feels heavier when the core is bigger, and lighter, harder to grasp, if most of the activity is out in the periphery. I&#39;m always trying to set up our marketing to move toward the center of the Bull&#39;s-Eye, but it&#39;s fine if people live in different rings. Just understanding where they are at is useful, both in terms of the conversations I have with them and the marketing activities we aim at them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;By the way, do you think the Bull&#39;s-Eye looks more like a universe, an atom, or a cell?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>