<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/tai-chi/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/tai-chi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Returning to an Old, Familiar Practice</title>
      <link>/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 09:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s easy to get caught in a linear, progress-oriented way of thinking about your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s new? What can I learn next? Am I improving...all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get so caught up in doing it right and refining every little detail that you can lose sight of the what&#39;s really great about practice in the first place...the restoration, integration, and feeling of wholeness you can walk away with each time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Return to a Familiar Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What if, instead of trying to always master something new, you went back to a practice you hadn&#39;t done in a while?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if that felt the same way it feels to see an old friend? Or visit a place you hadn&#39;t been in a long time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s an old friend I guess I&#39;d like you to meet (part of me was hoping this would be buried in YouTube&#39;s archives, never to surface again. Oh well!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I wanted to see what it looked like from the outside to hold a posture for an extended period of time. In this video, I&#39;m holding the final posture of Tai Chi&#39;s Single Whip for 25 minute...but it&#39;s sped up so you can really see the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/WALkgFQ9a2w&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s awful, right? You can see all the collapsing and poor breathing as I struggle through the duration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait. Why did I want to share this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oh, right, because every time I&#39;ve returned to this practice since that time, six months, a year, three years later, I can settle back into some of the practice grooves I established back then.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you return to an energetic practice like Standing Qigong, try not to just replicate the outward shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The feel of the posture (or movement) -- heavy, light, twisting, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The energetic pattern that defines the practice -- sinking, rising, absorbing, projecting, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The mind, the body, and the energetic pattern slotting into alignment, not immediately, but over a few minutes or several repetitions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last piece, the alignment, is critical. Part of the challenge of remembering an old practice is that you remember what it felt like &lt;em&gt;at the end&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, you&#39;re settling in to it, so you have to keep the end in mind, but patiently wait for the pieces to slot together again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, this waiting, and the eventual alignment, returning to a familiar place, is what is truly restorative and energizing about this method of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Return is the movement of the Tao.&lt;br /&gt;
Yielding is the way of the Tao.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things are born of being.&lt;br /&gt;
Being is born of non-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: right;&#34;&gt;- Tao Te Ching, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/lao-tzu/works/tao-te-ching/te.htm&#34;&gt;Chapter 40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi and Embodiment for Anxiety and Depression</title>
      <link>/2014/04/01/tai-chi-and-embodiment-for-anxiety-and-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 18:11:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/01/tai-chi-and-embodiment-for-anxiety-and-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the pleasure of recording a conversation with my friend and Tai Chi colleague Dorothy Fitzer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing on her background in movement, energy arts, and psychotherapy, Dorothy has put together a very interesting group of practitioners from several different modalities to address the question of &lt;strong&gt;how embodiment practices can lead to nourishing, healing, and even transformative experiences.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/reYPtvRbeE0?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was thrilled to make the case that this is at the core of so much of what we do in Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dorothy and I discussed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tai Chi&#39;s techniques for &lt;a title=&#34;How To Calm Your Mind Through Movement&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/&#34;&gt;synchronizing the movement of the mind and the body&lt;/a&gt; - and the grounding effect this has on the mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How you learn to recognize &#34;doing&#34; as another layer of tension when you practice any form of &lt;a title=&#34;Qigong and Meditative State&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/qigong-and-meditative-state/&#34;&gt;Taoist Qigong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different Tai Chi/qigong techniques for getting the mind to quiet down and experience stillness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Yin and Yang of Depression and Anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How &lt;a title=&#34;Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi&#39;s interactive practices&lt;/a&gt; teach you to resolve interpersonal conflicts without fear and bask in the spontaneity that comes from not going into fear-based reactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a few more things...&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can listen in on our conversation on Tuesday, April 8, but Dorothy will be sharing all of the conversations, some live and some pre-recorded, over the next two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To find out about all the other speakers and get alerts for each event, &lt;a href=&#34;http://theembodiedsoulcentertrainingseries1.com/&#34;&gt;visit The Embodied Soul Center&#39;s website&lt;/a&gt;. The sign-up box is right at the top.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 and the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Book</title>
      <link>/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 16:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m very excited to share some news about two big projects with you today: Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s annual Immersion Week and the publication of the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance as a physical book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/bATZ5_2SMno?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join me from Tuesday, April 22 - Friday, April 25 at Brookline Tai Chi in Boston for &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Energy Gates Moving Qigong Exercises&lt;/a&gt;. Times, cost, and registration details in the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance is now available for purchase on Amazon, but you can also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.createspace.com/4498724&#34;&gt;get your copy of the physical book directly from the publisher&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice, Stress, and Building Outward Connections</title>
      <link>/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 11:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&#34;At some point, don&#39;t we have to ask ourselves, &#34;Aren&#39;t I healthy enough?&#34;  Don&#39;t I need to work on &#34;waking up&#34;, on manifesting kindness and patience, and being other oriented?&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s from a conversation we&#39;ve been having in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/&#34;&gt;Inner Form discussion&lt;/a&gt; group and it got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be learning to cultivate your chi to heal old injuries or for the inner experience of meditative exploration, but at some point, shouldn&#39;t your practice extend into the world around you, to the people in your life, and your work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&#39;m often in favor of letting these connections emerge naturally, but the comment above and this TED talk on stress are pushing me to make &#34;practicing in the world&#34; a little more explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making Stress Your Friend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Stanford health psychologist Kelly McGonigal gives a great talk on transforming your relationship to stress. And it could save your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the video description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stress. It makes your heart pound, your breathing quicken and your forehead sweat. But while stress has been made into a public health enemy, new research suggests that stress may only be bad for you if you believe that to be the case.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RcGyVTAoXEU?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practicing in the World&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From this perspective, &lt;strong&gt;cultivating your internal energy is not about getting some horrible disease out of your system.&lt;/strong&gt; It&#39;s a way to process, digest, and to grow from what&#39;s useful while shedding what&#39;s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice homework this week: you know what it&#39;s like to find a special, quiet place to practice to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;build your chi&lt;/a&gt;, but what about your next interaction with another person as the best place to practice? Can you pause, hold the mind the same way when you do in your practice and let the encounter unfold the same way the qigong mind allows chi to resolve itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might draw some inspiration from &lt;a title=&#34;Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/&#34;&gt;Push Hands&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a title=&#34;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/24/transforming-conflict-with-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi-style conflict resolution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dust Off Your Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>/2013/12/06/dust-off-your-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2013 08:59:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/12/06/dust-off-your-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It looks like Energy Arts is releasing another set of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/tai-chi-mastery-program#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=82cf549a&#34;&gt;The Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;. This is a short message to those of you who have the program sitting on your bookshelf, collecting dust, or still pristinely packaged: &lt;strong&gt;Let&#39;s open it up and get to work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Now, if you&#39;re not familiar with this program, take a look at this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter  wp-image-4332&#34; alt=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#39; Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/10/Tai-Chi-Mastery-Program.png&#34; width=&#34;576&#34; height=&#34;565&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;That&#39;s a lot of DVDs!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&#39;s Inside The Tai Chi Mastery Program?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It all started back in 2011 when we spent a month in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011/&#34;&gt;England training the Wu Style Short Form with Bruce&lt;/a&gt;. Everyday for 8 hours or more, we worked on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choreography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relaxation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push Hands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meditation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more...&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here&#39;s what it was like to completely rebuild my Tai Chi practice at this training:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/HoXz88Vyxe0?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These events are always transformative, but what has been so cool is having the Mastery Program as a resource. And in the year since the initial release, I&#39;ve been working hard to create practice resources for you that make it even easier to learn Tai Chi using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/tai-chi-mastery-program#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=82cf549a&#34;&gt;Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Want to learn more about how to use the Tai Chi Mastery Program to build your Chi in 2014?  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-m11egdjc17es6rb&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/m11egdjc17es6rb&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var m11egdjc17es6rb;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;m11egdjc17es6rb&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;342&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;host&#39;:&#39;wufoo.com&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { m11egdjc17es6rb = new WufooForm();m11egdjc17es6rb.initialize(options);m11egdjc17es6rb.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maintaining the Four Points in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2013 08:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; alt=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, the question of &#34;should I rotate my spine in Tai Chi&#34; has come up frequently and led to a lot of confusion with some of our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are told to maintain the &#34;Four Points&#34; - a sort of internal frame that runs between the shoulders and the hips, forming a box that keeps the spine from rotating or side bending while you practice Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people hear this rule and think, &#34;but the spine has joints that rotate and bend in more than one plane&#34; or &#34;show me any athletic movement that doesn&#39;t make use of the rotational movement of the spine to generate power.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you reconcile these common sense observations with a principle that seems to limit natural movement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s look at the developmental context in a few stages of learning Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Maintaining the Four Points for Beginners&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First of all, you need to appreciate the context for each question and observation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start learning Tai Chi, most people haven&#39;t spent a lot of time separating upper body and lower body movement or thinking about which one drives the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for beginners, &lt;strong&gt;holding the Four Points in place allows you to more easily steer the shoulders from the hips&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you practice at this level, without rotating the spine, you train out all the upper-body-led exaggeration in your movements. You begin to learn how to feel the &#34;power coming from the legs, being steered by the waist, and expressed in the hands,&#34; to paraphrase the Tai Chi Classics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t follow the rule of the Four Points at this level, you tend to retain upper body dominance, never finding proper folding in &lt;a title=&#34;Basic Training: Focus on Your Kwa Squat&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/&#34;&gt;the hip joints and kwa&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hitting Your Limits&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, at a certain point, holding the Four Points as an &lt;em&gt;external frame &lt;/em&gt;starts to limit your movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you watch this video on the components of Roll Back, or Lu, you will see, especially around 3:30, the way that twisting and rotation enhances the subtly, connection, and power of your movements.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/PL8TPEu3TWw?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you progress to interactive practices, the additional rotational power you can generate from micro movements in the spine will improve the quality of your response to an incoming force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to only turning from the hips, having the capacity to create rotation in the spine is like typing with all 26 letters, not just 14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What the Rotators Miss&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, you can see this in the above video to a degree, but I want to also point out one of the less obvious benefits of maintaining what looks like a more rigid frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You have to take into account the difference between bone and soft tissue.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons we focus on maintaining bony alignments, beyond developing coordination and healthy movement patterns that don&#39;t wear on the joints, is finding separate movement in the fascia and muscles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you let the soft tissues turn around the bones, you begin to loosen them. If your bones and tissues are always turning together, you miss deeper internal loosening of these layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, a movement that looks very rigid and square may actually contain spirals throughout the soft tissues, but this is not obvious from the outside unless you&#39;ve been trained to look for subtle signs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you make a rule like &#34;never break the external frame of the Four Points,&#34; you don&#39;t account for someone&#39;s coordination, sensitivity, or body development. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several layers to the process of cultivating unified spiral-driven movement, but a simple rule like that doesn&#39;t account for very different needs at different stages of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, &#34;always twist the spine&#34; as a rule will keep you from developing certain sensitivity and connection and shouldn&#39;t be treated as an absolute outside of the right context either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? How do you make sense of these kinds of rules and principles in your own practice? Has your sense of their meaning changed over time?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seminar Recap - Detailed Report from ChicagoTaiChi.org</title>
      <link>/2013/11/17/seminar-recap-detailed-report-from-chicagotaichi-org/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 14:15:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/17/seminar-recap-detailed-report-from-chicagotaichi-org/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-4965&#34; alt=&#34;Buddha at the Art Institute of Chicago&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/11/20131108_141048-e1384715482717-168x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;168&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Checking in with one of my favorite sculptures at the Art Institute&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was thrilled to be able to share a weekend of Tai Chi in Chicago earlier this month, thanks to Energy Arts Instructor Chris Cinnamon and his students at Enso Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris just posted an incredibly detailed report summarizing the workshop &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chicagotaichi.org/2013/11/17/putting-more-chi-in-our-tai-chi-in-chicago-update-on-enso-tai-chis-fall-workshop-with-dan-kleiman/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read between the lines a little bit, you can come up with some great ways to structure your own practice. Think of the whole day as a single practice session. Can you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle in&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let your mind and energy sink all the way through you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expand your awareness 360 degrees around you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simultaneously find new space inside your body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grow that new space outward without tension or strain&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To me, this would be a nice restorative and engaging practice session. How do you normally structure yours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chicagotaichi.org/2013/11/17/putting-more-chi-in-our-tai-chi-in-chicago-update-on-enso-tai-chis-fall-workshop-with-dan-kleiman/&#34;&gt;Check out Chris&#39; post for some more ideas.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thanks again to everyone who came out for some Tai Chi!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Rooting, Sinking, and More in Chicago</title>
      <link>/2013/10/11/tai-chi-rooting-sinking-and-more-in-chicago/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 16:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/11/tai-chi-rooting-sinking-and-more-in-chicago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/5/5c/Calder_Flamingo.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;253&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Inspiration for Rooting and Lengthening in Chicago&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 9, I&#39;ll be teaching a seminar for my friend Chris Cinnamon at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chicagotaichi.org/&#34;&gt;Enso Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt; (registration details &lt;a title=&#34;Seminars&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/seminars/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we&#39;ll continue the &#34;Put More Chi in Your Tai Chi&#34; theme that we started last year by focusing on Tai Chi Rooting, Sinking Chi, Dissolving, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is to give everyone a clear sense of how nourishing it can be to find your root and feed it through solo exercises and interactive partner practice. Basically, you learn to continuously release and dissolve tension, stress, and pain, but more than just shedding uncomfortable feelings, you actually tap into a restorative wellspring of energy that keeps bubbling up the more you go down into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re in the area, come join us for a great day of training!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For background on the seminar, it helps to understand the different facets of Tai Chi Rooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Two Kinds of Tai Chi Rooting&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My Push Hands teacher &lt;a title=&#34;The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/&#34;&gt;Don Miller&lt;/a&gt; explains that there are two kind of &#34;root&#34; in Tai Chi: &lt;strong&gt;intrinsic root&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;situational root&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intrinsic root is the degree of root you are either born with, or have developed through practice over time, that spills into everything you do. Think of the most grounded person you know. They exude a high degree of intrinsic root, either physically or emotionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the fruits of Tai Chi practice have to do with increasing your intrinsic root and this is often why we see people mellow or soften as their practice matures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cultivating Intrinsic Root&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The most common way to build intrinsic root in Tai Chi is through standing practices, either holding qigong postures or postures drawn directly from the Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you&#39;re not just &#34;standing around.&#34; You have to go through &lt;a title=&#34;Guide to Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;several stages&lt;/a&gt; to get to rooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, you have to land the mind inside the body, or at least on, and begin to become present to sensations other than pain and discomfort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, you have to let the mind soak deeper and deeper into the body, transforming the tissues, making them wetter, heavier, and denser. This will happen naturally, like water soaking into a sponge, as circulation of fluids and chi increases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, as you refine your posture and alignments, the heavy feeling will move &lt;em&gt;through you&lt;/em&gt;, instead of just weighing you down (which is a sign of internal collapse). You start to feel lighter and more open, but someone lifting up your arms or legs would still perceive the heaviness.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In some standing qigong methods, like &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;Opening the Energy Gates&lt;/a&gt;, there is also a method for refining your sense of blocked internal energy, so that you begin to &#34;dissolve&#34; blocked chi. While dissolving is a healthy practice to undertake for its own sake, in this context, &lt;strong&gt;it gives you an extra advantage: as you become more aware of your internal energy, you start to feel the &#34;chi of ____.&#34; &lt;/strong&gt;In other words, you feel the chi of your leg or your kidneys or your feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of rooting, you begin to notice that your mind, and therefore your chi, has jumped up into your head, and is no longer feeding your root through your legs....and you notice this right before you go flying away!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rooting as a Response&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the following video, I show how situational root, or rooting as a response to another person, has to do with finding just the right amount of sinking and grounding, not fighting or running away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/dbt1nC9jypI&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here again, Lee I-Yu&#39;s advice from &lt;a href=&#34;http://scheele.org/lee/classics.html#Essentials&#34;&gt;The Essentials of the Practice of the Form and Push Hands&lt;/a&gt; is very helpful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Desiring to attract to emptiness and deflect a thousand pounds, first you must know yourself and others. If you want to know yourself and others, you must give up yourself and follow others. If you give up yourself and follow others, first you must have the correct timing and position. To obtain the correct timing and position, you must first make your body one unit. Desiring to make the body one unit, you must first eliminate hollows and protuberances. To make the whole body without breaks or holes, you must first have the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; [spirit of vitality] and &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; [vital life energy] excited and expanded. If you want the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; activated and expanded, you must first raise the spirit (pay attention) and the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; should not be unfocussed. To have your &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; not unfocussed, you must first have the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i &lt;/i&gt;gather and penetrate the bones. Desiring the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; to penetrate the bones, first you must strengthen the two thighs and loosen the two shoulders and let the &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; sink down.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In other words, what makes situational root work is listening to the other person and responding to them at the right time, with the right sensitivity, with unified energy and an open body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What that will look like in your practice, over time, is something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to feel your body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sink your chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open your energy field and correct alignments so that the physical body helps the energy become as full as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add more complex movements that challenge your ability to stay present to your own internal state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn interactive practices that teach you to tune into someone else&#39;s movement and energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and finally, practice being grounded in the face of challenging interactions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Of course, like all Taoist learning processes, this one is circular. So while there are stages of skills to master here, you will also find that every time you go back to something earlier on the list, you will get more and more depth and richness out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the November 9 workshop, we will try to touch on as much of this as possible, including techniques for unifying the body and energy, sinking and dissolving chi, feeding the root through interactive practices, and also exploring how to use the solo Tai Chi form as a vessel for integrating as much of this as possible. &lt;a title=&#34;Seminars&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/seminars/&#34;&gt;Learn more here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem with Learning Tai Chi from the Classics</title>
      <link>/2013/10/09/the-problem-with-learning-tai-chi-from-the-classics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 15:39:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/09/the-problem-with-learning-tai-chi-from-the-classics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4937&#34; alt=&#34;Yang Chen Fu Single Whip&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/10/yang_chen_fu-Single_whip_-256x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;256&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you read the Tai Chi Classics and look at photos of the old masters, everything looks graceful, flowing, and full of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, your daily practice can be full of aches, pains, kinks, binds and the feeling that you&#39;re never really going to get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of territory between, &#34;oh man, it hurts, I&#39;ll never get past it&#34; and &#34;be still like a mountain, flowing like a great river&#34; that isn&#39;t discussed in the Tai Chi Classics or most books on Tai Chi. They tend to just give you the gold standard for where you want to go, with not a lot of detail about what it&#39;s like to travel that road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I want to talk about some of those points in between, and the general challenge of learning from the Classics. I will refer mostly to &lt;a href=&#34;http://scheele.org/lee/classics.html#Yangs10&#34;&gt;Yang&#39;s Ten Important Points&lt;/a&gt;, by Yang Chen Fu, available from Lee Scheele (thank you!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, when you look at Yang&#39;s list, or begin receiving instruction, you feel like you have a checklist of things you &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first three points tell you how to hold your body:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.) Head upright to let the shen [spirit of vitality] rise to the top of the head.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&#39;t use li [external strength], or the neck will be stiff and the ch&#39;i [vital life energy] and blood cannot flow through. It is necessary to have a natural and lively feeling. If the spirit cannot reach the headtop, it cannot raise.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
2.) Sink the chest and pluck up the back.&lt;/strong&gt; The chest is depressed naturally inward so that the ch&#39;i can sink to the tan-t&#39;ien [field of elixir]. Don&#39;t expand the chest: the ch&#39;i gets stuck there and the body becomes top-heavy. The heel will be too light and can be uprooted. Pluck up the back and the ch&#39;i sticks to the back; depress the chest and you can pluck up the back. Then you can discharge force through the spine. You will be a peerless boxer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.) Sung [Relax] the waist.&lt;/strong&gt; The waist is the commander of the whole body. If you can sung the waist, then the two legs will have power and the lower part will be firm and stable. Substantial and insubstantial change, and this is based on the turning of the waist. It is said &#34;the source of the postures lies in the waist. If you cannot get power, seek the defect in the legs and waist.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Do you know what would happen if I read this list to a class on Day One? You&#39;d see people lifting, sinking, squirming and bobbing up and down trying to make all 3 happen at the same time. In fact, even more experienced Tai Chi practitioners continue to practice in a mindset where they are constantly worried about whether they are doing 7 or 8 different things right all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice this way, how can you follow point number 8?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8.) Harmonize the internal and external.&lt;/strong&gt; In the practice of T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan the main thing is the &lt;em&gt;shen&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore it is said &#34;the spirit is the commander and the body is subordinate.&#34; If you can raise the spirit, then the movements will naturally be agile. The postures are not beyond insubstantial and substantial, opening and closing. That which is called open means not only the hands and feet are open, but the mind is also open. That which is called closed means not only the hands and feet are closed, but the mind is also closed. When you can make the inside and outside become one, then it becomes complete.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you focus on the alignment checklist, there is no room for the mind to open and close. Whatever you are trying work on is contracted, locked down, and disintegrated from everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this problem sends people in the opposite direction. They just go by feel, tuning out physical sensations, body awareness and internal connection in exchange for a state of bliss generated from images and ideas, not grounded in the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So how do you approach all the things you &#34;should&#34; do in Tai Chi for health and still make it enjoyable? (And yes, get better at Tai Chi too.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some common stumbling blocks and my recommendation for gradually dissolving them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stiffness in The Body&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It&#39;s not uncommon to feel stiff when you try to achieve certain body alignments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Yang&#39;s Ten Important points, his description of integrated movement is actually incredibly useful for how you should hold yourself posturally:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;9.) Move with continuity.&lt;/b&gt; As to the external schools, their &lt;i&gt;chin&lt;/i&gt; is the Latter Heaven brute &lt;i&gt;chin&lt;/i&gt;. Therefore it is finite. There are connections and breaks. During the breaks the old force is exhausted and the new force has not yet been born. At these moments it is very easy for others to take advantage. T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan uses &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; and not &lt;i&gt;li&lt;/i&gt;. From beginning to end it is continuous and not broken. It is circular and again resumes. It revolves and has no limits. The original &lt;i&gt;Classics&lt;/i&gt; say it is &#34;like a great river rolling on unceasingly.&#34; and that the circulation of the &lt;i&gt;chin&lt;/i&gt; is &#34;drawing silk from a cocoon &#34; They all talk about being connected together.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So, when you attempt to hold an alignment (in a static posture, for example), move yourself into it and continue to move into it imperceptibly, &#34;like a great river rolling on unceasingly.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This applies to: the lift through the crown of the head, sinking the tailbone/relaxing the lower back, lengthening the elbows away from the spine, and generally anything else where the bones have to move into a particular position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Forcing Your Body to Change&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The problem with using &#34;Latter Heaven brute &lt;em&gt;chin&lt;/em&gt;&#34;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;or overt muscular force to correct yourself is that the tissues never have time to release and you lose the sensitivity that will also allow you to feel what is happening energetically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yang covers this in point number 6:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;6.) Use the mind instead of force.&lt;/b&gt; The T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan &lt;i&gt;Classics&lt;/i&gt; say, &#34;all of this means use &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; [mind-intent] and not &lt;i&gt;li&lt;/i&gt;.&#34; In practicing T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan the whole body relaxes. Don&#39;t let one ounce of force remain in the blood vessels, bones, and ligaments to tie yourself up. Then you can be agile and able to change. You will be able to turn freely and easily. Doubting this, how can you increase your power?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body has meridians like the ground has ditches and trenches. If not obstructed the water can flow. If the meridian is not closed, the &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; goes through. If the whole body has hard force and it fills up the meridians, the &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; and the blood stop and the turning is not smooth and agile. Just pull one hair and the whole body is off-balance. If you use &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt;, and not &lt;i&gt;li&lt;/i&gt;, then the &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; goes to a place in the body and the &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; follows it. The &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; and the blood circulate. If you do this every day and never stop, after a long time you will have &lt;i&gt;nei chin&lt;/i&gt; [real internal strength]. The T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan&lt;i&gt; Classics&lt;/i&gt; say, &#34;when you are extremely soft, you become extremely hard and strong.&#34; Someone who has extremely good T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan &lt;i&gt;kung fu&lt;/i&gt; has arms like iron wrapped with cotton and the weight is very heavy. As for the external schools, when they use &lt;i&gt;li&lt;/i&gt;, they reveal &lt;i&gt;li&lt;/i&gt;. When they don&#39;t use &lt;i&gt;li&lt;/i&gt;, they are too light and floating. There &lt;i&gt;chin&lt;/i&gt; is external and locked together. The &lt;i&gt;li&lt;/i&gt; of the external schools is easily led and moved, and not too be esteemed.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Our challenge is to always be connected and moving enough physically, but also leave room in our awareness for the energetic flows and sensations that arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, this method of practice will help you discover where your energy is blocked and get at the source of aches and pains or resolve them without you having to fixate on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Too Relaxed and Collapsed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you feel collapsed, often in the knees when people are first learning stances, or in the abdomen if you feel tired or out of breath when you practice, you need to follow the first point, or at least a version of it. Remember point number one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.) Head upright to let the shen [spirit of vitality] rise to the top of the head.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&#39;t use li [external strength], or the neck will be stiff and the ch&#39;i [vital life energy] and blood cannot flow through. It is necessary to have a natural and lively feeling. If the spirit cannot reach the headtop, it cannot raise.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Collapsed knees or similar feelings that come from trying to sink the energy, lower your center of gravity, or create a root are all symptoms of going too far. You need opening and rising to connect, literally, all the way to the crown of the head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the complex matrix of bones, joints, tissues, and energy channels, you&#39;ve closed down an important flow point. Instead of thinking there is something wrong with a particular body part, you need to investigate what supports it and how you are connecting through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Give Up Yourself and Follow Others - Finding a Tai Chi Process&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, Scheele does share an essay that talks about process and not just goals. The theme is an explanation of another saying from the Classics, that &#34;four ounces deflects a thousand pounds,&#34; probably the most famous description of high-level Tai Chi as an interactive practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you read the beginning of the essay, you&#39;ll start to see how the holy grail of Tai Chi&#39;s interactive capabilities can be traced all the way back to your attitude starting out in solo practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;http://scheele.org/lee/classics.html#Essentials&#34;&gt;The Essentials of the Practice of the Form and Push Hands,&lt;/a&gt; by Lee I-Yu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Formerly people said: &#34;being able to attract to emptiness, you can use four ounces to deflect a thousand pounds.&#34; Not being able to attract to emptiness, you cannot deflect a thousand pounds. The words are simple, but the meaning is complete. The beginner cannot understand it. Here I add some words to explain it. If someone is ambitious to learn this art, he can find some way to enter it and every day he will have some improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desiring to attract to emptiness and deflect a thousand pounds, first you must know yourself and others. If you want to know yourself and others, you must give up yourself and follow others. If you give up yourself and follow others, first you must have the correct timing and position. To obtain the correct timing and position, you must first make your body one unit. Desiring to make the body one unit, you must first eliminate hollows and protuberances. To make the whole body without breaks or holes, you must first have the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; [spirit of vitality] and &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; [vital life energy] excited and expanded. If you want the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; activated and expanded, you must first raise the spirit (pay attention) and the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; should not be unfocussed. To have your &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; not unfocussed, you must first have the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i &lt;/i&gt;gather and penetrate the bones. Desiring the &lt;i&gt;shen&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; to penetrate the bones, first you must strengthen the two thighs and loosen the two shoulders and let the &lt;i&gt;ch&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; sink down.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I think we need to expose ourselves to more of this kind of process discussion. Too often, the most experienced practitioners forgot how they trained to achieve their high levels of skill and those of us at lower levels don&#39;t yet know where we are going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I get a great &#34;process&#34; report, I&#39;ll share it with you here. Do you have any?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Practice Advice from Master Feng Zhiqiang</title>
      <link>/2013/09/26/tai-chi-practice-advice-from-master-feng-zhiqiang/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 14:44:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/26/tai-chi-practice-advice-from-master-feng-zhiqiang/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Feng Zhiqiang was a famous Tai Chi Master from Beijing who was a major influence on my teacher &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;. Master Feng did some teaching in the West as well and we are fortunate to have access to a transcript of a 2001 workshop he taught in the Bay Area (thanks to the folks at SilkReeler.com for making &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.silkreeler.com/drupal/?q=node/24&#34;&gt;this transcript&lt;/a&gt; available and thanks to Igor for sending it my way!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here he is in 1986 performing a Chen Style Form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/gVtO7pod5hM?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2001 workshop, Master Feng gives some great advice about different dimensions of practicing Tai Chi and qigong. I think you&#39;ll find the advice relevant to your own practice. Throughout the interview Master Feng is humble about his incredible skill and what&#39;s more, you can really tell that he was still actively practicing and learning, not resting on his credentials as the Master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even here, when he&#39;s describing a training process, we learn that he&#39;s working on it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master Feng says, &#34;... Gentle practice is more effective than forceful practice. Lengthening is better than contracting. It&#39;s not just a simple matter of health, it&#39;s also a very good stretching exercise.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which his student replies, &#34;Some of us may have noticed Grandmaster Feng has much longer arms than the rest of us. That&#39;s a result of practicing lengthening. Thirty years ago when we took a picture together, I noticed in the photograph that Master Feng&#39;s arm is about one finger longer than mine.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The master always keeps working!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve pulled a series of quotes and questions and answers from the transcript that I found particularly helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Structure and Body Alignment for Tai Chi&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even when you are standing upright, your weight should only be on one leg. When you&#39;re standing you should be relaxed and have your weight shifting from one leg to the other, never stationary and fifty-fifty. But not too obvious, that looks too funny. Don&#39;t let it be visible to an observer, but you should shift your weight from one leg to the other. Same thing with the foot. When you are standing you should never tighten your foot, and you should also flex it gently. Never stay in one position. Practicing in a relaxed manner is better than tensing up.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Whole-Body Coordination and Power&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Curved line is better than straight line. Even when your limbs are lengthened, they should also be curved. The body is the same. It should never be too straight. There should always be a curve somewhere. The Taiji body has five bows [Verbal clarification from translator: as in &#34;bow&#34; and arrow]. One arm, the other arm &amp;mdash; two bows. One leg, the other leg, and your spine - your body. So, five bows. There is a Taiji saying that &#34;once the body has cultivated five bows, (and can express the spring-like power) there is no equal opponent under Heaven.&#34; [Demonstration] This is one bow as well. Curving the chest is also a bow. Only by practicing in a slow and lengthening manner, you can then cultivate the spring-like energy. Something with springiness is very strong. If you drop it, it will never break. But if you have something that is hard and brittle, when you drop it it will shatter. That&#39;s what the old martial arts masters would say. If your body has five bows and you have this spring-like power, you will have no equal opponent under Heaven. Practicing martial art, you should know the theory. Only by knowing the theory can you grasp the martial aspect of Taiji.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Uncontrollable Shaking during Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the Q&amp;amp;A section of the transcript, Master Feng gives some direct, and indirect, practice advice. The first question is about standing qigong. He is asked, &#34;Basically, how should we stand? Any tips on standing? Some students have experienced interesting phenomena like uncontrollable shaking, whether that&#39;s good or bad, and whether we should do anything about it.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master Feng starts off with what appears to be a very theoretical answer, but I found it to be a pretty accurate description of the &#34;interesting phenomena.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone, greetings. This is a good question. Standing posture is Wuji, [Translator note: as in &#34;ultimate nothing&#34;]. Standing posture is posture of Wuji. Wuji is the state before Heaven and Earth was formed, when everything was in the primordial soup, when yin and yang were not differentiated. Wuji is silence, not moving, is quiet, whereas Taiji, the name of our practice, is opposite. Even though it looks as if standing posture/standing meditation there&#39;s no movement, however inside, just like in the primordial soup, there&#39;s always something, there&#39;s always something moving. When the internal subtle movement suddenly reaches critical level, then there&#39;s a Big Bang. That&#39;s when the light stuff floats up and the heavy stuff sinks down. And those that floats up form the heaven, and things that condenses become the Earth. The Big Bang essentially causes Taiji to happen. Taiji is yin and yang, the interplay between yin and yang. Between the interplay of yin and yang, everything else in this world is born. Without Taiji there&#39;s nothing, there&#39;s not even us. Everything, all life forms. Plants, animals. Human being are at the top of the animal kingdom, we are spiritual beings. The relationship between Heaven, Human, and Earth is the three pillars of the universe. Basically, from Wuji, even though there&#39;s no apparent movement, there&#39;s always something happening internally. When the time is right, the universe is formed, and Taiji is born. Same thing when we&#39;re doing standing meditation. There&#39;s no apparent movement, but there&#39;s always a little subtle shift. And after you&#39;ve been doing it for a while you could generate so much energy in your body that you&#39;d just have to move, that&#39;s the time for you to start doing your form. Within Wuji, even though the external is without motion, inside there is the beating of the heart, the circulation of blood, the flowing of chi. So within the motionless external something is contained inside that is moving.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
He continues with a very detailed cosmological description of the process of moving from Wu Ji to Tai Chi and beyond, which I won&#39;t add here. But then he returns to a very practical tip. I bolded the parts I thought were especially important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s go back to the standing meditation and involuntary movement. Not everyone will experience it. Some people will experience different feelings, different sensations, when your qigong practice is up to a certain level. Movement is one of them. It&#39;s normal to move. &lt;strong&gt;However, do not seek movement for its own sake.&lt;/strong&gt; The movement is a side effect. What we want to do is keep our attention, our intention, within our DanTien, and let the movement be. If the movement continues without bothering you, that&#39;s fine. But if it gets bigger and bigger, then you should use your will power, your mind, to tell it &#34;look, just stop it; don&#39;t move.&#34; Usually that will take away or control the movement. However if the movement is so big that it&#39;s beyond your control, then it&#39;s time to stop. You should do the DanTien turning exercise, gathering all the Qi that is wandering about back into your DanTien, and stop doing QiGong. &lt;strong&gt;Some movements are actually good phenomena. However we should not seek the phenomena. We should just focus on practicing QiGong.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Fitting Practice into Our Busy Lives&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, I love how he addressed the question about learning all these forms and exercises, but not having enough time each day to practice them. If you follow his rules for practicing on limited time, you&#39;ll definitely turn even a few minutes into high-quality practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we have limited time, what should we do on a daily basis? You should at least cover two things: One is qigong, as many movements as you can do, and then the 24-form. However if you don&#39;t even have time to cover those two things, what you can do is, put the 24 aside and concentrate on a subset of qigong exercises. And those examples he was showing us, &#34;Heaven open, Earth close,&#34; or &#34;Earth open, Heaven close,&#34; that&#39;s one. Or &#34;double hand open-close,&#34; that&#39;s another one. So if you do those, that&#39;s ok. But you need to do more than nine repetitions if you just want to do one thing. And he&#39;s suggesting a few hundred repetitions. At least a hundred times or two hundred times. He&#39;s saying that because qigong is the foundation, is the core of our practice, if you don&#39;t have time for anything else, then do the core. However, it&#39;s best that you try to put aside at least an hour a day to do qigong as well as the 24.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So there you have it, practice advice from a Master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, last spring, Master Feng passed away. You can read more about him &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/tai-chi/feng-zhi-qiang-death/&#34;&gt;in this tribute from Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Five Movement Centers</title>
      <link>/2013/08/22/exploring-the-five-movement-centers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2013 16:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/22/exploring-the-five-movement-centers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Allow me to share with you a Tai Chi principle so simple and clear that it is often overlooked, even by practitioners who have been doing Tai Chi for 10 years or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Five Movement Centers is a template for understand HOW you move and applying it to any form you know or any repetitive movement you can perform, like going for a walk, is going to have a serious impact on how grounded, fluid, and connected you feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this clip from the &lt;a title=&#34;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/better-balance/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/a&gt;, Don Miller demonstrates each of the Movement Centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch how his shifting changes as he goes through all five. Do you recognize these patterns?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9F2cP6r10I8?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it out and let me know how it feels!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Inner Form of Balance</title>
      <link>/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 09:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4807&#34; alt=&#34;Ocean Balance Rocks&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/08/iStock_000020131551XSmall-300x198.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;198&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When my first Tai Chi teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis Tai Chi Resources&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis-tai-chi-resources/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, came back to the US forty years ago to spread the Tai Chi he learned in China, he found out that many basic Tai Chi concepts were not being taught, either because of communications issues or lack of knowledge. Only a fraction of the vast potential of the art was being shared. Bruce set out to teach &lt;em&gt;the Inner Form of Tai Chi&lt;/em&gt; and that&#39;s what I have studied for the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of endless forms and choreography, we dove into the inner workings &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/&#34;&gt;that make Tai Chi so powerful for restoring health &lt;/a&gt;and unlocking hidden internal energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Tai Chi is moving into a new phase of popular understanding in the West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Brookline Tai Chi, we are being approached more and more often by insurance companies, federal and state government agencies, and research universities to weigh in on what makes an effective Tai Chi balance training program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi is being brought into a medical context, but I worry that we will just repeat Tai Chi&#39;s last emergence onto the Western scene: as a watered-down shell of what it could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that reason, I have sought out another champion of the Inner Form approach to Tai Chi to help me share with you the real Tai Chi Way to Better Balance. Don Ethan Miller has practiced and taught Tai Chi for more than 40 years, won national titles in Tai Chi Push Hands and has, in my opinion, a unique, direct, and profound approach to Tai Chi education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re working together on the &lt;a title=&#34;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/better-balance/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/a&gt; and I wanted to share with you why I think Don&#39;s approach to teaching Tai Chi is going to be so useful for your own practice and for when you want to share Tai Chi with the people around you whose balance is failing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simple, Yet Profound&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The exercises in the program may seem simple at first. They are accessible to almost any level of physical fitness and balance. In fact, the exercises are precisely layered (more on that below) to allow almost anyone to regain their balance safely and gradually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&#39;s the thing. I have seen firsthand, watching Don teach these exercises to people who have done Tai Chi for 5, 10 or even 20 years, that if you, the experienced Tai Chi practitioner, approach the program with an open mind, you will reignite your stale or faltering Tai Chi practice. Seasoned practitioners will find depth in the simplest instructions here and marvel at the layers of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re anything like me, you&#39;ll be jealous of the beginners who take on this program, because they&#39;re getting the depth you had to search for years to find, going from teacher to teacher for bits and pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Feel, Then Do&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For those of you who are new to Tai Chi, chances are, if you wander into your local YMCA or church Tai Chi class, you&#39;ll be thrown into &#34;The Form.&#34; With a great teacher, the form will be presented alongside the principles (Inner Form!) that make the movements work. Too often, though, the principles are absent and you&#39;re just asked to follow along until you get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To us, especially if you have the urgent need to improve your balance, this is the long way around&amp;hellip;in the best-case scenario. At worst, you fumble around, get frustrated and quit. No benefit there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won&#39;t find a forms-based approach here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, follow this simple rule as you work through the exercises in the program: &lt;strong&gt;feel, then do&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a practically limitless space to feel into when you open up your inner world with Tai Chi. From &lt;a title=&#34;Wu Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/wu-chi/&#34;&gt;the very first exercise&lt;/a&gt;, you&#39;ll be asked to explore by feel. This is Tai Chi from the inside out. It&#39;s all about what you learn to feel. And feeling leads to moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After each exercise, you will also feel and reflect on what you&#39;ve just done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, Don is like a master chef. He&#39;s crafted a book of recipes for you here. All the ingredients are laid out. The directions are clear. You just need to put them together and then, enjoy the dish. Taste it. Savor it. And be satiated with the wonderful, nurturing meals you are cooking for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Layers of Progress&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you work through the levels in the program, you&#39;ll notice that the skills you build are layered one on top of the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you get comfortable on two legs, with no distractions. But what happens when you only have one leg to stand on? &lt;a title=&#34;Dragon Scans the Horizon&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dragon-scans-the-horizon/&#34;&gt;Or you add an arm motion and a head turn?&lt;/a&gt; Slowly, you will add layers, and each time, you will understand how the new layer makes you stronger, more stable, and more internally connected in accordance with key Tai Chi principles like Rooting and Central Equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the complexity of the exercises increase, so will your rate of discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see people burst out of classes all the time. They can&#39;t wait to bounce down the street or frolic in the park. It&#39;s kind of goofy when you their eyes light up like little kids again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s what I wish for you and hope we can share with the world about the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later this month, we will be releasing the first DVD and eBook in this program, but you can start working on Tai Chi balance training right now. &lt;a title=&#34;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/better-balance/&#34;&gt;Click here to learn more.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Course: Introduction to Rooting and Stability</title>
      <link>/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 07:36:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you listed to the recent Qigong Radio episode on &lt;a title=&#34;The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/&#34;&gt;Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Balance&lt;/a&gt;, you probably want more insight into how to put Tai Chi balance training to work in your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4790&#34; alt=&#34;MiniCover&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/08/MiniCover-300x231.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;231&#34; /&gt;Now you can start Tai Chi balance training with our new eBook&lt;/strong&gt;, &#34;An Introduction to Rooting and Stability,&#34; where you will take the Tai Chi Way to re-gaining, one of life&#39;s simplest yet most essential treasures--&lt;em&gt;the gift of balance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Chi Balance Exercises in this course will produce a noticeable improvement in your sense of being grounded, or connected to the earth, centrally stabilized around a vertical axis, and able to change visual orientation while remaining balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you practice these exercises, you will begin to feel and understand the essential Tai Chi concepts of Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Dragon Body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exercises are drawn from the more than 45 separate exercises contained in the complete Tai Chi Way to Better Balance program, which includes both an ebook and DVDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ez-boxtitle-black&#34;&gt;Course Details&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost:&lt;/strong&gt; $14.99&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Taught By:&lt;/strong&gt; Don Ethan Miller, presented by Dan Kleiman&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How to Register:&lt;/strong&gt; Click &#34;Add to Cart&#34; and sign up below&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How to Access Course Materials:&lt;/strong&gt; You will receive instant access to a PDF download.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ez-boxtitle-black&#34;&gt;Course Registration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.e-junkie.com/ecom/gb.php?c=cart&amp;i=1284998&amp;cl=253146&amp;ejc=2&#34; target=&#34;ej_ejc&#34; class=&#34;ec_ejc_thkbx&#34; onClick=&#34;javascript:return EJEJC_lc(this);&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-4830 alignnone&#34; alt=&#34;addtocart&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/08/addtocart-300x108.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;108&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Tai Chi Rooting eBook: $14.99&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Instant PDF Download&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Connection Between Rooting and Strength in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/2013/07/26/the-connection-between-rooting-and-strength-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 08:42:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/26/the-connection-between-rooting-and-strength-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a recent post, we looked at &lt;a title=&#34;5 Ways to Build Stronger Legs Using Tai Chi Exercises&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/02/5-ways-to-build-stronger-legs-using-tai-chi-exercises/&#34;&gt;5 Ways to Build Strong Legs&lt;/a&gt;. When I posted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j34DhSHvaxo&amp;amp;feature=share&amp;amp;list=UU4DJ7xUL-TWEBOgDp_ekI5Q&#34;&gt;the video to Youtube&lt;/a&gt;, someone replied:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think nowadays there is a great misunderstanding of internal martial arts goals and methodology. The great issue is not to become strong but to become very weak!&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, I think the commenter is &lt;em&gt;kind of&lt;/em&gt; right, but misses a critical point, by simply reducing Tai Chi to the art of getting weaker and weaker. Just look at these Tai Chi Masters, &lt;strong&gt;specifically in the legs&lt;/strong&gt;, and tell me if they seem weak:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://taiji.scotthuette.net/files/2012/02/tai-chi-master-liu-hung-chieh.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;409&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Master Liu Hung Chieh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://www.sunion.warwick.ac.uk/socs/su173/Wu%20Jienquan.PNG&#34; width=&#34;310&#34; height=&#34;465&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Wu Style Tai Chi Founder Wu Jian Quan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://taijionmaui.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/hu-ling.jpg&#34; width=&#34;550&#34; height=&#34;586&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Yang Style Master Tung Hu Ling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no weakness in these Masters. You can see softness, an immense amount of relaxation, and they almost glow with internal calm. But weakness? Not here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the connection between the strength and the stillness they display? If you listed to last week&#39;s &lt;a title=&#34;The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/&#34;&gt;Qigong Radio episode on Tai Chi for Better Balance&lt;/a&gt;, you heard me discuss &#34;Rooting&#34; with Don Miller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a 4-minute clip from the episode, where Don specifically draws the connection between strength, stability, balance, and relaxation. When you have Tai Chi Root, you can have them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen now or download for later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training</title>
      <link>/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 13:49:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-4731&#34; alt=&#34;don U post on bridge&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/07/don-U-post-on-bridge-e1374169158691.jpg&#34; width=&#34;179&#34; height=&#34;344&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/don-ethan-miller/&#34;&gt;Don Miller&lt;/a&gt; and I explore the essential elements of Tai Chi Balance Training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you probably know, Tai Chi is being used more and more for falls prevention programs for the elderly and becoming a mainstream part of the Western medical vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what are the actual elements that make up a great Tai Chi balance training program?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can you use them for your own well-being?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you share Tai Chi balance training with your friends and family?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are our thoughts on:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ways to develop &#34;Root&#34; that make you more stable and relaxed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding &#34;Central Equilibrium&#34; for more integrated movement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The psychological dimensions of Tai Chi practice, and how you can sneak up on them by improving your body awareness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The deep satisfaction that comes from literally connecting to the Earth&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We explore student experiences, roadblocks, and concerns as well as giving you practical tidbits to play with while you listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>