<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/tai-chi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Returning to an Old, Familiar Practice</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 09:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s easy to get caught in a linear, progress-oriented way of thinking about your practice.
What&#39;s new? What can I learn next? Am I improving...all the time.
You get so caught up in doing it right and refining every little detail that you can lose sight of the what&#39;s really great about practice in the first place...the restoration, integration, and feeling of wholeness you can walk away with each time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi and Embodiment for Anxiety and Depression</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/04/01/tai-chi-and-embodiment-for-anxiety-and-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 18:11:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/04/01/tai-chi-and-embodiment-for-anxiety-and-depression/</guid>
      <description>Last week I had the pleasure of recording a conversation with my friend and Tai Chi colleague Dorothy Fitzer.
Drawing on her background in movement, energy arts, and psychotherapy, Dorothy has put together a very interesting group of practitioners from several different modalities to address the question of how embodiment practices can lead to nourishing, healing, and even transformative experiences.

Of course, I was thrilled to make the case that this is at the core of so much of what we do in Tai Chi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 and the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Book</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 16:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m very excited to share some news about two big projects with you today: Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s annual Immersion Week and the publication of the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance as a physical book.

Join me from Tuesday, April 22 - Friday, April 25 at Brookline Tai Chi in Boston for Energy Gates Moving Qigong Exercises. Times, cost, and registration details in the link.
The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance is now available for purchase on Amazon, but you can also get your copy of the physical book directly from the publisher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice, Stress, and Building Outward Connections</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 11:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</guid>
      <description>&#34;At some point, don&#39;t we have to ask ourselves, &#34;Aren&#39;t I healthy enough?&#34; Don&#39;t I need to work on &#34;waking up&#34;, on manifesting kindness and patience, and being other oriented?&#34;
That&#39;s from a conversation we&#39;ve been having in the Inner Form discussion group and it got me thinking.
You might be learning to cultivate your chi to heal old injuries or for the inner experience of meditative exploration, but at some point, shouldn&#39;t your practice extend into the world around you, to the people in your life, and your work?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dust Off Your Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/12/06/dust-off-your-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2013 08:59:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/12/06/dust-off-your-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>It looks like Energy Arts is releasing another set of The Tai Chi Mastery Program. This is a short message to those of you who have the program sitting on your bookshelf, collecting dust, or still pristinely packaged: Let&#39;s open it up and get to work!
Now, if you&#39;re not familiar with this program, take a look at this:
That&#39;s a lot of DVDs!
What&#39;s Inside The Tai Chi Mastery Program?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maintaining the Four Points in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2013 08:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>Recently, the question of &#34;should I rotate my spine in Tai Chi&#34; has come up frequently and led to a lot of confusion with some of our students.
We are told to maintain the &#34;Four Points&#34; - a sort of internal frame that runs between the shoulders and the hips, forming a box that keeps the spine from rotating or side bending while you practice Tai Chi.
Some people hear this rule and think, &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seminar Recap - Detailed Report from ChicagoTaiChi.org</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/11/17/seminar-recap-detailed-report-from-chicagotaichi-org/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 14:15:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/11/17/seminar-recap-detailed-report-from-chicagotaichi-org/</guid>
      <description>Checking in with one of my favorite sculptures at the Art Institute
I was thrilled to be able to share a weekend of Tai Chi in Chicago earlier this month, thanks to Energy Arts Instructor Chris Cinnamon and his students at Enso Tai Chi.
Chris just posted an incredibly detailed report summarizing the workshop here.
If you read between the lines a little bit, you can come up with some great ways to structure your own practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Rooting, Sinking, and More in Chicago</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/10/11/tai-chi-rooting-sinking-and-more-in-chicago/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 16:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/10/11/tai-chi-rooting-sinking-and-more-in-chicago/</guid>
      <description>Inspiration for Rooting and Lengthening in Chicago
On November 9, I&#39;ll be teaching a seminar for my friend Chris Cinnamon at Enso Tai Chi (registration details here).
This year we&#39;ll continue the &#34;Put More Chi in Your Tai Chi&#34; theme that we started last year by focusing on Tai Chi Rooting, Sinking Chi, Dissolving, and more.
The goal is to give everyone a clear sense of how nourishing it can be to find your root and feed it through solo exercises and interactive partner practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Problem with Learning Tai Chi from the Classics</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/10/09/the-problem-with-learning-tai-chi-from-the-classics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 15:39:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/10/09/the-problem-with-learning-tai-chi-from-the-classics/</guid>
      <description>When you read the Tai Chi Classics and look at photos of the old masters, everything looks graceful, flowing, and full of life.
The problem is, your daily practice can be full of aches, pains, kinks, binds and the feeling that you&#39;re never really going to get it.
There is a lot of territory between, &#34;oh man, it hurts, I&#39;ll never get past it&#34; and &#34;be still like a mountain, flowing like a great river&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Practice Advice from Master Feng Zhiqiang</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/09/26/tai-chi-practice-advice-from-master-feng-zhiqiang/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 14:44:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/09/26/tai-chi-practice-advice-from-master-feng-zhiqiang/</guid>
      <description>Feng Zhiqiang was a famous Tai Chi Master from Beijing who was a major influence on my teacher Bruce Frantzis. Master Feng did some teaching in the West as well and we are fortunate to have access to a transcript of a 2001 workshop he taught in the Bay Area (thanks to the folks at SilkReeler.com for making this transcript available and thanks to Igor for sending it my way!).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Five Movement Centers</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/08/22/exploring-the-five-movement-centers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2013 16:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/08/22/exploring-the-five-movement-centers/</guid>
      <description>Allow me to share with you a Tai Chi principle so simple and clear that it is often overlooked, even by practitioners who have been doing Tai Chi for 10 years or more.
The Five Movement Centers is a template for understand HOW you move and applying it to any form you know or any repetitive movement you can perform, like going for a walk, is going to have a serious impact on how grounded, fluid, and connected you feel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Inner Form of Balance</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 09:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</guid>
      <description>When my first Tai Chi teacher, Bruce Frantzis, came back to the US forty years ago to spread the Tai Chi he learned in China, he found out that many basic Tai Chi concepts were not being taught, either because of communications issues or lack of knowledge. Only a fraction of the vast potential of the art was being shared. Bruce set out to teach the Inner Form of Tai Chi and that&#39;s what I have studied for the last 15 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Course: Introduction to Rooting and Stability</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 07:36:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</guid>
      <description>If you listed to the recent Qigong Radio episode on Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Balance, you probably want more insight into how to put Tai Chi balance training to work in your practice.
Now you can start Tai Chi balance training with our new eBook, &#34;An Introduction to Rooting and Stability,&#34; where you will take the Tai Chi Way to re-gaining, one of life&#39;s simplest yet most essential treasures--the gift of balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Connection Between Rooting and Strength in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/07/26/the-connection-between-rooting-and-strength-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 08:42:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/07/26/the-connection-between-rooting-and-strength-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>In a recent post, we looked at 5 Ways to Build Strong Legs. When I posted the video to Youtube, someone replied:
I think nowadays there is a great misunderstanding of internal martial arts goals and methodology. The great issue is not to become strong but to become very weak!
Now, I think the commenter is kind of right, but misses a critical point, by simply reducing Tai Chi to the art of getting weaker and weaker.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 13:49:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/</guid>
      <description>In this episode of Qigong Radio, Don Miller and I explore the essential elements of Tai Chi Balance Training.
As you probably know, Tai Chi is being used more and more for falls prevention programs for the elderly and becoming a mainstream part of the Western medical vocabulary.
But what are the actual elements that make up a great Tai Chi balance training program?
How can you use them for your own well-being?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>