<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>favorite-quotes on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/favorite-quotes/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in favorite-quotes on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/favorite-quotes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Jack White on the Value of a Form</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/06/jack-white-on-the-value-of-a-form/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2011 08:28:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/06/jack-white-on-the-value-of-a-form/</guid>
      <description>Check out this advice from Jack White on why you should limit yourself with formal constraints if you want to be creative. The lesson here for anyone who does tai chi, qigong, or meditation is &#34;stick to your form&#34;. Inside the limits of the form, you&#39;ll find vastly more inner space to explore than you ever would in free-form movement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health Month Wrap-Up</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/29/health-month-wrap-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 14:48:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/29/health-month-wrap-up/</guid>
      <description>As March comes to an end, I&#39;m wrapping up playing Health Month, an online game that helps you integrate new habits and change behavior. Here&#39;s my review of Health Month and a recap of what I experienced. I have to say, I don&#39;t think I really explored it to the fullest, but there were a couple of things I really liked about it and a couple of things I didn&#39;t connect with in the design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buried Psychological Nuggets</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/05/buried-psychological-nuggets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2011 09:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/05/buried-psychological-nuggets/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s a long post from one of my favorite authors, Ramit Sethi. He often writes about putting ideas into action and I think this post is another great example, BUT, that&#39;s not what I want to highlight here.
First of all, I think this is my new favorite concept:
Skepticism is not a strategy.
I spoke to one of my top Earn1k students last week &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; she earned over $80,000 in 8 weeks &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work, Speed, Mistakes</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/08/work-speed-mistakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2011 08:49:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/08/work-speed-mistakes/</guid>
      <description>Work hard, right at the edge of your abilities, fast enough to make mistakes, but slow enough to notice and correct them. Do it often. Do it with the deliberate intention of making every training session and every rep better. Do this by focusing not on outcomes such as winning or losing but rather on small chunks of skill that can be developed on an ongoing basis.

-Dr. Eric Cobb, founder of Z Health</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>