<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>don-ethan-miller on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/don-ethan-miller/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in don-ethan-miller on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/don-ethan-miller/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Five Movement Centers</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/08/22/exploring-the-five-movement-centers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2013 16:05:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/08/22/exploring-the-five-movement-centers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Allow me to share with you a Tai Chi principle so simple and clear that it is often overlooked, even by practitioners who have been doing Tai Chi for 10 years or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Five Movement Centers is a template for understand HOW you move and applying it to any form you know or any repetitive movement you can perform, like going for a walk, is going to have a serious impact on how grounded, fluid, and connected you feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this clip from the &lt;a title=&#34;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/better-balance/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/a&gt;, Don Miller demonstrates each of the Movement Centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch how his shifting changes as he goes through all five. Do you recognize these patterns?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9F2cP6r10I8?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it out and let me know how it feels!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Inner Form of Balance</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 09:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4807&#34; alt=&#34;Ocean Balance Rocks&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/08/iStock_000020131551XSmall-300x198.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;198&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When my first Tai Chi teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis Tai Chi Resources&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis-tai-chi-resources/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, came back to the US forty years ago to spread the Tai Chi he learned in China, he found out that many basic Tai Chi concepts were not being taught, either because of communications issues or lack of knowledge. Only a fraction of the vast potential of the art was being shared. Bruce set out to teach &lt;em&gt;the Inner Form of Tai Chi&lt;/em&gt; and that&#39;s what I have studied for the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of endless forms and choreography, we dove into the inner workings &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/&#34;&gt;that make Tai Chi so powerful for restoring health &lt;/a&gt;and unlocking hidden internal energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Tai Chi is moving into a new phase of popular understanding in the West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Brookline Tai Chi, we are being approached more and more often by insurance companies, federal and state government agencies, and research universities to weigh in on what makes an effective Tai Chi balance training program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi is being brought into a medical context, but I worry that we will just repeat Tai Chi&#39;s last emergence onto the Western scene: as a watered-down shell of what it could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that reason, I have sought out another champion of the Inner Form approach to Tai Chi to help me share with you the real Tai Chi Way to Better Balance. Don Ethan Miller has practiced and taught Tai Chi for more than 40 years, won national titles in Tai Chi Push Hands and has, in my opinion, a unique, direct, and profound approach to Tai Chi education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re working together on the &lt;a title=&#34;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/better-balance/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/a&gt; and I wanted to share with you why I think Don&#39;s approach to teaching Tai Chi is going to be so useful for your own practice and for when you want to share Tai Chi with the people around you whose balance is failing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simple, Yet Profound&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The exercises in the program may seem simple at first. They are accessible to almost any level of physical fitness and balance. In fact, the exercises are precisely layered (more on that below) to allow almost anyone to regain their balance safely and gradually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&#39;s the thing. I have seen firsthand, watching Don teach these exercises to people who have done Tai Chi for 5, 10 or even 20 years, that if you, the experienced Tai Chi practitioner, approach the program with an open mind, you will reignite your stale or faltering Tai Chi practice. Seasoned practitioners will find depth in the simplest instructions here and marvel at the layers of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re anything like me, you&#39;ll be jealous of the beginners who take on this program, because they&#39;re getting the depth you had to search for years to find, going from teacher to teacher for bits and pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Feel, Then Do&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For those of you who are new to Tai Chi, chances are, if you wander into your local YMCA or church Tai Chi class, you&#39;ll be thrown into &#34;The Form.&#34; With a great teacher, the form will be presented alongside the principles (Inner Form!) that make the movements work. Too often, though, the principles are absent and you&#39;re just asked to follow along until you get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To us, especially if you have the urgent need to improve your balance, this is the long way around&amp;hellip;in the best-case scenario. At worst, you fumble around, get frustrated and quit. No benefit there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won&#39;t find a forms-based approach here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, follow this simple rule as you work through the exercises in the program: &lt;strong&gt;feel, then do&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a practically limitless space to feel into when you open up your inner world with Tai Chi. From &lt;a title=&#34;Wu Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/wu-chi/&#34;&gt;the very first exercise&lt;/a&gt;, you&#39;ll be asked to explore by feel. This is Tai Chi from the inside out. It&#39;s all about what you learn to feel. And feeling leads to moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After each exercise, you will also feel and reflect on what you&#39;ve just done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, Don is like a master chef. He&#39;s crafted a book of recipes for you here. All the ingredients are laid out. The directions are clear. You just need to put them together and then, enjoy the dish. Taste it. Savor it. And be satiated with the wonderful, nurturing meals you are cooking for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Layers of Progress&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you work through the levels in the program, you&#39;ll notice that the skills you build are layered one on top of the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you get comfortable on two legs, with no distractions. But what happens when you only have one leg to stand on? &lt;a title=&#34;Dragon Scans the Horizon&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dragon-scans-the-horizon/&#34;&gt;Or you add an arm motion and a head turn?&lt;/a&gt; Slowly, you will add layers, and each time, you will understand how the new layer makes you stronger, more stable, and more internally connected in accordance with key Tai Chi principles like Rooting and Central Equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the complexity of the exercises increase, so will your rate of discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see people burst out of classes all the time. They can&#39;t wait to bounce down the street or frolic in the park. It&#39;s kind of goofy when you their eyes light up like little kids again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s what I wish for you and hope we can share with the world about the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later this month, we will be releasing the first DVD and eBook in this program, but you can start working on Tai Chi balance training right now. &lt;a title=&#34;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/better-balance/&#34;&gt;Click here to learn more.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Course: Introduction to Rooting and Stability</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 07:36:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you listed to the recent Qigong Radio episode on &lt;a title=&#34;The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/&#34;&gt;Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Balance&lt;/a&gt;, you probably want more insight into how to put Tai Chi balance training to work in your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4790&#34; alt=&#34;MiniCover&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/08/MiniCover-300x231.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;231&#34; /&gt;Now you can start Tai Chi balance training with our new eBook&lt;/strong&gt;, &#34;An Introduction to Rooting and Stability,&#34; where you will take the Tai Chi Way to re-gaining, one of life&#39;s simplest yet most essential treasures--&lt;em&gt;the gift of balance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Chi Balance Exercises in this course will produce a noticeable improvement in your sense of being grounded, or connected to the earth, centrally stabilized around a vertical axis, and able to change visual orientation while remaining balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you practice these exercises, you will begin to feel and understand the essential Tai Chi concepts of Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Dragon Body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exercises are drawn from the more than 45 separate exercises contained in the complete Tai Chi Way to Better Balance program, which includes both an ebook and DVDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ez-boxtitle-black&#34;&gt;Course Details&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost:&lt;/strong&gt; $14.99&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Taught By:&lt;/strong&gt; Don Ethan Miller, presented by Dan Kleiman&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How to Register:&lt;/strong&gt; Click &#34;Add to Cart&#34; and sign up below&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How to Access Course Materials:&lt;/strong&gt; You will receive instant access to a PDF download.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ez-boxtitle-black&#34;&gt;Course Registration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.e-junkie.com/ecom/gb.php?c=cart&amp;i=1284998&amp;cl=253146&amp;ejc=2&#34; target=&#34;ej_ejc&#34; class=&#34;ec_ejc_thkbx&#34; onClick=&#34;javascript:return EJEJC_lc(this);&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-4830 alignnone&#34; alt=&#34;addtocart&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/08/addtocart-300x108.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;108&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Tai Chi Rooting eBook: $14.99&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Instant PDF Download&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Connection Between Rooting and Strength in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/07/26/the-connection-between-rooting-and-strength-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 08:42:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/07/26/the-connection-between-rooting-and-strength-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a recent post, we looked at &lt;a title=&#34;5 Ways to Build Stronger Legs Using Tai Chi Exercises&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/02/5-ways-to-build-stronger-legs-using-tai-chi-exercises/&#34;&gt;5 Ways to Build Strong Legs&lt;/a&gt;. When I posted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j34DhSHvaxo&amp;amp;feature=share&amp;amp;list=UU4DJ7xUL-TWEBOgDp_ekI5Q&#34;&gt;the video to Youtube&lt;/a&gt;, someone replied:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think nowadays there is a great misunderstanding of internal martial arts goals and methodology. The great issue is not to become strong but to become very weak!&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, I think the commenter is &lt;em&gt;kind of&lt;/em&gt; right, but misses a critical point, by simply reducing Tai Chi to the art of getting weaker and weaker. Just look at these Tai Chi Masters, &lt;strong&gt;specifically in the legs&lt;/strong&gt;, and tell me if they seem weak:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://taiji.scotthuette.net/files/2012/02/tai-chi-master-liu-hung-chieh.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;409&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Master Liu Hung Chieh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://www.sunion.warwick.ac.uk/socs/su173/Wu%20Jienquan.PNG&#34; width=&#34;310&#34; height=&#34;465&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Wu Style Tai Chi Founder Wu Jian Quan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://taijionmaui.files.wordpress.com/2010/03/hu-ling.jpg&#34; width=&#34;550&#34; height=&#34;586&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Yang Style Master Tung Hu Ling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no weakness in these Masters. You can see softness, an immense amount of relaxation, and they almost glow with internal calm. But weakness? Not here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the connection between the strength and the stillness they display? If you listed to last week&#39;s &lt;a title=&#34;The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/&#34;&gt;Qigong Radio episode on Tai Chi for Better Balance&lt;/a&gt;, you heard me discuss &#34;Rooting&#34; with Don Miller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a 4-minute clip from the episode, where Don specifically draws the connection between strength, stability, balance, and relaxation. When you have Tai Chi Root, you can have them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen now or download for later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 13:49:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-4731&#34; alt=&#34;don U post on bridge&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/07/don-U-post-on-bridge-e1374169158691.jpg&#34; width=&#34;179&#34; height=&#34;344&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/don-ethan-miller/&#34;&gt;Don Miller&lt;/a&gt; and I explore the essential elements of Tai Chi Balance Training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you probably know, Tai Chi is being used more and more for falls prevention programs for the elderly and becoming a mainstream part of the Western medical vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what are the actual elements that make up a great Tai Chi balance training program?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can you use them for your own well-being?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you share Tai Chi balance training with your friends and family?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are our thoughts on:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ways to develop &#34;Root&#34; that make you more stable and relaxed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding &#34;Central Equilibrium&#34; for more integrated movement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The psychological dimensions of Tai Chi practice, and how you can sneak up on them by improving your body awareness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The deep satisfaction that comes from literally connecting to the Earth&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We explore student experiences, roadblocks, and concerns as well as giving you practical tidbits to play with while you listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Obviously Tai Chi Improves Balance, But How Do You Explain It?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 14:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4716&#34; alt=&#34;don + sue 2&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/07/don-+-sue-2-e1373377188614-261x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;261&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We often talk about the way Tai Chi can &lt;a title=&#34;The Transformational Power of Tai Chi Body Mechanics&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/07/the-transformational-power-of-tai-chi-body-mechanics/&#34;&gt;improve your physical health and mental and emotional well-being&lt;/a&gt; from the point of view of the practitioner. But not everyone out there is as familiar with practical ways to use Tai Chi to support their health and wellness goals as you may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later this year, I&#39;m thrilled to have the chance to share Tai Chi with physicians in a course at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hmscme.com/activelives/faculty&#34;&gt;Harvard Medical School&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s always exciting to be able to present a combination of research and practice to knowledgeable caregivers, especially because in this case, the focus of the course is on promoting healthy, active lifestyles to their patients. What do you think I should share with them? If you have suggestions for what I should cover, please leave a note in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the mean time, I&#39;d like to invite you into a conversation about &lt;em&gt;how we talk about the benefits of our practice.&lt;/em&gt; As Brookline Tai Chi has been working with the Department of Public Health and other senior care agencies to spread practical implementation of &lt;a title=&#34;Dr. Fuzhong Li&#39;s Tai Chi Research&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dr-fuzhong-lis-tai-chi-research/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi falls prevention research&lt;/a&gt;, we find ourselves in a very different world, using new language and talking to new audiences about the benefits of Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent episode of Qigong Radio, Dr. Peter Wayne discussed the &lt;a title=&#34;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, a framework that he uses to define his Tai Chi research. We need more thoughtful ways like this to express the benefits of Tai Chi practice in an understandable way, without watering everything down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to keep the conversation moving in this direction, so I took the problem to one of my most eloquent teachers, Don Ethan Miller. As a result, Don and I have been working on a new program, called &lt;strong&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/strong&gt;, which will be out later this summer. In The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance, we set out to refine the language around Tai Chi balance concepts and, more importantly, get at the essence of what makes Tai Chi so good for improving balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we would like you to join in the conversation. Please join us for a discussion of The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance on Thursday, July 18, from 12-1pm EST. We will explore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The essential elements of a Tai Chi balance training program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to make sure you include these balance exercises in every practice session, whether your goal is falls prevention, becoming more relaxed and centered,  or training for competition-level Push Hands &lt;em&gt;(the secret is that it can be the same training!)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to share Tai Chi balance training with friends and family -- without making them feel like they have to take on a serious practice to get real benefits.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p3p1&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p3p1&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p3p1;(function(d, t) { var s = d.createElement(t), options = { &#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,  &#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p3p1&#39;,  &#39;autoResize&#39;:true, &#39;height&#39;:&#39;728&#39;, &#39;async&#39;:true, &#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,  &#39;ssl&#39;:true}; s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;; s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() { var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return; try { r7p3p1 = new WufooForm();r7p3p1.initialize(options);r7p3p1.display(); } catch (e) {}}; var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr); })(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing Your Internal State through Tai Chi Equipment Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/09/17/testing-your-internal-state-through-tai-chi-equipment-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 09:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/09/17/testing-your-internal-state-through-tai-chi-equipment-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One aspect of Tai Chi that tends to get overlooked is testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t mean testing for rank or belts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean testing the smoothness of your nervous system that should be evolving as you go deeper into your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this video, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Master Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt; demonstrates an exceptional degree of smoothness. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4164&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though he is demonstrating a Ba Gua rolling exercise, all of the internal arts aim to cultivate this degree of fluidity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/owK-odZ8e9s?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, watch how he changes speeds and the size of the ball. There are no gaps in his changes. He doesn&#39;t pause and think about what to do next. The smoothness he demonstrates goes beyond external choreography and reveals a seamlessly integrated nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing this kind of fluidity is only possible with feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can set a baseline level of relaxation when you do &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;standing qigong&lt;/a&gt;, or the slow-motion flow of the solo form, but it will only take you so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go deeper, you need to interact....with other people, with external objects, and with the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch how these instructors from Brookline Tai Chi use &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi Equipment Training with Don Ethan Miller&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/27/tai-chi-equipment-training-with-don-ethan-miller/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Equipment Training&lt;/a&gt; to hone their sensitivity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_vMsAN5LFl4?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see the way that they respond to each other, before and after the equipment upgrades?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, compare that to the first video. Can you see where freeing yourself from any internal gaps would make you more responsive, alive, and able to handle external pressure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beautiful thing about internal practices like Tai Chi is that you are training your nervous system to better respond to external pressure, but every encounter with an external force is an opportunity for refining internal awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Equipment Training with Don Ethan Miller</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/08/27/tai-chi-equipment-training-with-don-ethan-miller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 07:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/08/27/tai-chi-equipment-training-with-don-ethan-miller/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you cultivate the mind-body benefits of Tai Chi, you will likely focus on solo training and interactive two-person practices like Push Hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a third kind of Tai Chi training, though, that will make the link between the other two stronger, Tai Chi Equipment Training.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4140&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/-yhR31mD-r4?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using stones, balls, disks, belts, and other objects you find in nature, you can develop important attributes of the Tai Chi body and mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renown teacher and multiple-time national Push Hands champion Don Ethan Miller explains how to go about using objects to enhance your training in this episode of Qigong Radio.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Don&#39;s Tai Chi Equipment Training DVD is &lt;a href=&#34;http://mastodonproductions.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;amp;cPath=3&amp;amp;products_id=8&#34;&gt;available for purchase here on his website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>