<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>foundations-of-relaxation on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/foundations-of-relaxation/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in foundations-of-relaxation on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/foundations-of-relaxation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress Reduction Techniques That Work in 5 Minutes or Less</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you have cultivated a daily practice that takes you into deep relaxation, it&#39;s helpful to have a set of stress reduction techniques &#34;that work in 5 minutes or less.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can pull these out during the day when you have a few minutes of downtime. If you are busy and really stressed out, these relaxation techniques can prevent your stress level from going through the roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try them and let me know what you think.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2540&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5 Minute Body Scan&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a few minutes of trying to tune into your body, instead of being stuck in your head, can help reduce the weight of some of the stress you are feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-2355&#34; title=&#34;basic standing qigong posture&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture-141x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; width=&#34;141&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standing posture pictured, here, do a 5-minute downward body scan, starting at the top of the head and working your way down, feeling height-by-height until you reach your feet.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First, set your posture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;place your feet hip-width apart, so your joints are aligned &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll feel the weight balanced evenly in each foot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lengthen the back of your neck, so the chin drops slightly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax your shoulders, as if the arms were slipping off the rib cage, to the left and right, not slouched forward or pulled back&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Next, settle in:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your breathing go smooth, so the turn-over from inhale to exhale feels natural and not forced&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Begin to scan:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bring your feeling awareness up to the crown of your head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;once you feel like you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve gathered your awareness to a single point, let your mind spread out through the crown of the head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give in to gravity and let your mind drop down the body, height-by-height, feeling front, sides, and back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your mind rest lightly on any sensations you feel as you scan, checking in, without trying to do anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work downward until you can feel your feet settle into the floor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more guidance on practicing this technique, check out &lt;a title=&#34;Settling in with Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;this article on Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt; (with a free guided-practice mp3 download).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Metronome Mobility&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This exercise is great for coordination and control and it&#39;s just distracting enough to let your nervous system reset its stress level by the time you are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s use this Z Health shoulder circle as an example for the metronome exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you feel comfortable performing the basic shoulder circle as in the video above, you&#39;ll need to set a metronome to 60 beats per minute. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a baseline for one repetition at your &#34;normal&#34; speed. How many beats?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, perform a circle at half your normal speed, or 2x as many beats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat this process, slowing down each time until the movement gets too choppy to be a smooth circle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now repeat the process getting faster each time instead of slower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you keep the rest of the body &#34;quiet&#34; -- you don&#39;t get any points for flailing around!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating this process for hip circles, ankle circles, or even finger/wrist/hand circles will work too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of metronome mobility as a stress reduction technique is to draw your mind and away from the mental and emotional pressures that are causing stress in the first place. Moving your body at different speeds provides novelty for your nervous system, which helps achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tai Chi Short Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; /&gt;When you do 5 minutes of tai chi, you have to change how you are practicing. You need to shift out of your normal &#34;training&#34; mindset, where you focus on little details, or work a principle over and over again until it clicks. That kind of deep practice mindset is great for 30 minutes or an hour of practice or more, but it&#39;s not going to do the trick in 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 5 minute practice for stress reduction, you need to focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moving smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making large, circular shapes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feeling the space around you, in your etheric field, not deep inside your body&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point, about putting your mind into your etheric field, might sound a little strange. What you are trying to do is clear the energetic layer around your body. Think of it as where you interface with the world. If you can sweep everything clean here, then the stress doesn&#39;t have the chance to soak into your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Got More Stress Reduction Techniques?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The thing that all these techniques have in common is that they are designed to recharge your nervous system through physical and energetic circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you accomplish this same goal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share your stress reduction techniques in the comments below.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Achieve Whole Body Relaxation</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/15/how-to-achieve-whole-body-relaxation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2011 08:42:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/15/how-to-achieve-whole-body-relaxation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a Tai Chi teacher trying to educate people about relaxation, I come across some pretty common misconceptions. Which of the following two ways is how you think about your personal energy levels? Your answer will determine how well you can achieve whole body relaxation:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1686&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Couch Potato Model of Relaxation&lt;/strong&gt; -- How many people try to bust their butts during the day only to come home and completely crash at night? Maybe you play this out during the week and crash on the weekends? I call this cycle the Couch Potato Model of&amp;Acirc;  Relaxation. You have to become one with the cushions of your couch to recharge your batteries. This is a fundamental misconception about the nature of work and rest being like an on/off switch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energy on a Dimmer Switch&lt;/strong&gt; --&amp;Acirc;  In tai chi and chi gung, we actually value the ability to seamlessly shift between high and low energy output, like a light on a dimmer switch. This is in direct contrast to the Couch Potato Model of Relaxation that alternates between complete crashes (the light is turned off) with&amp;Acirc;  the short, quick bursts of high energy (the light is turned on).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the Dimmer Switch Model, relaxation has a form. In the Couch Potato Model, it is formless, floppy, and disconnected. In order to smoothly shift the gears of your energy level between complete relaxation and high output performance, you need to build an energetic matrix that supports this process. One of the best ways to build up your energy matrix is through a standing chi gung practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exploring Inner Space&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The secret to standing chi gung is exploring and opening up internal space. When the space inside the body feels open and connected, your energy flows cleanly throughout the entire body and you begin to move toward that effortless gearing up and down that we&#39;re talking about in the Dimmer Switch Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this photo, I&#39;ve highlighted some of the key &#34;spaces&#34; inside the body you&#39;ll pay attention to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-1688&#34; title=&#34;Standing Chi Gung&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/07/Single-Whip-Highlights.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;141&#34; height=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what the highlights represent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White oval: the space around the middle internal organs and all the tissue in the pelvis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Green dot: the lift through the crown of the head that completes the flow up the spine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Red lines: the connection from the spine out to the fingertips&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In standing chi gung, you do two distinct things. First you make these connections in order to build the right container for relaxation. Then, starting at the crown of the head, you let everything release downward. If this were the Couch Potato Model, you would simply collapse on the floor when you began to release down. Instead, you create an internal sensation of releasing and relaxing down, which uncovers the structure of the body, which counteracts the sinking down with an effortless buoyant force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True whole body relaxation in chi gung comes from this dynamic interplay of natural buoyancy and complete letting go, playing out inside the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a video I shot in this same posture, taken over a 30-minute period. I talk through the process of creating structure and then letting go. See if you can see buoyant moments and sinking moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/V05FDZbMHo4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/V05FDZbMHo4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Get Started&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you first begin to explore whole body relaxation through standing chi gung, you want to start with a very simple posture, as opposed to the one in the video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the arms hang by your sides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gently lift the skull off the spine, by tucking your chin slightly (feel like you&#39;re lifting your ears straight up)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place the tongue on the roof of your mouth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sit in the hips a little, like you&#39;re perched on a high stool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your feet should be hip-width apart and the legs should always be springy, not locked&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Set a timer for 5 minutes and just begin to feel from the top of the head down to your feet and notice what you feel. At first, don&#39;t try to do anything. Notice different physical sensations and expect that there will be places that you can&#39;t feel into or that you&#39;ll skip over. That&#39;s normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you do this practice more and more it will feel natural to want to stand for longer periods and you&#39;ll be able to tune into more subtle sensations. There is a method for releasing bound energy and opening up internal space. My teacher discusses it in detail in his book about this practice, called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/store/products/books/opening-energy-gates-your-body-book&#34;&gt;Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body&lt;/a&gt;. You can experiment on your own, with the book for guidance, or by checking in with a qualified instructor. Compared to lots of other practices though, you make the most progress toward relaxation when you put in the time just standing. Eventually, the rush of fluids, the sinking of chi, and the releasing of the nerves, all skills that contribute to whole body relaxation, will become a habit. You&#39;ll find yourself &#34;letting go&#34; throughout your day. When you cross this threshold, you know you&#39;ve moved into the Dimmer Switch Model of relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So remember, don&#39;t just do something, stand there!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi for Weight Loss?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/08/tai-chi-for-weight-loss/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2011 08:24:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/08/tai-chi-for-weight-loss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People often ask me if tai chi is good for losing weight. If they&#39;re asking whether tai chi is a substitute for running or lifting weights, the answer is usually &#34;no&#34;. When someone has been really injury or hasn&#39;t exercised in a long time, tai chi can get you back on your feet and moving pain free. For these folks, tai chi can be a safe first step towards more demanding exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum, if you&#39;re into the martial side of tai chi, the answer is &#34;yes&#34;. You&#39;ll be training like a boxer, doing lots of heavy sparring, and weapons training becomes the equivalent of lifting weights. Most people aren&#39;t going down the martial tai chi road, training hours each day, so you need to look at the whole issue a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this explanation of stress on weight management, from Dr. Arya M. Sharma, Professor of Medicine &amp;amp; Chair in Obesity Research and Management at the University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1574&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stress has both a psychological and physiological impact on weight management as it affects a patient&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s eating and exercise behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physiologically, stress increases serum cortisol, which in turn affects appetite. Eating can be an appropriate response to stress as it decreases serum cortisol levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychologically, stressed individuals may find themselves more distractible with decreased ability to focus, concentrate and plan &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; abilities that are essential to lifestyle-based weight management. As well, individuals under stress may fall into more disorganized patterns of eating and miss meals or snacks, thereby allowing hunger to influence their eating decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching patients stress-reduction techniques, or directing them to appropriate stress-reduction resources may help with their weight-management efforts. Meditation, yoga, deep-breathing techniques, exercise and professional counselling can all be considered. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drsharma.ca/obesity-best-weight-stress.html&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What I really like about this explanation is that you have to address stress on a psychological and physiological level to understand its full impact. As you begin to understand and identify the different facets of stress, you can adapt your behavior accordingly. It&#39;s not uncommon to write off our experiences as entirely psychological or entirely physiological, making us at fault in the first case and helpless in the second. It&#39;s so much more productive to try to understand the interplay of psychological and physiological forces at play in the stress -- and hopefully, relaxation -- cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that point of view, having a tai chi practice will teach you to recognize the signs of stress in your life and give you a way to process them before they take a psychological and physical toll. So what are you waiting for? Hurry up and relax!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Does Qigong Work?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/25/how-does-qigong-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2011 04:12:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/25/how-does-qigong-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In class the other day, a student asked me what kind of chi gung (qigong) we study. She said a friend of hers had been learning a different form and they wanted to compare notes. This is always an interesting conversation, because the term &#34;qigong&#34; covers a lot of different forms of exercise. Literally, it means &#34;energy development&#34; or &#34;energy cultivation&#34;. The chief aim of any qigong practice is to develop your natural energy levels, making your energy, or chi, smoother, increasing your capacity to move it through your system or using it for specific applications, like martial arts or meditation.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1715&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you compare different qigong sets, you&#39;ll find different models for understanding your body&#39;s energy behind each one. Some sets look at the &#34;five elements&#34; -- a theory applied to things that come in phases like the changing seasons. Other sets used the acupuncture meridian model of the body, so they are designed to activate these lines through light touch, rubbing, patting, off-body stimulation, or even imagery. Still others focus on activating the different tissues of the body through movements, big and small, and as the mind moves through the physical body, the chi starts to flow in particular patterns.  I teach this last method, so I&#39;m going to explain how qigong works from that point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, though, you need to understand what we mean when we use the term &#34;energy&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What We Mean When We Say Energy&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You probably use the word &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; all the time to describe things that are not far out and esoteric. You have a much more intuitive sense of your own body energy than you might realize. For starters, just think of what &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; meant at different times in you life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you were a baby, life was a cycle of eating, sleeping, pooping, and laughing. If you spend time around a newborn, you can clearly see the peaks and valleys of energy and rest. That&#39;s what we&#39;re talking about when we say energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s the quality of the energy that you need for your daily adult responsibilities? If adolescence was all about shaking up a soda can and watching it burst with crazy kid energy, as an adult, you need to let that fizz out slowly. Adult work life, with long hours, 24/7 electronic stimulation, and complex relationships, requires a steady, even flow of energy that you can draw on consistently and deep reserves for when you need to push.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you know if you have that kind of chi? And if you don&#39;t have it, how do you get it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you have to recognize energetic patterns in your daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Patterns and Cycles&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Starting to detect energetic patterns and cycles in your life can sound esoteric, but it&#39;s not. In the West it&#39;s common to think that energy talk sounds woo-woo and new-agey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The Expressiveness of the Body and the Divergence of Greek and Chinese Medicine&lt;/span&gt;, Shigehisa Kuriyama explains why, as a culture, it&#39;s hard for us to accept the Eastern view of the body and energy. Kuriyama traces two medical traditions back to their roots, trying to get at why they went in such different directions. Guess what a cornerstone of Kuriyama&#39;s argument is: dissection in the West and no dissection in the East put the two traditions on different paths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about that. If you cut away skin, and you see muscle and bone, won&#39;t you start thinking about pulleys and levers and start developing mechanical stories about how the body works? On the other hand, if you couldn&#39;t cut away the layers, how you would begin to sense what was going on under the surface? What models and stories would you develop that captured the global patterns you observed? This is the central issue that separates an analytic, reductionist approach from an intuitive, pattern-based approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that point of view, qigong is an internal exploration of intrinsic patterns and cycles, so you need to take an empirical approach and make some observations about your daily energy flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sleep:&lt;/strong&gt; How easy is it for you to go to bed at night or wake up in the morning? What&#39;s your wake/rest transition speed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illness:&lt;/strong&gt; How quickly do you recovery from a cold or the flu?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food:&lt;/strong&gt; Observe your eating/digestion/elimination cycle. Does &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;food coma&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; kick in every time you eat? When was the last time you had a good bowel movement? I&#39;m not kidding! This is a key piece of information for taking stock of your energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work:&lt;/strong&gt; Think about weekly and even yearly cycles of work and rest or vacation. Do you recharge with two days off? Do a couple of weeks a year give you the juice to complete your annual workflow? I&#39;m sure you sense patterns, annual, quarterly, on a project basis, in your professional field. Why not develop the same sense of flow for your own personal energy levels?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Qigong Enhances Natural Restorative Cycles&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you learn qigong, you start moving in prescribed patterns:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/whzHtISshho?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/whzHtISshho?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circularity and repetition allows you to move deeply into the body in a relaxed way. You start to feel things like soft tissue turning and joints opening and closing. The better your physical rhythms get, the smoother your chi gets, and the more your mind relaxes. This is how qigong works on your body, energy, and mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is wide range of qigong exercises, though. Sometimes, the best practice is to do nothing at all and just stand still:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;272&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/V05FDZbMHo4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;272&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/V05FDZbMHo4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, instead of moving the body to slow down the mind, you hold the body still and move the mind through it. It&#39;s crucial to make this a felt experience. You don&#39;t want to dissociate and go somewhere else mentally. You &#34;run your mind through your body&#34; and find all kinds of internal space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, the goal is the same, even though the approach is different: learn to feel the natural flows inside the body, and by feeling, enhance them. When you make these flows strong, the benefits of qigong kick in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disrupt the Stress Cycle with Better Breathing</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/26/disrupt-the-stress-cycle-with-better-breathing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2011 10:06:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/26/disrupt-the-stress-cycle-with-better-breathing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1473&#34; title=&#34;Diaphragmatic Breathing Exercise&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/05/High-Low-Breathing-Test-300x169.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Diaphragmatic Breathing Exercise&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;169&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the practice tips on this blog are about setting good practice habits in motion, but bad habits, like poor breathing, need to be disrupted too. The tools you use to disrupt bad habits are the same ones you use to create good practice habits:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1486&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the &#34;when&#34; and &#34;how&#34; of your practice highly contextual: &lt;em&gt;&#34;On Tuesday, I will practice for 15 minutes between meetings in my office, so that I can feel more energized as I head into the afternoon.&#34;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on small chunks of skill: &lt;em&gt;&#34;As I do my qigong form, I will focus on how the weight-shifting connects my feet to the floor.&#34;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, leave yourself wanting more. If you always finish a practice session feeling like you&#39;re not burnt out, but actually a little bit hungry for more practice, you&#39;re going to crave your next practice session.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Over time, you create a practice snowball, where the little doses of highly contextual practice add up to a greater inner drive to practice, more practice stamina, and the ability to focus on meaningful aspects of your practice. This is the best path to acquiring new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relaxation is Not Necessarily Skill Acquisition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I never really liked hearing people say they want to &#34;fight stress&#34;. Stress is fighting by definition! And thinking about &#34;getting really good at relaxing&#34; seems equally paradoxical to me. I think there is value to relaxation techniques, of course, and many of them are embedded in the deep breathing exercises I teach as part of qigong and tai chi. It&#39;s just that it&#39;s not so much about increasing your lung capacity, learning diaphragmatic breathing as a skill, or even specific exercises for anxiety, &lt;strong&gt;as it is about disrupting the stress cycle&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction here is that your are not &#34;doing more relaxation&#34;, you are breaking up &#34;doing more stress&#34; so that the effects of stress and anxiety can&#39;t build up in your nervous system. Think of it like a snowball, as it rolls downhill, it gets bigger and bigger, right? Well, by taking conscious breathing exercise breaks, you break up the hill, so the snowball can&#39;t build up. I&#39;m not saying it&#39;s never going to snow again, it&#39;s just that you won&#39;t experience the accumulation. Here&#39;s how to disrupt the stress cycle with the same three techniques that we use to create good practice habits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make the &#34;when&#34; and &#34;how&#34; of your stress highly contextual.&lt;/strong&gt; Once you understand where the spikes are in your day, you can intervene and add breathing exercises to re-balance or keep the snowball from building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on small chunks of skill. &lt;/strong&gt;When you learn a set of breathing exercises, each exercise should serve a purpose. It&#39;s always effective to focus a small number of skills, 1-3, in each practice session.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, leave yourself wanting more. &lt;/strong&gt;This piece gets really interesting in a stress-cycle-breaking session. You want to explore the barrier between your practice and your return to your day. Notice when thoughts of outside pressures start to creep back into your head during the practice session. That&#39;s fine and natural, but the key is to learn how to transition back into your day as smoothly as possible. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Posture, Stress, and Breathing Exercises&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a tai chi teacher, one facet of stress that I think gets overlooked is the role that posture and (lack of) movement play in reinforcing the stress cycle. The good news is that when you begin to work on your breathing, you are already working on your posture, and as that work carries over into your non-practice time, you will continue to see the benefits. Here&#39;s a short clip on how good diaphragmatic breathing works:&lt;br / &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/R8zmohhzKsE?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/R8zmohhzKsE?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;br / &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In order for the diaphragm to move properly, you must maintain a &#34;long spine&#34;. Good spinal length allows the movement of the diaphragm to pull on ligaments connected to the internal organs and the spine and gentle massage and tone everything in the torso. Not only does diaphragmatic breathing create better air exchange, deep breathing exercises also contribute to the health of the internal organs, like you were giving yourself a massage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a reinforcing cycle: good posture lets the breathing mechanism work better, you get better air exchange and your body handles stress better. As stress has less of an impact, your body is in &#34;fight or flight mode&#34; (the opposite of good posture -- the fetal curl) less often, and it becomes easier to breathe well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaways for Your Home Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to make a lasting impact on your health and sense of well-being, setting out to break your stress cycle is very important. Remember these tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore the context of stress spikes in your day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break the snowball effect with breathing breaks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-balance your internal environment and ability to handle stress by learning about posture and doing breathing exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to go further into relaxation, start building a daily practice like standing meditation or tai chi (remember, it&#39;s the daily cycle that&#39;s powerful, not any one practice session).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>