<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>practice-tip on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/categories/practice-tip/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in practice-tip on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/categories/practice-tip/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Returning to an Old, Familiar Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 09:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s easy to get caught in a linear, progress-oriented way of thinking about your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s new? What can I learn next? Am I improving...all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get so caught up in doing it right and refining every little detail that you can lose sight of the what&#39;s really great about practice in the first place...the restoration, integration, and feeling of wholeness you can walk away with each time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Return to a Familiar Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What if, instead of trying to always master something new, you went back to a practice you hadn&#39;t done in a while?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if that felt the same way it feels to see an old friend? Or visit a place you hadn&#39;t been in a long time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s an old friend I guess I&#39;d like you to meet (part of me was hoping this would be buried in YouTube&#39;s archives, never to surface again. Oh well!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I wanted to see what it looked like from the outside to hold a posture for an extended period of time. In this video, I&#39;m holding the final posture of Tai Chi&#39;s Single Whip for 25 minute...but it&#39;s sped up so you can really see the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/WALkgFQ9a2w&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s awful, right? You can see all the collapsing and poor breathing as I struggle through the duration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait. Why did I want to share this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oh, right, because every time I&#39;ve returned to this practice since that time, six months, a year, three years later, I can settle back into some of the practice grooves I established back then.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you return to an energetic practice like Standing Qigong, try not to just replicate the outward shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The feel of the posture (or movement) -- heavy, light, twisting, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The energetic pattern that defines the practice -- sinking, rising, absorbing, projecting, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The mind, the body, and the energetic pattern slotting into alignment, not immediately, but over a few minutes or several repetitions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last piece, the alignment, is critical. Part of the challenge of remembering an old practice is that you remember what it felt like &lt;em&gt;at the end&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, you&#39;re settling in to it, so you have to keep the end in mind, but patiently wait for the pieces to slot together again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, this waiting, and the eventual alignment, returning to a familiar place, is what is truly restorative and energizing about this method of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Return is the movement of the Tao.&lt;br /&gt;
Yielding is the way of the Tao.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things are born of being.&lt;br /&gt;
Being is born of non-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: right;&#34;&gt;- Tao Te Ching, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/lao-tzu/works/tao-te-ching/te.htm&#34;&gt;Chapter 40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhythm, Timing, and Intuition</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/21/rhythm-timing-and-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 08:30:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/21/rhythm-timing-and-intuition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why is it that sometimes you feel confident, connected, and at ease and other times you get flustered, disoriented and nothing seems to come together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Greek poet Archilocus, &#34;we don&#39;t rise to the level of our expectations, we fall to the level of our training.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now does that mean that every possible situation you go through needs to be practiced, rehearsed, and trained? That seems a little overwhelming!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, when we practice Tai Chi and qigong, we are making the bet that they will infuse the rest of our lives with the calm, centered awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Training to Reveal Your Intuition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lately, I&#39;ve been questioning how we learn and teach practices that are designed to connect us to our deeper channels of energy, awareness and being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are we over-thinking things?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came across a popular book from the 70s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://theinnergame.com/about-tim-gallwey/&#34;&gt;The Inner Game of Tennis&lt;/a&gt; and the author, Tim Gallwey, confirmed my suspicion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1971, while on sabbatical from a career in higher education, I took a job as tennis professional in Seaside, California. While teaching on the court one day, I realized that many of my instructions were being incorporated in the student&#39;s mind as a kind of &#34;command and control&#34; self-dialogue that was significantly interfering with both learning and performance. When I inquired further, I found there was a lot going on in the mind of my tennis students that was preventing true focus of attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then began to explore ways to focus the mind of the player on direct and non-judgmental observation of ball, body, and racquet in a way that would heighten learning, performance, and enjoyment of the process. With this new awareness, amateur tennis players seemed to naturally develop the instincts and physicality of much more experienced players without specific instruction.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
His techniques allowed people to bypass their verbal filters, where we normally try to communicate about learning, and tap directly into deeper, more intuitive ways of perceiving and performing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of bypassing your thinking brain, I&#39;d like you to take 5 minutes and watch the video below of Tai Chi Master Cheng Man Ching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t analyze it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the soundtrack of the video to help you feel the rhythm and timing of his steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then do your form or work on pushes or whatever other practice you enjoy, feeling for the same rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/fSYPOhSgiis?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By the way, I highly recommend you subscribe to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/mnpli&#34;&gt;Mario Napoli&#39;s Youtube Channel&lt;/a&gt;. He posts great archival footage and really interesting training videos of himself and his students.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reporting Live from the Beach</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/12/reporting-live-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 10:38:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/12/reporting-live-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2014/02/D0D3E67C-7A7E-4922-89F3-85A0FA4D143B1392219396.012004.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;margin: 5px; border: 0px none;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2014/02/D0D3E67C-7A7E-4922-89F3-85A0FA4D143B1392219396.012004.jpg&#34; width=&#34;158&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I&#39;m on day 4 of daily practice by the ocean, but it&#39;s more than that. We&#39;re staying right on the beach, so I get to soak up the energy of the ocean pretty much all day long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I didn&#39;t used to have any sense for what &#34;the energy of the ocean&#34; meant and like pretty much everything else energetic, I&#39;m sure my sense for it will evolve even more, but I want to share my experiences from this week with you anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately we&#39;ve been talking about two ways of practicing standing qigong: &lt;a title=&#34;Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;by form or by feel&lt;/a&gt;. This week I&#39;ve been using both and both methods have revealed interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First By Feel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Holding the same posture for the same amount of time when you stand gives you the opportunity to &#34;just feel.&#34; By having a consistent baseline, the posture and duration, you can compare the feel from one day to the next to reveal new internal space and sensations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice by a huge natural power source like the ocean, though, you can also discover &#34;activity&#34; that varies day to day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy of the ocean works like a giant amplifier this way. When you settle in and get quiet, you can connect to it and get a big signal boost. In other words, the volume gets turned up on all the internal sensations you typically listen for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has been so exciting about practice this week is that the thing that gets amplified and really stands out is different each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day it was the lower tantien directing energy down through the legs and stabilizing the lower body. The next day, I found more space and expansiveness through the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the very first day, a stuck spot I had been working with for a few months began to open up and continued to unwind itself as I sat by the ocean after practice. Thanks, Ocean!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I tell you about practice experiences like this, it&#39;s not that I want you to go out and search for these specific ones. You can&#39;t. You might encounter them, but I didn&#39;t set out with an agenda to experience them ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;You have to open your awareness to see what naturally emerges and your reward is the surprise of discovery.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Doing the Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, this all might sound like spontaneous practice, but there&#39;s an important role for the form here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember how I framed &#34;just feel&#34; practice? Set the same conditions as much as possible, then be surprised by the contrast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get the boost from a natural power source like the ocean, you can go back into the form and have extra juice for feeling, sinking, and dissolving, as you work through the body in a systematic way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of you have been sending me questions about sinking versus dissolving lately and I&#39;ve been thinking a lot about the best way to capture the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we go through the process of working on the Gates, you use both techniques in each practice session, dissolving the &#34;&lt;a title=&#34;Energy Gates Dissolving Series&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;gate of the week&lt;/a&gt;,&#34; then sinking down through the rest of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, you have the opportunity to contrast the two techniques every time you practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissolving is lighter, sinking saturates your tissues and gets heavy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissolving breaks things apart, sinking pulls them down through your body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissolving is letting go without forcing, so is sinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases you have to rest your mind in one place and let the process unfold, but dissolving and sinking happen on different frequencies. Don&#39;t ask me what kind of frequencies. I can tell you that model captures my experience, but I don&#39;t honestly know if that&#39;s an analogy or what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I do know from practicing by the ocean this week, though, is that when you get a Great Amplifier for your form, you build stronger internal connections, go deeper, release more and if you listen just right, you figure out new things about old patterns that you can hopefully bring back with you to your regular practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice, Stress, and Building Outward Connections</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 11:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&#34;At some point, don&#39;t we have to ask ourselves, &#34;Aren&#39;t I healthy enough?&#34;  Don&#39;t I need to work on &#34;waking up&#34;, on manifesting kindness and patience, and being other oriented?&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s from a conversation we&#39;ve been having in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/&#34;&gt;Inner Form discussion&lt;/a&gt; group and it got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be learning to cultivate your chi to heal old injuries or for the inner experience of meditative exploration, but at some point, shouldn&#39;t your practice extend into the world around you, to the people in your life, and your work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&#39;m often in favor of letting these connections emerge naturally, but the comment above and this TED talk on stress are pushing me to make &#34;practicing in the world&#34; a little more explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making Stress Your Friend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Stanford health psychologist Kelly McGonigal gives a great talk on transforming your relationship to stress. And it could save your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the video description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stress. It makes your heart pound, your breathing quicken and your forehead sweat. But while stress has been made into a public health enemy, new research suggests that stress may only be bad for you if you believe that to be the case.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RcGyVTAoXEU?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practicing in the World&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From this perspective, &lt;strong&gt;cultivating your internal energy is not about getting some horrible disease out of your system.&lt;/strong&gt; It&#39;s a way to process, digest, and to grow from what&#39;s useful while shedding what&#39;s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice homework this week: you know what it&#39;s like to find a special, quiet place to practice to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;build your chi&lt;/a&gt;, but what about your next interaction with another person as the best place to practice? Can you pause, hold the mind the same way when you do in your practice and let the encounter unfold the same way the qigong mind allows chi to resolve itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might draw some inspiration from &lt;a title=&#34;Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/&#34;&gt;Push Hands&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a title=&#34;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/24/transforming-conflict-with-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi-style conflict resolution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Obviously Tai Chi Improves Balance, But How Do You Explain It?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 14:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4716&#34; alt=&#34;don + sue 2&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/07/don-+-sue-2-e1373377188614-261x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;261&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We often talk about the way Tai Chi can &lt;a title=&#34;The Transformational Power of Tai Chi Body Mechanics&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/07/the-transformational-power-of-tai-chi-body-mechanics/&#34;&gt;improve your physical health and mental and emotional well-being&lt;/a&gt; from the point of view of the practitioner. But not everyone out there is as familiar with practical ways to use Tai Chi to support their health and wellness goals as you may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later this year, I&#39;m thrilled to have the chance to share Tai Chi with physicians in a course at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hmscme.com/activelives/faculty&#34;&gt;Harvard Medical School&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s always exciting to be able to present a combination of research and practice to knowledgeable caregivers, especially because in this case, the focus of the course is on promoting healthy, active lifestyles to their patients. What do you think I should share with them? If you have suggestions for what I should cover, please leave a note in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the mean time, I&#39;d like to invite you into a conversation about &lt;em&gt;how we talk about the benefits of our practice.&lt;/em&gt; As Brookline Tai Chi has been working with the Department of Public Health and other senior care agencies to spread practical implementation of &lt;a title=&#34;Dr. Fuzhong Li&#39;s Tai Chi Research&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dr-fuzhong-lis-tai-chi-research/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi falls prevention research&lt;/a&gt;, we find ourselves in a very different world, using new language and talking to new audiences about the benefits of Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent episode of Qigong Radio, Dr. Peter Wayne discussed the &lt;a title=&#34;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, a framework that he uses to define his Tai Chi research. We need more thoughtful ways like this to express the benefits of Tai Chi practice in an understandable way, without watering everything down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to keep the conversation moving in this direction, so I took the problem to one of my most eloquent teachers, Don Ethan Miller. As a result, Don and I have been working on a new program, called &lt;strong&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/strong&gt;, which will be out later this summer. In The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance, we set out to refine the language around Tai Chi balance concepts and, more importantly, get at the essence of what makes Tai Chi so good for improving balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we would like you to join in the conversation. Please join us for a discussion of The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance on Thursday, July 18, from 12-1pm EST. We will explore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The essential elements of a Tai Chi balance training program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to make sure you include these balance exercises in every practice session, whether your goal is falls prevention, becoming more relaxed and centered,  or training for competition-level Push Hands &lt;em&gt;(the secret is that it can be the same training!)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to share Tai Chi balance training with friends and family -- without making them feel like they have to take on a serious practice to get real benefits.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p3p1&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p3p1&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p3p1;(function(d, t) { var s = d.createElement(t), options = { &#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,  &#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p3p1&#39;,  &#39;autoResize&#39;:true, &#39;height&#39;:&#39;728&#39;, &#39;async&#39;:true, &#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,  &#39;ssl&#39;:true}; s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;; s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() { var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return; try { r7p3p1 = new WufooForm();r7p3p1.initialize(options);r7p3p1.display(); } catch (e) {}}; var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr); })(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-4629&#34; alt=&#34;help-browser&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/05/help-browser-150x150.png&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend last night about &lt;a title=&#34;Guide to Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; and different &lt;a title=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;meditation traditions&lt;/a&gt; that we had both tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many different reasons, on any given day, that we sought out the practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To clear our heads of racing thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To more deeply relax the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explore layers of the mind and emotions that aren&#39;t so obvious during our normal busy days.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It seems like we had really similar reasons to practice, but I was left wondering if it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; similar when we practice. What are the sensations that tell you you&#39;re on the right track? It seems like we want to end up in the same place, but are we taking the same road to get there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p4r3&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p4r3&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p4r3;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p4r3&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;554&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { r7p4r3 = new WufooForm();r7p4r3.initialize(options);r7p4r3.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personal Practice Journey</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/17/personal-practice-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 10:12:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/17/personal-practice-journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having the luxury of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011&#34;&gt;full month of training&lt;/a&gt; this summer has made me step back and reflect on my own personal practice over the last 13 years. I tried to put together some of what this process has been like for me and sum it up &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/about/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;m curious to know what you think. Have you gone through periods of practicing without a teacher? Have you had times where you&#39;ve made huge strides in your practice? What was that like? Did the fruits of that period last a long time? Use the comments section below and let me know what it was like for you (or shoot me an email, but other people are probably curious too!).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take Home One New Thing</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/24/take-home-one-new-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 10:32:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/24/take-home-one-new-thing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-825&#34; title=&#34;Telluride&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/03/P1000033-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hiking in Telluride&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m on vacation this week in Telluride, Colorado. Telluride nestled into a box canyon, with peaks jutting up all around it. Pretty amazing scenery and hiking around at 10,000 feet gives you plenty of time to think. Whenever I come to a place like this, I always play the game of &#34;What If I Lived Here&#34;, where I try to envision life as a local. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-730&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Compared to what I hear about some ski towns, by the way, Telluride has a nice mellow blend of local vibe and constant visitor turn over. But why is that game so interesting? What&#39;s so fascinating about picturing yourself living somewhere you don&#39;t?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#39;ve thought about it over the last few days, it seems pretty similar to a learning problem you have as a student, a professional development problem you face as a teacher, and even a business problem you have running a small business. The problem is this: &lt;em&gt;how does inspiration that comes from somewhere outside of your normal routine impact and integrate with what you go back to doing on a regular basis?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, can I take something away from these gorgeous mountains without feeling like I need to move here? Can I learn a new form or exercise without abandoning everything I&#39;ve learned before?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the obvious answer is, of course you can. But as I&#39;m sitting here watching the mountains in the distance fade into morning clouds, I feel like really knowing this place is going to take more than a couple of days. So that&#39;s the flip side: if I take a little piece away with me, is it going to mean anything?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Take Home When I Travel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just getting a taste of place may not be the same thing as knowing it like your own home town, but I think it can help you know your home better. The things that jump out at you when you&#39;re in a new place have certainly faded into the background when you&#39;re at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, we were talking to a pilot in a bar yesterday. Recently arrived from the Bay Area, he says his most pressing problem in Telluride is whether to ski, fish, or go to the airport everyday. The good news was, if he timed it right, he could do all three. While we joked about the laid back rhythm of life here, it got me thinking about rhythms at home. You become blind to them as you go about your day, but I&#39;ve learned from Tai Chi that if you can be aware of an internal rhythm as you go through it, it&#39;s energizing, not draining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, being out in the mountains, there are many more geographic features to appreciate, and you can be sure when I go home, I&#39;ll be looking at rivers and oceans, and ok, hills, a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I&#39;m trying to say that coming to a place that feels so different from home gives you fresh appreciation for home and is worth it for that alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Take Home When I Study With Someone New&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Learning qigong, martial arts, or fitness over the years, I&#39;ve been exposed to many teachers, styles, and philosophies of movement. At this point, whenever I study with someone new, I try to treat it just like a travel experience: I&#39;m not moving anywhere, but just seeing things from a fresh perspective helps me appreciate the trajectory of my own practice and highlights certain elements of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say &#34;at this point&#34; because I think there is a learning threshold for being able to take small pieces from different sources and make sense of them. If you are too early in your practice, this is not a good approach. See, the drive to &#34;move to Telluride&#34; is a drive to have an integrated experience and understanding of something. Just like moving from country to country or town to town would make it hard to answer &#34;where are you from&#34;, trying to throw together understanding of movement by adding bits and pieces from different sources right from the start doesn&#39;t make sense either. You need to have an integrated learning experience first, before you try to add new elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to movement, my intuition is that 3-5 years of learning in a coherent system gives you this foundation. Many of my favorite practitioners and teachers talk about &#34;forging&#34; your body, like making a sword. You need to devote time to a single approach to let the method work on you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But once you cross this threshold, learning from a new teacher can be just like traveling to a new place. I&#39;ve experienced this time and again in workshops or seminars. Someone will have a very clear way to present (talking in Tai Chi terms now), how to feel the arms driven by the legs -- it might happen in an external form I&#39;ve never trained before, but the principle behind the movement is translateable into what I already know. And so you can take on new facets of your practice, without dabbling. It&#39;s more like refining the trajectory you are already on. The path becomes clearer and more focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the degree that you have a foundation in an art (and here&#39;s where I think learning, teaching, and doing business are all similar), being exposed to new ideas will refine what you already do. But there&#39;s one final hurdle that you need to overcome to really make this work: &lt;strong&gt;You have to throw away more than you keep.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s an art to finding the right ratio of &#34;throwing away&#34; and &#34;keeping&#34;, but it boils down to this. If you can take home one new thing, each time you go to a workshop, observe someone else&#39;s class, or read a business book, that&#39;s a huge success. It&#39;s so tempting, when someone presents a compelling idea, to say, &#34;that&#39;s it, I&#39;m abandoning everything I&#39;ve learned before and doing it this way!&#34; But you can&#39;t do that. It&#39;s the very same urge you feel when you travel to someplace beautiful and say &#34;Ok, I&#39;m dropping everything and moving here!&#34;. What about 99% of your life that exists back home. Transforming it into a new life in a new place isn&#39;t so simple. Yes, the pull is there, but if you can &#34;throw away&#34; most of that desire and &#34;keep&#34; the core of it, you&#39;ll be fond of the new place you&#39;ve visited AND deepen your appreciation for where you are from. It&#39;s the same for learning, teaching, and business.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signing the Contract</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/04/signing-the-contract/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 08:38:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/04/signing-the-contract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-674&#34; title=&#34;Commitment&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/03/Commitment.bmp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;550&#34; height=&#34;413&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of playing Health Month is signing a contract to commit to follow your rules....and I was really surprised when I did it! &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-672&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;One of the things I&#39;m thinking about while playing is how this is different from simply tracking what you eat, when you work out, and even setting goals in other areas. I didn&#39;t think it was going to be a big deal to actually sign this commitment, but it was. I have to say, I got a little nervous before I clicked on my name there. How many electronic signatures or license agreements do you sign online all the time? But this felt just a little bit different and I think that&#39;s an ingenious feature!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epic Meaning, Sheep Knuckles, and The Institute for the Future</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2011 09:30:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-531&#34; title=&#34;gaming superpowers&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/01/gaming-superpowers-300x207.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;207&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jane McGonigal gives a fascinating talk about the &#34;superpowers&#34; cultivated by the game-playing masses (more than 500 million with another billion coming up in the next decade!). Obviously we all have the image of the gamer locked in his mother&#39;s basement, endlessly pawing away at an electronic reward system, like a hamster. McGonigal&#39;s takeaway is a little different though.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-528&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She emphasizes the motivation, inspiration, and social purpose built into game play. I think that&#39;s an interesting take. When I talked to an early pioneer of these games, he said that &#34;we knew they were addictive from the beginning&#34;, but it sounded like the dirty little secret that no one wanted to admit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I think the interesting question is whether the virtues of gaming (along the lines of motivation and engagement) can be transferred to real world activity without the addictive over-use that leads to unhealthy, sedentary life. Maybe as technology comes out of the basement and into the palm of your hand more readily, this is becoming a more reasonable goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, her talk is definitely worth watching (oh, and the sheep knuckles tie back nicely into Herodotus for a lesson on real world gaming!):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;446&#34; height=&#34;326&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;wmode&#34; value=&#34;transparent&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;bgColor&#34; value=&#34;#ffffff&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;vu=http://video.ted.com/talks/dynamic/JaneMcGonigal_2010-medium.flv&amp;amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/JaneMcGonigal-2010.embed_thumbnail.jpg&amp;amp;vw=432&amp;amp;vh=240&amp;amp;ap=0&amp;amp;ti=799&amp;amp;introDuration=15330&amp;amp;adDuration=4000&amp;amp;postAdDuration=830&amp;amp;adKeys=talk=jane_mcgonigal_gaming_can_make_a_better_world;year=2010;theme=what_s_next_in_tech;theme=the_rise_of_collaboration;theme=a_taste_of_ted2010;theme=design_like_you_give_a_damn;theme=art_unusual;theme=media_that_matters;event=TED2010;&amp;amp;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;bgcolor&#34; value=&#34;#ffffff&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;446&#34; height=&#34;326&#34; src=&#34;http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf&#34; flashvars=&#34;vu=http://video.ted.com/talks/dynamic/JaneMcGonigal_2010-medium.flv&amp;amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/JaneMcGonigal-2010.embed_thumbnail.jpg&amp;amp;vw=432&amp;amp;vh=240&amp;amp;ap=0&amp;amp;ti=799&amp;amp;introDuration=15330&amp;amp;adDuration=4000&amp;amp;postAdDuration=830&amp;amp;adKeys=talk=jane_mcgonigal_gaming_can_make_a_better_world;year=2010;theme=what_s_next_in_tech;theme=the_rise_of_collaboration;theme=a_taste_of_ted2010;theme=design_like_you_give_a_damn;theme=art_unusual;theme=media_that_matters;event=TED2010;&amp;amp;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;&#34; bgcolor=&#34;#ffffff&#34; wmode=&#34;transparent&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>