<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>breathing-exercise on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/breathing-exercise/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in breathing-exercise on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/breathing-exercise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathing Techniques: Am I Doing it Right?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/05/06/breathing-techniques-am-i-doing-it-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 11:52:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/05/06/breathing-techniques-am-i-doing-it-right/</guid>
      <description>I recently received this breathing question and I thought it was worth sharing with everyone here as a post. (Don&#39;t forget, you can send me your practice questions!)
I&#39;m really confused! I took a Yang Style Tai Chi course and at the end of the class we would do Qigong. He said &#34;We will do diaphragmatic breathing. As you breath in draw the navel into the spine, as you exhale release and let the belly relax but don&#39;t collapse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing Qigong Breathing Exercises -- Mp3</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 08:38:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</guid>
      <description>The biggest question people ask me about standing qigong, especially when they hear about the 2-hour project, is &#34;what do you do, just stand there?&#34;
There is actually a really delicate balance between &#34;doing&#34; and &#34;feeling&#34; when you stand. You learn lots of different techniques, like breathing, sinking, dissolving, and pulsing, but how you apply them internally when you are holding a static posture is a tricky topic.
If you rev your engine too much -- activating strong diaphragmatic breathing the entire time, for example -- then you miss the potential stillness in the posture.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>