<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>heaven-and-earth on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/heaven-and-earth/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in heaven-and-earth on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/heaven-and-earth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong is Packed with Internal Content</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</guid>
      <description>This summer, Bruce Frantzis will be teaching a Marriage of Heaven and Earth Instructor training. Heaven and Earth was the first instructor training I attended in 2004 and I can still remember what a profound effect learning to &#34;pulse&#34; had on me.
Within the Energy Arts system, Heaven and Earth is considered a bridge from the basic to more advanced practices.
We discussed how Heaven and Earth works in an early episode of Qigong Radio, but I wanted to share this explanation from Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel with you too:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/</guid>
      <description>Next session at Brookline Tai Chi, we are re-introducing a course on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong.
In preparation for the course, I sat down with several Energy Arts instructors who are certified to teach this set, to discuss why these exercises are beneficial, how they related to other forms of qigong, and what it&#39;s like for people to learn some of the stranger techniques involved, like &#34;pulsing&#34; the joints.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>