<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>behavior-change on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/behavior-change/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in behavior-change on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/behavior-change/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Absolutely Anything in 2012</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 09:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>At this time of year, you hear a lot about New Year&#39;s resolutions.
This year, I was happy to see a lot of people saying &#34;New Year&#39;s resolutions don&#39;t work.&#34; We all know that&#39;s true from personal experience, but these folks were referencing a growing understanding about how learning and skill-building take place. Most of what we now know about how the nervous system works flies in the face of changing through the strength of your willpower alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Man Who Did His Tai Chi Form 19,100 Times</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2011 07:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</guid>
      <description>I got an email the other day that was a little bit different than the usual requests for lessons. It read:
&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I learned the Short Form at Brookline Tai Chi under the tutelage of Bill Ryan back about 1996-1997. For seven years, I continued to do the short form three times every morning. Then for the past eight years or so, I have done the short form four times every morning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Practice Partners You Should Avoid</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/17/4-practice-partners-you-should-avoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 08:29:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/17/4-practice-partners-you-should-avoid/</guid>
      <description>The next time you go to class, watch out for these 4 practice partners. While they all start out with good intentions, if you hang out with them too much, you&#39;ll get sucked into their quirky habits and slow down your own progress. Don&#39;t say I didn&#39;t warn you!

1. Checklist Charlie
Checklist Charlie is the tai chi student who is forever stuck in his own head. Every time he practices, instead of feeling his body, he recites a list of stuff he is supposed to be doing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kilimanjaro Made Easy</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 10:05:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</guid>
      <description>Z-Health Master Trainer Jen Waak is a self-described &#34;recovering management consultant&#34;. These days, she helps other &#34;Keyboard Athletes&#34; improve and maintain their bodies and stay healthy even when they&#39;re stuck behind a desk all day. What surprised me about reading Jen&#39;s advice on &#34;what you should do at your desk&#34;, was that it sounded a lot like what she did last year to get ready for a climb up Mount Kilimanjaro.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Day Better Breathing Challenge</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 10:17:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I&#39;ve been talking a lot about two things, improving your breathing to give you a major energy/relaxation boost and developing tools that help you follow-through on your home practice. I&#39;ve even created an online course with all the information you need to cultivate better breathing habits: Better Breathing. The biggest lesson we learned as we talked to BTC students&amp;Acirc; was that the best time to use reminders to trigger your practice was when you were invested in learning a new skill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Things Modern Athletes Can Learn from the Tai Chi Classics</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/27/10-things-modern-athletes-can-learn-from-the-tai-chi-classics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 09:58:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/27/10-things-modern-athletes-can-learn-from-the-tai-chi-classics/</guid>
      <description>By training the principles of body-alignment and movement as described in the Tai Chi Classics, you can move with much more grace, fluidity, and power. Instead of wasting energy holding excess tension, relaxation can lead the way to more powerful movement. Here&#39;s what Yang Cheng-fu said about it a hundred years ago (the following is adapted from YANG&#39;S TEN IMPORTANT POINTS by Yang Cheng-fu (1883 &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; 1936) as researched by Lee N.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Home Practice Challenge</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:19:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</guid>
      <description>From the recent practice survey we conducted at Brookline Tai Chi and experiments I&#39;ve been running in online learning, it&#39;s become clearer and clearer to me that most people need some external motivation when they are learning a new skill. That&#39;s not a judgment about willpower and motivation, it actually says more about the way we are wired for survival. In Z Health, we always talk about the way that the nervous system is at once the most plastic system -- it can adapt to lots of different changes -- and also the most stable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Student Practice Habits</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2011 08:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</guid>
      <description>What the heck does Donkey Kong have to do with the practice habits of tai chi students? It turns out the ladders and platforms in the video game are a perfect model for understanding the ecosystem of students practice habits. Let me explain the survey design and then I&#39;ll share some really fascinating results about how people engage Brookline Tai Chi to develop their tai chi practice.
Survey Design
Last week we conducted a small practice survey to try to get a more accurate picture of what students do outside of class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Better Practice Tools</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 09:20:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m running a little experiment right now at Brookline Tai Chi to see if we can help our students develop better home practice habits. Specifically, I&#39;m experimenting with self-reporting and automated reminders to spark daily practice sessions outside of class.
Now, when I talk to other people in our international tai chi community, I realize what a powerful practice aid Brookline Tai Chi already is. What I mean is, the bricks-and-mortar experience of coming to the school and being around other people removes so many barriers people have to doing tai chi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health Month Wrap-Up</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/29/health-month-wrap-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 14:48:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/29/health-month-wrap-up/</guid>
      <description>As March comes to an end, I&#39;m wrapping up playing Health Month, an online game that helps you integrate new habits and change behavior. Here&#39;s my review of Health Month and a recap of what I experienced. I have to say, I don&#39;t think I really explored it to the fullest, but there were a couple of things I really liked about it and a couple of things I didn&#39;t connect with in the design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March is Going to be Health Month</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/21/march-is-going-to-be-health-month/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2011 09:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/21/march-is-going-to-be-health-month/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m pretty excited to try this one out. Health Month is a behavior change game where you set rules to follow each month and do daily tracking, with rewards and penalties for how well you follow them. I&#39;m just digging into it, but so far it looks like you can choose &#34;do more of this&#34; or &#34;do less of that&#34;. I like the idea of limiting the scope of the goal to a month (what BJ Fogg calls a &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simplicity, Persuasion and Technology</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 08:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been reading/watching a lot of BJ Fogg&#39;s work lately. He studies the persuasive power of technology for positive behavior change. You&#39;ll recognize my interest here if you read some of my recent posts on game design mechanics and the potential to integrate technology into real world learning. 
(Check out his Youtube channel for some shorter videos that explain facets of his work &#34;in 60 seconds&#34;)
Here&#39;s Dr. Fogg on simplicity:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>