<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>motivation on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/motivation/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in motivation on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/motivation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Intrinsic Practice Motivation</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 09:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</guid>
      <description>For the last couple of years, I&#39;ve been teaching regular workshops in Farmington, Maine. When I went up again last week, I had a fascinating conversation with one of the students. She was telling me how the core group had been coming along and that other people have come in and out of practicing with them. She said, &#34;you know, it&#39;s not really for everyone.&#34;
Now, I don&#39;t know if that jumps out at you as a significant statement, but as a Tai Chi teacher, it&#39;s something I&#39;ve been thinking about for years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Absolutely Anything in 2012</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 09:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>At this time of year, you hear a lot about New Year&#39;s resolutions.
This year, I was happy to see a lot of people saying &#34;New Year&#39;s resolutions don&#39;t work.&#34; We all know that&#39;s true from personal experience, but these folks were referencing a growing understanding about how learning and skill-building take place. Most of what we now know about how the nervous system works flies in the face of changing through the strength of your willpower alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Man Who Did His Tai Chi Form 19,100 Times</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2011 07:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</guid>
      <description>I got an email the other day that was a little bit different than the usual requests for lessons. It read:
&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I learned the Short Form at Brookline Tai Chi under the tutelage of Bill Ryan back about 1996-1997. For seven years, I continued to do the short form three times every morning. Then for the past eight years or so, I have done the short form four times every morning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Day Better Breathing Challenge</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 10:17:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I&#39;ve been talking a lot about two things, improving your breathing to give you a major energy/relaxation boost and developing tools that help you follow-through on your home practice. I&#39;ve even created an online course with all the information you need to cultivate better breathing habits: Better Breathing. The biggest lesson we learned as we talked to BTC students&amp;Acirc; was that the best time to use reminders to trigger your practice was when you were invested in learning a new skill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Home Practice Challenge</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:19:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</guid>
      <description>From the recent practice survey we conducted at Brookline Tai Chi and experiments I&#39;ve been running in online learning, it&#39;s become clearer and clearer to me that most people need some external motivation when they are learning a new skill. That&#39;s not a judgment about willpower and motivation, it actually says more about the way we are wired for survival. In Z Health, we always talk about the way that the nervous system is at once the most plastic system -- it can adapt to lots of different changes -- and also the most stable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Student Practice Habits</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2011 08:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</guid>
      <description>What the heck does Donkey Kong have to do with the practice habits of tai chi students? It turns out the ladders and platforms in the video game are a perfect model for understanding the ecosystem of students practice habits. Let me explain the survey design and then I&#39;ll share some really fascinating results about how people engage Brookline Tai Chi to develop their tai chi practice.
Survey Design
Last week we conducted a small practice survey to try to get a more accurate picture of what students do outside of class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Better Practice Tools</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 09:20:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m running a little experiment right now at Brookline Tai Chi to see if we can help our students develop better home practice habits. Specifically, I&#39;m experimenting with self-reporting and automated reminders to spark daily practice sessions outside of class.
Now, when I talk to other people in our international tai chi community, I realize what a powerful practice aid Brookline Tai Chi already is. What I mean is, the bricks-and-mortar experience of coming to the school and being around other people removes so many barriers people have to doing tai chi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>xkcd: Let Go</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 08:43:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</guid>
      <description>Be sure to mouse over for the original title text from the comic (Thanks, Nate!).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buried Psychological Nuggets</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/05/buried-psychological-nuggets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2011 09:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/05/buried-psychological-nuggets/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s a long post from one of my favorite authors, Ramit Sethi. He often writes about putting ideas into action and I think this post is another great example, BUT, that&#39;s not what I want to highlight here.
First of all, I think this is my new favorite concept:
Skepticism is not a strategy.
I spoke to one of my top Earn1k students last week &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; she earned over $80,000 in 8 weeks &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simplicity, Persuasion and Technology</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 08:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been reading/watching a lot of BJ Fogg&#39;s work lately. He studies the persuasive power of technology for positive behavior change. You&#39;ll recognize my interest here if you read some of my recent posts on game design mechanics and the potential to integrate technology into real world learning. 
(Check out his Youtube channel for some shorter videos that explain facets of his work &#34;in 60 seconds&#34;)
Here&#39;s Dr. Fogg on simplicity:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>