<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>motivation on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/motivation/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in motivation on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/motivation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Intrinsic Practice Motivation</title>
      <link>/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 09:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Marden Hill Road Sunset II; Palermo, Maine by Jody Roberts, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/jroberts72/6003983172/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Marden Hill Road Sunset II; Palermo, Maine&#34; src=&#34;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6010/6003983172_fc0cfb3308_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For the last couple of years, I&#39;ve been teaching regular workshops in Farmington, Maine. When I went up again last week, I had a fascinating conversation with one of the students. She was telling me how the core group had been coming along and that other people have come in and out of practicing with them. She said, &#34;you know, it&#39;s not really for everyone.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don&#39;t know if that jumps out at you as a significant statement, but as a Tai Chi teacher, it&#39;s &lt;a title=&#34;Brookline Tai Chi has no &#34;Former Students&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34;&gt;something I&#39;ve been thinking about for years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this one casual statement, she was really saying that her motivation to practice now comes from inside of herself. Along with a small group of dedicated classmates, she gets everything she needs from the practice itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a remarkable attitude. Every day, we get bombarded by messages that tell us to buy something to become something or fit in with other people. To be able to have a practice that lives inside of you, that&#39;s validated by performing it for yourself, and grows because you feed it with energy and time, is really incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, we&#39;re going to talk about how you discover your intrinsic motivation to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Absolutely Anything in 2012</title>
      <link>/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 09:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Chess at Starbucks by radioflyer007, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/radioflyer007/4677003347/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1304/4677003347_3bcb440632.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chess at Starbucks&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;205&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;At this time of year, you hear a lot about New Year&#39;s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I was happy to see a lot of people saying &#34;New Year&#39;s resolutions don&#39;t work.&#34; We all know that&#39;s true from personal experience, but these folks were referencing a growing understanding about how learning and skill-building take place. Most of what we now know about how the nervous system works flies in the face of changing through the strength of your willpower alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I urge you to leave that mindset behind in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you should think about any changes, anything you want to learn, as slowing building a skill, with small steps you can practice, building like a snowball, until you&#39;re doing great new things without trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s how that works.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3160&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deliberate Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You often hear people say, &#34;practice makes perfect&#34;, but the reality is a little more complicated. One retort is &#34;practice makes permanent&#34;, which speaks to the way that your nervous system ingrains what you do over and over so that it becomes close to automatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you actually want to learn something new this year, you need get smart about how you build your new skills. The model that captures this the clearest is the deliberate practice model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deliberate practice has four components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need a framework for understanding what to practice -- this is where seeking out guidance from someone who has mastered that skill or taught others to do so is critical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to practice a very specific skill because you need a high degree of focus -- trying to juggle two or three new things at a time won&#39;t work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need immediate feedback on your practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to practice over and over and over again, a lot.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The irony for most of us is that we want to get better at something, so we just go out and do it. It&#39;s like trying to drive somewhere new without a map. You&#39;ll base your decisions, turn-by-turn, on old information about places you&#39;ve been before, which may work pretty well, but clearly won&#39;t get you there with the same directness as having a roadmap to guide you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, step one of any new deliberate practice endeavor that you seek out is to find the right map. Get good guidance, regular feedback, and keep practicing, biting off a little at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other thing you need to worry about, once you have the deliberate practice cycle down, is staying in a healthy &#34;learning zone&#34; as you take on new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recognizing Fight-or-Flight&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A natural part of trying to master any new skill is working beyond your current capacity. The problem is that pushing yourself too far into new territory will be counter-productive. When you exceed your limites, your body initiates the fight-or-flight response and you will no longer engage in productive learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the core Z Health training principles is learning to identify the onset of the stress response in any activity. When you recognize the signs of fight-or-flight, you learn to dial back your training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you may find:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your heart rate speeds up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your breathing gets heavy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your face becomes flushed or pale or alternates between them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your mouth dries up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You move toward the fetal position in subtle ways -- your shoulders hike up, your facial muscles contract, you draw your arms in to protect your body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You stop hearing what&#39;s going on around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get &#34;tunnel vision&#34; and lose your peripheral field.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you experience these things, or more likely, when someone points out to you that they are happening or you realize it in hindsight, you know you&#39;ve exceeded your capacity to integrate new information in that moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the poise and relaxation that comes through smart, modulated training in this boxing clip. Obviously, boxing can be a brutal sport, but watch the way that this training is structured, to stretch him in different ways, testing his visual skills, playing with his threat level and capacity to integrated movement information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that the training is done correctly because of how graceful and relaxed he is able to be under this kind of pressure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/2y5jB0uZOrM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/2y5jB0uZOrM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you work through this process, probably without an army of coaches, camera crews, and fans, you&#39;ll have to look back on the experience and break down how things came together and what you could do to decrease the threat level next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one of my favorite examples of this is a college football coach who plays crowd noise over the loudspeaker during practice sessions. He wants his players to simulate game conditions as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the gradual increase in game-like threat levels as they learn new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the coach introduces a new play in the locker room. He maps it out for the players and they get the idea. Next, they head to the field without pads on and with no defense trying to stop them. Little by little, the coach can introduce new elements that demand concentration, and most importantly from our point of view, integration of new information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can control a situation so that you can selectively increase the amount of information -- visual, auditory, spatial, or physical -- that you need to integrate to master a skill, then you will be able to learn anything in a smooth, steady manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&#39;s it going to be in 2012?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Man Who Did His Tai Chi Form 19,100 Times</title>
      <link>/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2011 07:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;I got an email the other day that was a little bit different than the usual requests for lessons. It read:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I learned the Short Form at Brookline Tai Chi under the tutelage of Bill Ryan back about 1996-1997. For seven years, I continued to do the short form three times every morning. Then for the past eight years or so, I have done the short form four times every morning.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;I keep a log of my centering practices, and have documentation that over the past 15 years, I have only missed doing my tai chi on three days, two when I was strapped down in hospital beds and unable to get up, and one day when I simply forgot to practice. (I practiced twice the next day.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Thus, I have done the short form now over 17,800 times.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;There were so many things that fascinated me about getting this email. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2966&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;First of all, it reinforced my belief that there&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s no such thing as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34;&gt;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;former student&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/a&gt;. As a teacher, this was a powerful reminder that you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t know the full extent of what you are giving your students and just how far they will take what they learn.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Then, consider this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He practices tai chi every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He practices several repetitions of the short form every time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He logs his practice every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;As you know from reading this blog, I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m a little obsessed with the idea of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;practice.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Clearly this man knew something about cultivating a practice. I wanted to know more about what motivated him to practice daily and record it with such diligence. So I asked him, but I wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t ready for the depth and thoughtfulness of his answer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3105&#34; title=&#34;Sandy Davis&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/12/IMG_0518-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sandy Davis runs Resilience Works&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;It turns out, I was talking to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;The Resilience Guy.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Sandy Davis runs a company called &lt;a href=&#34;http://resilienceworks.com/&#34;&gt;ResilienceWorks&lt;/a&gt;, dedicated to teaching people how to become more resilient, or as he puts it:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;CENTER&#34;&gt;&amp;Acirc; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: small;&#34;&gt;The more you invest wisely in your own vitality,&lt;br /&gt;
The more resilient you become, and&lt;br /&gt;
The easier it is to thrive.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Many of us come to movement arts like tai chi or qigong because of an innate desire to thrive, but Sandy has gone into great depth explaining the structures that make this process possible. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He advocates for &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Seven Simple Self-Care Structures&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; that make this possible:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Keep all your agreements.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Eat well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Sleep well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Have a daily centering practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Exercise aerobically on a regular basis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Have a daily creative practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Log your self-care results every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Now, when we talk about &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;practice&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; here, we often talk about 3 or 4 of these structures (mainly centering, exercise, and sleep). We often imply that a lot of what grabs you about something like tai chi is the creative expression you derive from continually refining it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;And certainly we talk about tracking your practice -- although I haven&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t yet met anyone else who has taken this habit to quite the same degree as Sandy -- he&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s missed three days of practice in the last 14 years, and he can prove it!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;So what is it about &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;keeping all your agreements&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; that adds to your store of energy? When I heard Sandy describe this particular structure, it broadened my sense of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what builds your energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what uses up your energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; in a way I had never considered. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.resilienceworks.com/resiliencemanual&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Resilience Manual&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s guide to developing these structures, he writes:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;There is much satisfaction to be had in knowing that you are someone who can be relied upon to keep your word. By consistently walking your talk, &lt;strong&gt;you can acquire a deep-seated self-confidence in your ability to successfully follow through&lt;/strong&gt; on whatever you agree to undertake. This includes faithfully attending to your own foundational self-care habits, as well as to faithfully doing your chosen daily self-care practices.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Alternatively, there is much disappointment to be had in knowing that you are someone who routinely fails to follow through on your commitments. Whenever you fail to keep your word, whenever you fail to do what you promised, whenever you do 95% of what you said you would do and leave the last 5% unfinished, in all these instances, you experience a loss of self-respect. Each of these failures, whether obvious and public, or miniscule and private, generates a measure of personal disappointment and/or discouragement. &lt;strong&gt;Such breakdowns cost you valuable energy. They undermine your self-confidence. And they get in the way of deepening your resilience-readiness. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;What I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve highlighted in bold above should be familiar language when you think about your movement practice. You are either moving in a way that builds and integrates your coordination and your energy, or in a way that saps both and leads to dis-integration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Many of us have a gut feeling that how we cultivate a movement practice spills over into other dimensions of life, but I think Sandy has clearly articulated exactly how that works in the above passage. The lesson is that doing your movement practice won&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t make you a better person, but &lt;em&gt;it is a template for how to move toward more wholeness in other areas of your life&lt;/em&gt;. In Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s language, both structures feed your resilience-readiness and the store of resilience that you naturally draw energy from, no matter what situation you are facing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;The linchpin to all of this, from Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s point of view, is the seventh structure, or the meta-structure of logging the results of the other six structures on a daily basis. In &lt;em&gt;The Resilience Manual,&lt;/em&gt; he makes several compelling arguments for keeping a daily practice log both to gain perspective and to sustain accountability to yourself. For me, the most compelling reason is the deep satisfaction this seventh structure generates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;A week or so after our lesson, Sandy e-mailed me to make a correction to the number of times he has done the short form (hence the title of this post):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;FYI, I re-checked the numbers, and it turns out that I have actually done the short form more than 19,100 times. It will be a treat to pass the 20,000 mark. At my current rate of four times each day, that will take me another seven-plus months. But who&#39;s counting?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Think about how great that must feel to realize that you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re actually a little closer to 20,000? And not because you can brag about a number, but because you know you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve made a serious ongoing investment in your own well-being.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Big thanks to Sandy for sharing his method with so much clarity and simplicity! His website has more information, including some useful free resources and more in-depth explanations of the daily self-care structures. Check them out here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://resilienceworks.com/download.asp&#34;&gt;ResilienceWorks.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oh, and we also agreed that Sandy should come in for a tune-up every 3,000 forms, not every 10,000 or 15,000!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Day Better Breathing Challenge</title>
      <link>/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 10:17:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&#39;ve been talking a lot about two things, &lt;a title=&#34;Follow the 20-20-20 Rule for Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/21/follow-the-20-20-20-rule-for-better-breathing/&#34;&gt;improving your breathing&lt;/a&gt; to give you a &lt;a title=&#34;Disrupt the Stress Cycle with Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/26/disrupt-the-stress-cycle-with-better-breathing/&#34;&gt;major energy/relaxation boost&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a title=&#34;Building Better Practice Tools&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/&#34;&gt;developing tools&lt;/a&gt; that help you &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/?p=1494&#34;&gt;follow-through on your home practice&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve even created an online course with all the information you need to cultivate better breathing habits: &lt;a title=&#34;Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/courses/better-breathing/&#34;&gt;Better Breathing&lt;/a&gt;. The biggest lesson we learned as we talked to BTC students&amp;Acirc;  was that the best time to use reminders to trigger your practice was when you were invested in learning a new skill.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1510&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; When you&#39;re going through a period of sustained practice, integrating stuff you&#39;ve learned before, you need external tools less. However, when you shift back into learning mode and set a specific training goal, getting extra, regular motivation from an outside source can push you over the line from wanting to learn something to ingraining it as a habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to cultivate better breathing habits is a great example of skill building that benefits from extra stimulation. As I explain in the breathing course, there is a clear threshold with your breathing practice that you need to cross to make a lasting impact on your habits. In one sense, the secret to mastering better breathing habits is just putting in the time. The steps along the path to better breathing aren&#39;t always exciting or immediately gratifying, but crossing the breathing threshold puts you into a different world where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;each breath feels deep and nourishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your insides feel smooth and relaxed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you radiate a sense of well-being and easy-to-sustain energy throughout your day&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These are the kinds of things you only notice once you&#39;ve had them and lost them. The biggest challenge of cultivating these qualities is that you can&#39;t do it in one single act of will power. You need sustained, regular practice to take you over the threshold. The good news is that you can leverage external tools, instead of just will power, to carry you over the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s why I&#39;ve created the 30 Day Breathing Challenge. If you want to hit a new depth of practice in the next month, I will give you the tools to get there. For a limited time, I&#39;m giving away my online breathing course (normally $29), for free. All you have to do is sign-up for the 30-Day Challenge using the form below. I will send you daily practice reminders and weekly video instruction drawn from the course. In 30 days, you&#39;re going to see a major shift in your personal practice. Ready?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://eepurl.com/xORb&#34;&gt;Sign up for the 30 Day Challenge here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Home Practice Challenge</title>
      <link>/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:19:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the recent practice survey we conducted at Brookline Tai Chi and experiments I&#39;ve been running in online learning, it&#39;s become clearer and clearer to me that most people need some external motivation when they are learning a new skill. That&#39;s not a judgment about willpower and motivation, it actually says more about the way we are wired for survival. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1523&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In Z Health, we always talk about the way that the nervous system is at once the most plastic system -- it can adapt to lots of different changes -- and also the most stable. The stability of the nervous system is a good thing from a survival and energy management point of view -- it doesn&#39;t cost you a lot of cognitive energy to get through your day if you run on habit. In that sense, the plasticity of the nervous system -- your ability to change and learn new things -- has to deal with the inertia of stability in your nervous system. When we are trying to learn new behaviors and forge new habits, these two things can be at odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&#39;ve seen and heard from my tai chi students, is that a little bit of external motivation goes a long way to spark the small changes you need to make on a daily basis to put new behavior in place. Last week, one of my students said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was liberating to think that 5 minutes of tai chi practice meant I could make progress, because until I thought about it that way, I avoided practice, assuming it was going to take 30 minutes or more.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, if you look at some studies on mental rehearsal and brain function, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1580438,00.html&#34;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;, you start to see that the cognitive component of learning new skills can be practiced in a much easier way than devoting hours and hours of grueling practice -- time that very few people I work with have to spare anyway. The smarter you get about your practice, the better you&#39;ll get at getting good at new things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#39;s my DIY Home Practice Challenge for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drill down into your practice until you get to a small chunk you can practice in 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick the easiest time of day to devote to your practice -- what&#39;s the perfect scenario for practicing this skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a recurring reminder in your calendar -- pick the medium that will be most accessible to get the reminder at the right time, i.e. on your desktop to interrupt your work, via email, or even text message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each day when you get the reminder, do your 5 minute practice, and then maybe take a minute or two to reflect on the success of what you just did or refine the scenario if necessary&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You will fail to build up this practice habit if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pick too big a skill to work on, e.g. I want to become a ballerina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are vague about when you are going to do it, e.g. I will practice it daily&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&#39;t get the reminder at the right time, e.g. I&#39;ll practice at noon each day, but my reminder comes in at 6pm&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I know those failures might sound obvious, and you should pick something pretty simple and obvious to begin with, but what I hope is that once you see the power in this simple approach, you&#39;ll start to tackle more complex and exciting skill building and begin to reflect on a lot of different experiences, in business, at work, in personal relationships, with the same desire to make incremental progress as you do with a hobby or healthy habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m always curious to hear how this goes for people, so send me an email or drop a comment below once you get set up and start hitting your daily targets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Student Practice Habits</title>
      <link>/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2011 08:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Donkey Kong from Arcade-Musuem.com&#34; src=&#34;http://www.arcade-museum.com/images/118/1181242103213.png&#34; alt=&#34;The Donkey Kong Model of Learning&#34; height=&#34;256&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What the heck does Donkey Kong have to do with the practice habits of tai chi students? It turns out the ladders and platforms in the video game are a perfect model for understanding the ecosystem of students practice habits. Let me explain the survey design and then I&#39;ll share some really fascinating results about how people engage Brookline Tai Chi to develop their tai chi practice.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1494&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Survey Design&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Last week we conducted a small practice survey to try to get a more accurate picture of what students do outside of class. We sent out a request to participate to about 2000 people on our email list, and 30 completed the survey in detail. I then divided the 30 into 3 groups, to test the difference between two types of daily reminders and a weekly follow-up. The initial survey, sent on a Sunday, asked people about &#34;typical&#34; practice habits: frequency, duration, and content. I followed up on Friday with the same set of questions, but instead of asking what people &#34;typically&#34; practice, I asked them what they specifically practiced &#34;last week&#34;. In between the initial Sunday survey and the follow-up Friday survey, 1/3 of participants received a daily email that said &#34;Thanks again for volunteering to help us develop better practice tools for our tai chi community. I&#39;m going to send you a little practice reminder every day this week and ask you about it at the end of the week. So...take a few minutes today to do some practice!&#34;. Another third got a similar email, but it included a link to a one-question survey: &#34;what did you practice today?&#34; The last third only got the Sunday and Friday surveys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who Participated in the Survey&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, in this case, we actually know just about everyone who participated in the survey, but that&#39;s a good thing. We&#39;re not trying to run a randomized, controlled, double-blinded study. We&#39;re trying to gain deeper insight into our students&#39; experience and develop tools for them that makes the practice more rewarding. So who participated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people were relatively new to learning tai chi and chi gung&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people have been doing home practice for 15 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people attend classes 3-5 times per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people don&#39;t live nearby the school or in Massachusetts (but they were tuned in enough to what we do to complete this survey, hmmm)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I was really excited to see that we got such a range of people interested in participating in this experience. It speaks to richness of our community that the request to &#34;help us develop better practice tools&#34; was embraced by people with so many different relationships to the school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the results started coming in, it looked to me that people fell into a few distinct categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Home Practicers vs. School Practicers vs. Blended Practice People&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skill Acquisition Mode vs. Practice Plateau Mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There was also a category of what I think of now as &#34;Super Practicers&#34;. Whereas most people reported on practice frequency as a number of days, these folks said &#34;daily&#34;. As I watched their survey results come in and read how they talked about their practice, it was clear that their practice is so ingrained into their lives, that practicing for them is just like eating or breathing. Surprisingly, the amount of time the Super Practicers reported varied from 10 minutes to 2 hours. It wasn&#39;t like the 10 minute Super Practicer was yearning to be in the 2 hour category, though. It was just that 10 minutes a day makes perfect sense for the role practice plays in their life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Skill Ladders and Practice Platforms&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ok, so here&#39;s where the Donkey Kong Model comes in. It was very clear that the students we surveyed fell into two different groups, which roughly matched up to how long they had been in their practice, but not completely. Some of the participants were actively engaged in learning new material, which is usually the choreography of a tai chi or chi gung set. The folks in this category who received daily email reminders to practice did more practice during the week than they thought they typically do. The folks in this category who only got the end-of-week follow-up did less practice than they reported initially.&lt;strong&gt; It seems clear from these results that when you are on the ladder of new skill acquisition, daily practice triggers help you get there faster.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, we have the people who are maintaining a regular, ongoing practice. For these folks, there was almost no change in reported practice, whether they received daily emails or the weekly survey. To these people, the reminders were more of an annoyance (they told me so!). The conclusion here isn&#39;t that the tool is not useful, it&#39;s that these folks don&#39;t need an external reminder to perform something that is internally motivated. More importantly, seeing very little change in the Practice Plateau group highlighted the impact of the daily reminders on the Skill Acquisition group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Donkey King Model is useful here, because over the course of your lifetime of practice, you don&#39;t just go through one Skill Acquisition Phase and one Practice Plateau. I like that image from the game of hanging out on a platform for a while, at a certain level of practice, before you embark on another climb up the skill ladder. From my own experience as a student and as a teacher, I think this is much more common. My intuition is that the daily reminder tool could be refined, if it&#39;s goal-specific enough, to be useful to anyone who is in a Skill Acquisition Phase, not just complete beginners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where Does Motivation Come From?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Where does motivation come from? I don&#39;t actually know for sure, but we learned some really interesting stuff about how people construct their practice. There seems to be a spectrum from internal to external sources of motivation. Again, this often correlated to how long people have been doing the practice, but not completely. Here&#39;s what I mean: when people first walk through the door to learn chi gung or tai chi, they need external motivation: they don&#39;t have the right information yet, they don&#39;t know what to practice, and they don&#39;t have any practice habits yet (for this art).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you climb one or two skill ladders, you start to feel the benefits of practice. You no longer practice &#34;because my doctor told me to&#34; or because &#34;I saw people doing it in the parks in China&#34;. Instead, the practice starts to satisfy you on some level. At this point, we see some branching. There are a small number of people who take one course and then go off and practice on their own forever. To me, they&#39;ve abandoned all of the external motivation we can provide, and made regular practice 100% internally driven. More often we see students who are happy to have the social support of classmates, a physical place to practice, and the guidance of an instructor -- all external motivators --- to keep their practice going. Many slot into this relationship with the school indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our instructors tells a funny story where a friend of hers, on hearing that she&#39;s been coming to classes for 15 years, said &#34;Don&#39;t you know it already?&#34; That&#39;s a perfect example of assuming that long term practice is one big skill ladder to climb. It&#39;s not. The practice plateaus along the way are not the same as the linear climb to skill acquisition and part of what a community like Brookline Tai Chi offers is not only external motivation, but external connection -- to people and a place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any progress we make developing practice tools for our students will have to consider all of these factors, internal and external motivators, phases of skill acquisition and even the satisfaction of practice plateaus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That brings me to the most surprising result in our survey. Many of the participants fell into the Super Practicer category, with extremely high internal motivation to practice, and in some cases no immediate geographic proximity to the school. By all appearances, this is the group who has moved on from everything we have to offer -- weekly classes, skill ladders, a space, people to practice with, instructor feedback . So why did so many of these folks respond to a request to develop practice tools for our community? In one sense, they appear to be the least connected to the day-to-day activities of the school and the least in need of help with practice, but they all responded to our request and gave a tremendous amount of insight into their practice habits. It&#39;s going to be a huge payoff for me when we finally figure out what makes these folks tick.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Better Practice Tools</title>
      <link>/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 09:20:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m running a little experiment right now at Brookline Tai Chi to see if we can help our students develop better home practice habits. Specifically, I&#39;m experimenting with self-reporting and automated reminders to spark daily practice sessions outside of class.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1438&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when I talk to other people in our international tai chi community, I realize what a powerful practice aid Brookline Tai Chi already is. What I mean is, the bricks-and-mortar experience of coming to the school and being around other people removes so many barriers people have to doing tai chi. It sounds too obvious to mention, but that is exactly why participating at the school is such a powerful way to build a practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this project, though, I&#39;m experimenting with email reminders and surveys to get an initial feel for what people do outside of class. I want to see if I can help them trigger more practice sessions during the week. From the initial self-reporting, it also appears that there are many daily practicers already, so I also want to see if there is a systematic way to help them shape their practice and get more out of it. Hopefully, this is the beginning of a longer conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not going to explain the experiment in detail just yet, because I want people to go through it without too much bias, but I&#39;ll share the results here once we know what we&#39;ve found. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>xkcd: Let Go</title>
      <link>/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 08:43:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Be sure to mouse over for the original title text from the comic (Thanks, Nate!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/862/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; title=&#34;After years of trying various methods, I broke this habit by pitting my impatience against my laziness. I decoupled the action and the neurological reward by setting up a simple 30-second delay I had to wait through, in which I couldn&#39;t do anything else, before any new page or chat client would load (and only allowed one to run at once). The urge to check all those sites magically vanished--and my &#39;productive&#39; computer use was unaffected.&#34; src=&#34;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/let_go.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;518&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buried Psychological Nuggets</title>
      <link>/2011/02/05/buried-psychological-nuggets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2011 09:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/05/buried-psychological-nuggets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/mba-earn-more-money/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a long post&lt;/a&gt; from one of my favorite authors, Ramit Sethi. He often writes about putting ideas into action and I think this post is another great example, BUT, that&#39;s not what I want to highlight here.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-598&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I think this is my new favorite concept:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skepticism is not a strategy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to one of my top Earn1k students last week &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; she earned over $80,000 in 8 weeks &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; and she was talking about how much her entire viewpoint has changed. Once you realize that you can control your situation &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; how much you earn, how much you work, where you live, etc &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s amazing to look back at ourselves a few years ago&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;when we were skeptical and disbelieving that any of this could work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skeptics always have an excuse because it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s easier to be skeptical than to take the risk of trying something and possibly failing. Skeptics use codewords &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; much like racists do &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; to mask their fear and loathing of something different. For example, they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll say they don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have enough time (when everyone has the same 24 hours per day). They&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll complain about having &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;already tried that,&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; but when you dig in and ask them what they actually tried, they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll demur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s nothing I hate more than vocal skeptics &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; not only because they cheat themselves out of their own potential, but because they convince others that they can&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t do it, either.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can see this all over the place. It&#39;s another version of the Taoist saying that &#34;you become what you practice&#34;. You can literally watch skeptics develop a hard shell of denial as they try fewer and fewer new things. I&#39;m not necessarily blaming someone for this tendency, but I think it becomes a cycle that reinforces itself. That&#39;s why I love Ramit&#39;s writing: &#34;skepticism is not a strategy&#34; doesn&#39;t get into the blame, shame, or origin of the behavior, but it calls it out directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way he writes just draws such clean lines. Take this distinction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I write for the As, Bs, and Cs &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; but I systematically ignore one of them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine  the world has As, Bs, and Cs in  any field. In this one, the As are  already managing their money,  they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve read my book (and others), and  they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re earning as much as they  need to lead the lifestyle they choose. They&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re already doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The  Bs are the greatest in number. They  have the potential to do something  great, but for whatever reason &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;  like actual barriers, self-imposed  barriers, or external  responsibilities &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; they &amp;Acirc; haven&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t achieved what  their potential first. &lt;em&gt;They can be reached if you communicate to them in the right way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The  Cs are a lost cause. Sure, they  might be salvageable to help, but  that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s not something I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m interested  in or capable of. This enrages  certain people who believe that we  should help everyone, but I live in  the world of practicality, not  utopia. If I have the chance to help an A  become an A+ in 3 months, or a  C become a B- in 3 years, who am I going  to choose? There are other  people who make it their life&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s work to work  with Cs, but it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s not me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And  so this is also applicable for you.  When I teach negotiation, or  interviewing, or automation, or even  earning more money, I teach you how  to focus on the right level of  analysis for you. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s ok not to please everyone. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d rather spend my  time hyper-focused on exactly your needs than try to serve everyone.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Great stuff! Here&#39;s that link again: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/mba-earn-more-money/&#34;&gt;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/mba-earn-more-money/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simplicity, Persuasion and Technology</title>
      <link>/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 08:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been reading/watching a lot of BJ Fogg&#39;s work lately. He studies &lt;a href=&#34;http://captology.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;the persuasive power of technology for positive behavior change&lt;/a&gt;. You&#39;ll recognize my interest here if you read some of my recent posts on game design mechanics and the potential to integrate technology into real world learning. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-557&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Check out his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/bjfogg&#34;&gt;Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; for some shorter videos that explain facets of his work &#34;in 60 seconds&#34;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s Dr. Fogg on simplicity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/2094487&#34;&gt;BJ Fogg on Simplicity&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/bjfogg&#34;&gt;BJ Fogg&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He makes a really important distinction around the 3:20 mark. We tend to think of simplicity as a feature of our technology, but he disagrees. Instead, he says &#34;simplicity is a perception we have of the experience in accomplishing the task&#34;. This means that you have to consider the person and the context if you want to facilitate behavior change, not just the information you are giving them, or the medium you are using to deliver the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, I&#39;ll write more about his 3-part behavior change model, summed up as &#34;putting hot triggers in the path of motivated people&#34; and try to explain how I see Motivation, Ability, and Triggers applied to teaching, business, and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all fascinating stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>