<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>courses-and-events on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/categories/courses-and-events/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in courses-and-events on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/courses-and-events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching the First &#34;Foundations of Relaxation&#34; Course</title>
      <link>/2011/03/15/launching-the-first-foundations-of-relaxation-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 16:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/15/launching-the-first-foundations-of-relaxation-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m pretty excited about this: &lt;a href=&#34;/courses/eyes-and-visual-training/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eyes and Visual Training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-714&#34; title=&#34;Floating Hot Dog&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/03/Hot-Dog-300x169.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;169&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s my new online course and the first in the Foundations of Relaxation Series I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As I&#39;ve been developing the course, I keep saying to myself, &#34;I wish everyone who comes to see me for pain relief or to learn tai chi did this first.&#34; In fact, that&#39;s how I developed the whole series. There are a few simple things that don&#39;t take a lot of oversight or feedback from an instructor that everyone can do to move better (meaning more gracefully and in less pain).&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-712&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m offering it at a pretty steep discount on what I plan to sell it for: $49 for now, instead of $97 (so snatch it up!). Plus, you get lifetime access to the material, so you can keep coming back to it and working on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a host of secondary reasons this is exciting too. One of them is that I&#39;m using Trainerfly, my web-based training app, to run the course. I&#39;m already using it with private clients and remotely teaching a tai chi group in Maine, but this is the first full course. I&#39;m sure I&#39;ll learn a ton by doing it, which is great, because I have a few other tai chi teachers interested in doing the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for updates on how it&#39;s going once people are in the system working with the course material!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>