<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-gates on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/energy-gates/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy-gates on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/energy-gates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 Update</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 09:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s a quick update on what we&#39;ve been working on during Immersion Week 2014.

I&#39;m very impressed (and I say so in the video about 15 times!) with the way this group has patiently explored many different facets of the Swings and Spine Stretch without rushing ahead to try to fit seemingly contradictory pieces together conceptually.
Instead, they&#39;re doing a great job experiencing/exploring each different component on its own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Moving Exercises: Immersion Week 2014</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 10:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m getting excited about Immersion Week at BTC next month, where we&#39;ll take another look at the Spine Stretch and the Three Swings. Another look? Like we&#39;ve done it before? Yes!
Why is it exciting to go back to the same qigong sets over and over again?
So-called creative people understand better than most that there is nothing new under the sun. Working with boulders of granite, with empty stages, with blank paper, they are credited with making something out of nothing, but that isn&#39;t exactly what they do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 and the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Book</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 16:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m very excited to share some news about two big projects with you today: Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s annual Immersion Week and the publication of the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance as a physical book.

Join me from Tuesday, April 22 - Friday, April 25 at Brookline Tai Chi in Boston for Energy Gates Moving Qigong Exercises. Times, cost, and registration details in the link.
The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance is now available for purchase on Amazon, but you can also get your copy of the physical book directly from the publisher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When to Follow a Practice Recipe and When to Reflect on Your Practice</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 09:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>In this video, we&#39;re talking about building up the skill of Outer Dissolving in your standing qigong practice.
When you start out, it pays to follow a recipe - a set of instructions that lead through a certain procedure physically, energetically, and with your mind. However, there are times you want to break away from the recipe and times you&#39;ll want to reflect on your experience verbally -- but there are good and bad ways to do both.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting at the Crown of the Head</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/01/16/starting-at-the-crown-of-the-head/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 14:13:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/01/16/starting-at-the-crown-of-the-head/</guid>
      <description>If you read last week&#39;s post on standing qigong and the Energy Gates book, or better yet, you can stand comfortably &#34;just feeling&#34; for 15-20 minutes, you&#39;re probably ready to embark on the downward dissolving process.
This week, I want to help you get started.
I recorded a guided practice mp3 to get you through the first workout in the Energy Gates series: Feeling the Gate at the Crown of the Head.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 09:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>When you set out to develop your internal energy using standing postures, there are two main ways you can go about it: by feel or by form.
Now, there will be a lot of overlap in these two broad approaches, like aligning your body with gravity without collapsing internally and progressively releasing and relaxing as you stand, but when it comes to the role of the mind, form and feel can be very different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates in Vancouver, BC, Spring 2014</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 17:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</guid>
      <description>Dan standing in New Mexico, not Vancouver (yet!).
Do you live in or near Vancouver?
Are you willing to travel to refine your Energy Gates practice?
At the behest of a few eager Vancouver locals, I wanted to reach out and see if any of our Northwest-oriented readers would be interested in a spring 2014 Energy Gates seminar.
Date and exact location haven&#39;t been nailed down yet, but if there&#39;s enough demand, I would love to come out and do some Energy Gates with you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dragon and Tiger Exercises for Activating the Lower Tantien</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 07:32:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re borrowing a technique from Dragon and Tiger qigong to try and get a better sense of the lower tantien. The lower tantien (&#34;dan-tee-en&#34;) is the energetic center of your physical body, located just below your navel, on the central axis of the body. If you dropped a line down from the crown of the head, through the body, and out the bottom of the pelvis, it would pass through the lower tantien.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 08:23:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>From the outside, standing qigong can look calm, peaceful and meditative.
On the inside, if you don&#39;t ask yourself these 3 essential questions, standing can be grueling. Your muscles ache, you tremble and sweat, and in burning discomfort you strain to see how much longer you must endure.
It doesn&#39;t have to be torture, though, if you adopt the right mindset as you practice.

Over the years, I have learned many different standing qigong techniques from my teacher Bruce Frantzis, but when I practice what he&#39;s taught about mindset and attitude in standing qigong, I&#39;ve had some of my biggest breakthroughs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Do I Keep My Awareness for Jumping Around?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/01/09/how-do-i-keep-my-awareness-for-jumping-around/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 11:57:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/01/09/how-do-i-keep-my-awareness-for-jumping-around/</guid>
      <description>One of the major goals of standing qigong is to develop a strong downward flow that clears stagnant energy out of your system and strengthens your natural restorative abilities.
When you begin to work on this process, though,&amp;Acirc; it&#39;s natural to wonder how strict you need to be able sticking with the downward flow and what to do if you start to notice other things happening in the body. Recently, I got this question via email that nails the exact issue:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guided Practice Aides</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/guided-practice-aides/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 15:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/guided-practice-aides/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s a round-up of guided practice aides I&#39;ve put together in various sections of the site.
What else would help you with your current practice? Let me know here.

To download the audio files below, right click and &#34;save as&#34;.
Breathing
Use these basic principles as a guide for your breathing and standing practice:

Downloads:
20-Minute Guided Practice #1
20-Minute Guided Practice #2
Standing Qigong
You can progress through longer standing sessions with these guided practice mp3s or pick one on any given day that matches your practice goals:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Case Study: Energy Gates Tune-Up</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/21/case-study-energy-gates-tune-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 06:51:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/21/case-study-energy-gates-tune-up/</guid>
      <description>In this case study, you&#39;ll see how Kevin improved his Cloud Hands and Swings through video feedback.
While you can follow a guided practice for the standing qigong portion of Energy Gates, doing a follow-along for the moving exercises doesn&#39;t really help you improve your practice, so feedback is key.
Going through the process of not only getting a correction, but watching yourself before and after, helps you internalize the new movement pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swings Webinar Replay</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/12/swings-webinar-replay/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 08:15:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/12/swings-webinar-replay/</guid>
      <description>Just a quick note to let you know that if you missed Sunday&#39;s webinar on the Three Swings from Opening the Energy Gates, you can check out a replay here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Active Should I Be When Standing?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/08/how-active-should-i-be-when-standing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2011 15:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/08/how-active-should-i-be-when-standing/</guid>
      <description>Lately, I&#39;ve been trying to do some sinking during standing qigong,&amp;Acirc; in addition to other practices, like opening and closing, but I don&#39;t get the full calming effect of the sinking.&amp;Acirc; This is a problem, because it gets a lot of energy moving and something this manifests as more anger than I would like. What should I do?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s The Best Way to Practice &#34;Sinking the Chest?&#34;</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/06/whats-the-best-way-to-practice-sinking-the-chest-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2011 16:01:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/06/whats-the-best-way-to-practice-sinking-the-chest-2/</guid>
      <description>Sinking the chest while raising the spine is a key energetic alignment practiced in Tai Chi to facilitate a grounding, downward flow of energy.
Martial artists use it to develop their root and anyone who &#34;gets stuck in their head&#34; will find some relief employing this principle.
The question is:
Do you have a good standing position to practice sinking the chest?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>