<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>moodle on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/moodle/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in moodle on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/moodle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>New Video for Tai Chi Group</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2010 09:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a sneak peek at some online learning support I&#39;m doing with a Tai Chi group in Farmington, Maine. I went up a couple weeks ago to teach an afternoon workshop and this was the practice set we did by the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop participants also have access to a private Q&amp;amp;A forum, so as they practice between now and the next live training, I can give them feedback. I&#39;ll probably add some new videos as we go to answer any questions that come up. I also think it will be a useful way to pre-load content for the next workshop, i.e., if I can get them to learn some basic choreography before I arrive, we can spend our time focusing on refinements or more subtle internal principles that are best learned by feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the clip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/yu9gAYbhZi4?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/yu9gAYbhZi4?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learn Qigong Online?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/18/learn-qigong-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 06:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/18/learn-qigong-online/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Can you learn qigong, or any movement art, online? This is a burning question for me right now. My immediate reaction is &#34;NO!&#34;. However, I believe there is a significant role for supplemental online material in the overall learning process, even for movement arts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s why it&#39;s a bad idea to learn movement online:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning movement is a kinesthetic experience, not a visual one -- you have to feel where you are in space and you certainly can&#39;t get that from staring at a screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need feedback -- when you are learning something new, you need refinement and guidance, usually hands-on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some things need to be felt on another person -- we get into this all the time with more subtle qigong principles and there is no way around feeling what&#39;s going on in the instructor&#39;s body to learn what you are trying to do in your own&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Those are my big 3 &#34;No way!&#34; reasons you can&#39;t learn qigong online. Or I should say, the reason why online learning shouldn&#39;t be your sole way of learning this stuff. Let&#39;s look at it from a different point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assuming you have some in-person feedback, at some time, can online resources supplement your movement education? Absolutely!&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here&#39;s why:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need practice. If you really want to &#34;get it&#34; you need to practice more outside of class time with an instructor than in class time. So, will a double-check of something you already learned help keep you on track? Yup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say you don&#39;t have regular access to an instructor. Are there certain things that you can begin to work on so that when you do meet up, you&#39;ll make the most of your time? Uh huh.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So, I think you can see, while I doubt how effective it is to learn movement exclusively online, I&#39;m in favor of online resources for movement education that support live training. I think there are novel uses for prep to maximize in-person time and follow-up to keep personal practice on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Moodle, I&#39;ve been developing an online qigong program with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.relaxationmeditation.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; and we&#39;ll be rolling out a version for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brooklinetaichi.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt; in the coming months. Paul developed the course material initially to keep his workshop students on track between seminars. We&#39;re going to use some of the same content to help people interested in starting at BTC get a jump start before new classes roll around.&amp;Acirc;  Of course, you&#39;ll hear more about how this all goes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile-izing Wordpress and Moodle</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/15/mobile-izing-wordpress-and-moodle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 14:16:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/15/mobile-izing-wordpress-and-moodle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time today upgrading the site and my phone so that I would have better mobile access to the site on my phone and so that you can too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what I ended up doing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding the &lt;a href=&#34;http://mobilepress.co.za/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MobilePress&lt;/a&gt; plugin to DanKleiman.com, so that the site adapts to your mobile browser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing the Wordpress app on my Droid, so that I can update the site from my phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.moodle.org/en/Moodle_for_Mobiles&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Moodle for Mobiles&lt;/a&gt;, which is &#34;is designed to work with mobile phones in Japan&#34;. Is that why it failed? I couldn&#39;t get the php to run cleanly.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overall, I think this was a good step forward, except for the Moodle situation. It looks like there are several different native apps for mobile devices that are or are becoming available. That&#39;s good. I don&#39;t know if I&#39;ll have to modify the site to accommodate them or what. Depending on how I migrate current clients of mine over to Trainerfly, I may or may not look into this further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading a site update!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Mobile</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/15/going-mobile/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 14:05:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/15/going-mobile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a test post from my phone. I just installed a Wordpress app for Android. I&#39;m also working on upgrading the blog and the noodle site for easy mobile access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: It looks like it picked up the post tags from my phone, but it missed the category. Also have to edit the post author through the site. But you don&#39;t really care about that, do you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;;-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Backstory: The Moodle Project</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/14/trainerfly-backstory-the-moodle-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2010 14:42:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/14/trainerfly-backstory-the-moodle-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post is the second in a series I&#39;m doing on the backstory of how I came to develop a web-based software application called Trainerfly. You can read more about it &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/category/trainerfly/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For about a year after I decided I need a way to manage all my clients&#39; programs, and share information with them privately, I wrestled with finding the right software. I tried private blogs, but at that time it was tons of work to partition information for each client. I tried creating a private social network for all my clients through &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ning.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ning&lt;/a&gt;, with the idea that I would message people with their individual updates and share videos inside the network, but it never quite had the right feel. Finally, short of building something from scratch, I found Moodle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moodle.org&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-306&#34; title=&#34;moodle-logo&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/moodle-logo.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;46&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moodle stands for Modular Object Oriented Dynamic Learning Environment, in case you thought people just randomly came up with names for websites and programs on the internet! Basically, Moodle is an open-source online classroom software and it had everything I needed, including a huge development community, to get my clients set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a school structure, you have students, courses, and teachers. What I was able to do was create a unique &#34;course&#34; in which I enrolled every client as a &#34;student&#34; and I was the teacher. The nice thing about Moodle is that teachers can do lots of behind the scenes stuff, like editing courses and sharing resources that follow them around the school and most importantly for my needs, control enrollment. That was the element I was missing before. Now, every client could log in and see their program information, inside a course, but they didn&#39;t have access to anyone else&#39;s information. And, I could share the same info over and over again with different clients, with the click of the mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-350&#34; title=&#34;student screen&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/student-screen2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;732&#34; height=&#34;363&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What you&#39;re looking at above is a screen cap from a typical student program.&amp;Acirc;  After my first session with a new client, I would log in to my Moodle installation on my website and create a new client profile, a new course for them and enroll them in that course. Then, I would write up a recap of what we covered. All together it would take me five minutes to set it up and fill in the details, once the system was set up. Eventually, I was also able to share video of the exercises with them, thanks to an agreement with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zhealth.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Z Health&lt;/a&gt; to test this system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After subsequent sessions, I would simply update this program section in their course with new information or new links to video, audio, or other type of files. Some trainers that I set up on this system also began to include interactive pieces, where their clients could write back to them through Moodle. Think of a regular classroom environment, with quizzes and reports and you can image the scope of things Moodle was able to do. In fact, I found it could do too much for what I needed, but more on that below...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was one other huge advantage that I want to point out of having a system like this in place. The typical trainer is juggling 20-30 clients at once throughout their training week. How do they stay organized when everyone has different goals and is working on different material? Well, for me, it became a simple matter of logging in to this system and calling up a particular client&#39;s program -- even if I hadn&#39;t seen them in 3 months, I could pick up right where we left off! Think about the confidence in me and the value they felt when they walked back into the room after a long absence and I could say, &#34;Joe, how&#39;s the right knee doing?&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s part of my program dashboard where I could call up anyone&#39;s program instantly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-large wp-image-309&#34; title=&#34;program screen&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/program-screen-1024x640.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for about a year this was working great with my clients. As I mentioned above, I brought the concept to Z Health and they were interested in sharing this with their whole community of trainers. The next time I went out to Phoenix, I presented what I had been working on to a group of about 30 Z trainers and from there, signed up half a dozen to test the system live with their clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll talk about the interesting things I learned from this &#34;beta test&#34; soon. Eventually, it led me to seek out someone to build brand new web app, from the ground up, based on the concept we proved in Moodle, but ultimately with a more user-friendly environment and scalable infrastructure. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>