<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>business-tools on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/business-tools/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in business-tools on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/business-tools/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>User Feedback from Trainerfly Beta</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 08:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</guid>
      <description>Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve gotten Trainerfly out into people&#39;s hands and I&#39;ve been learning some really interesting lessons. I think it was easy for me to get wrapped up in how I&#39;ve evolved it as a tool in my business over the last two years and lose perspective on how other people might be trying to add it into their business from scratch, with none of that prior history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Cycles</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 14:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m coming to another big teaching cycle in Trainerfly and I think this short clip of David Heinemeier Hansson speaking at Stanford&#39;s Entrepreneurship Corner is really useful to frame the mindset:

I know the point in the clip above is more about a strategy to take when you look at the &#34;big guys&#34;, but I really feel like the alternating cycles of &#34;spending&#34; and &#34;teaching&#34; are relevant here. We just went through a &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with the Old....Business Model</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 16:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s the end of the year and it&#39;s time to get out of old habits and mindsets.
So, here&#39;s my prediction for the best business model for independent fitness and wellness pros, for the next DECADE. Yeah, I think it&#39;s going to take a few years to unfold, but the groundwork has been laid:
 No more brick-and-mortar businesses. Trust me, I know what it&#39;s like to cut a $10,000 rent check each month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become an Enterprise of One </title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 09:04:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</guid>
      <description>Over at TechCrunch, Stephen Martin lays out his thesis about an interesting turning point for entrepreneurs in this economic climate. I could quote the piece at length, but I think this part is especially important:
These business mavericks live by a new dynamic of success &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; unique individual strengths, expertise and credibility &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; fueled by today&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s cultural and technological changes. In this new dimension of business lies the secret to success in our transformed world of commerce.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Systems? No Raise for You This Year!</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/10/no-systems-no-raise-for-you-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 09:50:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/10/no-systems-no-raise-for-you-this-year/</guid>
      <description>You probably don&#39;t realize it, but there is a good chance you are letting a lot of extra money in your business slip right out of your hands. In fact, if you don&#39;t have good systems in place, I can almost guarantee it. In this post I&#39;ll pull back the curtain and show you some of the systems I use to keep things running tighter. Specifically, I&#39;m going to tell you about an end of year/new year&#39;s marketing campaign, targeting my private clients from 2010.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Pre-Launch in the Works</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/29/trainerfly-pre-launch-in-the-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 14:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/29/trainerfly-pre-launch-in-the-works/</guid>
      <description>I spent a fair amount of time today migrating, connecting, and updating. Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve been building out a wordpress front-end site for Trainerfly. My brother Sam has come through with some awesome illustration, including the logo and characters for the blog tutorials.
We had a funny debate about the use of flies on the site and got pretty carried away at one point. It started to look like &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can you teach movement online?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/19/can-you-teach-movement-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 15:44:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/19/can-you-teach-movement-online/</guid>
      <description>In a recent post, I asked the question &#34;Can you learn qigong (or any movement art) online?&#34; The answer was a big fat qualified &#34;yes.&#34; I think there is a limited role that online resources can play in your movement education --- even though movement is something best learned through live human interaction.
So the question for you, as a movement coach, is not whether or not you can teach online, the question is &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Backstory: The Moodle Project</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/14/trainerfly-backstory-the-moodle-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2010 14:42:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/14/trainerfly-backstory-the-moodle-project/</guid>
      <description>This post is the second in a series I&#39;m doing on the backstory of how I came to develop a web-based software application called Trainerfly. You can read more about it here.
For about a year after I decided I need a way to manage all my clients&#39; programs, and share information with them privately, I wrestled with finding the right software. I tried private blogs, but at that time it was tons of work to partition information for each client.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Backstory: The Practice Problem</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 08:05:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m sure I&#39;m not alone here. Teachers in all disciples, if they need their students to practice to learn what they are teaching, will relate. I don&#39;t know if &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;movement educators&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; have it worse because people tend to think of all movement as &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;working out&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; -- something you go and do, not an art you have to practice.
In fact, one of my favorite concepts when you are talking about getting really good at something is called &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;deliberate practice&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>