<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>posture on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/posture/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in posture on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/posture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoid Bad Tai Chi Posture</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/14/avoid-bad-tai-chi-posture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 17:12:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/14/avoid-bad-tai-chi-posture/</guid>
      <description>Tai Chi has the potential to solve many common posture-related problems, but only if you follow the correct Tai Chi principles.
Specifically, you want to pay attention to the body alignments that unify the arms, legs, and spine, creating effortless openness throughout the skeletal system.
In Tai Chi, the way you hold your neck and head and release the pelvis into the legs are the exact opposite of what those of us who sit all day do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Shift Your Sense of Time in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/02/how-to-shift-your-sense-of-time-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2013 08:40:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/02/how-to-shift-your-sense-of-time-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>Last month, we discussed the sense of progress you can sometimes struggle with in your practice. At the time, I mentioned that I&#39;ve been working up to a two-hour standing session, which is a very structured practice goal.
Today, I wanted to report back about what I&#39;ve been experiencing in standing qigong and show you how to shift your sense of the time that passes when you stand. The structure of adding one minute to the length of the stand each day is seems like it should make for a very linear sense of time when you practice.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>