<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>chicago-tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/chicago-tai-chi/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in chicago-tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/chicago-tai-chi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Seminar Recap - Detailed Report from ChicagoTaiChi.org</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/17/seminar-recap-detailed-report-from-chicagotaichi-org/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 14:15:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/17/seminar-recap-detailed-report-from-chicagotaichi-org/</guid>
      <description>Checking in with one of my favorite sculptures at the Art Institute
I was thrilled to be able to share a weekend of Tai Chi in Chicago earlier this month, thanks to Energy Arts Instructor Chris Cinnamon and his students at Enso Tai Chi.
Chris just posted an incredibly detailed report summarizing the workshop here.
If you read between the lines a little bit, you can come up with some great ways to structure your own practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Rooting, Sinking, and More in Chicago</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/11/tai-chi-rooting-sinking-and-more-in-chicago/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 16:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/11/tai-chi-rooting-sinking-and-more-in-chicago/</guid>
      <description>Inspiration for Rooting and Lengthening in Chicago
On November 9, I&#39;ll be teaching a seminar for my friend Chris Cinnamon at Enso Tai Chi (registration details here).
This year we&#39;ll continue the &#34;Put More Chi in Your Tai Chi&#34; theme that we started last year by focusing on Tai Chi Rooting, Sinking Chi, Dissolving, and more.
The goal is to give everyone a clear sense of how nourishing it can be to find your root and feed it through solo exercises and interactive partner practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put More Chi in Your Tai Chi -- Upcoming Chicago Seminar</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/15/put-more-chi-in-your-tai-chi-upcoming-chicago-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 14:03:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/15/put-more-chi-in-your-tai-chi-upcoming-chicago-seminar/</guid>
      <description>Next month I&#39;ll be teaching at Enso Tai Chi.
If you&#39;re in the Chicago area, come by to and learn how to go deeper into the internal work of your Tai Chi practice.
Here&#39;s what we&#39;ll be focusing on:

Seminar Details
Date: Saturday, November 10
 Time: 10:00am - 12:30pm and 2:00 - 4:00pm
 Cost: $65
 Pre-requisite: Open to all Tai Chi styles
 Location: Enso Studio, 412 S.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>