<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi-research on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/tai-chi-research/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi-research on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/tai-chi-research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Obviously Tai Chi Improves Balance, But How Do You Explain It?</title>
      <link>/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 14:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4716&#34; alt=&#34;don + sue 2&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/07/don-+-sue-2-e1373377188614-261x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;261&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We often talk about the way Tai Chi can &lt;a title=&#34;The Transformational Power of Tai Chi Body Mechanics&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/07/the-transformational-power-of-tai-chi-body-mechanics/&#34;&gt;improve your physical health and mental and emotional well-being&lt;/a&gt; from the point of view of the practitioner. But not everyone out there is as familiar with practical ways to use Tai Chi to support their health and wellness goals as you may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later this year, I&#39;m thrilled to have the chance to share Tai Chi with physicians in a course at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hmscme.com/activelives/faculty&#34;&gt;Harvard Medical School&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s always exciting to be able to present a combination of research and practice to knowledgeable caregivers, especially because in this case, the focus of the course is on promoting healthy, active lifestyles to their patients. What do you think I should share with them? If you have suggestions for what I should cover, please leave a note in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the mean time, I&#39;d like to invite you into a conversation about &lt;em&gt;how we talk about the benefits of our practice.&lt;/em&gt; As Brookline Tai Chi has been working with the Department of Public Health and other senior care agencies to spread practical implementation of &lt;a title=&#34;Dr. Fuzhong Li&#39;s Tai Chi Research&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dr-fuzhong-lis-tai-chi-research/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi falls prevention research&lt;/a&gt;, we find ourselves in a very different world, using new language and talking to new audiences about the benefits of Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent episode of Qigong Radio, Dr. Peter Wayne discussed the &lt;a title=&#34;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, a framework that he uses to define his Tai Chi research. We need more thoughtful ways like this to express the benefits of Tai Chi practice in an understandable way, without watering everything down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to keep the conversation moving in this direction, so I took the problem to one of my most eloquent teachers, Don Ethan Miller. As a result, Don and I have been working on a new program, called &lt;strong&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/strong&gt;, which will be out later this summer. In The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance, we set out to refine the language around Tai Chi balance concepts and, more importantly, get at the essence of what makes Tai Chi so good for improving balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we would like you to join in the conversation. Please join us for a discussion of The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance on Thursday, July 18, from 12-1pm EST. We will explore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The essential elements of a Tai Chi balance training program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to make sure you include these balance exercises in every practice session, whether your goal is falls prevention, becoming more relaxed and centered,  or training for competition-level Push Hands &lt;em&gt;(the secret is that it can be the same training!)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to share Tai Chi balance training with friends and family -- without making them feel like they have to take on a serious practice to get real benefits.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p3p1&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p3p1&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p3p1;(function(d, t) { var s = d.createElement(t), options = { &#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,  &#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p3p1&#39;,  &#39;autoResize&#39;:true, &#39;height&#39;:&#39;728&#39;, &#39;async&#39;:true, &#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,  &#39;ssl&#39;:true}; s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;; s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() { var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return; try { r7p3p1 = new WufooForm();r7p3p1.initialize(options);r7p3p1.display(); } catch (e) {}}; var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr); })(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living between the Lab and the Classroom with Dr. Peter Wayne</title>
      <link>/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2012 09:50:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-3237&#34; title=&#34;PW Correction&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/01/PW-Correction.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;215&#34; height=&#34;197&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trained in Evolutionary Biology, Peter Wayne, Ph.D., has spent the last 12 years in medical research and more than 35 years studying and teaching Tai Chi. He now serves as Research Director for the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine jointly based at the Harvard Medical School and Brigham and Women&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Hospital, where a primary focus of his research is studying the clinical and physiological impacts of Tai Chi on health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to Peter about the unique opportunities and challenges of being both a Tai Chi teacher and a researcher and how these two different roles inform each other. He is currently working on a book about the same topic. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3233&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little about your book&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book summarizes what the medical research community knows about the clinical health benefits of Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;for example, Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s impact on heart disease, balance, psychological well being, and overall quality of life. But it also tries to go a little further, exploring the biological mechanisms that may underlie why Tai Chi is effective for so many conditions. To do this, I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve organized the book around what I call &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the eight active ingredients of Tai Chi.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; The grouping of these ingredients reflect both what I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve learned is essential in Tai Chi from my many Tai Chi and qigong teachers, and also what I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve learned from our Tai Chi research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The concept of isolating active ingredients is common in other medical research. But does it really make sense to think of Tai Chi within this framework?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great question&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;..and I think absolutely so. Part of why I chose this language is to bend the ear of my medical colleagues&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;to try to communicate in their language. Even if we see positive clinical effects in Tai Chi trials, without plausible mechanisms&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; that is, being able to attribute clinical health effects to specific &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;active ingredients&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;, research results often have little traction in the medical community. Mechanisms are part of what we call the totality of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, by using this language, we&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve been able to emphasize Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s richness&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;that it includes not just one active ingredient&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;but many&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;including those related to neuromuscular control, breathing, cognitive processes, etc. This may explain why it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s helpful for so diverse a set of health issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a teacher, thinking in terms of active ingredients has helped me shape a curriculum that tries to maximize the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;dosage&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; of essential tai chi principles in as short a period of time as is possible. This is key for teaching in clinical trials which are often constrained in length due to funding limitations; but also relevant to community-based classes where we want people to get a real taste of deep Tai Chi as quickly and efficiently as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living in the research world and the Tai Chi world at the same time allows Peter to apply lessons from one to the other. Here he explains how his scientific education influences the way he understands teaching Tai Chi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My formal academic training was in evolutionary biology and ecological modeling, and my research for the first 15 years was with plants. So shifting to medical research 12 years ago was a big change for me. Consequently, I bring a somewhat unique perspective to the teams of medical researchers I work with. My training to think ecologically, in terms of systems, is more like Chinese Medicine in that it focuses on ecological interactions within the body&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;how systems interact to create a complex whole that is greater than the sum of its parts. In contrast, Western medicine has traditionally emphasized reductionist thinking, focusing on smaller and smaller parts, often at the cost of not seeing the whole person. Interestingly, systems biology is being increasingly appreciated in medicine, and Tai Chi research fits beautifully into this more ecological framework of health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you give an example?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;,breathing is a really important element in our tai chi and qigong training. But there&#39;s no way you can substantially change your breathing without changing your posture and how you hold your structure. And your breathing deeply affects you nervous and cardiovascular system, and many aspects of your mood; it can be a great tool for focusing the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;monkey mind&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; and becoming more sensitive to the inner landscape of our body. And of course changes in all these processes feedback on how we move and socially respond and interact with others. All these processes are ecologically intertwined with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also still think it&#39;s useful to unpack the interconnected components&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;for example to teach breathing exercises on their own and to study the physiological impacts of breathing exercises, in isolation of the larger package of Tai Chi. As a teacher, focusing on individual components helps brings awareness to finer scale processes, and it helps make a clearer teaching intention. Also talking about the physiology of breathing in classes helps some students appreciate the work, and for the students, there can be a lot of power in knowing. Most of us like to be told why we are doing a given practice in a given way. It really helps if students are informed. It creates buy in. I really love building bridges between traditional practices and modern science for this reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, what&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s it like for you teaching in a clinical trial compared to your community-based classes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In clinical trials, we are asking individuals to volunteer their time as a study participant so we can learn more about the health effects of Tai Chi. Often, these individuals have serious health conditions, and may not have chosen Tai Chi, or even heard of it, were it not for their doctor telling them about the trial. So many come to class not because they especially want to do tai chi, but because it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s a &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;new therapy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; they are hopeful it might improve their health. So there is sometimes a bit more time devoted to easing them into the work and making them feel comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think in your classes, in my classes, everyday someone walks in, and it&#39;s like an energetic push-hands. How do you meet that person exactly where they are and make them feel comfortable. And sometimes it has to be with a joke, sometimes it has to be with empathic solemnness, sometimes it&#39;s with a little distance&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;some do not initially care for intimacy. And you just have to feel that out. The real challenge, of course, is when you try to feel it out with 30 different people at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoying the challenge of connecting with diverse populations, and find humor and science help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite moments in teaching new Tai Chi students, both in clinical trials and community-based classes, is introducing them to a qigong warm-up exercise called &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Washing yourself with qi from nature.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; This very simple exercise, done either standing or seated, is designed to gather in healing, rejuvenating, peaceful energy from nature and guide this energy through every cell of the body, starting at the crown of the head and down through the chest, shoulders, spine, all the internal organs, through the legs and feet. I ask participants&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;not uncommonly older housewives and retired blue collar workers with little or no exposure to New Age practices --to imagine doing this while standing on a mountaintop, a beach, or wherever they feel they would be surrounded by nourishing energy. As they do the movement, I invite them to trust the energy to permeate and revitalize every cell of their body, while at the same time, tired sick energy is filter out and washed out through the soles of their feet into the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll abruptly stop, smile, and acknowledge with them how odd or weird this all sounds. They typically agree and we all laugh together. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll then share with them some of the research my colleagues and I have done related to the placebo effect, that sheds light on the exercise we are learning, and more generally supports the Tai Chi principle that what you think and believe impacts your physiology and how you feel. Typically, I draw on the well-documented placebo effect in asthma patients. Briefly, asthma patients in placebo studies were recruited to participate under the guise of evaluating new asthma drugs. Wearing an air-tight breathing mask, first they were told they would be challenged with an airborne insult, for example, ragweed, but actually they were simply given saline sprayed into the air they inhaled. Just the suggestion of ragweed induced physiologically measurable asthmatic attacks in the majority of participants. Following this insult, they were then told they were being given a new asthma &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;rescue&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; medication, which again was saline, and most of those who had had the asthma attacks quickly recovered. A huge body of research now shows that this so-called placebo effect -- that is, that placebos can have a real therapeutic effect -- is true for nearly all medical interventions, including sugar pills, mock injections, even surgery, and for nearly all medical conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this brief interlude, I return back to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;washing yourself with qi from heavens&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and jokingly say &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;so as we wash with qi from heavens, you can go to your special place and imagine breathing in and bathing every cell in your body with healing energy, or you can breath in ragweed or other toxic substances. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s your choice!&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Learn more about Peter&#39;s school here at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.treeoflifetaichi.com/&#34;&gt;Tree of Life Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YouTube AudioSwap</title>
      <link>/2010/11/23/youtube-audioswap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2010 19:56:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/23/youtube-audioswap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been working on this video, documenting an instructor training we recently hosted at Brookline Tai Chi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/sm-DhBtxy8U?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&amp;amp;color1=0x006699&amp;amp;color2=0x54abd6&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/sm-DhBtxy8U?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&amp;amp;color1=0x006699&amp;amp;color2=0x54abd6&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our director, Perry, selected music, but YouTube came back saying it was copyright infringement to use that track. Ok...so it gave me an alternative called AudioSwap. This is unbelievable. Basically, YouTube has a soundtrack generation engine, that you can browse by genre and artist and even filter per the length of your video. All of the tracks are fair game to use. You preview the new track and if you like it, YouTube overwrites the audio on your video with the new music. Problem solved. Indeed!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s Collaboration with the Department of Public Health</title>
      <link>/2010/11/05/brookline-tai-chis-collaboration-with-the-department-of-public-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 15:03:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/05/brookline-tai-chis-collaboration-with-the-department-of-public-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure I&#39;ll have more to say about this work in the future, but we&#39;ve just done a series of demos this fall highlighting the expanding role of evidence-based Tai Chi programs as public health interventions. When you look at the cost of a fall for older adults (I&#39;ve heard figures like $20,000) and the good evidence that Tai Chi can reduce falls and fear of falling (now considered a risk factor for falling), it makes so much sense to fund Tai Chi classes all over: senior centers, assisted living facilities, community centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out video from a recent demo I did in Worcester. I didn&#39;t know the Home Care Alliance camera was rolling!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/SubjqnO7F64?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&amp;amp;color1=0x006699&amp;amp;color2=0x54abd6&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/SubjqnO7F64?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&amp;amp;color1=0x006699&amp;amp;color2=0x54abd6&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>