<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>brookline-tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/brookline-tai-chi/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in brookline-tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/brookline-tai-chi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Gratitude for Immersive Learning</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 09:33:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</guid>
      <description>Last night I taught my last two weekly classes at Brookline Tai Chi.
Next month, I&#39;ll be diving into a new intensive learning experience, building software applications and learning about the web from a depth I&#39;ve only poked at up until now.
(I have some really cool stuff planned for Immersion Week too, so I&#39;m not quite done yet!)
It&#39;s going to be a big change for me. I don&#39;t quite know what to make of shedding a professional identity that I&#39;ve held for almost 10 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Moving Exercises: Immersion Week 2014</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 10:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m getting excited about Immersion Week at BTC next month, where we&#39;ll take another look at the Spine Stretch and the Three Swings. Another look? Like we&#39;ve done it before? Yes!
Why is it exciting to go back to the same qigong sets over and over again?
So-called creative people understand better than most that there is nothing new under the sun. Working with boulders of granite, with empty stages, with blank paper, they are credited with making something out of nothing, but that isn&#39;t exactly what they do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Inner Form of Balance</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 09:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</guid>
      <description>When my first Tai Chi teacher, Bruce Frantzis, came back to the US forty years ago to spread the Tai Chi he learned in China, he found out that many basic Tai Chi concepts were not being taught, either because of communications issues or lack of knowledge. Only a fraction of the vast potential of the art was being shared. Bruce set out to teach the Inner Form of Tai Chi and that&#39;s what I have studied for the last 15 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Obviously Tai Chi Improves Balance, But How Do You Explain It?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 14:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</guid>
      <description>We often talk about the way Tai Chi can improve your physical health and mental and emotional well-being from the point of view of the practitioner. But not everyone out there is as familiar with practical ways to use Tai Chi to support their health and wellness goals as you may be.
Later this year, I&#39;m thrilled to have the chance to share Tai Chi with physicians in a course at Harvard Medical School.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Rhythms at Tai Chi Immersion Week </title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/04/23/practice-rhythms-at-tai-chi-immersion-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 11:16:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/04/23/practice-rhythms-at-tai-chi-immersion-week/</guid>
      <description>Here is my mid-week update from Tai Chi Immersion Week 2013 at Brookline Tai Chi.
It&#39;s pretty cool to see folks come from all over to train for a week, but you really have to have the right mind set to make the most of the format.
See what I mean here:
http://youtu.be/tBOBhSljYNo
When you practice, be sure to include a clear:
 Warm-up: where you settle in and transition from the rest of your day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.
Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Cloud Hands Fall Workshop</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 17:31:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</guid>
      <description>We are in the process of finalizing the details of a Tai Chi Cloud Hands workshop with Robert Tangora this fall in Boston, from October 26-28.
As preparation for the workshop, I will be teaching a fall course at Brookline Tai Chi, covering the basic mechanics of Cloud Hands, as well as the prep exercises from Robert&#39;s newly published book.
I&#39;m really looking forward to taking everyone at Brookline Tai Chi through these exercises and at the same time, working with members of the Inner Form coaching program to improve their Cloud Hands practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Straight Lines, Circles, and Spheres</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/04/11/straight-lines-circles-and-spheres/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2012 07:53:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/04/11/straight-lines-circles-and-spheres/</guid>
      <description>One of the most fascinating connections between your mind and your body is the way that the actual physical movements that you make affect your awareness.
When your movements are linear and jerky, your mind stops and starts too, essentially gapping out.
If you can move in a smooth circular way, your mind tends to stay calmer too. Or at least, you can calm your mind through circular movement.
The next level of &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow and Stabilizing the Mind with Craig Barnes</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 08:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</guid>
      <description>Stability and flow seem to be at odds with each other. Stability can mean rigidity, or at least, it seems to conjure up something fixed, sturdy, and unmoving. Flow isn&#39;t any of those things. It&#39;s fluid and changing. So how does Energy Arts Senior Instructor Craig Barnes blend the two so seamlessly?

Recently, Craig taught a workshop about awakening energetic sensitivity, drawn from principles of Dragon and Tiger Qigong. We worked a lot on the opening of the set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning Tai Chi for the First Time</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/08/learning-tai-chi-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2011 09:54:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/08/learning-tai-chi-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>We are about to start the Early Fall session at Brookline Tai Chi and I&#39;ve been thinking a lot about how to teach the introductory class. The challenge, when you learn tai chi for the first time, is all about mindset. I want to see if I can teach them &#34;how to learn tai chi&#34; as much as actually teaching tai chi. This might sound like a beginner-only problem, but I have a challenge for more experienced readers at the end of this post and I&#39;m wondering if you can keep up with my beginners on this one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Form Training Final Update</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 12:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m heading home to Boston tomorrow, but I&#39;ve already begun looking through my notes and thinking about what I will personally practice and what I&#39;ll be able to share with my students in classes this coming year. Here are some of my initial thoughts:

How Material is Woven together over a Month:
 Day to day we&#39;re looking at really small specific pieces but now going back through my notes, I can start to see different threads that run throughout the duration of the month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update from the Beach</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>Week 3 wraps up and testing is right around the corner. What was Bruce&#39;s big message as we prepare for testing? Work your ass off and cram all night for the big test? Not quite. You might be surprised. Check it out:

A Lesson about Integration:
The biggest thing that Bruce is emphasizing in the last couple days of class is that with this stage of the training, a month long training, you need integration time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 of the Short Form Instructor Training</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 09:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s my Week 2 update. Some big milestones this week: group 1 finished the form and group 2 has been languishing in the purgatory that is holding static postures. Check it out:

Inner Form vs. Outer Form
 In the two groups, we&#39;re doing very different things. The group one just finished the form this week. So on Thursday after they finished it, we came in Friday, and it was a really interesting dividing line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am Learning at the Wu Tai Chi Instructor Training</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 01:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re a week into the Wu Tai Chi short form instructor training in Brighton, UK, with Lineage Holder Bruce Frantzis. So far we&#39;ve been completely rebuilding our forms, working on Tai Chi leg power, and exploring the meditative aspects of the art. Check it out:

On Rebuilding Your Form:
It&#39;s crazy when you come at these things, you&#39;re completely rebuilding your Tai Chi form. We&#39;re about two-thirds of the way through the form and it feels so different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Quiet Awareness with Lee Burkins</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</guid>
      <description>In June, between sessions at Brookline Tai Chi and during master classes with Bruce Frantzis, a small group of students got a special treat. Energy Arts Senior Instructor Lee Burkins was in town to train with Bruce, and on one of the nights off, he offered a special evening course on a topic he calls &#34;Investing in Loss&#34;.
What I love about studying with someone like Lee is that he&#39;s a practitioner whose art has soaked so deeply into his bones, that it practically oozes out of his DNA.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>