<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>events on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/categories/events/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in events on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Gratitude for Immersive Learning</title>
      <link>/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 09:33:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-5033&#34; alt=&#34;Thank_You&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2014/04/Thank_You-e1397827802683-242x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;242&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night I taught my last two weekly classes at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next month, I&#39;ll be diving into &lt;a href=&#34;http://launchacademy.com/&#34;&gt;a new intensive learning experience&lt;/a&gt;, building software applications and learning about the web from a depth I&#39;ve only poked at up until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I have some really cool stuff planned for Immersion Week too, so I&#39;m not quite done yet!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s going to be a big change for me.  I don&#39;t quite know what to make of shedding a professional identity that I&#39;ve held for almost 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I don&#39;t quite know what to say to the students I&#39;ve worked so closely with over all this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I think about what&#39;s coming, I recognize a pattern that I&#39;ve repeated many times in my life. On many occasions now, I&#39;ve been able to dive into a pool that I couldn&#39;t swim in at first, and then somehow, float.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 10 years teaching weekly classes at Brookline Tai Chi, I feel ready to swim in a new pool and in a strange way, I&#39;m excited to be really out of my element, because I know that with the right structure, in the right environment, I will float back up to the surface buoyed by new skills and new perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ten Years Ago at Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I still remember walking across the room, not making eye contract with anyone, just shuffling out into the lobby to wait for students to come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was just a couple of weeks into my job as the new director of Brookline Tai Chi, in the summer of 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after that, many of our lead instructors left the school and while I was in the process of training to teach, I found myself with close to 20 hours a week of classes, not the 3 to 5 I had expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that being thrust into such a high volume of classes created one of the best learning environments I could have hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every night I would have 3 different classes, sometimes 4 on the weekends. That meant that each hour I had to do a complete reset, with a fresh new group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students would come in from whatever they had done all day and I had to &#34;land&#34; them, make the feel comfortable, relaxed and slowly tune them inward to become more present. I watch this arc, from scattered and tired, to relaxed and focused happen over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process, I learned how to more artfully make that transition myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we would get &#34;to work&#34; - the middle 20 - 30 minutes of class. In the work phase we would go into a form or a principle and really train it. Once you&#39;ve opened up, relaxed repetition is much easier, and more meaningful to your nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the hour, we would do an easy practice where the goal wasn&#39;t to keep squeezing in more and more information, but rather to feel integration, letting things settle and come to rest so that your body could more easily absorbs the training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, everything would go quiet&amp;hellip;.and then I would start all over again with the next group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did that for the last ten years, so 3 x 5 x 44 x 10 or over 6,000 times. When you factor in workshops and personal practice time, I&#39;m confident that I&#39;ve paid attention to this work-rest-integration cycle for well over 10,000 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Supportive Learning Environment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;m so grateful for the opportunity to have done this kind of learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to Brookline Tai Chi for its community and its structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to my teachers who gave me material to work on and also guided me through the meta layer of learning even more through teaching and sharing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful for all the students who were excited to learn with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to all of you reading this post who have indulged my sharing my teaching experiences on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even now, as I open a new chapter professionally, the combination of training, learning, and teaching will form the foundation for new endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve benefitted from my writing, podcasts, videos, or teaching in any form on this site, I want you to know that it&#39;s largely because of the opportunities I had to develop a teaching voice at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you will &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/thank-you-dan-retrospective-and-appeal-for-transition-contributions/&#34;&gt;consider supporting Brookline Tai Chi at this time&lt;/a&gt;, so that our learning community will continue to produce new teachers, who work hard to benefit all of us, and that as a group, we will always have a home base to return to for deep learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Moving Exercises: Immersion Week 2014</title>
      <link>/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 10:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m getting excited about &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Immersion Week at BTC next month&lt;/a&gt;, where we&#39;ll take another look at the Spine Stretch and the Three Swings. Another look? Like we&#39;ve done it before? Yes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it exciting to go back to the same qigong sets over and over again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So-called creative people understand better than most that there is nothing new under the sun. Working with boulders of granite, with empty stages, with blank paper, they are credited with making something out of nothing, but that isn&#39;t exactly what they do. All art is derived from what is in actuality a remarkably finite human experience. Whatever the medium, the creative person&#39;s task is to interpret an essentially unchanging reality, a dog-eared reality pondered by Homer and Mel Brooks and everyone in between. The artist succeeds if he or she can present something familiar from an unfamiliar angle.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rheta Grimsley Johnson&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This quote comes from a book about Charles Schulz, the creator of Peanuts. &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinkleon.com/2007/10/29/the-twelve-devices-of-peanuts/&#34;&gt;In this post&lt;/a&gt;, Austin Kleon breaks down the 12 familiar devices that Schulz used over and over again to tell different stories in his comic strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reusing the devices, Schulz at once created context for the reader to return to and at the same time set us up to be surprised by new insights, twists, and revelations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s try to do the same thing in our qigong practice, instead of letting familiar sets become stale and dead.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/86kIjmFf9_U?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Insight in Old Exercises&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In planning this year&#39;s event, here are the themes I hope to explore and &#34;discover.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the Spine Stretch&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How the movements reveal physical layers -- from superficial fascia to the deep muscles surrounding the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legwork that enhances your connection to the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difference between sinking chi and dissolving and the way this contrast will help you get more rooted (sinking) and penetrate deeper into the spine (dissolving).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finishing the spine stretch with a more integrated connection between the arms, legs, and spine and a sense of internal stillness.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
See, many of these qualities can be found in a standing practice or a complex moving form of Tai Chi, but the interesting question is how we can draw them out of the procedure of the Spine Stretch. I know they&#39;re in there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the Swings&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we release the arms throughout the swings series in a way that enhances the overall feeling of release and relaxation in the body?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How, given the degree of movement in the swings, can we tune into steady and continuous head-to-toe sinking or dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we use the rotational motion and rhythm of the Swings to refine our feeling of the Central Channel as an axis of movement?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the end of the series, can will come to rest in a way that feels loose, alive, and settled simultaneously?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I love the challenge of extending internal awareness into an active practice like the Swings. Even as the arms are flying up above the head, you have to learn to stay grounded and connected. The rhythm and timing become an anchor for your mind in a way that&#39;s hard to get even in a slow-motion Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Immersion Week: April 22-25&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We&#39;ll spend 2.5 hours a day on each topic for four days, April 22-25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be doing Swings in the morning and Spine Stretch in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This format lets us approach all of the exercises from many different angles: direct feeling with the mind (standing qigong), partner exercises to sensitize different body parts/capacities (twisting, loosening, sinking), and mini-exercises that allow us to feel key principles/pieces of each larger exercise (arm drops and swing, kwa squats, folds, and hinges).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both events will be held at Brookline Tai Chi and there is limited space. If you plan to attend, I encourage you to sign up by April 1 to ensure a space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Here are the details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you&#39;re coming in from out of town, consider extending your stay to refine your &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/long-form-spring-series/&#34;&gt;Long Form with Craig Barnes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 and the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Book</title>
      <link>/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 16:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m very excited to share some news about two big projects with you today: Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s annual Immersion Week and the publication of the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance as a physical book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/bATZ5_2SMno?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join me from Tuesday, April 22 - Friday, April 25 at Brookline Tai Chi in Boston for &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Energy Gates Moving Qigong Exercises&lt;/a&gt;. Times, cost, and registration details in the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance is now available for purchase on Amazon, but you can also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.createspace.com/4498724&#34;&gt;get your copy of the physical book directly from the publisher&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates in Vancouver, BC, Spring 2014</title>
      <link>/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 17:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-4518 &#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong &#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/03/20130326-094857.jpg&#34; width=&#34;360&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Dan standing in New Mexico, not Vancouver (yet!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you live in or near Vancouver?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you willing to travel to refine your Energy Gates practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the behest of a few eager Vancouver locals, I wanted to reach out and see if any of our Northwest-oriented readers would be interested in a spring 2014 Energy Gates seminar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Date and exact location haven&#39;t been nailed down yet, but if there&#39;s enough demand, I would love to come out and do some Energy Gates with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/rz6mzho0i8y4y5/&#34;&gt;Already excited? Sign up here so we can explore it more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Energy Gates Seminar Topics&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are so many great Energy Gates subjects related to &lt;a title=&#34;3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;Case Study: Energy Gates Tune-Up&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/21/case-study-energy-gates-tune-up/&#34;&gt;Cloud Hands&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;The Challenge of the Three Swings&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/&#34;&gt;The Swings&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a title=&#34;Spinal Qigong Exercises&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/spinal-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;The Spine Stretch&lt;/a&gt;, but I&#39;d like to take the approach of &lt;strong&gt;answering the burning questions that always come up when you start working on Standing, Sinking and Dissolving,&lt;/strong&gt; like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a lot of tension around my low back (or knees), how do I adapt the posture so it&#39;s not painful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should I use the actual gates in my practice or focus on general sinking and dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is quite a struggle to constantly remind myself to slow down. How do I slow my mind down without causing mental tension?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#39;m starting to feel chi when I stand. What do I do with it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can&#39;t feel chi when I stand. What do I do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I integrate standing, breathing, sinking, and dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I sink the chi of one part of my body, does it go all the way down to the ground?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get too tense when I try to maintain my alignments as I stand. What should I do&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#39;m experiencing shaking, sweating, heat or other weird bodily sensations. Is that normal?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to get live, personal feedback and soak up all the good chi of intensive group practice, then come stand with us in Vancouver next year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill out the form below and I will in touch directly with you about the details. If we can get a big enough group together, we&#39;ll make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again to the folks who initiated this conversation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var rz6mzho0i8y4y5;(function(d, t) { var s = d.createElement(t), options = { &#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,  &#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#39;,  &#39;autoResize&#39;:true, &#39;height&#39;:&#39;403&#39;, &#39;async&#39;:true, &#39;host&#39;:&#39;wufoo.com&#39;, &#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,  &#39;ssl&#39;:true}; s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;; s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() { var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return; try { rz6mzho0i8y4y5 = new WufooForm();rz6mzho0i8y4y5.initialize(options);rz6mzho0i8y4y5.display(); } catch (e) {}}; var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr); })(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put More Chi in Your Tai Chi -- Upcoming Chicago Seminar</title>
      <link>/2012/10/15/put-more-chi-in-your-tai-chi-upcoming-chicago-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 14:03:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/15/put-more-chi-in-your-tai-chi-upcoming-chicago-seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Next month I&#39;ll be teaching at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ensostudio.com/taichi.html&#34;&gt;Enso Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re in the Chicago area, come by to and learn how to go deeper into the internal work of your Tai Chi practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what we&#39;ll be focusing on:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/K8IVx5QsSrE?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Seminar Details&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Saturday, November 10&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 10:00am - 12:30pm and 2:00 - 4:00pm&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; Cost:&lt;/strong&gt; $65&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; Pre-requisite:&lt;/strong&gt; Open to all Tai Chi styles&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; Location:&lt;/strong&gt; Enso Studio, 412 S. Wells Street, 7th Floor, Chicago, IL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/seminars/&#34;&gt;Learn more here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>