<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>events on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/categories/events/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in events on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Gratitude for Immersive Learning</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 09:33:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</guid>
      <description>Last night I taught my last two weekly classes at Brookline Tai Chi.
Next month, I&#39;ll be diving into a new intensive learning experience, building software applications and learning about the web from a depth I&#39;ve only poked at up until now.
(I have some really cool stuff planned for Immersion Week too, so I&#39;m not quite done yet!)
It&#39;s going to be a big change for me. I don&#39;t quite know what to make of shedding a professional identity that I&#39;ve held for almost 10 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Moving Exercises: Immersion Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 10:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m getting excited about Immersion Week at BTC next month, where we&#39;ll take another look at the Spine Stretch and the Three Swings. Another look? Like we&#39;ve done it before? Yes!
Why is it exciting to go back to the same qigong sets over and over again?
So-called creative people understand better than most that there is nothing new under the sun. Working with boulders of granite, with empty stages, with blank paper, they are credited with making something out of nothing, but that isn&#39;t exactly what they do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 and the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Book</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 16:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m very excited to share some news about two big projects with you today: Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s annual Immersion Week and the publication of the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance as a physical book.

Join me from Tuesday, April 22 - Friday, April 25 at Brookline Tai Chi in Boston for Energy Gates Moving Qigong Exercises. Times, cost, and registration details in the link.
The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance is now available for purchase on Amazon, but you can also get your copy of the physical book directly from the publisher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates in Vancouver, BC, Spring 2014</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 17:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</guid>
      <description>Dan standing in New Mexico, not Vancouver (yet!).
Do you live in or near Vancouver?
Are you willing to travel to refine your Energy Gates practice?
At the behest of a few eager Vancouver locals, I wanted to reach out and see if any of our Northwest-oriented readers would be interested in a spring 2014 Energy Gates seminar.
Date and exact location haven&#39;t been nailed down yet, but if there&#39;s enough demand, I would love to come out and do some Energy Gates with you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put More Chi in Your Tai Chi -- Upcoming Chicago Seminar</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/15/put-more-chi-in-your-tai-chi-upcoming-chicago-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 14:03:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/15/put-more-chi-in-your-tai-chi-upcoming-chicago-seminar/</guid>
      <description>Next month I&#39;ll be teaching at Enso Tai Chi.
If you&#39;re in the Chicago area, come by to and learn how to go deeper into the internal work of your Tai Chi practice.
Here&#39;s what we&#39;ll be focusing on:

Seminar Details
Date: Saturday, November 10
 Time: 10:00am - 12:30pm and 2:00 - 4:00pm
 Cost: $65
 Pre-requisite: Open to all Tai Chi styles
 Location: Enso Studio, 412 S.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>