<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>qigong-radio on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/qigong-radio/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in qigong-radio on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/qigong-radio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Outer Dissolving and The Role of the Mind in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/30/outer-dissolving-and-the-role-of-the-mind-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 10:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/30/outer-dissolving-and-the-role-of-the-mind-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Next month, we&#39;ll be starting a new Energy Gates course at &lt;a title=&#34;Brookline Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, focused on Outer Dissolving and working through the Gates of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you work on dissolving the gates, you will inevitably be fighting the urge to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;visualize instead of feel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;chase&#34; energetic releases, untethered from the physical body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wonder if you are really feeling anything at all&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In this episode of Qigong Radio, I&#39;ll give my recommendations for avoiding these pitfalls and for &lt;strong&gt;setting up the conditions for actual energetic resolution&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ll indulge me, I&#39;ll even share one of my favorite passages from Moby Dick and tell you why I think it&#39;s a perfect description of standing qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Training Xing Yi&#39;s Five Elements with Isaac Kamins</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/31/training-xing-yis-five-elements-with-isaac-kamins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 11:44:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/31/training-xing-yis-five-elements-with-isaac-kamins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4960&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Instructor Isaac Kamins&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/10/Isaac_Kamins-207x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;207&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you know from other episodes of &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/qigongradio/&#34;&gt;Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt; and other interviews, I always try to track down authoritative sources when I want to learn more about a subject and share it with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that my teacher Bruce Frantzis is releasing two more DVD sets on Xingyi&#39;s Five Elements, I wanted to talk to someone about these practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the best of my knowledge, Isaac Kamins is the only person actively teaching the Energy Arts Xingyi curriculum who also trained with Bruce Frantzis in weekly classes for several years in the Bay Area in the 90&#39;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isaac has shared his deep knowledge of the Energy Arts system in &lt;a title=&#34;Spiraling Energy Body Qigong with Isaac Kamins&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/28/spiraling-energy-body-qigong-with-isaac-kamins/&#34;&gt;past episodes of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt; and I think you&#39;ll find that he doesn&#39;t hold back on his training insights in this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The unique way Xingyi forges a strong mind-body connection and helps you overcome mental gaps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How the 5 Elements are manifested in the simple, repetitive forms of Xingyi&#39;s 5 Fists -- and how this gives you a direct experience of Water, Earth, Metal, Fire, and Wood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What it was like to go through the entire 5 Element cycle with Bruce three different times, each time over a two-year period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How, even if you don&#39;t &#34;major&#34; in Xingyi, you can gain insight into Tai Chi, Bagua, or even qigong, with the direct, experiential quality of 5 Element practice.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bonus Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I asked Isaac to go beyond just talking about the practice and actually teach you some Xingyi. Isaac created a short video tutorial and guided audio practice that helps you get the feel of San Ti, Xingyi&#39;s main power-building practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you download the audio (fill out the form below to receive it via email), watch this video a few times to get a feel for the opening movement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/7SY56FCto5Y?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r146hes70esx1il&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r146hes70esx1il&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r146hes70esx1il;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r146hes70esx1il&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;495&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;host&#39;:&#39;wufoo.com&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { r146hes70esx1il = new WufooForm();r146hes70esx1il.initialize(options);r146hes70esx1il.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chasing Secrets and Shortcuts in Taoist Energy Arts</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/23/chasing-secrets-and-shortcuts-in-taoist-energy-arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2013 16:19:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/23/chasing-secrets-and-shortcuts-in-taoist-energy-arts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1537&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you set out to learn Taoist Energy Arts like Tai Chi, qigong, or meditation, you come across the lore of masters with supernatural abilities or techniques too deadly to teach openly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or more insidious, we grasp after images of unattainable perfection, always slightly beyond reach, unless we just find the right technique or are initiated into a secret practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even if we&#39;ve given up silly kung fu fantasies of flying through the bamboo reeds, on a subtle level we still chase ideas and dreams that only live in the mental realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality - and I&#39;m not trying to disappoint you, but stay with me because the reality is deeply rewarding, meaningful, and rich too - is that Taoist Energy Arts must be lived-through and practiced-through to be truly discovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Paul Cavel and I explore the disconnect you can sometimes feel in the day-to-day of your practice and the idea of where you ought to be in your practice - it&#39;s not because you must be a chosen one or special to get it, but rather, because you can&#39;t directly perceive or experience energy when you operate solely on the mental realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll give you some guidelines for how to recognize when you slip back into the mental realm of fantasy practice and talk about the struggles, as a student and as a teacher, of communicating your practice experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul also shares specific neigong techniques that will keep you present, engaged, and help you cultivate a direct experience of your natural internal energy, that can be applied to any energy practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more from Paul about the best way to study Taoist Practices by signing up for his newsletter here (includes a free guide to getting started with Taoist Energy Arts):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;http://forms.aweber.com/form/68/1737149068.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 13:49:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-4731&#34; alt=&#34;don U post on bridge&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/07/don-U-post-on-bridge-e1374169158691.jpg&#34; width=&#34;179&#34; height=&#34;344&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/don-ethan-miller/&#34;&gt;Don Miller&lt;/a&gt; and I explore the essential elements of Tai Chi Balance Training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you probably know, Tai Chi is being used more and more for falls prevention programs for the elderly and becoming a mainstream part of the Western medical vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what are the actual elements that make up a great Tai Chi balance training program?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can you use them for your own well-being?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you share Tai Chi balance training with your friends and family?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are our thoughts on:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ways to develop &#34;Root&#34; that make you more stable and relaxed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding &#34;Central Equilibrium&#34; for more integrated movement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The psychological dimensions of Tai Chi practice, and how you can sneak up on them by improving your body awareness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The deep satisfaction that comes from literally connecting to the Earth&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We explore student experiences, roadblocks, and concerns as well as giving you practical tidbits to play with while you listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 11:14:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft  wp-image-4644&#34; alt=&#34;HMS guide to Tai Chi&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/05/HMS-guide-to-Tai-Chi1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;120&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; In his new book, the Harvard Medical School Guide to Tai Chi, &lt;a title=&#34;Living between the Lab and the Classroom with Dr. Peter Wayne&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/&#34;&gt;Dr. Peter Wayne&lt;/a&gt; lays out the &#34;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; to help us understand the interface between traditional Tai Chi practice and the Western biomedical paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Research Director of the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, jointly based at Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, and the founder of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.treeoflifetaichi.com/instructors.html&#34;&gt;Tree of Life Tai Chi Center&lt;/a&gt;, Peter blends more than three decades of teaching experience with ongoing inquiry into what makes Tai Chi an effective medical intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, we explore the development of the 8 Active Ingredients and how help translate Tai Chi into a Western context&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi are:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awareness, Mindfulness, Focused Attention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intention, Belief, Expectation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic Structural Integration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active Relaxation of Mind and Body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aerobic Exercise, Musculoskeletal Strengthening, and Flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natural, Freer Breathing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Interaction and Community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embodied Spirituality, Philosophy, and Ritual&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I asked Peter to explain how he understands Tai Chi practice through these 8 ingredients and how they are related to each other. While there are many ways to explain what Tai Chi is, this framework has to explain Tai Chi to a Western medical audience, making each element of the practice related to biomedical and psychological principles rooted in evidence-based medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter tells us what was easy to convey and where the Tai Chi principles were more esoteric, but important to explain through the framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also makes the case for greater medical literacy amongst Tai Chi teachers and practitioners because, as Tai Chi research gets more sophisticated, the feedback loop between what gets studied and how Tai Chi is defined will get tighter and tighter. If you&#39;re concerned with the legacy of Tai Chi in the West, you need to be a part of this conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the podcast for all that and a great sense for Peter&#39;s insight, generosity, and caring as a practitioner and leader in the Tai Chi research field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Intrinsic Practice Motivation</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 09:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Marden Hill Road Sunset II; Palermo, Maine by Jody Roberts, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/jroberts72/6003983172/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Marden Hill Road Sunset II; Palermo, Maine&#34; src=&#34;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6010/6003983172_fc0cfb3308_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For the last couple of years, I&#39;ve been teaching regular workshops in Farmington, Maine. When I went up again last week, I had a fascinating conversation with one of the students. She was telling me how the core group had been coming along and that other people have come in and out of practicing with them. She said, &#34;you know, it&#39;s not really for everyone.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don&#39;t know if that jumps out at you as a significant statement, but as a Tai Chi teacher, it&#39;s &lt;a title=&#34;Brookline Tai Chi has no &#34;Former Students&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34;&gt;something I&#39;ve been thinking about for years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this one casual statement, she was really saying that her motivation to practice now comes from inside of herself. Along with a small group of dedicated classmates, she gets everything she needs from the practice itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a remarkable attitude. Every day, we get bombarded by messages that tell us to buy something to become something or fit in with other people. To be able to have a practice that lives inside of you, that&#39;s validated by performing it for yourself, and grows because you feed it with energy and time, is really incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, we&#39;re going to talk about how you discover your intrinsic motivation to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2013 07:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; explains the 3 different layers of neigong practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beginner or Foundational Practices&lt;/strong&gt; -- Dragon and Tiger, Opening the Energy Gates, and Heaven and Earth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intermediate or Power-Production Practices&lt;/strong&gt; -- Spiraling Energy Body and Bend the Bow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced or Integration Practices&lt;/strong&gt; -- Gods Playing in the Clouds&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter  wp-image-4491&#34; alt=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/01/for_danny-1024x483.jpg&#34; width=&#34;717&#34; height=&#34;338&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Paul explains what to focus on at each level and how your learning spiral takes you back through them over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I found Paul&#39;s explanation of the relationships between the sets particularly useful. Specifically, understanding &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;Energy Gates&lt;/a&gt; as direct preparation for &lt;a title=&#34;Spiraling Energy Body Qigong with Isaac Kamins&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/28/spiraling-energy-body-qigong-with-isaac-kamins/&#34;&gt;Spiraling&lt;/a&gt; -- first you clear the downward flow of chi, then you strengthen the upward flow. Similarly, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/heaven-and-earth/&#34;&gt;Heaven and Earth&lt;/a&gt; you learn to expand the body (through opening/closing the joints and lengthening the soft tissue) before you really go into deep internal compression in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/bend-the-bow/&#34;&gt;Bend the Bow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we discussed the meaning of &#34;integration,&#34; Paul explained how neigong is the basis for Taoist meditation and where neigong shows up inside your meditation practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the episode, we talk about the great training resources available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://paulcavel.com&#34;&gt;PaulCavel.com&lt;/a&gt;, including the Inner Quest Journal (&lt;a title=&#34;Recommended Products&#34; href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p5x7/&#34;&gt;download a free issue here&lt;/a&gt;). If you get the chance, please let Paul know how much we all appreciate the high quality material he is putting out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Sensations That Arise When You Are Developing Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 07:24:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, I answer some questions about different sensations readers have been experiencing when they practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dragon-and-tiger-medical-qigong/&#34;&gt;Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong&lt;/a&gt; Instruction Manual, Bruce Frantzis lays out important guidelines for what kinds of &#34;chi reactions&#34; to expect. I want to show you how to apply these guidelines to your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Expect Chi Reactions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dragon and Tiger is a powerful tool for awakening your body on physical, energetic, emotional, mental and spiritual levels. As you practice these movements and begin to move your body in ways that may be different for you, energy and fluids in your body are stirred up and begin to move more vigorously. At some point you may experience reactions that may seem either positive or negative to you. These are called chi reactions: the body&#39;s response to the effects of energy beginning to flow more freely through previously blocked places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These reactions may show up immediately, hours after practicing, or even a day or two later. Although many people will not begin to feel either negative or positive reactions without practicing a lot, others, particularly if they have done other forms of personal development work, may notice reactions almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Positive Chi Reactions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Positive reactions can range from feeling less pain and having more energy to being more centered, relaxed and comfortable with your body. Some people report that they sleep much better; others report greater flexibility and balance. You may also notice that you are calmer and have fewer mood swings. You may experience an overall reduction in stress and tension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A transformative effect that most people consider positive, is an increase in and awareness of sexual energy. This is entirely normal as it is the most fundamental energy in your body, and practice of Dragon and Tiger will increase sexual energy. Finally, a transformative effect that confuses many people is what we call &#34;good pain.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dragon and Tiger is designed to gradually work more and more deeply into your body, to release muscles and other tissues and joints that have been restricted or blocked. When an area of your body that has been frozen begins to loosen and realign, more energy moves through that area than you are used to. But if the energy cannot flow freely or fully, you may experience temporary pain in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese medical theory of the body holds that pain in an area is a sign that the energy there is not flowing freely. You feel &#34;bad&#34; pain when an area is newly injured or hurt. In general, &#34;good&#34; pains tend to be temporary (lasting from a minute to at most a couple of days) and are usually dull, rather than sharp. As you practice you will learn to recognize such pains as signs of progress. Treat them with great care and keep within the 40 to 50 percent rule when you have pain, illness or injury (see p. 7). Back off practicing and be sure to consult your healthcare provider if you begin experiencing either significant pain or pain that does not go away quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Negative Chi Reactions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As your body wakes up on various levels, it may do so the same way as when aroused from a deep slumber &amp;mdash;cranky, sore and confused. You may experience some negative chi reactions. These can range from relatively mild but confusing aches, nausea, light-headedness, tingles, fatigue, unsteadiness, body temperature shifts or mood changes to strong emotional releases and mood swings to unusual dreams or shifts in perception. You may also experience physical discharges, such as stronger body odors or more frequent bowel movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As blocked and stagnant energy moves or leaves the body, energetic memories that are associated with the problem, stored in either your energy channels or physical tissue can awaken and cause you to relive the underlying and often repressed causes of the problem&amp;mdash;especially if you have a severe condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might experience what doctors refer to as a &#34;healing crisis.&#34; The term refers to that time during healing when a patient&#39;s body temporarily feels worse before it feels better. For example, when the body burns out infections, the patient often has a high fever. When the fever breaks, the symptoms of the disease pass. The fever may cause the patient to feel terrible, until the stored toxins or blocked energy are released. Afterwards the individual feels better as the illness passes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these reactions are common to many natural forms of healing and are often a sign that your body is cleansing itself. Many people have a healing crisis when they fast or switch to a cleansing or vegetarian diet. The practice of Dragon and Tiger may often trigger such effects; they are fairly normal reactions. What is important to remember is that these reactions are temporary and usually pass when your body begins to rebalance itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you begin to experience strong or uncomfortable sensations, immediately sit down, put your hands on your belly and gently breathe with your belly to ground and center yourself. Such sensations will usually pass within minutes. Then suspend or reduce your practice for a while. Start again by following the 20 percent or 40 percent rule and very gently explore your body&#39;s reactions to these practices. Remember that you are not alone in such experiences; almost everyone who practices will experience some of these reactions at some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the symptoms are intense, pull back your practice to 30 percent or 40 percent of what you consider your normal practice and consult with your teacher. Remember to drink plenty of water. Water helps accelerate the release of toxins. Taking some vitamin C also helps that process. Make sure you rest after practicing. Be sure to consult a healthcare professional immediately if you have any symptoms that might be a sign of a medical or psychological problem.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Listen to the episode to find out how to apply this principles to rising energy, activating the lower tantien, and differentiating between nerve flow, blood flood, and normal physical movement.&lt;br /&gt;
[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/q3tlLKD4YdM?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you download or listen to the episode below, you might also want to check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/bend-bow-spinal-qigong&#34;&gt;the description of Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong on EnergyArts.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/classes/chi-gung-bend-bow-introduction-bend-bow-and-shoot-arrow-december-1-2-late-fall-session&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be sure to check out Eric&#39;s Bend the Bow workshop, December 1 and 2, 2012 at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Equipment Training with Don Ethan Miller</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/27/tai-chi-equipment-training-with-don-ethan-miller/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 07:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/27/tai-chi-equipment-training-with-don-ethan-miller/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you cultivate the mind-body benefits of Tai Chi, you will likely focus on solo training and interactive two-person practices like Push Hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a third kind of Tai Chi training, though, that will make the link between the other two stronger, Tai Chi Equipment Training.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4140&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/-yhR31mD-r4?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using stones, balls, disks, belts, and other objects you find in nature, you can develop important attributes of the Tai Chi body and mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renown teacher and multiple-time national Push Hands champion Don Ethan Miller explains how to go about using objects to enhance your training in this episode of Qigong Radio.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Don&#39;s Tai Chi Equipment Training DVD is &lt;a href=&#34;http://mastodonproductions.com/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;amp;cPath=3&amp;amp;products_id=8&#34;&gt;available for purchase here on his website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Your Relationship to Your Qigong Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/06/what-is-your-relationship-to-your-qigong-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2012 07:27:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/06/what-is-your-relationship-to-your-qigong-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/22280677@N07/&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34; alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3403/3544203863_7f8d71c55f.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Teapots and Cups &amp;copy; by Svadilfari&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I&#39;m posting this episode on my annual summer retreat/vacation/recharge, where I assess my practice and teaching from the past year and plan courses for the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, in the midst of big changes at Brookline Tai Chi, I&#39;ve been wondering a lot about the way qigong practice informs your encounters with change in other areas of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I always like to think that there&#39;s a strong connection, but this year everyone at Brookline Tai Chi is truly testing whether the art of smooth change in the classroom manifests itself in real life as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4105&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving Your Energy to Soothe Your Mind</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/15/moving-your-energy-to-soothe-your-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2012 17:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/15/moving-your-energy-to-soothe-your-mind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;wp-image-4066 alignright&#34; title=&#34;Dejota Dragon and Tiger&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/07/Dejota-Dragon-and-Tiger-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dejota Apostol moving chi with Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, I thought I was going to get a report about the Dragon and Tiger instructor training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the six instructors who joined me for the episode talked about the training. If you missed Maui, you&#39;ll get a sense of what it was like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they also shared some true qigong gems with us, that I think you&#39;ll be able to apply to all of your energy practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4065&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relaxation in the West vs. Qigong perspective on relaxation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way stagnant chi impacts your mind and how a tense mind freezes up your chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Dragon and Tiger helps relax the mind into a feeling state as opposed to a thinking state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Dragon and Tiger&#39;s emphasis on chi circulation transforms other practices like Tai Chi and Ba Gua&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks to everyone who participated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/dorchester/ana-sorina-popa&#34;&gt;Ana Popa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/edgartown/eric-l-peters&#34;&gt;Eric Peters&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/edgartown/eileen-murphy&#34;&gt;Eileen Murphy&lt;/a&gt; from Boston.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/radford/paul-pallante&#34;&gt;Paul Pallante from Radford, Virginia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/san-jose/dejota-apostol&#34;&gt;Dejota Apostol from San Jose, California.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ensostudio.com/taichi.html&#34;&gt;Chris Cinnamon from Chicago.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
They all teach regularly in their local areas, so if you&#39;re looking for a live class to attend, but sure to check them out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Expectations and Progress in Your Qigong Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/25/on-expectations-and-progress-in-your-qigong-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 09:07:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/25/on-expectations-and-progress-in-your-qigong-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/sick_rdm/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4001&#34; title=&#34;Making Progress in Your Qigong Practice&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/06/free-climbing-201x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;photo credit: sick_rdm&#34; width=&#34;201&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;We just started summer classes at Brookline Tai Chi this week, which means new students are coming in for the first time and experienced students are coming back after a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means there are lots of good questions floating around about getting started, making progress, and the frustrations you encounter along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, I hope to address some of those concerns.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4000&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you think is the ultimate goal of your practice, anyway?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have a &#34;listening&#34; practice in your current routine?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where is the gel point in your daily practice?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks to everyone who has supported the Qigong Radio project by making a donation to our equipment upgrade fund. I hope you can hear the difference in quality that the new equipment made in this interview. If you enjoyed the content, consider making a small donation. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;cmd&#34; value=&#34;_s-xclick&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;hosted_button_id&#34; value=&#34;JM5L8XE2BBXM4&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_donateCC_LG.gif&#34; alt=&#34;PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/form&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Putting The Mind Inside The Body with Cathy Kerr</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/11/putting-the-mind-inside-the-body-with-cathy-kerr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2012 07:47:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/11/putting-the-mind-inside-the-body-with-cathy-kerr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34; wp-image-3981 &#34; title=&#34;Dr. Cathy Kerr&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/06/large_catherine.kerr_.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dr. Cathy Kerr&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we mean when we say we &#34;put our mind inside our body&#34; when we meditate, do qigong, or Tai Chi?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Cathy Kerr helps us understand this question from the perspective of modern neuroscience. In addition to being a Tai Chi practitioner, Cathy is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://brown.academia.edu/CatherineKerr&#34;&gt;Director of Translational Neuroscience&lt;/a&gt; at Contemplative Studies Initiative and an Assistant Professor in the Department of Family Medicine at Brown University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing on a growing body of research from mindfulness meditation, her own work on sensory processes, and ancient texts, Cathy explains these Eastern practices develop your Western brain in areas that span physical health as well as mental and emotional well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3980&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks to everyone who has supported the Qigong Radio project by making a donation to our equipment upgrade fund. I hope you can hear the difference in quality that the new equipment made in this interview. If you enjoyed the content, consider making a small donation. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;cmd&#34; value=&#34;_s-xclick&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;hosted_button_id&#34; value=&#34;JM5L8XE2BBXM4&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_donateCC_LG.gif&#34; alt=&#34;PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/form&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spiraling Energy Body Qigong with Isaac Kamins</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/28/spiraling-energy-body-qigong-with-isaac-kamins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2012 06:57:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/28/spiraling-energy-body-qigong-with-isaac-kamins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-3925 &#34; title=&#34;Isaac Kamins Spiraling&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/05/BaGuaIT09.3-217-224x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Isaac Kamins Spiraling&#34; width=&#34;224&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spiraling Energy Body Qigong set is one of the toughest in the Energy Arts system, so I asked &lt;a href=&#34;http://watertradition.net/about.html&#34;&gt;Energy Arts Instructor Isaac Kamins&lt;/a&gt; to tell us about his experiences with this practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Isaac explains how as a teenager he came to appreciate the counter-intuitive approach that the internal martial arts take to fighting and how &lt;strong&gt;the energetic sensitivity he has developed doing Spiraling Energy Body qigong&lt;/strong&gt; has influenced how he interacts with other people and the world around him, far beyond the martial arts.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3924&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, Isaac discusses how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spiraling is different from Energy Gates and I Chuan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The downward dissolving practice from Energy Gates prepares you to handle the upward currents of energy in Spiraling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You work directly with the gates in Spiraling to create more integrated, flexible, and spontaneous internal connections&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Be sure to listen to the entire episode because towards the very end, Isaac gives one of the best descriptions I&#39;ve heard in a long time of the way the entire Energy Arts system is designed to help you grow over time by circling back to material at ever-deeper layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we discussed in the episode, Isaac teaches regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://watertradition.net/home.html&#34;&gt;Ba Gua, Tai Chi, and Qigong classes and workshops in the Bay Area&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks to everyone who has supported the Qigong Radio project by making a donation to our equipment upgrade fund. I hope you can hear the difference in quality that the new equipment made in this interview. If you enjoyed the content, consider making a small donation. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;cmd&#34; value=&#34;_s-xclick&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;hosted_button_id&#34; value=&#34;JM5L8XE2BBXM4&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_donateCC_LG.gif&#34; alt=&#34;PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/form&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>