<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-arts on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/energy-arts/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy-arts on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/energy-arts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Training Xing Yi&#39;s Five Elements with Isaac Kamins</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/31/training-xing-yis-five-elements-with-isaac-kamins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 11:44:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/31/training-xing-yis-five-elements-with-isaac-kamins/</guid>
      <description>As you know from other episodes of Qigong Radio and other interviews, I always try to track down authoritative sources when I want to learn more about a subject and share it with you.
Now that my teacher Bruce Frantzis is releasing two more DVD sets on Xingyi&#39;s Five Elements, I wanted to talk to someone about these practices.
To the best of my knowledge, Isaac Kamins is the only person actively teaching the Energy Arts Xingyi curriculum who also trained with Bruce Frantzis in weekly classes for several years in the Bay Area in the 90&#39;s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chasing Secrets and Shortcuts in Taoist Energy Arts</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/23/chasing-secrets-and-shortcuts-in-taoist-energy-arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2013 16:19:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/23/chasing-secrets-and-shortcuts-in-taoist-energy-arts/</guid>
      <description>When you set out to learn Taoist Energy Arts like Tai Chi, qigong, or meditation, you come across the lore of masters with supernatural abilities or techniques too deadly to teach openly.
Or more insidious, we grasp after images of unattainable perfection, always slightly beyond reach, unless we just find the right technique or are initiated into a secret practice.
And even if we&#39;ve given up silly kung fu fantasies of flying through the bamboo reeds, on a subtle level we still chase ideas and dreams that only live in the mental realm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong is Packed with Internal Content</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</guid>
      <description>This summer, Bruce Frantzis will be teaching a Marriage of Heaven and Earth Instructor training. Heaven and Earth was the first instructor training I attended in 2004 and I can still remember what a profound effect learning to &#34;pulse&#34; had on me.
Within the Energy Arts system, Heaven and Earth is considered a bridge from the basic to more advanced practices.
We discussed how Heaven and Earth works in an early episode of Qigong Radio, but I wanted to share this explanation from Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel with you too:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.
Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</guid>
      <description>After teaching thousands of people of all ages and physical abilities over the last eight years, it is clear to me that there is one technique in Tai Chi that is more powerful than all others.
My main teacher, Bruce Frantzis, introduced me to this technique and taught me how to use all its variations, under different conditions. He has encouraged all his instructors to pass along this technique because it is practically a lost art.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Eight Energies of Tai Chi and the Physical Attributes of Roll Back</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 13:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</guid>
      <description>As part of the Tai Chi Mastery Program, Bruce Frantzis recently published a report called &#34;The Eight Principles of Tai Chi Chuan.&#34; The report is full of detail about stages of training 8 different energies of Tai Chi, laid out in clear and straightforward language.
But I always have a problem with writing like this....
On the one hand, it is invaluable for anyone who wants to understand the bigger context of their Tai Chi practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Calm Your Mind Through Movement</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 08:45:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</guid>
      <description>Movement can be a powerful tool for creating a calm mind, but only when you follow some very specific rules.
Tai Chi was designed with these specific movement rules because the goal is to take you from tense to relaxed and from relaxed to vital and strong.
When my Tai Chi teacher, Bruce Frantzis explains the learning progression for Tai Chi, he makes it clear that when your primary focus is on the mind, and your goal is to calm your mind, you must follow this progression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bill Ryan on Developing Energy Sensitivity</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 06:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/</guid>
      <description>When learning qigong or Tai Chi, people are often either more tuned into to energy or to their physical bodies. In this episode of Qigong Radio, I asked my first qigong and Tai Chi teacher, Energy Arts Senior Instructor and founder of Brookline Tai Chi, Bill Ryan to explain why this is.
More importantly, Bill teaches you how to navigate the experiences of developing your internal energy, regardless of how you first become aware of them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Intensive 9 Months Later</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/04/tai-chi-intensive-9-months-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 06:54:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/04/tai-chi-intensive-9-months-later/</guid>
      <description>When you spend a month training Tai Chi 10-12 hours a day, what happens when you go home? What does it feel like several months later when your life has returned to normal? Is it a let down? Do you need to be inspired again to continue your training?
What have you continued to discover about your practice? How has the intensive training infused your teaching?
I sat down with several Energy Arts Tai Chi instructors to discuss these issues for Episode 3 of Qigong Radio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow and Stabilizing the Mind with Craig Barnes</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 08:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</guid>
      <description>Stability and flow seem to be at odds with each other. Stability can mean rigidity, or at least, it seems to conjure up something fixed, sturdy, and unmoving. Flow isn&#39;t any of those things. It&#39;s fluid and changing. So how does Energy Arts Senior Instructor Craig Barnes blend the two so seamlessly?

Recently, Craig taught a workshop about awakening energetic sensitivity, drawn from principles of Dragon and Tiger Qigong. We worked a lot on the opening of the set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Form Training Final Update</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 12:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m heading home to Boston tomorrow, but I&#39;ve already begun looking through my notes and thinking about what I will personally practice and what I&#39;ll be able to share with my students in classes this coming year. Here are some of my initial thoughts:

How Material is Woven together over a Month:
 Day to day we&#39;re looking at really small specific pieces but now going back through my notes, I can start to see different threads that run throughout the duration of the month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update from the Beach</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>Week 3 wraps up and testing is right around the corner. What was Bruce&#39;s big message as we prepare for testing? Work your ass off and cram all night for the big test? Not quite. You might be surprised. Check it out:

A Lesson about Integration:
The biggest thing that Bruce is emphasizing in the last couple days of class is that with this stage of the training, a month long training, you need integration time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 of the Short Form Instructor Training</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 09:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s my Week 2 update. Some big milestones this week: group 1 finished the form and group 2 has been languishing in the purgatory that is holding static postures. Check it out:

Inner Form vs. Outer Form
 In the two groups, we&#39;re doing very different things. The group one just finished the form this week. So on Thursday after they finished it, we came in Friday, and it was a really interesting dividing line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am Learning at the Wu Tai Chi Instructor Training</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 01:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re a week into the Wu Tai Chi short form instructor training in Brighton, UK, with Lineage Holder Bruce Frantzis. So far we&#39;ve been completely rebuilding our forms, working on Tai Chi leg power, and exploring the meditative aspects of the art. Check it out:

On Rebuilding Your Form:
It&#39;s crazy when you come at these things, you&#39;re completely rebuilding your Tai Chi form. We&#39;re about two-thirds of the way through the form and it feels so different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Quiet Awareness with Lee Burkins</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</guid>
      <description>In June, between sessions at Brookline Tai Chi and during master classes with Bruce Frantzis, a small group of students got a special treat. Energy Arts Senior Instructor Lee Burkins was in town to train with Bruce, and on one of the nights off, he offered a special evening course on a topic he calls &#34;Investing in Loss&#34;.
What I love about studying with someone like Lee is that he&#39;s a practitioner whose art has soaked so deeply into his bones, that it practically oozes out of his DNA.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>