<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-arts on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/energy-arts/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy-arts on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/energy-arts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Training Xing Yi&#39;s Five Elements with Isaac Kamins</title>
      <link>/2013/10/31/training-xing-yis-five-elements-with-isaac-kamins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 11:44:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/31/training-xing-yis-five-elements-with-isaac-kamins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4960&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Instructor Isaac Kamins&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/10/Isaac_Kamins-207x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;207&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you know from other episodes of &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/qigongradio/&#34;&gt;Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt; and other interviews, I always try to track down authoritative sources when I want to learn more about a subject and share it with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that my teacher Bruce Frantzis is releasing two more DVD sets on Xingyi&#39;s Five Elements, I wanted to talk to someone about these practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the best of my knowledge, Isaac Kamins is the only person actively teaching the Energy Arts Xingyi curriculum who also trained with Bruce Frantzis in weekly classes for several years in the Bay Area in the 90&#39;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isaac has shared his deep knowledge of the Energy Arts system in &lt;a title=&#34;Spiraling Energy Body Qigong with Isaac Kamins&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/28/spiraling-energy-body-qigong-with-isaac-kamins/&#34;&gt;past episodes of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt; and I think you&#39;ll find that he doesn&#39;t hold back on his training insights in this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The unique way Xingyi forges a strong mind-body connection and helps you overcome mental gaps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How the 5 Elements are manifested in the simple, repetitive forms of Xingyi&#39;s 5 Fists -- and how this gives you a direct experience of Water, Earth, Metal, Fire, and Wood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What it was like to go through the entire 5 Element cycle with Bruce three different times, each time over a two-year period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How, even if you don&#39;t &#34;major&#34; in Xingyi, you can gain insight into Tai Chi, Bagua, or even qigong, with the direct, experiential quality of 5 Element practice.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bonus Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I asked Isaac to go beyond just talking about the practice and actually teach you some Xingyi. Isaac created a short video tutorial and guided audio practice that helps you get the feel of San Ti, Xingyi&#39;s main power-building practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you download the audio (fill out the form below to receive it via email), watch this video a few times to get a feel for the opening movement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/7SY56FCto5Y?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r146hes70esx1il&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r146hes70esx1il&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r146hes70esx1il;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r146hes70esx1il&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;495&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;host&#39;:&#39;wufoo.com&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { r146hes70esx1il = new WufooForm();r146hes70esx1il.initialize(options);r146hes70esx1il.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chasing Secrets and Shortcuts in Taoist Energy Arts</title>
      <link>/2013/10/23/chasing-secrets-and-shortcuts-in-taoist-energy-arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2013 16:19:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/23/chasing-secrets-and-shortcuts-in-taoist-energy-arts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1537&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you set out to learn Taoist Energy Arts like Tai Chi, qigong, or meditation, you come across the lore of masters with supernatural abilities or techniques too deadly to teach openly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or more insidious, we grasp after images of unattainable perfection, always slightly beyond reach, unless we just find the right technique or are initiated into a secret practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even if we&#39;ve given up silly kung fu fantasies of flying through the bamboo reeds, on a subtle level we still chase ideas and dreams that only live in the mental realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality - and I&#39;m not trying to disappoint you, but stay with me because the reality is deeply rewarding, meaningful, and rich too - is that Taoist Energy Arts must be lived-through and practiced-through to be truly discovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Paul Cavel and I explore the disconnect you can sometimes feel in the day-to-day of your practice and the idea of where you ought to be in your practice - it&#39;s not because you must be a chosen one or special to get it, but rather, because you can&#39;t directly perceive or experience energy when you operate solely on the mental realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll give you some guidelines for how to recognize when you slip back into the mental realm of fantasy practice and talk about the struggles, as a student and as a teacher, of communicating your practice experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul also shares specific neigong techniques that will keep you present, engaged, and help you cultivate a direct experience of your natural internal energy, that can be applied to any energy practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more from Paul about the best way to study Taoist Practices by signing up for his newsletter here (includes a free guide to getting started with Taoist Energy Arts):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;http://forms.aweber.com/form/68/1737149068.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong is Packed with Internal Content</title>
      <link>/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-4444 alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Paul Cavel performs the Marriage of Heaven and Earth&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/12/qi-gong-class-11.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;250&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This summer, Bruce Frantzis will be teaching a Marriage of Heaven and Earth Instructor training. Heaven and Earth was the first instructor training I attended in 2004 and I can still remember what a profound effect learning to &#34;pulse&#34; had on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the Energy Arts system, Heaven and Earth is considered a bridge from the basic to more advanced practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;how Heaven and Earth works in an early episode of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt;, but I wanted to share this explanation from &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; with you too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Heaven + Earth Works On So Many Levels&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As discussed in earlier issues, classically Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body Qigong is the foundation of the entire Water tradition since it initiates all neigong practice through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alignments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sinking chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissolving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bending and stretching techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic breathing methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Circulating chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaging the kwa as the leader of all motion&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Energy Gates softens the body and prepares the &#34;shell&#34; by creating a containment field with the body and its energy to develop more sophisticated neigong technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas Heaven + Earth takes the baton from Energy Gates and folds in the internal content learned there. So everything you learn and the skill you develop in each qigong system can and should be packed up and shipped off to the next set in the series. Yes, the arrangement will be completely unique, but you don&#39;t throw away or leave dormant any components while developing superior forms. For example, recall that Dragon + Tiger Medical Qigong is one of the three foundational practices in the neigong lattice. Dragon + Tiger&#39;s underlying technology develops the etheric field and wei chi, and thereby serves as a subcomponent of Heaven + Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as a more advanced practice than either Energy Gates or Dragon + Tiger, Heaven + Earth not only encompasses everything within these sets, but also further develops and upgrades each strand of neigong learned within them. This adds up to a serious amount of internal content&amp;mdash;even before material specific to Heaven + Earth is on the table. These include fundamental techniques like pulsing and developing the macrocosmic and microcosmic orbits of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as Heaven + Earth is a two-part, single exercise rather than a set of five, six or seven movements (like the other core practices in our system), its simplistic format encourages the internal rather than external focus needed to train deeper, more sophisticated neigong methods.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The excerpt above is from Paul&#39;s Inner Quest Newsletter, a monthly publication I highly recommend. Each month he writes in depth about a different aspect of learning and training neigong. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p5x7/&#34;&gt;You can download a free sample issue here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/q3tlLKD4YdM?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you download or listen to the episode below, you might also want to check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/bend-bow-spinal-qigong&#34;&gt;the description of Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong on EnergyArts.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/classes/chi-gung-bend-bow-introduction-bend-bow-and-shoot-arrow-december-1-2-late-fall-session&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be sure to check out Eric&#39;s Bend the Bow workshop, December 1 and 2, 2012 at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique</title>
      <link>/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After teaching thousands of people of all ages and physical abilities over the last eight years, it is clear to me that there is one technique in Tai Chi that is more powerful than all others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis Tai Chi Resources&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis-tai-chi-resources/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, introduced me to this technique and taught me how to use all its variations, under different conditions. He has encouraged all his instructors to pass along this technique because it is practically a lost art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just this week, he released &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/tai-chi/the-insiders-guide-to-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;The Insider&#39;s Guide to Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, where he describes Tai Chi&#39;s most powerful technique in detail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upon recognizing what your own qi feels like, you begin two separate phases that synergistically work with each other. The first is centered on your central nervous system. Having gained the experience of putting your mind (awareness) into your muscles, you now learn to put it into your nerves. Relaxing and releasing the nerves themselves enables you to recognize the constant buzz that runs through your entire nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are not aware of this ever-present stressful buzz because it has become so normal. This buzz is a sure sign that your nervous system is either beginning to rev up (like a car going from 0-60 miles per hour in a few seconds), or even worse, has been locked habitually into a constant rev. This rev or buzz is how stress seeps through and hardens into your body. You now focus on ways to re-soften this nervous buzz inside you and progressively relax and release it from your nerves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a growing capacity to relax, you move into the second phase. Here you want to release the more-subtle nervous buzz of blocked qi inside all your body&#39;s tissues. Progressively, step-by-step, you find and release the rev in your joints, blood flow, spinal system, internal organs and glands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each stage of releasing the rev from your bodily systems makes your body more awake. This takes you into more subtle and powerful experiences of what it means and feels like for your body to be fully alive.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The enlivening technology of Tai Chi -- not what is visible on the outside, but what you do on the inside, with your mind, your chi, and in your nervous system -- holds the potential to transform the way you feel throughout the day, every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time I get a clear hit of just how to release a new layer, or relax to a new level, it blows me away and makes me hope that you can find a way to experience it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Eight Energies of Tai Chi and the Physical Attributes of Roll Back</title>
      <link>/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 13:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;a title=&#34;Your Guide to the Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/your-guide-to-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;, Bruce Frantzis recently published a report called &#34;The Eight Principles of Tai Chi Chuan.&#34; The report is full of detail about stages of training 8 different energies of Tai Chi, laid out in clear and straightforward language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I always have a problem with writing like this....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, it is invaluable for anyone who wants to understand the bigger context of their Tai Chi practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re not careful, though, you can fall into a Tai Chi trap (see below after the video).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Physical Attributes of Roll Back&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the report, Bruce details each of the different energies and one of the sections that jumped out at me was the chapter on &#34;Lu&#34; or &#34;Roll Back.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roll Back is Tai Chi&#39;s signature yielding or softening energy. Bruce lays out an excellent progression for training Roll Back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I demonstrate the five points he makes about the &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; aspects of Roll Back:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/PL8TPEu3TWw?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Tai Chi Trap&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, when you read the report, Bruce lays out the physical aspects of Roll Back, then the energetic ones. Once he explains the physical aspects, he says,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the early stages of learning Roll Back, your movements will be large and obvious, both in your joints and in your waist. Over time, however, as your physical movements become more refined and circular, they can become extremely small, so tiny, in fact, that they are virtually invisible to the eye of someone untrained in observing subtlety of movement.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;And here&#39;s the trap: you read about subtlety and refinement and energetics that seem superhuman and because you are a well-trained, sophisticated thinker, you choose to imagine that you can do the subtle version right away.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bruce just gave you a road map, but you think you&#39;re already at your destination because you can read the map and picture the destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that&#39;s not how a journey really works and that&#39;s not how growth occurs in your Tai Chi practice. Especially when it gets to the subtle energetics, you have to work your way into them slowly over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Big Road Map: The Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bruce is about to release a huge road map for a lifelong journey through Tai Chi. My biggest fear is that people will buy the map and fantasize about the destinations, but never actually begin the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who does want to go on that journey, though, I&#39;m getting ready to go with you and I&#39;d be happy to be your guide along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To get the rest of my guided tour of the Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/strong&gt; (including &#34;The Eight Energies of Tai Chi Chuan&#34; report from Bruce), &lt;a title=&#34;Your Guide to the Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/your-guide-to-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;visit this page and sign up&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bon Voyage!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Calm Your Mind Through Movement</title>
      <link>/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 08:45:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads/2011/10/P10001922.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2313&#34; title=&#34;Repulse Monkey&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/10/P10001922-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tai Chi in Gloucester, MA&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Movement can be a powerful tool for creating a calm mind, but only when you follow some very specific rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi was designed with these specific movement rules because the goal is to take you from tense to relaxed and from relaxed to vital and strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my Tai Chi teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt; explains the learning progression for Tai Chi, he makes it clear that when your primary focus is on the mind, and your goal is to calm your mind, you must follow this progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relax Your Muscles and Your Mind&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
At the first stage, you go for the big obvious stuff. Most of us are more tuned into muscular contraction and mental tension than to constrictions in our soft tissues or jammed joints. Start with what you can feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you are learning basic exercises and a broad-stroke version of the Tai Chi form, focus on relaxing your muscles and begin to catch yourself in moments of mental tension. Learn to let go of each one as you move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By training yourself to find these moments in motion, you begin to make relaxation a habit that will follow you into daily activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Find Your Shape&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you go through the Tai Chi form for the first time, you are sketching the basic shape that will be filled in in detail later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, don&#39;t overstretch, don&#39;t contract too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to feel basic alignments, like centering the weight in your feet as you shift and turn and squat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the cadence of the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By following these movement rules, you are building a physical container. The more unified this container becomes, the more you can run your mind through your body. Following all of the rhythms and flows of the form with your awareness leads to the same kind of letting go for your mind that we began to work in with the muscles in the first stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Layer By Layer&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you relax your mind and your body, you can go deeper. Your mind penetrates deeper into the space inside your body and as a result, your body is knit together in a stronger way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You learn to make deep internal connections that optimize how you move and how you respond to your surroundings. You have more energy.You can interact with your internal environment in a smoother way too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how relaxation leads to strength.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bill Ryan on Developing Energy Sensitivity</title>
      <link>/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 06:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-3850&#34; title=&#34;Bill Ryan Energy Arts Senior Instructor&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/04/Bill_LO_150w.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bill Ryan Energy Arts Senior Instructor&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When learning qigong or Tai Chi, people are often either more tuned into to energy or to their physical bodies. In this episode of Qigong Radio, I asked my first qigong and Tai Chi teacher, Energy Arts Senior Instructor and founder of Brookline Tai Chi, Bill Ryan to explain why this is.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3844&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, Bill teaches you how to navigate the experiences of developing your internal energy, regardless of how you first become aware of them. It turns out, you&#39;re probably already more tuned in than you think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are very sensitive to energy, Bill also has some great advice about how to become more grounded and balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to the episode here and then &lt;a href=&#34;http://towardharmony.com/about_us/bill_ryan.html&#34;&gt;learn more about Bill and what he teaches at Toward Harmony Tai Chi and Qigong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks for supporting the Qigong Radio project. I know the audio quality isn&#39;t great &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt;...but if you enjoyed the content, consider making a small donation ($15 goes a long way!) to help us upgrade our equipment. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;cmd&#34; value=&#34;_s-xclick&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;hosted_button_id&#34; value=&#34;JM5L8XE2BBXM4&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_donateCC_LG.gif&#34; alt=&#34;PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/form&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Intensive 9 Months Later</title>
      <link>/2012/04/04/tai-chi-intensive-9-months-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 06:54:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/04/tai-chi-intensive-9-months-later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34; wp-image-3752&#34; title=&#34;Energy Arts Tai Chi Instructors at Push Hands&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/04/Photo-Mar-30-2-27-16-PM-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you spend a month training Tai Chi 10-12 hours a day, what happens when you go home? What does it feel like several months later when your life has returned to normal? Is it a let down? Do you need to be inspired again to continue your training?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have you continued to discover about your practice? How has the intensive training infused your teaching?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sat down with several Energy Arts Tai Chi instructors to discuss these issues for Episode 3 of Qigong Radio. Here&#39;s what they had to say. Since we were all together for a Push Hands training, designed to be a follow-up to the Short Form training, we also talked about the ways we were seeing connections between the two topics.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3751&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to these guys for participating: Senior Instructors &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.balancedenergyarts.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Jamie Dibdin from Brighton, UK&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/edgartown/eric-l-peters&#34;&gt;Eric Peters from Martha&#39;s Vineyard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/harpers-ferry/aaron-green&#34;&gt;Aaron Green from Washington, DC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://taichi.studioyugen.com/&#34;&gt;Scott Huette from Eugene, OR&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ensostudio.com/taichi.html&#34;&gt;Chris Cinnamon from Chicago&lt;/a&gt;, Thomas Herrington from Maui, Chris Redmond from California, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/london/lucy-amis&#34;&gt;Lucy Amis from London&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/manchester/alexander-daniel-connor&#34;&gt;Alex Connor from Manchester, UK&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;Acirc;  &lt;a href=&#34;http://taichi-shiatsu.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Peter Ling&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/pforzheim/franz-heutschy&#34;&gt;Franz Heutschy from Pforzheim, Germany&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zendokan.de/&#34;&gt;Olaf Rolving from Muelhiem, Germany&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichievi.byethost13.com/jeannehome/index.htm&#34;&gt;Jeanne Houde&lt;/a&gt;, and local instructors Ana Popa, Janak Sanariya, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.natehribar.com&#34;&gt;Nate Hribar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow and Stabilizing the Mind with Craig Barnes</title>
      <link>/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 08:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2203&#34; title=&#34;Craig Barnes doing Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-3-199x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Craig Barnes doing Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; width=&#34;199&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;Stability and flow seem to be at odds with each other. Stability can mean rigidity, or at least, it seems to conjure up something fixed, sturdy, and unmoving. Flow isn&#39;t any of those things. It&#39;s fluid and changing. So how does Energy Arts Senior Instructor Craig Barnes blend the two so seamlessly?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2191&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Recently, Craig taught a workshop about awakening energetic sensitivity, drawn from principles of Dragon and Tiger Qigong. We worked a lot on the opening of the set. The goal was to &#34;fill up your chi&#34; before you start doing the movements, so that the body is awake and engaged and each movement is more alive and more connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specific method for waking up your energetic sensitivity begins with refining awareness of your physical body. How do you move each part under conscious control, in a smooth circular way? Craig is very skilled at leading a group through a gradual progression that brings each new piece online and then weaves it together with the previous pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What impressed me more, though, was the way he included &#34;stability points&#34;, while maintaining the flow of the teaching, which was also what he was teaching people to do in their practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps &#34;stability point&#34; is the wrong term. Certainly this was a &#34;point&#34; in time in the flow of practice, but what Craig teaches, as far as stabilizing the mind, has a more diffuse quality than &#34;point&#34; conveys. You miss it if you focus on all the little details of body mechanics. If you treat the components of your practice like a checklist, you never become internally connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stability of the mind, when Craig expresses it, becomes the ground for your practice. A stable mind is like a table, set for a great meal. The specific exercises are the plates and bowls and cups that get filled up with delicious food, but you need to set the table for the meal to come together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-medium wp-image-2204&#34; title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Sword Fingers&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-2-224x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Sword Fingers&#34; width=&#34;224&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Internalizing the paradox of stability and flow goes a step or two beyond &#34;setting the table&#34;, though. Dragon and Tiger is a great place to learn how to stabilize the mind in the flow of movements because, between each distinct movement pattern, there are transitional moves that you can repeat as much as you need to. In these transitions, it&#39;s much easier to return to stability, but you don&#39;t have to break the flow. You do something simple, like circle the arms back and forth around the waist, or pulse the hands in and out, which keeps up a smooth flow. Through the simple repetition, your mind can settle down again at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Dragon and Tiger is made for this kind of work, you can still go through this process in any qigong set, if you follow these rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start your practice with simple, repetitive movements that allow you to tune into the background or underlying stability of your mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tease out gradually bigger and bigger movements, without losing the stable ground feeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work up into larger flow patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take soft landings throughout the set that return you to something simple and repetitive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For tai chi people: this is why a phrase like Grasp Sparrow&#39;s Tail is repeated a dozen times in a long form.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Form Training Final Update</title>
      <link>/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 12:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m heading home to Boston tomorrow, but I&#39;ve already begun looking through my notes and thinking about what I will personally practice and what I&#39;ll be able to share with my students in classes this coming year. Here are some of my initial thoughts:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1827&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ZkLnAA8ejb8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ZkLnAA8ejb8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Material is Woven together over a Month:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Day to day we&#39;re looking at really small specific pieces but now going back through my notes, I can start to see different threads that run throughout the duration of the month. It&#39;s almost like you don&#39;t even notice some of the nuances as in the moment, but like we&#39;ll look at something about the legs in Tai Chi from the first day and then we came back to it four or five days later and then we look at it again, and when you actually line up the pieces side by side, what you start to see is that...versus looking at it from like sort of looking at a ball, you look at it from one side and then the next time you look at it from this angle, then you look at it from this angle. And by taking this kind of spherical approach to it, looking at different facets of the subject, you start to develop a sense for the whole. And it&#39;s not the progression that he always teaches and it&#39;s not linear. It&#39;s not one, two, three, four, five. It&#39;s look at it this way, look at it that way and it&#39;s sort of up to you to put the pieces together to create the whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Handling Stress on a Whole New Level&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;They&#39;re all are these layers to that and progressions that I&#39;ll be able to lay out for my students, but personally for me I think one of the most exciting ones that I&#39;ll be able to bring to people is some really specific technical information about burnout and stress and no, I mean, if you think about Tai Chi in general, that&#39;s kind of what it&#39;s known for. It&#39;s a relaxation practice and it looks calming in that way. Everybody&#39;s first impression of it is that it is gentle and relaxing, but we actually got in much deeper into the technical stuff and the form that actually makes the softness of Tai Chi really work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;s not always contrasted to the couch potato model of relaxation where we live in this culture where we think, okay just go, go, go, go, go 24/7 and when you want to relax, pass out on the couch in front of the TV. So we have these two extremes. Tai chi is sort of an antidote to stress. It works on relaxation but it&#39;s a little more complicated than that. It&#39;s not... relaxation isn&#39;t just a flop. Relaxation has to do much more with your capacity to put energy out and take energy in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there&#39;s some really interesting technical stuff in terms of being able to absorb and nourish the body that is really Tai Chi&#39;s strong suit that you&#39;re not going to get in this kind of fast paced go, go, go, very Yang, very revved up kind of mentality. Instead, Tai Chi has a way of building the nervous system and building the body up so that it can rest, absorb and regenerate and we looked at some really specific ways to highlight in the form to make sure that happens for people.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update from the Beach</title>
      <link>/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 3 wraps up and testing is right around the corner. What was Bruce&#39;s big message as we prepare for testing? Work your ass off and cram all night for the big test? Not quite. You might be surprised. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1823&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/BQcg7CR5F78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/BQcg7CR5F78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Lesson about Integration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing that Bruce is emphasizing in the last couple days of class is that with this stage of the training, a month long training, you need integration time. And we talk about this all the time in regular weekly classes. We talk about in a given practice session, whether it&#39;s an hour or 20 minutes or whatever, you always have this sort of startup time where you just get warmed up. And then from there you go into the work period, where you just kind of crank and crank and crank, and that&#39;s when your system is the most open. You can get a lot done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the biggest mistake people make is that they do that hard charge all the way to the end. The secret to all of these energy practices, to really get your energy to smoothed out and then get into your nervous system in the best possible way, is that you need to have integration. So, we talk about it all the time. That&#39;s how we try to do each practice session. So, to me, it&#39;s really cool to watch this month-long work and hear Bruce talk about that and emphasize that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Yesterday he talked a lot about what to do on the day off, in terms of even just mentally rehearsing the form, going through and trying to feel it through your body without doing the movements. So there&#39;s a lot of interesting stuff about mental rehearsal that we talked about, but also just to let it kind of soak into your system. And I find when students can recognize that integration phase as a legitimate part of the practice, then you take it to a whole deeper level, because you recognize rest as an important part of hard work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And I think there are a lot of ways that we&#39;ve lost that idea culturally and a lot of ideas of success and hard work don&#39;t really acknowledge the resting and integration phase as an important piece of it. So even though we&#39;ve come through intensive month-long training, as we&#39;re rounding into the final stretch, rest and integration and relaxation is a key piece to learning all this stuff. And to me that&#39;s very cool. So that&#39;s what we&#39;re up to this week.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 of the Short Form Instructor Training</title>
      <link>/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 09:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my Week 2 update. Some big milestones this week: group 1 finished the form and group 2 has been languishing in the purgatory that is holding static postures. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1816&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/FpsecDulvWc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/FpsecDulvWc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inner Form vs. Outer Form&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;In the two groups, we&#39;re doing very different things. The group one just finished the form this week. So on Thursday after they finished it, we came in Friday, and it was a really interesting dividing line. Bruce made the big distinction between, on the one hand, on Thursday we finished the shape and the form, that&#39;s sort of the container. He said, &#34;Now, everything that we&#39;re going to do has to do with internal content.&#34; So he made this distinction all the time. He talked about the bottle versus the wine you put inside it and we even have an article at Brookline Tai Chi that we put out from, I think, it&#39;s from 1989 Tai Chi Magazine. The title of the article is &#34;The Inner Form is the Key to Health.&#34; And in the article, Bruce talks about all the different internal content things that should be going on that to be Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And I find this working with beginners all the time is such a huge hurdle to get them over. Because people know Tai Chi by looks like in the outside, they see the shapes and the movements, and they see it flowing and graceful and relaxed, but it&#39;s really hard unless you&#39;re used to looking at it, to see what&#39;s going on inside. But Bruce always makes this big point, it actually what goes on inside that makes Tai Chi actually effective. It makes it not just choreography but it makes it work to improve your health, we&#39;re going to do meditation and martial arts. If you don&#39;t have the internal content, it&#39;s like driving a car without an engine. So it&#39;s interesting to hear him talk about for a group that&#39;s just finishing the container of the form. Now, to start to see what he started out with. And as far as internal content for them and how we&#39;re going to build that up. So that&#39;s a cool inflection point in the halfway point for the first group.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Finding Internal Stability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the second group we&#39;ve been holding postures. And so we&#39;ve gone through now, I think, eight of the postures and the form, and building out from twenty, twenty-five, thirty minutes. And this is one of my favorite methods - the posture holding and you see up here, look at some other posing here, you see me messing around with 30 minutes in one posture or something else like that, I&#39;ve always liked it in the standing practice. It was the thing that kind of, for me, made the difference of what&#39;s in the outside and &#34;Hey, if you stand still and start to just feel into the body, there&#39;s this whole internal landscape you can start to explore.&#34; And that was the thing that always got me excited about Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&#39;m very happy that we&#39;ve been going through and holding posture by posture. What it is about it, is that if you get into each posture and the form, each of them because of the physical constraints, higher twisting, one way twisting, the other way, whether the posture&#39;s more extended, or whether the posture is more condensed, all of these things add up to determine in a specific posture how you manifest the energy of that posture. And so by holding it, you start to feel those internal gears kind of click and lock together in a way that you just if you&#39;re always just going through the form doing whatever, you totally missed that aspect. Sometimes you noticed really where you&#39;re tense, where things are stuck. But once you get each one of these things, it has kind of like a threshold where it clicks in. And I&#39;ve always thought about it in terms of, &#34;Okay, I&#39;m going to hold this one for twenty, this one for thirty, this one longer, longer.&#34; But one of the key points that Bruce made was that once you hit a certain stability point for that posture, everything opens up and lights up. The pathways light up or this connection lights up that gives the posture a unique flavor. That&#39;s the key moment. And then you wanted to maintain that for as long as you can. And inevitably you lose it, you shrink out of it, you start to collapse a little bit, something gets off. And this is game of like, &#34;Okay, how do I connect to it?&#34; Reliably create that effective posture and then stabilize it. And once you can stabilize it for a long time, then you move into this thing where the quality, the posture becomes integrated into your form and to how you move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to me, I don&#39;t know, it&#39;s a fascinating process. Other people joke that the fastest way clear Tai Chi class and get everybody to flee out of the room is to just make them close their eyes and hold the posture. So it&#39;s definitely a matter of personal preference. But I mean it&#39;s really cool, that&#39;s what we&#39;ve been focusing on all week.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am Learning at the Wu Tai Chi Instructor Training</title>
      <link>/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 01:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re a week into the Wu Tai Chi short form instructor training in Brighton, UK, with Lineage Holder Bruce Frantzis. So far we&#39;ve been completely rebuilding our forms, working on Tai Chi leg power, and exploring the meditative aspects of the art. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2964&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HoXz88Vyxe0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HoXz88Vyxe0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Rebuilding Your Form:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s crazy when you come at these things, you&#39;re completely rebuilding your Tai Chi form. We&#39;re about two-thirds of the way through the form and it feels so different. When you&amp;Acirc;  run through the whole thing one time, you get up to what we&#39;ve done so far and it feels brand new, like a completely different moves. And then you get to the last thing we&#39;ve done, you come around to the last move that you finished and you go back to your old form and it has a totally different feeling.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Yin and Yang of Tai Chi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contrast is that the biggest thing that he took from the London trainings into the Tai Chi training was this idea. He talks about it in terms of Yin and Yang, in terms of soft and hard, or in the sitting practice, it&#39;s about how do you go deep inside the body. You find this internal space and then let go of anything you find that&#39;s stuck. But there&#39;s an interesting contrast, it&#39;s not just let go and relax and collapse because the quality of mind it takes is that you have to sort of go inside, find and hold your awareness on something and persist with this awareness. That&#39;s a stronger quality. So this is interesting, this is Yin and Yang blend of getting your mind onto something and holding it there, giving it shape and containing this feeling. But then the other side it to completely let go, completely relaxing. So that&#39;s the Yin and Yang of the dissolving process. And we&#39;ve expanded that idea where he&#39;s talking about the energies in the Tai Chi form, the way we working on Tai Chi, the forming energies to the form, that balance of finding it, holding it and adding this kind of consistent, persistent meditative awareness as you do Tai Chi, is mirrored in the sort of the Yang aspects of the Tai Chi form. And then that letting go, softening, releasing, relaxing and just completely not holding on anything is there&#39;s the Yin qualities to the form, that have that same thing. So through Peng, Lu, Ji and An, each one of those from a meditative point of view can figure into how you&#39;re doing, making your Tai Chi form a true meditation practice, not just relaxation practice. So there&#39;s really great stuff there.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Quiet Awareness with Lee Burkins</title>
      <link>/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1656&#34; title=&#34;Lee Burkins Ba Gua&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/06/ABG1-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lee Burkins Ba Gua&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In June, between sessions at Brookline Tai Chi and during master classes with Bruce Frantzis, a small group of students got a special treat. Energy Arts Senior Instructor Lee Burkins was in town to train with Bruce, and on one of the nights off, he offered a special evening course on a topic he calls &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/blog/special-evening-mini-topic-lee-burkins&#34;&gt;&#34;Investing in Loss&#34;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I love about studying with someone like Lee is that he&#39;s a  practitioner whose art has soaked so deeply into his bones, that it  practically oozes out of his DNA. Everything he teaches seems so  obviously and natural when he explains it, but you&#39;ve never thought about  it before and never accessed it so effortlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second time he&#39;s taught at Brookline Tai Chi. The first  time, a couple of years ago, he did the same thing with the&amp;Acirc;  Ba Gua  Single Palm Change. Lee took a group of people, most of whom had never  done Ba Gua, and got them gliding around the room, finding the Ba Gua  step, and eventually even spontaneously twisting and turning into the  Single Palm Change. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1651&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our topic this year seemed more esoteric at first, so I was wondering if he&#39;d be able to do the same thing. What  the heck is &#34;Quiet Awareness&#34; and how do you let that run your physical  body? You could see that with many other teachers, this could have been a  2-hour theoretical lecture. Not with Lee. He snuck up on us with really  clear and simple physical exercises, just letting go of tension and  posture through movements. We let ourselves swirl around and find a  sloshing, fluid, sense of internal space. Once people had settled down  into deeper internal awareness, he showed us how to shape an internal  sense of letting go into a solid physical structure and full, alive, and  responsive physical movement. Obviously this is all a little hard to  explain in writing....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funniest moment though, was after everyone began to really get  what he was driving at, he said, &#34;ok, ok, you&#39;re doing it, so let me  give you something to feed your thinking mind too.&#34; See, the bigger  point he was driving at was that Quiet Awareness is a different mode for  your mind to be in, and you need that to understand your body, your  mind, and your energy. The internal arts are all about accessing this  mode and manifesting it. The problem is, most of us are trained to use a  different mode of awareness, i.e. the thinking mind. As a masterful  teacher, he recognized that, and with the gentle humor he always uses in  teaching, he graciously gave our thinking minds something to chew on  too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Here&#39;s the model he shared:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Leaves on river by rstrawser, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/14696088@N04/1544960560/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2395/1544960560_9e4ba9f9f8_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Leaves on river&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lee took the classic Chinese medicine phrase, &#34;the mind moves the chi  and the chi moves the blood&#34; and formulated it as &#34;the Quiet Awareness  moves the chi and the chi moves the fluids inside the body and therefore  the body as well&#34;. To really get this concept, he explained it like the  current in a river. Think of a leaf floating along in the river. That&#39;s  your body. When the current changes, that&#39;s like the chi shifting. It  shifts direction (inward to outward, up to down), because your Quiet  Awareness shifts first. The interesting part is the lag time between  the change of the current and movement of the leaf. Your Quiet Awareness  turns over, the chi follows, and so does the leaf, but as you are learning  to tune into this process, you can feel the leaf moving along the old  current pattern, even as the current is going a different direction.  Those are the circular transitions you feel in your form.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don&#39;t know if I quite captured what we did or what Lee was  aiming to teach, but if you ever do get a chance to work with him, take  it. He&#39;s a kind and generous teacher and the naturalness of his art form  that pours out is a real treasure. &lt;a href=&#34;http://coloradointernalarts.com/practitioners.htm&#34;&gt;Lee lives and teaches in Colorado&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In his own words: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I followed up with Lee to see if this recap came close to capturing what he was teaching. Here&#39;s how he describes the process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the mind&#39;s frequency to smoothly transition from  the&amp;Acirc; vibration&amp;Acirc; of the intellectual aspect to approach and begin to  connect with the vibration/frequency of the intuitive mind. Once you  &#39;experience&#39; this shift in frequency and are able to stay in this mode  (a posture of the mind), &#39;what is hidden will be revealed&#39;, ie, the  connection of the quiet awareness to the chi to the body (nerves,  fluids, and tissues).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>