<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi-for-health-and-happiness on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi-for-health-and-happiness/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi-for-health-and-happiness on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi-for-health-and-happiness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi with David-Dorian Ross on PBS</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/04/tai-chi-with-david-dorian-ross-on-pbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2012 13:23:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/04/tai-chi-with-david-dorian-ross-on-pbs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This winter, PBS is airing a special one-hour introduction to Tai Chi with &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-instructor-david-dorian-ross/&#34; title=&#34;Tai Chi Instructor David Dorian Ross&#34;&gt;David-Dorian Ross&lt;/a&gt;.  I highly recommend watching the episode, whether you have a lot or a little Tai Chi experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way Ross presents basic concepts and teaches body alignment and choreography is simple and clear. Above all, he moves between classical explanations rooted in Chinese Medicine and Western, physiological-based explanations in an elegant and understandable manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the trailer from PBS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Y-SD2we_LYQ?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What New Practitioners Can Learn from &#34;T&#39;ai Chi for Health and Happiness&#34;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you have never done Tai Chi, or are new to the practice, David-Dorian Ross&#39;s approach will help you build a solid Tai Chi foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He frames the practice around 3 main components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Freedom&lt;/strong&gt; -- the freedom from limitations we all tend to impose on ourselves. Many Tai Chi players will tell you they feel more confident and willing to experience new things, which I believe comes from the self-exploration inherent in learning Tai Chi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flow&lt;/strong&gt; -- the phrase, &lt;a title=&#34;Bill Ryan on Developing Energy Sensitivity&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/&#34;&gt;&#34;the mind moves the chi and the chi moves the blood&#34;&lt;/a&gt; is a central teaching in Tai Chi and he explains what this actually means, through easy-to-feel exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt; -- an interesting choice of words here because the height of &#34;power&#34; in Tai Chi is classically described as &#34;non-doing&#34; or &#34;non-effort&#34;. He does a nice job moving people out of the Western mindset that tension or strength equals power. From a Tai Chi perspective, &lt;a title=&#34;Learning to Soften the Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/26/learning-to-soften-the-body/&#34;&gt;strength only blocks flow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;For Experienced Practitioners (Especially Instructors)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, if you watch this program and you have more experience in Tai Chi, you&#39;ll pick up a whole other layer of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I especially enjoyed the way he translated concepts from the Classics in an accessible way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make flow more tangible, he had people &lt;a title=&#34;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands by Robert Tangora&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/&#34;&gt;&#34;Wave Hands Like Clouds&#34;&lt;/a&gt; sitting down before they attempted to move arms and legs together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He described &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;Song&lt;/a&gt; as the internal state your cat or your child takes on when they don&#39;t want to be picked up and showed people how to have &#34;heavy feet&#34;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He introduced &lt;a title=&#34;Refining Your Opening and Closing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/&#34;&gt;opening and closing&lt;/a&gt; in one of the first lessons on choreography.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The very first principle he taught was &lt;a title=&#34;Spinal Qigong Exercises&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/spinal-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;spinal alignment&lt;/a&gt; in the broadest sense of spinal lengthening, but refined it several times as he was layering in more information.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Within the Tai Chi community, there is tendency to make the practice very obscure. People hide behind lofty concepts instead of giving clear explanations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, what you feel when you practice may be hard to explain, but I&#39;m all in favor of seeing as much teaching as possible done in plain and direct language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that reason, I think this program is an excellent one for people to see as part of their introduction to Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/tv_schedules/&#34;&gt;Check you local PBS listing here&lt;/a&gt; to find out if T&#39;ai Chi for Health and Happiness is airing soon in your area.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>