<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>systems on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/systems/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in systems on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/systems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Home Practice Challenge</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:19:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the recent practice survey we conducted at Brookline Tai Chi and experiments I&#39;ve been running in online learning, it&#39;s become clearer and clearer to me that most people need some external motivation when they are learning a new skill. That&#39;s not a judgment about willpower and motivation, it actually says more about the way we are wired for survival. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1523&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In Z Health, we always talk about the way that the nervous system is at once the most plastic system -- it can adapt to lots of different changes -- and also the most stable. The stability of the nervous system is a good thing from a survival and energy management point of view -- it doesn&#39;t cost you a lot of cognitive energy to get through your day if you run on habit. In that sense, the plasticity of the nervous system -- your ability to change and learn new things -- has to deal with the inertia of stability in your nervous system. When we are trying to learn new behaviors and forge new habits, these two things can be at odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&#39;ve seen and heard from my tai chi students, is that a little bit of external motivation goes a long way to spark the small changes you need to make on a daily basis to put new behavior in place. Last week, one of my students said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was liberating to think that 5 minutes of tai chi practice meant I could make progress, because until I thought about it that way, I avoided practice, assuming it was going to take 30 minutes or more.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, if you look at some studies on mental rehearsal and brain function, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1580438,00.html&#34;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;, you start to see that the cognitive component of learning new skills can be practiced in a much easier way than devoting hours and hours of grueling practice -- time that very few people I work with have to spare anyway. The smarter you get about your practice, the better you&#39;ll get at getting good at new things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#39;s my DIY Home Practice Challenge for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drill down into your practice until you get to a small chunk you can practice in 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick the easiest time of day to devote to your practice -- what&#39;s the perfect scenario for practicing this skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a recurring reminder in your calendar -- pick the medium that will be most accessible to get the reminder at the right time, i.e. on your desktop to interrupt your work, via email, or even text message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each day when you get the reminder, do your 5 minute practice, and then maybe take a minute or two to reflect on the success of what you just did or refine the scenario if necessary&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You will fail to build up this practice habit if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pick too big a skill to work on, e.g. I want to become a ballerina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are vague about when you are going to do it, e.g. I will practice it daily&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&#39;t get the reminder at the right time, e.g. I&#39;ll practice at noon each day, but my reminder comes in at 6pm&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I know those failures might sound obvious, and you should pick something pretty simple and obvious to begin with, but what I hope is that once you see the power in this simple approach, you&#39;ll start to tackle more complex and exciting skill building and begin to reflect on a lot of different experiences, in business, at work, in personal relationships, with the same desire to make incremental progress as you do with a hobby or healthy habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m always curious to hear how this goes for people, so send me an email or drop a comment below once you get set up and start hitting your daily targets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Better Practice Tools</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 09:20:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m running a little experiment right now at Brookline Tai Chi to see if we can help our students develop better home practice habits. Specifically, I&#39;m experimenting with self-reporting and automated reminders to spark daily practice sessions outside of class.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1438&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when I talk to other people in our international tai chi community, I realize what a powerful practice aid Brookline Tai Chi already is. What I mean is, the bricks-and-mortar experience of coming to the school and being around other people removes so many barriers people have to doing tai chi. It sounds too obvious to mention, but that is exactly why participating at the school is such a powerful way to build a practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this project, though, I&#39;m experimenting with email reminders and surveys to get an initial feel for what people do outside of class. I want to see if I can help them trigger more practice sessions during the week. From the initial self-reporting, it also appears that there are many daily practicers already, so I also want to see if there is a systematic way to help them shape their practice and get more out of it. Hopefully, this is the beginning of a longer conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not going to explain the experiment in detail just yet, because I want people to go through it without too much bias, but I&#39;ll share the results here once we know what we&#39;ve found. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pros and Cons of Automation</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 09:32:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Pro: My Car Broke Down and I Was Actually Happy about It&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I guess I need to explain that a little more. I wasn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; happy that it broke down. I was on the way to Maine to teach the &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/&#34;&gt;tai chi group in Farmington&lt;/a&gt;, so that sucked. And it was the clutch the completely died, so I knew it was going to be a few dollars to repair. But that was actually part of the silver lining. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-661&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;See, a couple of years ago, I read about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/tip-6-use-gas-prices-to-become-your-own-hedge-fund/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ramit Sethi&#39;s strategy for hedging fuel costs&lt;/a&gt;. The theory goes, if you are paying for something that goes up and down over the course of a year, you should find a way to even out the costs. This makes sense from a paycheck point of view, right? You take home the same amount of money each week, so you&#39;ll be in more predictable shape if your expenses work the same way. I adapted that strategy to create a car savings account. Looking back we realized we spent roughly the same amount of money on car-related expenses year to year, but they almost always came in spikes when something went wrong. To smooth out the spikes, I took a monthly average of those annual expenses and started putting it away automatically into a savings account each month. Now, when something breaks down, the money is already sitting there and I don&#39;t have to sweat a disruptive spike in our monthly expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dog has his own account too, for &#34;random&#34; vet visits that actually happen on a pretty predictable basis. And I guess that&#39;s the bigger lesson here. Looking back year over year, you start to see some clear patterns for stuff like this, even though the clutch dying or the dog eating something awful seems like a random occurrence. So, if you automate savings around these &#34;random predictable&#34; expenses, you save yourself a huge headache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Con: I Want Automation Now&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I get the &#34;automation itch&#34; whenever I&#39;m starting a new project. The &#34;automation itch&#34; is the desire to put a system in place, which is ultimately a good thing, but it usually strikes prematurely. Getting the itch can be a major trap and I&#39;ve slowly learned to recognize that it usually takes more time to set up an automated system early in a project than it takes to execute something manually. The best advice I&#39;ve ever gotten here is &#34;do it manually until you don&#39;t have enough hours in the day.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went through this at Brookline Tai Chi with an online registration system for classes. In summer 2009, we added online registration and probably 1/3 of current students adopted it right away. What was striking was that close to 80% of new students took to the system. Those statistics are interesting, but probably more appropriate for a post about changing systems in a business....another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flash forward to last week. This session, we got back to back cases of students who couldn&#39;t register online because of their unique situations. That means we need to rebuild the system to fit their situation, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wrong. That was two cases out of how many? Let&#39;s say 200. 1% of registrations. Do you think we have time to do 1% by hand? Especially if you consider that doing 1% of registrations this way takes 10 minutes of admin time, compared to several hours of developer time to make the change, it&#39;s a no-brainer. Of course, there&#39;s one other important factor: systems changes always have to put the user experience front and center. &lt;strong&gt;It&#39;s never a good idea to argue to your customer that they should interact with your business a certain way because it&#39;s easier for some back-end reason&lt;/strong&gt;. In this case though, to the students involved it looked like we were making a special exception for them, which they appreciated. So it worked out all around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a year ago I would have panicked a little more about these two cases. Or I would have thought about how to tinker with the system first. This time though, my first thought was &#34;2 out of how many?&#34; and my second thought was how to create the best manual solution. Beware the automation itch!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with the Old....Business Model</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 16:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Exit&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2245/2089485151_17f142a726_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s the end of the year and it&#39;s time to get out of old habits and mindsets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here&#39;s my prediction for the best business model for independent fitness and wellness pros, for the next DECADE. Yeah, I think it&#39;s going to take a few years to unfold, but the groundwork has been laid:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-514&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more brick-and-mortar businesses&lt;/strong&gt;. Trust me, I know what it&#39;s like to cut a $10,000 rent check each month. That&#39;s over with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more separation between in-person and on-line.&lt;/strong&gt; I read an article the other day that referred to &#39;90&#39;s style &#34;clicks-and-mortar&#34; business, e.g. Walmart.com for Walmart. You&#39;ve got to move past your website as a calling card for your services, even if you &#34;have really good content&#34;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more big barriers to scaling up your business.&lt;/strong&gt; This is great news. It&#39;s so easy to manage all the clients in your universe in a systematic way, through crm, email marketing, and interactive training apps like Trainerfly (ahem!), that the little guy or independent gal, can make it all by themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more one-size fits all products.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the same kind of dinosaur as a physical location. You might have some good reasons to put out video products (like standardizing a curriculum, for example), but you better have a way to tailor it to your clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more professional athlete fantasy.&lt;/strong&gt; You don&#39;t have to go pro or get sponsored or anything like that to make a decent living.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Welcome to the professional educator reality.&amp;Acirc;  I believe that the movement educator who is committed to honing a craft can make a real living. We all work really, really hard in our practice and now it&#39;s going to be possible to build a business around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at any public health statistics. Do you see a lack of movement in our society? Are we aging? Unhealthy? Totally divorced from the inherent human joys of movement? Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So those of us out there carrying the flag for better life through movement need to speak up. But we need to adapt too. We need to meet people where they are at, offer them chunks of wellness they can digest, and slowly change the conversation. And while we&#39;re at it, we need to make a living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is within reach in the next year or five years or ten years. You just need to start today with a little mental shift. Step into 2011 with some fresh perspective. You will be well rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exit photo courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/heathbrandon/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;heathbrandon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become an Enterprise of One </title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 09:04:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over at TechCrunch, Stephen Martin lays out his thesis about an interesting turning point for entrepreneurs in this economic climate. I could quote the piece at length, but I think this part is especially important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;These business mavericks live by a new dynamic of success &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; unique  individual strengths, expertise and credibility &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; fueled by today&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s  cultural and technological changes. In this new dimension of business  lies the secret to success in our transformed world of commerce. Armed  with a new viewpoint, and the tools to make a difference, these  entrepreneurs run their businesses based on the central principle that  once all of the barriers to entry, transaction costs and other hurdles  are stripped away by technology and cultural changes, an individual&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s  strengths and weaknesses are primarily what determine his or her  success.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve been trying to put my finger on something like this for a while and I think he says it really well. It&#39;s cheaper than ever to start a business and run a business because of all the technology small business owners can use to leverage their time.&amp;Acirc;  It&#39;s easier to communicate with lots and lots of people and instead of being buried in the back office, to quote Stephen again, &#34;the opportunities provided by the transformation to an online business  landscape...have left individual strengths, passions and  expertise as the only distinguishing factors remaining in an  individual&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s or business&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; success. Who you are as a person, and your  expertise and passions, are more important than ever. In fact, they  drive your own personal enterprise.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full article &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/12/27/entrepreneurs-great-reset/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning the Wheel</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2010 08:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Claude Hopkins, in &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Scientific Advertising&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Rapid stream ran by the writer&#39;s boyhood home. The stream turned a wooden wheel and the wheel ran a mill. Under that primitive method, all but a fraction of the streams&#39; potentiality went to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then someone applied scientific methods to that stream -- put in a turbine and dynamos. Now, with no more water, no more power, it runs a large manufacturing plant.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-470 alignleft&#34; title=&#34;falls&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/12/4121005703_2898edb080_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt; I love the image of harnessing more power from natural resources through better systems. Obviously, we&#39;re still taking about making a small business really churn, not powering a city from a hydro-electric plant, but the lesson is clear. If you&#39;re not using good systems in your small business, you&#39;re wasting potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&#39;d like to have it both ways, because the other part of the image that is so striking to me is the miller with the old wooden wheel. Every movement education professional that I know is really a craftsperson at heart. I just know there&#39;s a balance, though, between your craft and your business supporting a lifestyle you&#39;d like to live. That&#39;s what we&#39;re striving to find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/d-kav/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DaveKav&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Systems? No Raise for You This Year!</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/10/no-systems-no-raise-for-you-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 09:50:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/10/no-systems-no-raise-for-you-this-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You probably don&#39;t realize it, but there is a good chance you are letting a lot of extra money in your business slip right out of your hands. In fact, if you don&#39;t have good systems in place, I can almost guarantee it. In this post I&#39;ll pull  back the curtain and show you some of the systems I use to keep things running tighter. Specifically, I&#39;m going to tell you about an end of year/new year&#39;s marketing  campaign, targeting my private clients from 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But first, think about this problem in a system-less business.&amp;Acirc;  Coming up on the end of the year, I would think,  &#34;Shit, I better start training some more people next year...where can I  turn to find new clients? Should I advertise? Should I call some old clients? Do you think my current clients will pay me twice as much??? Oh my god, what am I going  to do!!!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so maybe you don&#39;t spiral out of control right  away, but if you have good tracking and good systems going all  along, it&#39;s so much easier. For an independent  movement educator to have simple systems in place (that are really cheap and not that hard to implement), it&#39;s like finding money between the cushions of your couch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sat down earlier this week and &#34;looked through the cushions&#34; in my business.&amp;Acirc;  My simple end-of-year audit turned up 5 different  strategies for picking up money around the edges of my&lt;em&gt; existing&lt;/em&gt; business -- no crazy new ventures either. You know what I forecast I could get from a little extra  effort? &lt;strong&gt;$10,000 in the coming year.&lt;/strong&gt; Who wouldn&#39;t give themselves a  $10,000 raise with found money? But you know what? You can only do it  with the right systems in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Putting Systems to Work&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are three systems that I use on a regular basis, that make launching a follow-up marketing campaign a piece of cake: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.students.dankleiman.com/login/index.php&#34;&gt;Online Training Notes for Each Client&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://highrisehq.com/&#34;&gt;Contact Management Database&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mailchimp.com/&#34;&gt;Email Marketing Software&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a part of live training, I always give my clients access to an online resources to supplement their training. I&#39;ll share notes about complicated exercises or a technique video. In this case, I&#39;m going to leverage the online resources to remind them about the training we did earlier in the year. Even if they haven&#39;t checked the resources in a while, they still have access to the material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 1: EXPORT 2010 CLIENT LIST FROM TRAINING DATABASE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I use Highrise for keeping track of all the people in my business universe. It&#39;s super easy to navigate -- both inside the application and in conjunction with other programs. Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://highrisehq.com/extras&#34;&gt;all the different applications&lt;/a&gt; that integrate with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 2: UPLOAD CONTACTS AND TAG THEM TO YOUR CAMPAIGN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My exported list from the training software is identified inside Highrise with a &#34;tag&#34; specific to this campaign. Every contact can have many tags. You get a picture of the different relationships with each client when you look at the tags they collect over time. The real beauty of the tag, though, comes when I use an integrated email marketing application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STEP 3: PULL CAMPAIGN TAG FROM HIGHRISE AND CREATE EMAIL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is the smoothest part by far. No need to download a list from one program and upload it to a new program, worrying about formatting. The email application and contact management application talk to each other through an API (the programs share how they each map data, so the information can flow back and forth). From inside the email application, I can select Highrise contacts, filtered by tag, and create a new mailing list just for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I&#39;ve got my list, crafting an email, or several (haven&#39;t decided yet) is easy in MailChimp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And there you have it, a quick and nerdy explanation of how to use your business systems to create better marketing and pick up the spare change lying around your business!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>