<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>zhong-ding on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/zhong-ding/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in zhong-ding on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/zhong-ding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>New Course: Introduction to Rooting and Stability</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 07:36:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you listed to the recent Qigong Radio episode on &lt;a title=&#34;The Essential Elements of Tai Chi Balance Training&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/18/the-essential-elements-of-tai-chi-balance-training/&#34;&gt;Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Balance&lt;/a&gt;, you probably want more insight into how to put Tai Chi balance training to work in your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4790&#34; alt=&#34;MiniCover&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/08/MiniCover-300x231.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;231&#34; /&gt;Now you can start Tai Chi balance training with our new eBook&lt;/strong&gt;, &#34;An Introduction to Rooting and Stability,&#34; where you will take the Tai Chi Way to re-gaining, one of life&#39;s simplest yet most essential treasures--&lt;em&gt;the gift of balance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Chi Balance Exercises in this course will produce a noticeable improvement in your sense of being grounded, or connected to the earth, centrally stabilized around a vertical axis, and able to change visual orientation while remaining balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you practice these exercises, you will begin to feel and understand the essential Tai Chi concepts of Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Dragon Body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exercises are drawn from the more than 45 separate exercises contained in the complete Tai Chi Way to Better Balance program, which includes both an ebook and DVDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ez-boxtitle-black&#34;&gt;Course Details&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost:&lt;/strong&gt; $14.99&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Taught By:&lt;/strong&gt; Don Ethan Miller, presented by Dan Kleiman&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How to Register:&lt;/strong&gt; Click &#34;Add to Cart&#34; and sign up below&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How to Access Course Materials:&lt;/strong&gt; You will receive instant access to a PDF download.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;ez-boxtitle-black&#34;&gt;Course Registration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.e-junkie.com/ecom/gb.php?c=cart&amp;i=1284998&amp;cl=253146&amp;ejc=2&#34; target=&#34;ej_ejc&#34; class=&#34;ec_ejc_thkbx&#34; onClick=&#34;javascript:return EJEJC_lc(this);&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-4830 alignnone&#34; alt=&#34;addtocart&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/08/addtocart-300x108.png&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;108&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Tai Chi Rooting eBook: $14.99&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Instant PDF Download&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master Wang Hao Da on Zhong Ding or Central Equilibrium</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/31/master-wang-hao-da-on-zhong-ding-or-central-equilibrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 06:57:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/31/master-wang-hao-da-on-zhong-ding-or-central-equilibrium/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In issue 48 of Qi Magazine, there is an article about Wu Style Tai Chi Master Wang Hao Da. The article describes Master Wang&#39;s early training and his desire to interact with as many different people as possible to refine his art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The description of Zhong Ding, or Central Equilibrium, drawn from the article, explains much of what organized Master Wang&#39;s teaching and personal practice, as described to me by one of my teachers, &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi Instructor Robert Tangora&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: Arial; font-size: small;&#34;&gt;Correct central equilibrium {Zhong Ding} is the basis for everything else in Taijiquan. One must focus with their complete intention {Yi} to differentiate that which is external and separate from one&#39;s centre. The centre is the key; it must remain straight and hidden, concentrated, deep inside the body constantly changing, spiraling into the earth for the most part. One must gather all the Qi {energy} to your centre. It is this structure that is the basis for internal power {Nei Jing} or Zhong Ding Jing, and essential for good health and longevity. The Dantien {lower abdomen} is alive! Not only does the Dantien push down inside the open hips but also it turns, spirals, bounces, and shoots; inside the structure is always full, always condensed. When you play the Taiji form you are performing the interaction of your Zhong Ding and Dantien. This hidden internal play moves the outside, not necessarily the entire body like a single lump of wood, rather by gathering everything to your centre, your outside body follows the direction of this internal command. It is because your inside works so intensively that you receive the health benefit of Taiji. If one only works externally and has strong skin and muscles but weak organs, vessels, and bones, then the outside may thrive while internally you are dying.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can read the full article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.susanamatthews.com/GeorgeXu/Wang%20Hao%20Da%20Article.htm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you understand the importance Master Wang placed on Zhong Ding, you can begin to understand the nature of his unique-looking form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/9QqUGNjMuZw?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sharp bursts sprinkled throughout the form are caused by the sudden release of energy from his Zhong Ding. The rest of the time he is actively gathering into the Zhong Ding, focusing his mind there and letting all the physical movement feed the sense of gathering and storing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked on &lt;a title=&#34;Exercises from The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/09/exercises-from-the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands/&#34;&gt;a basic version of this exercise&lt;/a&gt; in preparation for Tai Chi Cloud Hands.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>