<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>stress on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/stress/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in stress on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/stress/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi and Embodiment for Anxiety and Depression</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/04/01/tai-chi-and-embodiment-for-anxiety-and-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 18:11:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/04/01/tai-chi-and-embodiment-for-anxiety-and-depression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the pleasure of recording a conversation with my friend and Tai Chi colleague Dorothy Fitzer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing on her background in movement, energy arts, and psychotherapy, Dorothy has put together a very interesting group of practitioners from several different modalities to address the question of &lt;strong&gt;how embodiment practices can lead to nourishing, healing, and even transformative experiences.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/reYPtvRbeE0?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was thrilled to make the case that this is at the core of so much of what we do in Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dorothy and I discussed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tai Chi&#39;s techniques for &lt;a title=&#34;How To Calm Your Mind Through Movement&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/&#34;&gt;synchronizing the movement of the mind and the body&lt;/a&gt; - and the grounding effect this has on the mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How you learn to recognize &#34;doing&#34; as another layer of tension when you practice any form of &lt;a title=&#34;Qigong and Meditative State&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/qigong-and-meditative-state/&#34;&gt;Taoist Qigong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different Tai Chi/qigong techniques for getting the mind to quiet down and experience stillness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Yin and Yang of Depression and Anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How &lt;a title=&#34;Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi&#39;s interactive practices&lt;/a&gt; teach you to resolve interpersonal conflicts without fear and bask in the spontaneity that comes from not going into fear-based reactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And a few more things...&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can listen in on our conversation on Tuesday, April 8, but Dorothy will be sharing all of the conversations, some live and some pre-recorded, over the next two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To find out about all the other speakers and get alerts for each event, &lt;a href=&#34;http://theembodiedsoulcentertrainingseries1.com/&#34;&gt;visit The Embodied Soul Center&#39;s website&lt;/a&gt;. The sign-up box is right at the top.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice, Stress, and Building Outward Connections</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 11:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&#34;At some point, don&#39;t we have to ask ourselves, &#34;Aren&#39;t I healthy enough?&#34;  Don&#39;t I need to work on &#34;waking up&#34;, on manifesting kindness and patience, and being other oriented?&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s from a conversation we&#39;ve been having in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/&#34;&gt;Inner Form discussion&lt;/a&gt; group and it got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be learning to cultivate your chi to heal old injuries or for the inner experience of meditative exploration, but at some point, shouldn&#39;t your practice extend into the world around you, to the people in your life, and your work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&#39;m often in favor of letting these connections emerge naturally, but the comment above and this TED talk on stress are pushing me to make &#34;practicing in the world&#34; a little more explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making Stress Your Friend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Stanford health psychologist Kelly McGonigal gives a great talk on transforming your relationship to stress. And it could save your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the video description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stress. It makes your heart pound, your breathing quicken and your forehead sweat. But while stress has been made into a public health enemy, new research suggests that stress may only be bad for you if you believe that to be the case.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RcGyVTAoXEU?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practicing in the World&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From this perspective, &lt;strong&gt;cultivating your internal energy is not about getting some horrible disease out of your system.&lt;/strong&gt; It&#39;s a way to process, digest, and to grow from what&#39;s useful while shedding what&#39;s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice homework this week: you know what it&#39;s like to find a special, quiet place to practice to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;build your chi&lt;/a&gt;, but what about your next interaction with another person as the best place to practice? Can you pause, hold the mind the same way when you do in your practice and let the encounter unfold the same way the qigong mind allows chi to resolve itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might draw some inspiration from &lt;a title=&#34;Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/&#34;&gt;Push Hands&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a title=&#34;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/24/transforming-conflict-with-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi-style conflict resolution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>