<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>breathing on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/breathing/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in breathing on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/breathing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathing Techniques: Am I Doing it Right?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/06/breathing-techniques-am-i-doing-it-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 11:52:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/06/breathing-techniques-am-i-doing-it-right/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently received this breathing question and I thought it was worth sharing with everyone here as a post. (Don&#39;t forget, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/ask-me-anything/&#34;&gt;you can send me your practice questions&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m really confused! I took a Yang Style Tai Chi course and at the end of the class we would do Qigong. He said &#34;We will do diaphragmatic breathing. As you breath in draw the navel into the spine, as you exhale release and let the belly relax but don&#39;t collapse.&#34; What kind of breathing is this and what is the correct breathing for my qigong practice? Is this wrong?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is a great question. There are many, many different breathing methods, so it can be really hard to discern what any one practice is doing and how it fits in a larger practice context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, most of these techniques break down into big categories that are easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most breathing practices are designed to hit one or more of these areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effecient Gas Exchange&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internal Massage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energetic Activation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meditation/Working with the Mind&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Effecient Gas Exchange&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you breath well, in terms of moving gases in and out of the lungs, you can improve everything from your mood to your physical performance and focus, presence, and concetration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the most basic level, all breathing practices should make you a better breather in terms of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the correct muscles (diaphragm, intercostals)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reducing strain/effort in breathing at rest&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This &#34;Wall Exercise&#34; is one of my favorites for learning to feel the correct movement of the lungs/ribs during effecient breathing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oqsXcDA53YU&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal Massage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you hear &#34;diaphragmatic breathing,&#34; as in the initial question, at least in a Tai Chi/qigong context, it will often go beyond the simple effeciency model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to use the location of the diaphragm -- above the middle internal organs -- and its movement -- pumping up and down -- to actually massage the internal organs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you inhale, it creates a pressurization in the abdominal cavity. On the exhale, this pressure is released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternating compression and release creates massage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, the instructions are designed &lt;em&gt;to increase the massaging effect&lt;/em&gt;: &#34;As you breath in draw the navel into the spine, as you exhale release and let the belly relax but don&#39;t collapse.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a variation of a type of breathing practice called &#34;Reverse Breathing.&#34; When you do this kind of work, increasing internal pressures deliberately, you want to watch for your face turning red, the neck feeling tight, or a sense in your head of too much pressure. All of these are signs you need to back off and return to Natural Breathing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energetic Activation and Working with the Mind&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we extend this process of using the breath to enliven the inside of the body, eventually we will cross over from physical activation to energetic activation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, breathing techniques can be a part of &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/&#34;&gt;awakening the lower tantien&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, you will use the sense of movement from the breathing mechanisms (diaphragm pumping up and down) and pressure changes in the abdominal cavity to wake up more and more feeling sensation until you fill a still center-point deep in the pit of the abdomen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I always recommend that you dial back the deliberate action of conscious breathing, letting it go quiet instead. This is how you open up the space to working more directly with your energy and the mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you can start to feel the lower tantien, you may notice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tantien emerging as your clear center of gravity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pulsing in sync with the rhythm of the breath.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your mind shifting to the tantien, or as is sometimes said, &#34;you start to see from the lower tantien.&#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sense of gathering energy into the lower tantien, especially if you have a period of quiet, non-intention at the end of your practice.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hopefully, these big categories will help you navigate the different types of breathing practices that you will encounter. No matter how you practice, it&#39;s always a good idea to finish with quiet, natural breathing so that you smooth out your nervous system. This will stay with you 24 hours a day if you set up a nice easy rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Itch to Move Your Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 08:48:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We tend to think about our energy level like the money we have in the bank. You wake up in the morning, look in your energetic wallet and say, &#34;I&#39;ve got a lot of energy today&#34; or &#34;Man, I need 7 cups of coffee.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, to put it another way, thanks to this New Yorker cartoon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.condenaststore.com/-sp/If-we-re-all-just-energy-then-why-don-t-I-have-any-New-Yorker-Cartoon-Prints_i8481061_.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter  wp-image-4975&#34; alt=&#34;If we&#39;re all just energy, then why don&#39;t I have any?&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/12/Screen-Shot-2013-12-20-at-8.14.34-AM.png&#34; width=&#34;577&#34; height=&#34;445&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In qigong, we think about &#34;having energy&#34; a little bit differently. Often, it&#39;s not just how much or how little, but &lt;strong&gt;how well is your energy circulating?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good energetic circulation gives you a feeling of &#34;more,&#34; while stagnant or stuck energy feels draining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is such a different concept than most of us have, I&#39;ve often wondered about where these two ideas came from and where these two ways of seeing the world split. In this post, I&#39;m not going to give you a deeply researched exploration of the origins of the Taoist understanding of the world. I&#39;ll let &lt;a title=&#34;Straight Lines, Circles, and Spheres&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/11/straight-lines-circles-and-spheres/&#34;&gt;our practices&lt;/a&gt; stand as of evidence of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I want to share with you some of the writings of 20th century Western philosopher Hans Jonas. He wrote about the phenomenology of life and in his descriptions of biological processes, we get a really interesting connection to what many qigong practitioners come to realize: &lt;strong&gt;we have a fundamental need to circulate chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The Phenomenon of Life&lt;/span&gt;, Jonas is trying to reconcile the simplest forms of life with higher thought and our human experience of the mind. He tries to place them on a continuum and asks which one is for the sake of the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whatever the answer, one aspect of the ascending scale is that in its stages the &#34;mirroring&#34; of the world becomes ever more distinct and self-rewarding, beginning with the most obscure sensation somewhere on the lowest rungs of animality, even with the most elementary stimulation of organic irritability as such, in which somehow already otherness, world, and object are germinally &#34;experienced,&#34; that is, made subjective, and responded to (p.3).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My personal theory on the origins of qigong is that those early Taoists went exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They sat or stood in postures and listened, both inside themselves and to the natural world. &lt;strong&gt;As they got quieter and more perceptive, the heard the echoes of Jonas&#39; &#34;most obscure sensation.&#34;&lt;/strong&gt; The irritability that Jonas describes set them up against the world outside and framed their inner worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That irritability is the same itch you feel when you know you need to get your chi moving, circulating through you and passing back and forth between you, the natural world around you and the other people you interact with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things are flowing, in and out, up and down, towards and away, we feel good: &lt;strong&gt;connected to something outside ourselves but at the same time internally unified and integrated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like eating, breathing, and sleeping, circulating energy is a natural cycle that we can refine, enhance, and enjoy, but we need to pay attention to it on an ongoing, continuous basis to be healthy and feel whole.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing Qigong Breathing Exercises -- Mp3</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 08:38:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4412&#34; alt=&#34;Better Breathing&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/11/032-300x225.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest question people ask me about standing qigong, especially when they hear about &lt;a title=&#34;Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/&#34;&gt;the 2-hour project&lt;/a&gt;, is &#34;what do you do, just stand there?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is actually a really delicate balance between &#34;doing&#34; and &#34;feeling&#34; when you stand. You learn lots of different techniques, like breathing, sinking, dissolving, and pulsing, but how you apply them internally when you are holding a static posture is a tricky topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you rev your engine too much -- activating &lt;a title=&#34;My Favorite Breathing Hack&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/30/my-favorite-breathing-hack/&#34;&gt;strong diaphragmatic breathing&lt;/a&gt; the entire time, for example -- then you miss the potential stillness in the posture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you zone out, and don&#39;t connect to internal sensations, you&#39;ll miss the potential for integration and you won&#39;t build any chi or walk away with the sense of organization that your standing qigong can provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you strike the balance between &#34;do&#34; and &#34;feel&#34; in your standing qigong practice? I&#39;ve put together two breathing exercise mp3 for you to listen to while you practice standing qigong to help you find that balance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/[Standing]%20Breathing%20to%20Activate%20the%20Back.mp3&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong -- Breathing to Activate the Back&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/[Standing]%20Breathing%20to%20Activate%20the%20Feet.mp3&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong -- Breathing to Activate the Feet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These are short, easy practice sessions that focus in on one skill each: you will learn how to use the breath as a guide for your awareness, activating sensation, without overriding the potential for stillness. As you practice, you will be able to apply this same skill to longer and longer standing qigong practice sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One more thing:&lt;/strong&gt; if you enjoy these workouts and find them useful, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr?cmd=_s-xclick&amp;amp;hosted_button_id=QQC5GSTJLQRUW&#34;&gt;considering making a small contribution here&lt;/a&gt;. Think of it as a drop-in class fee. If I know that a lot of people are finding these helpful as practice aides, I will create more of them in the future. Thanks for your feedback and support!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-4629&#34; alt=&#34;help-browser&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/05/help-browser-150x150.png&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend last night about &lt;a title=&#34;Guide to Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; and different &lt;a title=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;meditation traditions&lt;/a&gt; that we had both tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many different reasons, on any given day, that we sought out the practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To clear our heads of racing thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To more deeply relax the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explore layers of the mind and emotions that aren&#39;t so obvious during our normal busy days.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It seems like we had really similar reasons to practice, but I was left wondering if it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; similar when we practice. What are the sensations that tell you you&#39;re on the right track? It seems like we want to end up in the same place, but are we taking the same road to get there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p4r3&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p4r3&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p4r3;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p4r3&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;554&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { r7p4r3 = new WufooForm();r7p4r3.initialize(options);r7p4r3.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Difference Between Breathing in Yoga and Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/21/the-difference-between-breathing-in-yoga-and-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/21/the-difference-between-breathing-in-yoga-and-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As Nate and I were discussing specific breathing challenges in qigong and Tai Chi, he started to explain the way he had learned to work with breathing and movement in his yoga training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s fascinating to compare strategies for working with the mind-body connection across different systems, and while this is by no means a definitive exploration of similarities and differences, I think you&#39;ll see that there are two distinct approaches.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3647&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/4LqqayxyCB4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/4LqqayxyCB4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this difference make sense to you? How does it compare to other breathing/meditation/mindfulness practices you&#39;ve explored? Leave a comment and let us know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why You Should Not Worry About Breathing in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/19/why-you-should-not-worry-about-breathing-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/19/why-you-should-not-worry-about-breathing-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this Inner Form office hours clip, Nate asked me about a specific issue on breathing in the Marriage of Heaven and Earth qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your main focus is Tai Chi, then I would recommend that you pretty much ignore breathing as you practice, but you should focus on opening up the body enough to facilitate deep, even, smooth breathing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following clips, we look at how opening up the body will lead to deeper breathing, what stages you will go through in this process, and finally, I show him a specific technique for keeping the deep internal connections loose as he does the Marriage of Heaven and Earth qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/eUtBbDZbjTw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/eUtBbDZbjTw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3637&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stages of Loosening the Body Up to Access Deeper Breathing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you work on the body from the outside-in, you will naturally go through several stages of opening the body. First, this will feel like a coordination project, but if you follow the rules laid out in the Tai Chi classics, you are actually creating more internal space, that will make breathing easier, deeper, and more nourishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_318&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=26029149&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/f2465210/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=26029149&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_318&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/f2465210/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=26029149&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=26029149&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Arm Lift Problem in Heaven and Earth&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Heaven and Earth is a great place to train the connection between the arms and the body when you&#39;re in any overhead lifting positions. You&#39;ll see these in Tai Chi to some degree, but definitely in Ba Gua, in the Energy Gates 3rd Swing, and in some standing postures designed to open the upper body. You can apply this principle to any of those practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_319&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=56502783&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/3e974ea1/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=56502783&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_319&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/3e974ea1/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=56502783&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=56502783&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Favorite Breathing Hack</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/30/my-favorite-breathing-hack/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2012 21:02:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/30/my-favorite-breathing-hack/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Wall Test is one of my favorite &#34;breathing hacks&#34; -- a simple, fast exercise you can do to get feedback on how well you are breathing. Check out this instruction in this video and try it for yourself:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3393&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/oqsXcDA53YU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/oqsXcDA53YU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This breathing exercise is taken from a live breathing class I taught last week. In the class, we looked at several different facets of training your breathing, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difference between nerves, fluids, and chi when you practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to play with internal pressures to get the biggest health benefit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The quality of all-day energy you get from massaging your internal organs (which is really different from the typical &#34;buzz&#34; you think of from stimulants like caffeine).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The class included theory, practical guidance, and follow-along exercises. If you didn&#39;t have the chance to attend live, you can still get the webinar replay, which is over an hour long. &lt;a title=&#34;To Breathe or Not To Breathe &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; January 29 Webinar&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/16/breathing-webinar-january-29/&#34;&gt;Sign up here for instant access&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve already registered for the class or are a member of the Inner Form section, &lt;a title=&#34;To Breathe or Not To Breathe&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/to-breathe-or-not-to-breathe/&#34;&gt;get access here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To Breathe or Not To Breathe -- January 29 Webinar</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/16/breathing-webinar-january-29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2012 09:13:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/16/breathing-webinar-january-29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1579&#34; title=&#34;Better Breathing&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/shutterstock_676632-e1309386517458-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;180&#34; height=&#34;135&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Join me for &#34;To Breathe or Not To Breathe&#34;, a webinar where we will explore the challenges and big payoffs that come from doing your breathing practice correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps more than any other technique, cultivating a breathing practice presents an interesting training paradox: &lt;strong&gt;how do you change something your body does automatically 20,000 times a day, that is so intertwined with your mind, emotions, and internal energy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3281&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this webinar, I will take you through the major issues around developing your breathing practice, whether your goal is to smooth out your breath (and thereby your nerves), increase your breathing capacity to have more energy, or use breathing as a gateway practice to relaxation and meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we will address:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I have a breathing problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to avoid the weakness of willpower.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The smart way to change your breathing mechanics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to achieve greater sensitivity through breathing.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original live class took place on Sunday, January 29, but you can still get access to the webinar replay here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;cmd&#34; value=&#34;_s-xclick&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;hosted_button_id&#34; value=&#34;LNVQCG266QTN4&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_buynowCC_LG.gif&#34; alt=&#34;PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/form&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34;&gt;&lt;/form&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost:&lt;/strong&gt; $9 (free for Inner Form members)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guided Practice Aides</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/guided-practice-aides/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 15:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/guided-practice-aides/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a round-up of guided practice aides I&#39;ve put together in various sections of the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else would help you with your current practice? Let me know &lt;a title=&#34;Submit a Practice Question&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/submit-a-practice-question/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3207&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To download the audio files below, right click and &#34;save as&#34;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Breathing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Use these basic principles as a guide for your breathing and standing practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_153&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=47617447&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/9d18c9bd/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=47617447&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_153&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/9d18c9bd/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=47617447&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=47617447&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Downloads:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Breathing_Practice_1.mp3&#34;&gt;20-Minute Guided Practice #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Expanded_Breathing_Practice.mp3&#34;&gt;20-Minute Guided Practice #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can progress through longer standing sessions with these guided practice mp3s or pick one on any given day that matches your practice goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Settling_In.mp3&#34;&gt;5-Minute Scan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Waking_Up_Feeling_Awareness.mp3&#34;&gt;10-Minute Softening Practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Sinking_Chi.mp3&#34;&gt;20-Minute Downward Flow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wu Tai Chi Short Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Let me help you pace yourself through 3 rounds of the short form with this video or the audio download below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_292&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=39309639&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/5cd5a24b/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=39309639&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_292&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/5cd5a24b/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=39309639&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=39309639&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Short_Form_Three_Times.m4a&#34;&gt;Short Form 3x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress Reduction Techniques That Work in 5 Minutes or Less</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you have cultivated a daily practice that takes you into deep relaxation, it&#39;s helpful to have a set of stress reduction techniques &#34;that work in 5 minutes or less.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can pull these out during the day when you have a few minutes of downtime. If you are busy and really stressed out, these relaxation techniques can prevent your stress level from going through the roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try them and let me know what you think.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2540&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5 Minute Body Scan&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a few minutes of trying to tune into your body, instead of being stuck in your head, can help reduce the weight of some of the stress you are feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-2355&#34; title=&#34;basic standing qigong posture&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture-141x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; width=&#34;141&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standing posture pictured, here, do a 5-minute downward body scan, starting at the top of the head and working your way down, feeling height-by-height until you reach your feet.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First, set your posture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;place your feet hip-width apart, so your joints are aligned &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll feel the weight balanced evenly in each foot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lengthen the back of your neck, so the chin drops slightly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax your shoulders, as if the arms were slipping off the rib cage, to the left and right, not slouched forward or pulled back&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Next, settle in:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your breathing go smooth, so the turn-over from inhale to exhale feels natural and not forced&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Begin to scan:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bring your feeling awareness up to the crown of your head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;once you feel like you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve gathered your awareness to a single point, let your mind spread out through the crown of the head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give in to gravity and let your mind drop down the body, height-by-height, feeling front, sides, and back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your mind rest lightly on any sensations you feel as you scan, checking in, without trying to do anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work downward until you can feel your feet settle into the floor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more guidance on practicing this technique, check out &lt;a title=&#34;Settling in with Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;this article on Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt; (with a free guided-practice mp3 download).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Metronome Mobility&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This exercise is great for coordination and control and it&#39;s just distracting enough to let your nervous system reset its stress level by the time you are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s use this Z Health shoulder circle as an example for the metronome exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you feel comfortable performing the basic shoulder circle as in the video above, you&#39;ll need to set a metronome to 60 beats per minute. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a baseline for one repetition at your &#34;normal&#34; speed. How many beats?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, perform a circle at half your normal speed, or 2x as many beats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat this process, slowing down each time until the movement gets too choppy to be a smooth circle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now repeat the process getting faster each time instead of slower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you keep the rest of the body &#34;quiet&#34; -- you don&#39;t get any points for flailing around!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating this process for hip circles, ankle circles, or even finger/wrist/hand circles will work too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of metronome mobility as a stress reduction technique is to draw your mind and away from the mental and emotional pressures that are causing stress in the first place. Moving your body at different speeds provides novelty for your nervous system, which helps achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tai Chi Short Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; /&gt;When you do 5 minutes of tai chi, you have to change how you are practicing. You need to shift out of your normal &#34;training&#34; mindset, where you focus on little details, or work a principle over and over again until it clicks. That kind of deep practice mindset is great for 30 minutes or an hour of practice or more, but it&#39;s not going to do the trick in 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 5 minute practice for stress reduction, you need to focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moving smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making large, circular shapes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feeling the space around you, in your etheric field, not deep inside your body&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point, about putting your mind into your etheric field, might sound a little strange. What you are trying to do is clear the energetic layer around your body. Think of it as where you interface with the world. If you can sweep everything clean here, then the stress doesn&#39;t have the chance to soak into your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Got More Stress Reduction Techniques?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The thing that all these techniques have in common is that they are designed to recharge your nervous system through physical and energetic circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you accomplish this same goal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share your stress reduction techniques in the comments below.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Circular Breathing Is Only the Beginning</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/24/why-circular-breathing-is-only-the-beginning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 08:56:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/24/why-circular-breathing-is-only-the-beginning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When people explain the connection between the mind and the body in tai chi, they often use the breath as a bridge between the two. In other words, you can unite the mind and the body through breathing practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is true, but it&#39;s only one technique. In fact, good tai chi includes several methods for making this link. Breathing is only the beginning. Here are a few other things you should be looking for: &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2148&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/LCjcsudkfvI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/LCjcsudkfvI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Breathing, Qigong, and Meditation Improve Quality of Life</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/20/how-breathing-qigong-and-meditation-improve-quality-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 08:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/20/how-breathing-qigong-and-meditation-improve-quality-of-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I asked my friend and fellow qigong practitioner Catherine Chenoweth to talk a little bit about her experience using qigong to manage a chronic health condition. Here&#39;s what she had to say:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1782&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/07/5349FC1E-3A30-461B-9D4C-EC402891879A0.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;margin: 5px;&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/07/5349FC1E-3A30-461B-9D4C-EC402891879A0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;160&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I was released from the hospital in 1996, it was after three months, and with a diagnosis of LAM (Lymphangioleiomyomatosis), a rare, progressive, untreatable and often fatal lung disease. I asked a friend who was well versed in alternative treatments what I should do for my health, and his response, immediate and emphatic, was &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;You need to do qigong!&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I did. What started as an effort to do something proactive for my health turned into a life long passion and became an irreplaceable part of my life. I think one of the smartest things I ever did was to take an entire week course of breathing with Bruce Frantzis. One thing that is very clear when one really starts to lose their ability to breathe is how much we take breathing for granted. It may even seem like a silly thing to spend money on &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; an entire week learning how to breathe! But it is a subject that has a surprising amount of depth, and you learn quickly that many people have very poor breathing habits. To learn to breathe with the entirety of your lungs, not just the lower half of the lung as opposed to the chest, but with the sides and back of the lung as well, is something that can increase overall efficiency, something that is a must for people with progressive lung disease who want to maintain the best quality of life that they can. Not only will proper technique and practice affect your breathing, but it will spill over into areas such as stress reduction, pain reduction, and overall well being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, a balance of breathing, meditation, and qigong has been the key to maximizing my quality of life with a lung disease. The slow, gentle movements of qigong give me a way to exercise when my body is unable to do any type of western exercise, for example when faced with chronic lung collapses or after a surgery. To progress in qigong means to go deeper into layers of your body, learning to become sensitive to and to manipulate soft tissue, fluids, joints and energy. To progress in certain other forms of exercise often means doing more physically demanding, more aerobic, bigger, faster movements &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; all aspects that can be impossible goals for someone who is sick or disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I applaud anyone who takes the first steps toward taking charge of their health. In an increasingly busy and distracted society, it can seem like the last thing on anyone&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s list is to be healthy and take care of their bodies. Whether you have an illness, disease, or injury, or whether you are healthy and wish to maintain your health into old age, find some time in your life to learn some of these ancient practices, and find some time in your day to practice them. A simple breathing or qigong practice will allow you to connect with your body again, and the rewards are well worth the effort. Being through what I have been through has given me a unique perspective and a deep appreciation of the limits and possibilities of the human body. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s the only vessel you have to get you through this life. Care for it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Day Better Breathing Challenge</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 10:17:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&#39;ve been talking a lot about two things, &lt;a title=&#34;Follow the 20-20-20 Rule for Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/21/follow-the-20-20-20-rule-for-better-breathing/&#34;&gt;improving your breathing&lt;/a&gt; to give you a &lt;a title=&#34;Disrupt the Stress Cycle with Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/26/disrupt-the-stress-cycle-with-better-breathing/&#34;&gt;major energy/relaxation boost&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a title=&#34;Building Better Practice Tools&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/&#34;&gt;developing tools&lt;/a&gt; that help you &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/?p=1494&#34;&gt;follow-through on your home practice&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve even created an online course with all the information you need to cultivate better breathing habits: &lt;a title=&#34;Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/courses/better-breathing/&#34;&gt;Better Breathing&lt;/a&gt;. The biggest lesson we learned as we talked to BTC students&amp;Acirc;  was that the best time to use reminders to trigger your practice was when you were invested in learning a new skill.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1510&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; When you&#39;re going through a period of sustained practice, integrating stuff you&#39;ve learned before, you need external tools less. However, when you shift back into learning mode and set a specific training goal, getting extra, regular motivation from an outside source can push you over the line from wanting to learn something to ingraining it as a habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to cultivate better breathing habits is a great example of skill building that benefits from extra stimulation. As I explain in the breathing course, there is a clear threshold with your breathing practice that you need to cross to make a lasting impact on your habits. In one sense, the secret to mastering better breathing habits is just putting in the time. The steps along the path to better breathing aren&#39;t always exciting or immediately gratifying, but crossing the breathing threshold puts you into a different world where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;each breath feels deep and nourishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your insides feel smooth and relaxed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you radiate a sense of well-being and easy-to-sustain energy throughout your day&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These are the kinds of things you only notice once you&#39;ve had them and lost them. The biggest challenge of cultivating these qualities is that you can&#39;t do it in one single act of will power. You need sustained, regular practice to take you over the threshold. The good news is that you can leverage external tools, instead of just will power, to carry you over the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s why I&#39;ve created the 30 Day Breathing Challenge. If you want to hit a new depth of practice in the next month, I will give you the tools to get there. For a limited time, I&#39;m giving away my online breathing course (normally $29), for free. All you have to do is sign-up for the 30-Day Challenge using the form below. I will send you daily practice reminders and weekly video instruction drawn from the course. In 30 days, you&#39;re going to see a major shift in your personal practice. Ready?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://eepurl.com/xORb&#34;&gt;Sign up for the 30 Day Challenge here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Things Modern Athletes Can Learn from the Tai Chi Classics</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/27/10-things-modern-athletes-can-learn-from-the-tai-chi-classics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 09:58:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/27/10-things-modern-athletes-can-learn-from-the-tai-chi-classics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By training the principles of body-alignment and movement as described in the Tai Chi Classics, you can move with much more grace, fluidity, and power. Instead of wasting energy holding excess tension, relaxation can lead the way to more powerful movement. Here&#39;s what Yang Cheng-fu said about it a hundred years ago (the following is adapted from YANG&#39;S TEN IMPORTANT POINTS by Yang  Cheng-fu (1883 &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; 1936) as researched by Lee N. Scheele and published on  http://www.scheele.org/lee/classics.html. Scheele&#39;s translation is first and my notes are in italics following):&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1581&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.) Head upright to let the shen [spirit of vitality] rise to the top of the head.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&#39;t use li [external strength], or the neck will be stiff and the ch&#39;i [vital life energy] and blood cannot flow through. It is necessary to have a natural and lively feeling. If the spirit cannot reach the headtop, it cannot raise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you&#39;re sitting at your computer right now, what do your head and neck feel like? The beginning of effortless posture is how you hold your head. As it collapses down and forward, you begin a stress-inducing cascade of neck and shoulder pain, poor breathing, and bad posture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.) Sink the chest and pluck up the back.&lt;/strong&gt; The chest is depressed naturally inward so that the ch&#39;i can sink to the tan-t&#39;ien [field of elixir]. Don&#39;t expand the chest: the ch&#39;i gets stuck there and the body becomes top-heavy. The heel will be too light and can be uprooted. Pluck up the back and the ch&#39;i sticks to the back; depress the chest and you can pluck up the back. Then you can discharge force through the spine. You will be a peerless boxer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here&#39;s another posture tip. Lengthen the spine. It&#39;s the opposite of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;fetal position&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; fight or flight response (again, think stress). When you keep the chest relaxed and sunk, you naturally begin to breathe deeply with the diaphragm, getting a more efficient breath and actually nourishing the internal organs, literally massaging them with internal pressure changes. This is all the opposite of what happens to breath and posture when you hyperventilate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 3.) Sung [Relax] the waist.&lt;/strong&gt; The waist is the commander of the whole body. If you can sung the waist, then the two legs will have power and the lower part will be firm and stable. Substantial and insubstantial change, and this is based on the turning of the waist. It is said &#34;the source of the postures lies in the waist. If you cannot get power, seek the defect in the legs and waist.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now we&#39;re getting into some more esoteric terminology, but as a tai chi teacher, I&#39;ve found that many of my students have frozen hips. Start there. If you can&#39;t distinguish the movement of the legs, pelvis, and trunk, then your source of power and movement is seriously diminished. You should be able to internally and externally rotate each leg independently of hip movement and roll the pelvis around without moving the spine or legs. Once you can move all these parts independently, you can learn to lead movements with hip drive and powerful rotation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 4.) Differentiate between insubstantial and substantial.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the first principle in T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan. If the weight of the whole body is resting on the right leg, then the right leg is substantial and the left leg is insubstantial, and vice versa. When you can separate substantial and insubstantial, you can turn lightly without using strength. If you cannot separate, the step is heavy and slow. The stance is not firm and can be easily thrown of balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ever see someone get caught &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;flat-footed&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; on the court? The ability to distinguish where your weight is by feel, and quickly shift your center of gravity left and right is critical for reaction speed and movement. In tai chi, you learn to make this distinction completely clearly in slow motion, and then you gradually increase the speed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 5.) Sink the shoulders and drop the elbows.&lt;/strong&gt; The shoulders will be completely relaxed and open. If you cannot relax and sink, the two shoulders will be raised up and tense. The ch&#39;i will follow them up and the whole body cannot get power. &#34;Drop the elbows&#34; means the elbows go down and relax. If the elbows raise, the shoulders are not able to sink and you cannot discharge people far. The discharge will then be close to the broken force of the external schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This principle has to do with power-generation in tai chi, and may not be completely adaptable to your sport, but I will point this out: whenever you are in motion and you feel your shoulders start to creep towards your ears, you&#39;re experiencing the beginning of that fight or flight response. By training the physical opposite, you are sending your body the message that relaxation in motion is possible, and you&#39;re getting better at maintaining it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 6.) Use the mind instead of force.&lt;/strong&gt; The T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan Classics say, &#34;all of this means use I [mind-intent] and not li.&#34; In practicing T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan the whole body relaxes. Don&#39;t let one ounce of force remain in the blood vessels, bones, and ligaments to tie yourself up. Then you can be agile and able to change. You will be able to turn freely and easily. Doubting this, how can you increase your power?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body has meridians like the ground has ditches and trenches. If not obstructed the water can flow. If the meridian is not closed, the ch&#39;i goes through. If the whole body has hard force and it fills up the meridians, the ch&#39;i and the blood stop and the turning is not smooth and agile. Just pull one hair and the whole body is off-balance. If you use I, and not li, then the I goes to a place in the body and the ch&#39;i follows it. The ch&#39;i and the blood circulate. If you do this every day and never stop, after a long time you will have nei chin [real internal strength]. The T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan Classics say, &#34;when you are extremely soft, you become extremely hard and strong.&#34; Someone who has extremely good T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan kung fu has arms like iron wrapped with cotton and the weight is very heavy. As for the external schools, when they use li, they reveal li. When they don&#39;t use li, they are too light and floating. There chin is external and locked together. The li of the external schools is easily led and moved, and not too be esteemed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When he refers to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;force&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;li&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; in this principle, you should read it as &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;extra&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;unnecessary tension&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. Too many people have a silly fantasy about tai chi relying on magical chi and no force as an excuse for not training hard. The way you get to effortless power in tai chi is by refining you movements, stripping them of unnecessary tension, layer by layer. You do tai chi in slow motion so that your mind can search every inch of your insides and find the extra tension that is holding back your movements.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.) Coordinate the upper and lower parts of the body.&lt;/strong&gt; The T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan Classics say &#34;the motion should be rooted in the feet, released through the legs, controlled by the waist and manifested through the fingers.&#34; Everything acts simultaneously. When the hand, waist and foot move together, the eyes follow. If one part doesn&#39;t follow, the whole body is disordered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This description of force generation, coming from the ground and going up through the body and out the fingers is almost word for word how Curt Schilling described throwing a perfect pitch. Again, think of the basic practices of tai chi, the slow motion form work, as awareness training that lets you pay attention to these connections in a way you wouldn&#39;t be able to always going fast. Take any movement from your sport and try it in slow motion. Can you find these links?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8.) Harmonize the internal and external.&lt;/strong&gt; In the practice of T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan the main thing is the shen. Therefore it is said &#34;the spirit is the commander and the body is subordinate.&#34; If you can raise the spirit, then the movements will naturally be agile. The postures are not beyond insubstantial and substantial, opening and closing. That which is called open means not only the hands and feet are open, but the mind is also open. That which is called closed means not only the hands and feet are closed, but the mind is also closed. When you can make the inside and outside become one, then it becomes complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You hear people describe moments of flow, when time slows down, or the ball or the net looks huge and making the shot was inevitable. These moments are perfect examples of the inside and the outside becoming one. When the mind opens up and the internal and external are harmonized, you access a different kind of awareness. Tai Chi actually includes a systematic training method for getting you into that state, again and again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9.) Move with continuity.&lt;/strong&gt; As to the external schools, their chin is the Latter Heaven brute chin. Therefore it is finite. There are connections and breaks. During the breaks the old force is exhausted and the new force has not yet been born. At these moments it is very easy for others to take advantage. T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan uses I and not li. From beginning to end it is continuous and not broken. It is circular and again resumes. It revolves and has no limits. The original Classics say it is &#34;like a great river rolling on unceasingly.&#34; and that the circulation of the chin is &#34;drawing silk from a cocoon &#34; They all talk about being connected together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Try this exercise: with your index finger, draw a box in front of you and keep going around, with sharp corners and edges. Try to pay attention to your breathing at the same time. Now compare that to what it feels like to make a circle with your finger. See how much easier it is to tune into your breathing doing circular movement? Feel how the stop and start of linear movement briefly &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;freezes&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; your nervous system as you change directions. It&#39;s this simple practice of circular movement, repeated on deeper and deeper levels, that is the key to relaxation in tai chi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.) Move with tranquility [Seek stillness in movement].&lt;/strong&gt; The external schools assume jumping about is good and they use all their energy. That is why after practice everyone pants. T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan uses stillness to control movement. Although one moves, there is also stillness. Therefore in practicing the form, slower is better. If it is slow, the inhalation and exhalation are long and deep and the ch&#39;i sinks to the tan-t&#39;ien. Naturally there is no injurious practice such as engorgement of the blood vessels. The learner should be careful to comprehend it. Then you will get the real meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Often, when people start learning tai chi, they think &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;ok, I&#39;m going to get this right&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;, as if doing the movement perfectly once was the end goal and they could stop there. That&#39;s the completely wrong way to think about it. In tai chi, you are setting up a state or a condition where all of the postural alignments, layers of relaxation, and continuity of movement can gel. Your goal is to experience that state, returning to it again and again, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;seeking stillness in movement&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. Daily practice, when you enter this state, becomes a major recharge and even when you are doing tai chi as a way to get better at something else, the nourishing, refreshing experience of doing the practice slowly becomes the goal itself. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disrupt the Stress Cycle with Better Breathing</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/26/disrupt-the-stress-cycle-with-better-breathing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2011 10:06:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/26/disrupt-the-stress-cycle-with-better-breathing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1473&#34; title=&#34;Diaphragmatic Breathing Exercise&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/05/High-Low-Breathing-Test-300x169.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Diaphragmatic Breathing Exercise&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;169&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the practice tips on this blog are about setting good practice habits in motion, but bad habits, like poor breathing, need to be disrupted too. The tools you use to disrupt bad habits are the same ones you use to create good practice habits:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1486&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the &#34;when&#34; and &#34;how&#34; of your practice highly contextual: &lt;em&gt;&#34;On Tuesday, I will practice for 15 minutes between meetings in my office, so that I can feel more energized as I head into the afternoon.&#34;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on small chunks of skill: &lt;em&gt;&#34;As I do my qigong form, I will focus on how the weight-shifting connects my feet to the floor.&#34;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, leave yourself wanting more. If you always finish a practice session feeling like you&#39;re not burnt out, but actually a little bit hungry for more practice, you&#39;re going to crave your next practice session.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Over time, you create a practice snowball, where the little doses of highly contextual practice add up to a greater inner drive to practice, more practice stamina, and the ability to focus on meaningful aspects of your practice. This is the best path to acquiring new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relaxation is Not Necessarily Skill Acquisition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I never really liked hearing people say they want to &#34;fight stress&#34;. Stress is fighting by definition! And thinking about &#34;getting really good at relaxing&#34; seems equally paradoxical to me. I think there is value to relaxation techniques, of course, and many of them are embedded in the deep breathing exercises I teach as part of qigong and tai chi. It&#39;s just that it&#39;s not so much about increasing your lung capacity, learning diaphragmatic breathing as a skill, or even specific exercises for anxiety, &lt;strong&gt;as it is about disrupting the stress cycle&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction here is that your are not &#34;doing more relaxation&#34;, you are breaking up &#34;doing more stress&#34; so that the effects of stress and anxiety can&#39;t build up in your nervous system. Think of it like a snowball, as it rolls downhill, it gets bigger and bigger, right? Well, by taking conscious breathing exercise breaks, you break up the hill, so the snowball can&#39;t build up. I&#39;m not saying it&#39;s never going to snow again, it&#39;s just that you won&#39;t experience the accumulation. Here&#39;s how to disrupt the stress cycle with the same three techniques that we use to create good practice habits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make the &#34;when&#34; and &#34;how&#34; of your stress highly contextual.&lt;/strong&gt; Once you understand where the spikes are in your day, you can intervene and add breathing exercises to re-balance or keep the snowball from building.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on small chunks of skill. &lt;/strong&gt;When you learn a set of breathing exercises, each exercise should serve a purpose. It&#39;s always effective to focus a small number of skills, 1-3, in each practice session.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, leave yourself wanting more. &lt;/strong&gt;This piece gets really interesting in a stress-cycle-breaking session. You want to explore the barrier between your practice and your return to your day. Notice when thoughts of outside pressures start to creep back into your head during the practice session. That&#39;s fine and natural, but the key is to learn how to transition back into your day as smoothly as possible. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Posture, Stress, and Breathing Exercises&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a tai chi teacher, one facet of stress that I think gets overlooked is the role that posture and (lack of) movement play in reinforcing the stress cycle. The good news is that when you begin to work on your breathing, you are already working on your posture, and as that work carries over into your non-practice time, you will continue to see the benefits. Here&#39;s a short clip on how good diaphragmatic breathing works:&lt;br / &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/R8zmohhzKsE?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/R8zmohhzKsE?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;br / &gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In order for the diaphragm to move properly, you must maintain a &#34;long spine&#34;. Good spinal length allows the movement of the diaphragm to pull on ligaments connected to the internal organs and the spine and gentle massage and tone everything in the torso. Not only does diaphragmatic breathing create better air exchange, deep breathing exercises also contribute to the health of the internal organs, like you were giving yourself a massage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a reinforcing cycle: good posture lets the breathing mechanism work better, you get better air exchange and your body handles stress better. As stress has less of an impact, your body is in &#34;fight or flight mode&#34; (the opposite of good posture -- the fetal curl) less often, and it becomes easier to breathe well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaways for Your Home Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to make a lasting impact on your health and sense of well-being, setting out to break your stress cycle is very important. Remember these tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore the context of stress spikes in your day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break the snowball effect with breathing breaks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-balance your internal environment and ability to handle stress by learning about posture and doing breathing exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to go further into relaxation, start building a daily practice like standing meditation or tai chi (remember, it&#39;s the daily cycle that&#39;s powerful, not any one practice session).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>