<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi-postures on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/tai-chi-postures/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi-postures on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/tai-chi-postures/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoid Bad Tai Chi Posture</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/05/14/avoid-bad-tai-chi-posture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 17:12:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/05/14/avoid-bad-tai-chi-posture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi has the potential to solve many common posture-related problems, but only if you follow &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/02/10/the-how-what-and-why-of-tai-chi-practice/&#34;&gt;the correct Tai Chi principles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, you want to pay attention to the body alignments that unify the arms, legs, and spine, creating effortless openness throughout the skeletal system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tai Chi, the way you hold your neck and head and release the pelvis into the legs are the exact opposite of what those of us who sit all day do. This is good news if you want to change your posture, but tough, because you probably spend lots of time in detrimental sitting positions each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the key postural elements of Tai Chi that rectify:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stiff Necks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eye Strain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compressed Lower Spine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unstable or Weak Legs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
http://youtu.be/4XskxdZbKyY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the video, you need to constantly avoid collapsed spinal posture and find length in every movement. Obviously this can be a big challenge when you are first learning Tai Chi. Your focus initially should be on learning the movements and separately working on the fundamentals, &lt;a title=&#34;Basic Training: Focus on Your Kwa Squat&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/&#34;&gt;especially leg alignments and kwa squats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the movement patterns become more comfortable, you can integrate healthy alignment principles, initially ignoring the details of the moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For more experienced practitioners:&lt;/strong&gt; All of the details of the movements should &lt;em&gt;enhance&lt;/em&gt; the way Tai Chi opens the body by more precisely loosening the soft tissue, expanding the joints, bringing spring to the ligaments, and relaxing the nervous system. If you find that &#34;getting it right&#34; ever sends you away from feeling looser, stronger, and more relaxed, something&#39;s off about your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>