<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>small-business on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/categories/small-business/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in small-business on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/categories/small-business/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Build Yourself a Pyramid</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/09/build-yourself-a-pyramid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2011 10:00:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/09/build-yourself-a-pyramid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not talking about a polygon with triangular faces or a marketing scam to rope your friends in. I&#39;m talking about The Pyramid Method, laid out by Cal Newport on his blog, &lt;a href=&#34;http://calnewport.com/blog/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Study Hacks&lt;/a&gt;. Newport tells the story of a friend of a friend&#39;s journey to becoming a professional hip-hop artist. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1262&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The key, he claims, was that the friend, Chris, followed the Pyramid Method -- named for the hip-hop club, The Pyramid, where he honed his craft. Chris went back to the Pyramid again and again and as he worked his way to becoming the undisputed champ of their weekly rap battles, he polished all the different facets of his hip-hop game. This is the essence of Newport&#39;s method. From the post where he tells Chris&#39;s story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Pyramid Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between the first two years after Chris&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s graduation, and the two years that followed our fateful phone call, couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t be starker. The key to his transformation was two-fold: (1) Chris focused his attention on improving his standing at a single venue; and (2) this venue provided clear metrics, so he could track his progress and use this to tweak his practice to be as effective as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call this general technique the Pyramid Method. &lt;strong&gt;I claim that it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s a powerful approach for anyone looking to transform an interest or natural talent into an expertise that cannot be ignored.&lt;/strong&gt; Regardless of the pursuit in question, if you want to take it someplace serious, follow Chris&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s example. This means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a single relevant venue to join at the entry level and work to increase your standing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure the venue offers clear metrics on your progress; use these metrics to guide your efforts to get better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forget all the other bullshit advice and mini-strategies people offer for getting ahead in your pursuit. If you can&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t master this one venue, then you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t yet deserve the world&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s respect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put your head down, and get it done.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As I read Newport&#39;s story, it dawned on me that the single biggest problem most teachers have getting better at teaching and building a student following along the way was that they were missing their Pyramid -- the one venue they could go again and again and get reliable feedback on their skills. I like Newport&#39;s tone and candid admission that there really isn&#39;t any glory in the Pyramid phase of honing your skills, but that&#39;s the big fat open secret to getting really good: you have to be there, doing it, all the time and adapting to feedback as you go. That&#39;s too boring for most people who think they deserve students because they&#39;ve been at their hobby for a long time. I&#39;m not going to go back down that road. I&#39;ve explored the psychological flip you need to make as a successful teacher &lt;a title=&#34;A Teacher&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Reality, Part 1&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;A Teacher&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Reality, Part 2&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a title=&#34;A Teacher&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Reality, Part 3&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, let&#39;s talk about building a Pyramid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Brookline Tai Chi as The Pyramid&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If we break down the four parts of Newport&#39;s model, we can actually see how BTC is the perfect place for teachers to hone their skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 1. Pick a single relevant venue to join at the entry level and work to increase your standing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a budding tai chi teacher in our system, this is the most relevant venue in the country. Most of my teaching peers have to teacher introductory sessions to a handful of students over and over again, because they don&#39;t have a venue with the kind of structure we do at BTC. For the new teacher, there is a clear entry-level opportunity and as they build a following, there is a natural progression for them to go through, teaching more advanced material.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Make sure the venue offers clear metrics on your progress; use these metrics to guide your efforts to get better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one teaching metric at BTC that matters: retention. Again, with a small sample size, it&#39;s easy to have a half-dozen excuses for why this student or that student didn&#39;t come back. Once you start seeing 20 new students every 7 weeks, though, you see trends (these excuses continually add &#34;old students&#34; back into the mix too, by the way). If you&#39;re perceptive, and you get some outside feedback on your teaching, you can begin to tweak how you run classes and how you related to students so that they are engaged, happy, and interested in studying with you on an ongoing basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Forget all the other bullshit advice and mini-strategies people offer for getting ahead in your pursuit. If you can&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t master this one venue, then you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t yet deserve the world&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s respect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love this piece of advice in the Pyramid Method. The classic example I&#39;ve experienced with BTC is outreach teaching. We get a steady stream of calls from groups, classes, and health fairs, stuff like that, looking for instructors to come teach to a group. For a while I didn&#39;t turn these down, at first for the wrong reason. See, at first, I thought being responsive to these requests would be a great way to get new business. It doesn&#39;t work that way. Don&#39;t get me wrong, I really enjoy talking to the student who came from that one conference, two years later, but this isn&#39;t the way to drive new business.....in one sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, this is an area where the Pyramid Method drove me outside of my &#34;single venue&#34;. I was getting some experience taking beginners through our six month introductory course cycle and I felt comfortable with the seven week format of a single course, but I didn&#39;t really know how to teach a good introductory &lt;em&gt;hour&lt;/em&gt;. What happens in the first hour that makes people excited to continue with the practice? Even though I taught that intro hour 4 times every 7 weeks, I decided to look outside of BTC for a way to practice what I call &#34;teaching cold&#34;. Teaching cold is all about teaching the intro to people who are less convinced that tai chi was right for them than the people who had made an effort to come into the school. That&#39;s why, for a while, I continued to say yes to every outreach teaching request we got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put another way, I know a small percentage of people will embrace a ten year practice arc and feel a deep connection to their personal journey. You can&#39;t teach to these people and survive professionally. You have to feed their journey differently, but it&#39;s not the main driver of successful commercial teaching. A much larger percentage of people will feel good about themselves, make a social connection, and enjoy a recreational version of the practice. These are the folks that have to be convinced in one hour and these are the folks the school is built to serve initially. So, I had to go out and find them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are versions of this experiment that you can perform at every stage of the learning process. Changing the format, the audience, and the context helps you build different skills, but I can always plug them back into better teaching at BTC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Put your head down, and get it done.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love that he sums up in one line what is typically a 3-5 year journey for most beginning instructors. Most people get over the initial excitement of being asked to teach in 6-8 months. It&#39;s hard for them to comprehend that coming to the end of September-August school year is the first lap around the track. What I always find interesting, though, is that these same people have yoked themselves with a personal practice that unfolds on that longer timeline. Most of them are excellent practitioners who must have that long view of their own personal development. Why is it that developing commercial teaching skills look so different to them? I can tell you that the ability to change gears with students -- delivering the one hour class then turning around and diving in with ten year veteran students -- has given me the ability to do the same in my practice. I just wish more people would see cultivating their teaching practice as an extension of their personal practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Brookline Tai Chi Fulfills Five Core Human Drives</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/25/how-brookline-tai-chi-fulfills-five-core-human-drives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2011 10:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/25/how-brookline-tai-chi-fulfills-five-core-human-drives/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been on my mind a lot in the past month that Brookline Tai Chi is approaching its 20th anniversary. With a rough calculation, that also means that we are approaching having taught 10,000 students in that time span. I can&#39;t decide which one of those milestones is going to look better on the big banner out front. How about &#34;10,000 People Relaxed&#34;?&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-922&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of reaching these major institutional marks, I&#39;ve also been wondering about the underlying mechanisms that have given the school such an amazing run so far. Surely, with this longevity, there have to be elements of the Brookline Tai Chi experience that transcend any one individual teacher, staff member or student. Then I came across the concept of &lt;a href=&#34;http://book.personalmba.com/core-human-drives/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Core Human Drives, from the Personal MBA by Josh Kaufman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;evp-706dca57ff4f870c95b76810b39ea177-wrap&#34; class=&#34;evp-video-wrap&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;http://book.personalmba.com/evp/framework.php?div_id=evp-706dca57ff4f870c95b76810b39ea177&amp;amp;id=MDItMDUtY29yZS1odW1hbi1kcml2ZXMtMS5tNHY%3D&amp;amp;v=1303391994&amp;amp;profile=default&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
  _evpInit(&#39;MDItMDUtY29yZS1odW1hbi1kcml2ZXMtMS5tNHY=&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you look at the overarching structure of Brookline Tai Chi, you can start to see how a system is in place to fulfill all five of these drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Learn&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The most obvious place to begin is the drive to learn. As a school, that is our most clearly stated goal. People come to us out of curiosity to learn, motivated to master new skills, and get satisfaction by progressing through the curriculum, course-by-course. We have multiple levels in each subject area and so, when you look at our course offerings on paper, the learning progression is very clearly laid out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, we get students whose drive to learn is more refined, and doesn&#39;t map on to the structure of our curriculum. These students can self-regulate the drive to learn more than the average student, and you see them adapting the curriculum to their needs, instead of relying on the external structure of the curriculum. I always have fascinating discussions with them, and many argue for dropping the curriculum model altogether. Having seen a thousands of people interface with our curriculum structure, though, I try to show these students that they are the exception, not the rule, when it comes to needing external guidance in fulfilling the drive to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Defend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As tai chi becomes more well known in the West and the body of research that supports its health benefits grow, we see more and more students who come at their doctor&#39;s recommendation. You could call this the drive to defend, because these people have identified a long-range threat to their health and are taking preventative countermeasures. Students who come in &#34;because my doctor recommended it&#34; are kind of like teachers who just teach the material. If this is their only motivation, it&#39;s going to be a hollow experience. Nobody lasts very long when their sole reason for learning tai chi is someone else&#39;s prescription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we&#39;re going to talk about the drive to defend, you can&#39;t simply say &#34;tai chi will prevent X&#34; or &#34;improves Y&#34; any more than you can make someone enjoy a salad by saying &#34;eat your vegetables&#34;. However, when someone makes the turn to embracing a personal practice, the drive to defend is fulfilled on a different level. For these students, the practice becomes an indispensable part of maintaining their health and wellness because they learn to manage their own energy. This is a very personal process though, and any prescription from a doctor or PT to practice is only incidental to internalizing personal practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as BTC fostering this drive, at best we can be a place where new students see other people modeling this behavior. You can&#39;t tell someone to adopt tai chi as a self-care energy management tool, but you can certainly show them what it looks like by example. In fact, this is one of the intangibles that comes across with the best teachers on day one. Whether or not students realize it, to some degree they are attracted to the teacher&#39;s personal practice as it comes out in their personality, bearing, and energetic demeanor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Acquire&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Because we live in a culture that conditions us to buy stuff in an attempt to fulfill our deeper drives, I&#39;ve always thought the drive to acquire had a funny place at Brookline Tai Chi. It&#39;s there, but it&#39;s pretty refined when you compare it to the urge to buy a shiny piece of plastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, we have a sort of dual economy, with external and internal currency. It&#39;s not uncommon to hear &#34;what class are you in?&#34; or have students who get excited about being in the advanced classes by 2015. What&#39;s more interesting to me is the subtle statement of status when people practice openly at the school. Don&#39;t get me wrong, I don&#39;t think it&#39;s a bad thing at all. In fact, I think the message it sends is, &#34;I&#39;m confident and comfortable with what I know and I&#39;m getting my practice in because this is important to me.&#34; I just think it&#39;s worth identifying this as part of fulfilling the drive to acquire on some level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drive to acquire in the tai chi world also motivates you to acquire &#34;spring in your ligaments&#34; or a 45-minute standing practice. We try to present the practice accordingly, like a giant developmental jigsaw puzzle, part mystery to figure out, part collection of pieces to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Feel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From the first class, we try to center each class around developing a facet of feeling awareness. As you look down the developmental path at the school, &#34;feeling&#34; becomes more and more refined. In the beginning, it can be as simple as noticing the speed at which your body wants to perform the opening movement of the tai chi form. &#34;Slowness&#34; is the first quality people associate with the practice and even appreciating that can have a felt impact on the first day of class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More experienced practitioners describe the learning arc as an ongoing process of feeling into and exploring an &#34;internal landscape&#34;. Bruce Frantzis often describes learning Taoist energy and meditation practices as &#34;awakening internal senses&#34;. From this point of view, the more someone invests in their practice, the more they are engaged in a grand process of feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an institutional point of view, we have to facilitate this process so students can gradually go deeper, but you can never assume that on any given day, for any person, you know what they are feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a class recently, I was showing a group how to do an exercise, not from the point of view of stretching muscles, but by releasing their nerve. It&#39;s a much lighter, gentle approach, but the goal is to perform the same exercise that often feels like a tissue stretch. A few students in class connected with the new approach in a way that made the exercise more accessible than ever before. When we discussed this, though, a couple of people were adamant that the new approach did nothing for them. Instead of convincing them that they should, in fact, feel in new and amazing ways, I was comfortable with them not connecting with this approach. This upset them or at least surprised them, but in order to have people genuinely connect with internal sensations, you have to make room for big misses too. There would be something disingenuous about every single person having a cathartic energetic awakening every hour of every class. In fact, not only would encouraging this kind of experience be dishonest on our part, it&#39;s unhealthy for students to work with their own energy that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I meet more and more people who come in to BTC with &#34;qigong experience&#34;, who have only ever really had these big group &#34;experiences&#34; that are in fact more disassociation and escapist fantasy than healthy energy development. One of the things I like about the way Bruce has always presented the Taoist tradition that he teaches is that, to some degree, it is mundane. The emphasis on slow and steady progress, tethered to concrete physical feeling awareness, is actually very stabilizing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Bond&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I tend to think that community develops around the edges of practice. When you talk about people connecting to each other through shared experience, the structure at Brookline Tai Chi again plays an interesting role. The quality of the shared experience shifts over time, from external to internal, like all of the other drives we&#39;ve looked at so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, people bond of feeling confused, klutzy, and slightly uncomfortable learning new skills. Since we start all of our beginners together, they can relax about performing to the standards of more experienced students and feel comfortable when they see their classmates fumbling along beside them. As they progress into deeper internal territory, the exercises they do with their classmates are a little more intimate, but they&#39;ve also become comfortable around each other, so it works most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you talk about fulfilling the drive to bond in the classroom, though, you&#39;ve already skipped over several steps in the process that get you into the classroom in the first place. From someone&#39;s very first interaction with the school, the drive to bond is sitting on their shoulder, asking them questions like &#34;Can I see myself there?&#34; or &#34;Is this a place for people like me?&#34; or even &#34;Will there be people there I get along with and who will like me?&#34;. In subtle ways, we have to answer this question 100 times before someone is comfortable enough to do a partner exercise where the instructions are &#34;let go&#34;. The drive to bond constantly asks &#34;Can I trust this place?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, as the program director, as the person who often writes the marketing copy, I&#39;m constantly trying to answer this question. When I walk into the school, eye contact, smiling, and addressing people by name goes a long way to always reinforcing this trust. Showing people that 20 years and 10,000 students later, we have a process that works is another strong indicator. What amazes me is that the weight of the 20 years/10,000 people experience comes through in the first 5 minutes of class. People can tell that there is something solid here, and it puts them at ease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess my one candid admission for this post is that sometimes conveying all this trust, and facilitating this bond makes me uneasy, because sometimes it feels very one-sided. By developing a trusting bond with 200 students at a time, lots of people share personal things with me. I have teachers like this too, where I&#39;m on the other side of the relationship. Without a relationship like this, I don&#39;t think deep learning can take place, but my hesitation is that often, people confuse it for more of a two-way street than it really is. Nothing makes me happier than overhearing two students in serious conversation, and knowing that I&#39;m not the glue that holds their bond together. Community forms around the edges of practice, and the more I can extricate myself from the bonds of that practice over time, the healthier our community is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Posted from Trainerfly: Launching an Online Course</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2011 10:36:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2011/04/11/how-i-launched-my-first-online-course/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this post from the Trainerfly blog&lt;/a&gt;. I talk to teachers and trainers all the time who want move beyond their live events, but the number of steps it takes, and the technology required to make it work seem overwhelming. Hopefully, I&#39;ve made a little dent in that perception!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 3</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 10:19:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/stephenagregory/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Dripping Faucet&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.static.flickr.com/69/165377377_6e9eabae34_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image courtesy of StephenAGregory&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;So far in this series we&#39;ve been talking about adapting &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;your teaching style&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the structure of your teaching business&lt;/a&gt; to fit the needs of your students. Now I want to look at a trait that all of the best teachers I&#39;ve studied with share, which is a work capacity they can turn on like a fire hose. If your work capacity only comes out like water from a dripping faucet, you won&#39;t be able to be &#34;big enough&#34; to encompass all of your students and their varying needs.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-894&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Work Ethic Isn&#39;t Work Capacity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first distinction I want to make here is between work ethic and work capacity. It&#39;s the difference between fire and water. Work ethic is a spark, the fire, that drives some of these teachers to be on the road 30 weeks a year, or fly half way around the world to learn from obscure masters. It&#39;s the drive that makes 14 hour days, 6 days seem like a worthwhile pursuit. But ultimately, it&#39;s not what makes these things possible. The spark initiates these crazy journeys, but along the way, work capacity gets built up. Work capacity is more like a habit, and when these guys get up in the morning to teach, it&#39;s like they turn on a faucet and get a steady stream of water to draw from all day long.  Again and again I watch my teaching mentors lead 5-8 hour workshops, continue teaching while every else takes a break for lunch, and then have 2-3 hours of meetings at the end of the day. Knowing them, there was probably a hour of personal practice going on before the teaching day began. So what is it that allows them to go for 12 or 14 hours when most of their students are worn out from the 5 hours of training in the middle?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Logging the Hours, Deliberately&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To say that they are used to teaching is a too simplistic. Yes, step one is to log the teaching hours. Any skill requires that you put in time. There are a couple more dimensions to building your work capacity and in this case we&#39;ll look at teaching for examples of what they are. I&#39;ve written about Geoff Colvin&#39;s deliberate practice model before &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, when I explained part of my motivation for building Trainerfly. Colvin outlines essential elements for getting better at any skill through practice.  When I look at my teaching mentors, they all follow this deliberate practice model in unique ways. Not only have they logged serious teaching hours, but they&#39;ve run the &#34;teaching chunks&#34; experiment, where you create feedback loops and reproduceable teaching moments that allow you to build a student base and your own work capacity simultaneously. Let&#39;s break their down approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bruce Frantzis&#39; Three City Model&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/bruces-frantzis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bruce&lt;/a&gt; has a prolific teaching record, spanning decades and many different format, from one-on-one lessons to workshops packed with 200 students, I think one of the most interesting models he&#39;s taught in is what I&#39;ll call the Three City Model. He did this in the Bay Area in the 1990&#39;s and in New Mexico before that. Some of his most successful certified instructors have also replicated this model. The basic strategy is to offer regular weekly classes in three locations that are near each other, but spread out. The distance criteria are that the locations are in distinct markets, but they are close enough to each other that really dedicated students could travel to any of the three sites to study more than once a week if they wanted. In the Bay Area, this was Berkeley, San Francisco, and Marin County. I&#39;ve contemplated this model in the Boston area, with sites in Cambridge, Boston, and Brookline, for example.  The geographic benefit is striking a balance between accessing a larger potential student base and catering to hard core students simultaneously. There is a financial benefit here too. You can weather the inevitable ups and downs in attendance at one site, because you have the other two.&amp;Acirc;  The benefit for the teacher, though, is that you can experiment with what you teach and how you present it. Separate sites give you the chance to have a more controlled experiment than if you just decided to try a new approach each week at a single site. You can watch two groups evolved over six months or a year and see if a better way to teach emerges on a lot of different levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dr. Eric Cobb, The Constant Presenter&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Whenever I attend a Z Health training, I&#39;m always impressed with the way &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zhealth.net/about-z-health&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Cobb&lt;/a&gt; shifts gears between group teaching and working one-on-one with clients before the seminar begins, during the breaks, and often at the end of the day. He does it as effortlessly as turning up the water pressure on a faucet. The flow is on from the moment he enters the room, cranked up for the group, then down to just the right volume for someone he&#39;s never worked with before and then back up for everyone at once.  I know the he spent years in clinical practice before he started teaching Z Health publicly, and you can see the fine-tuned empathy that comes from years of working one-on-one. There is also something very particular about his rapport with a group that feels like it&#39;s built on all the one-on-one relationships in the room.  When you look at his current teaching schedule, you see over 20-30 events a year, often in the same 3-4 topics. Some of these groups are only 10-12 people and some are capped at 50 attendees. He&#39;s also presented the core concepts of Z Health at professional gatherings, conferences and through the lens of group coaching. Once again, this is the deliberate practice model in action: take the same key concepts and present them in as many different venues as possible -- individual, small group, big group, written, recorded on video.  By teaching anywhere and to everyone, two very interesting things happen. The first is you hone your message and make it scalable (i.e. you know it so well, you know how to present just the right amount of it, from the right perspective, to the right people). The second is sort of a fortunate by-product and that is that you gradually recruit people who also believe in your message. I call that a by-product because most people assume they deserve to have a massive, faithful following as soon as they have an idea in their heads. The message from all of these teachers is exactly the opposite: if you get a big enough fire hose going for long enough, the faithful will follow. Lots of people have ideas. Untested, unhoned ideas are worthless. When you see Dr. Cobb tirelessly flying around the country to successfully build a business and nonchalantly acknowledging that he would likely keep that up for another 5 years to keep on building, you realize that building work capacity is the secret ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bill Ryan&#39;s Healing/Teaching Blend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the traits that all three of these teachers have in common is that they are all gifted hands-on healers. I can attest to this from being under their hands personally, but it was also a key tool they used for developing their businesses early on and growing a dedicated following of students. I&#39;m not sure anyone has blended the two with the intensity Bill Ryan did while he was building up Brookline Tai Chi in the 1990&#39;s, though.  On top of founding, running, and teaching daily at Brookline Tai Chi, Bill relied on private lessons and bodywork to keep the school running and cultivate a core of students at a punishing rate. When I trained with him to take over the operations of the school, he was in a quieter mode, but he would still be there from 10am-10pm almost every day. I&#39;m not sure I ever even saw him stop and eat in those 12 hours bursts...and this was when he was transitioning out. The bigger point here is not about keeping crazy work hours. The point is that by working intensely one-on-one and transitioning to group classes, the different skills each teaching scenario require begin to blend, and that&#39;s a good thing.  When Bill was training me to teach tai chi, we would practice how to give form corrections as hands-on adjustments. We would each start on opposite sides of the room and Bill would say &#34;I&#39;ll meet you in the middle.&#34; By the time I was fumbling through the second or third student, Bill would show up next to me, having corrected 9 or 10. He developed fast eyes and fast hands that could make meaningful corrections, largely due to the number of hours doing private bodywork. While I wasn&#39;t a trained bodyworker, he encouraged me to do as many private lessons as I could. He swore by them as a way to hone your teaching, just because you had more space and time to play with adjustments and get immediate feedback from students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Create Deliberate Practice Moments&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What I&#39;ve learned from these guys is that you create the opportunities to hone your teaching. I don&#39;t see where they are today and think &#34;I want to be up on stage teaching 150 people&#34;. I think about their process and how I can create the teaching moments to steadily grow my capacity.  Bruce likes to talk about the &#34;20 year overnight success&#34; when he&#39;s talking about learning tai chi, but as a teacher who now attracts hundreds of students to a single event, he&#39;s a model for this same approach in teaching. He often points out how this message doesn&#39;t really come across in our culture, unless you really look for it. He&#39;ll talk about a sports movie, with a little kid throwing the ball around in his backyard, who by the next scene is transformed into the World Series-winning major league pitcher. What&#39;s the message there? Hang on to a distant dream and it will magically happen? That&#39;s why I initially wanted to make the decision between work ethic and work capactiy.  The ethic, the idea, the spark -- that&#39;s important and necessary, but it&#39;s the inspiration. Each of these teachers has taken their unique inspiration or aspiration and slowly, over time, developed the capacity to steadily build toward that image. You need a slow, steady fuel to make that journey, more like a flowing river than a short burst of flame.&amp;Acirc;  So take any opportunity you can get to deliberately develop your work capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 2</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2011 14:33:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; title=&#34;Broadway Bridge&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2571/3817456902_962b9e082a.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; of this series, we talked about the social nature of wanting to belong to something bigger than yourself as one possible drive for learning tai chi. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-868&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The social drive is a major aid teachers can rely on to build their base of students. Another one, that we&#39;ll discuss here is our habitual drive, i.e. we are creatures of habit. That can be a good thing when it comes to maintaining a student base, but it is also the first major hurdle you have to clear as a teacher when it comes to getting new students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Habitual Inertia&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For some reason, it&#39;s easier to see inertia in other people, and attribute it to laziness or stupidity, than it is to appreciate the forces of habit working on ourselves. I&#39;ve had many conversations with sullen teachers who moan about students not coming to class. Whenever I hear them complain, I always wonder this: &#34;What&#39;s getting in the way of you offering classes six days a week? You know, it would be a lot easier for people to come to class if there almost always was a class for them to come to.&#34; And of course, these failing teachers throw up a long list of reasons why they can&#39;t offer more classes. This is the part that always stumps me: For the most part, the very same reasons they give for not offering more classes are the same reasons that make it hard for people to come to a class when it&#39;s only offered once a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s damn hard for people to get out and do things on a regular basis. How many different activities like that do you participate in? Survey 10 friends and ask them. I&#39;m guessing it&#39;s not too many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s why whenever someone actually walks through the door at Brookline Tai Chi and is ready to try out a class, it&#39;s a huge gift. They&#39;ve overcome so many barriers -- they&#39;re breaking their current routine, our schedules match, they&#39;ve done research and are motivated to try something new.&amp;Acirc;  And here&#39;s the thing, how many of those steps can I do for them with an advertising campaign? The answer is, approximately half.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, inertia can go one of two ways. The inertia of your own daily routine can keep you from participating in something new, or it can be the glue that holds together the things you are actively engaged in. From the point of view of running a school, we want to use the glue-side of inertia to keep people engaged, but we also have to be vigilant about finding the cracks in a new student&#39;s inertia, and help them shift into new routines and habits. I don&#39;t pretend to be an expert at doing this, but I know that there are two sides to this change process, the structural and the inspirational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Structural and The Inspirational&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The structural and the inspirational support each other. When you come to your first class and feel relaxed and energized after an hour of tai chi, that&#39;s inspirational. If there are three more times that week when the class fits your schedule and you know you can come back, that&#39;s a structural, systemic fact of how the business runs, and it supports the inspirational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, if class met once a week, more often than not, something comes up to break the new pattern you are trying to establish. You have fun on week one, you start to see yourself doing tai chi after a couple of weeks, but then you have to miss a week, and you don&#39;t make time to practice, and slowly, the other pulls in your life exert themselves, and your chance to make tai chi a habit slips away. It&#39;s not like I see this happen once in a while, I see it happen 30-40% of the time with new students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, you need to find the blend of structures and routines that support the moments of inspiration that you are out to engineer. The most successful teachers I know have this blend working for them. When teachers fail to build a student following, it&#39;s often because they don&#39;t balance these elements well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why a Structuralist Teacher Fails&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Structuralist teachers say things like &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;this week we learn this move and next week we learn that move and in 10 years you will benefit from the practice because Tai Chi is hard&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. I hate this approach. It&#39;s dry and sounds like &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;eat your vegetables.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Do you think any of your students who fought through all their habitual inertia want to wind up in your class only to be hit over the head with a boring, drawn-out curriculum that&#39;s more lecture than doing? You might get off on that, and I guess your one or two other students will too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not that the Structurists actually want to bore their students into relaxation. It&#39;s that they&#39;ve lost sight of the students through the mountains of information they&#39;ve combed through, first as a practitioner, then in preparing to be a teacher. They can see a sequence of material, but they can&#39;t see the material from the student&#39;s point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structuralists of the more self-absorbed variety thrive around people with similar experience in the practice. When they can talk to someone who is at the same level, they are very clear and compelling. The problem is that they can&#39;t see what&#39;s going on outside of themselves, in their students, so they fall back on external structure to teach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structuralists with less experience face the problem of not being able to motivate or inspire students. They come across as dogmatic and hollow, because they haven&#39;t seen far enough down the developmental pathway to come back and tell new students about it. Instead, they rely on the external structure to string people along, because they are also in the early stages of that process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where the Inspirationalists Fall Apart&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, you might think the antidote to the Structuralist is to turn on the charm and engage students in the moment as much as possible. We&#39;ve seen the all-inspiration, all-the-time trip too, and this fails because students don&#39;t have the context to understand the process they are going through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is a forest-for-the-trees problem, the Inspirationalists get students scratching at the bark, feeling it, and experiencing it so much that the students don&#39;t even know it&#39;s a tree. They just happen upon whatever tree the Inspirationalist feels like exploring that day. I see this tendency in long-time practitioners who have become looser about what they do in their own practice. They forget what they went through to develop their practice, and now they think they can teach people without using any process at all. It just leaves students confused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Inspirationalists lose students because they don&#39;t provide enough context and a clear structured process for working through the material. I find this is a real shame because all of the good traditions have a clear developmental path. This is what has allowed them to thrive over centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really gets me about Inspirationalists, though, is that they burn out and fall apart much faster than the Structuralists. They can stoke a lot of excitement in their students in the moment, but they&#39;re inconsistent. Maybe the have a good month and they&#39;re on a roll, but can you count on them to teach through a full year or even six months? Usually, you can&#39;t even get 3-4 times a week out of them. It&#39;s a classic loud burst vs. slow boil mentality. To be a successful teacher, and build a stable following of students, you can&#39;t be the flash in the pan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Consistent Inspiration or Inspired Structuralism&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So that leaves us somewhere in between. The Structuralists have a steadiness and consistency that makes them reliably available to students. The Inspirationalists create a spark that shows students what&#39;s possible. If you really want to build a student base, you&#39;ve got to work on both levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My teaching mentor, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.billryanenergyarts.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bill Ryan&lt;/a&gt;, figured out how to make both of these levels work at the same time. He has an artful blend of structural and inspirational teaching. As Brookline Tai Chi evolved under Bill&#39;s guidance, a large, university-like curriculum emerged, but he didn&#39;t fall into the Structuralist trap. Instead, every hour of every class was an engineered opportunity to find one-on-one inspirational moments for students. People felt like the practice was tailored to their needs as they received personal corrections. This is how you use structure to set up inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill also used inspiration to infuse structure with meaning. He always provided a narrative for where you were in the developmental process. Working your way through a structured curriculum feels like going on a journey when you use Inspirationalist teaching to tell the a story about the process. Every step along the path becomes a brief scene in a larger adventure. In that way, you can sustain inspired teaching of weeks and months and years. Each hour of class feels like picking up your favorite novel &lt;em&gt;(because the book is about YOU)&lt;/em&gt; and diving back into the story. Personal practice becomes writing the next paragraph and over the years you can look back on whole chapters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, teaching or running a school isn&#39;t very different from your own personal practice. Every time you go to practice, you address the particular form of the practice, and the art in your practice is about finding the deeper internal connection alive inside the form. Form without connection is hollow and connection without form is meaningless. Teaching a group for an hour or shepherding a student body through another school year is the same process at the core, just applied to different scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(image courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/nickweinrauch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;nickweinrauch&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2011 10:42:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, Energy Arts Instructor Jess O&#39;Brien was in town, &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/blog/five-elements-hsing-i&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;teaching at BTC&lt;/a&gt;. We got to spend some time together and talk about teaching, studying with different teachers, and trying to run a teaching business. One thing that we came back to again and again was how difficult it is to build up a student base. I think I know why.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-852&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;People are Lazy, Social, and Creatures of Habit&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, I know it sounds like a mean thing to say, but in the words of Stanford psychologist BJ Fogg, people are &#34;lazy, social, and creatures of habit.&#34; Rather than looking at this as a moral judgment, take it as a reality of the way we are wired to operate in the world. In fact, if you look at studies about willpower and motivation or start to research how our nervous system functions, you begin to see that these qualities are survival responses that drive efficient behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, I know plenty of teachers who love to take the moral high ground about how their students should behave, who, in fact, have no students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start to accept that habit drives lazy, social student behavior more than anything else, some interesting implications arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, people want to be a part of a school just as much as they want to learn the material. Brookline Tai Chi is almost 20 years old and people identify with the institution. I wrote about a &lt;a href=&#34;../2010/12/06/your-marketing-universe/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&#34;marketing universe&#34;&lt;/a&gt;, where students orbit the school at different levels, i.e. your hard core students or the ones that drift in and out. Brookline Tai Chi is a planet, exerting major gravitational pull for an entire community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the larger Energy Arts community, though, BTC is the exception, not the rule. So what does Jess do about this? He and his teaching partner Isaac have one night a week to teach. How can they create a feeling of belonging to a school? While they don&#39;t have a visible physical space as a symbol of their school, they can draw on other symbols. Whenever Jess comes to teach at BTC, he brings obscure articles about martial arts and usually has 3-4 rare martial arts books in tow. A self-described martial arts nerd, Jess can go on and on about history, theory, and training. This is huge. While students might not be able to say, &#34;I belong to a school with a physical address&#34;, they can certainly say, &#34;I belong to a tradition.&#34; Jess and Isaac both use language that points to a larger lineage. This goes a long way for making students feel like they belong to something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infusing the language you use with a bigger sense of a community or a tradition is one key step you can take. You will also need to tell a developmental story to your students, so they understand the larger process they are going through. We&#39;ll explore this more later in the series when we look at people who have mastered the blend of systematic offerings that feel fresh and new and inspired every time they teach them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s also worth point out that &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the language you use&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; doesn&#39;t just mean &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the language you use in the classroom&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. It&#39;s &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the language you use everywhere&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;, in print, on the web, in emails to students. Absent a physical space that people can belong to, or even to support it, you need language that also triggers this sense of belonging. At Brookline Tai Chi, our space is an asset because it&#39;s such a clear symbol for people, but I think you can create other symbols (for less than $10,000/month!) that do the same thing. When I talked to Jess about it, I encouraged him to capture the way he talks about martial arts. If he can make everything around the classes sound and feel the same way, people will be eager to participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sense of belonging we are talking about here points to the &#34;social&#34; nature of people. Having a physical space for people to train touches on the &#34;habitual&#34; part as well. In the next post in this series, we&#39;ll look at how you create a teaching space that balances the need for consistency with the need to inspire students every single time they come to class.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pros and Cons of Automation</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 09:32:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Pro: My Car Broke Down and I Was Actually Happy about It&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I guess I need to explain that a little more. I wasn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; happy that it broke down. I was on the way to Maine to teach the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/&#34;&gt;tai chi group in Farmington&lt;/a&gt;, so that sucked. And it was the clutch the completely died, so I knew it was going to be a few dollars to repair. But that was actually part of the silver lining. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-661&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;See, a couple of years ago, I read about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/tip-6-use-gas-prices-to-become-your-own-hedge-fund/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ramit Sethi&#39;s strategy for hedging fuel costs&lt;/a&gt;. The theory goes, if you are paying for something that goes up and down over the course of a year, you should find a way to even out the costs. This makes sense from a paycheck point of view, right? You take home the same amount of money each week, so you&#39;ll be in more predictable shape if your expenses work the same way. I adapted that strategy to create a car savings account. Looking back we realized we spent roughly the same amount of money on car-related expenses year to year, but they almost always came in spikes when something went wrong. To smooth out the spikes, I took a monthly average of those annual expenses and started putting it away automatically into a savings account each month. Now, when something breaks down, the money is already sitting there and I don&#39;t have to sweat a disruptive spike in our monthly expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dog has his own account too, for &#34;random&#34; vet visits that actually happen on a pretty predictable basis. And I guess that&#39;s the bigger lesson here. Looking back year over year, you start to see some clear patterns for stuff like this, even though the clutch dying or the dog eating something awful seems like a random occurrence. So, if you automate savings around these &#34;random predictable&#34; expenses, you save yourself a huge headache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Con: I Want Automation Now&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I get the &#34;automation itch&#34; whenever I&#39;m starting a new project. The &#34;automation itch&#34; is the desire to put a system in place, which is ultimately a good thing, but it usually strikes prematurely. Getting the itch can be a major trap and I&#39;ve slowly learned to recognize that it usually takes more time to set up an automated system early in a project than it takes to execute something manually. The best advice I&#39;ve ever gotten here is &#34;do it manually until you don&#39;t have enough hours in the day.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went through this at Brookline Tai Chi with an online registration system for classes. In summer 2009, we added online registration and probably 1/3 of current students adopted it right away. What was striking was that close to 80% of new students took to the system. Those statistics are interesting, but probably more appropriate for a post about changing systems in a business....another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flash forward to last week. This session, we got back to back cases of students who couldn&#39;t register online because of their unique situations. That means we need to rebuild the system to fit their situation, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wrong. That was two cases out of how many? Let&#39;s say 200. 1% of registrations. Do you think we have time to do 1% by hand? Especially if you consider that doing 1% of registrations this way takes 10 minutes of admin time, compared to several hours of developer time to make the change, it&#39;s a no-brainer. Of course, there&#39;s one other important factor: systems changes always have to put the user experience front and center. &lt;strong&gt;It&#39;s never a good idea to argue to your customer that they should interact with your business a certain way because it&#39;s easier for some back-end reason&lt;/strong&gt;. In this case though, to the students involved it looked like we were making a special exception for them, which they appreciated. So it worked out all around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a year ago I would have panicked a little more about these two cases. Or I would have thought about how to tinker with the system first. This time though, my first thought was &#34;2 out of how many?&#34; and my second thought was how to create the best manual solution. Beware the automation itch!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Feedback from Trainerfly Beta</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 08:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/estimmel/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-633&#34; title=&#34;megaphone&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/02/megaphone.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;megaphone by estimmel&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve gotten &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/&#34;&gt;Trainerfly&lt;/a&gt; out into people&#39;s hands and I&#39;ve been learning some really interesting lessons. I think it was easy for me to get wrapped up in how I&#39;ve evolved it as a tool in my business over the last two years and lose perspective on how other people might be trying to add it into their business from scratch, with none of that prior history.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-632&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Extra Layers&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you integrate a new business tool, you have a question of layers. In other words, if this is how I normally get something done, will the new tool add new layers of work, or remove them? And if it adds more work, is there another benefit that justifies the additional work. I got some strong feedback in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was amazingly clarifying for me to see the places where extra layers were not justified. Really specifically, the product is not strong enough right now to replace one-on-one communication if a trainer is using an email/youtube/spreadsheet system to get information to their clients. Why did I think I could compete with mature products from Google and Microsoft? Hahaha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if the communication issue is about hitting many people at different times with the same basic information, I think I have a winning solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Class, Deconstructed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The biggest thing that has been bugging me in the last 12-18 months on my own personal teaching front is summed up nicely by saying: &#34;teaching is a product that is consumed as it is produced&#34;. A little tear runs down my cheek at the end of every class, because I know that what happened in the last hour is lost forever in the ether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so maybe that&#39;s a little dramatic, but it bothers me that there&#39;s not a better way to preserve the moment, and from a business point of view, earn more money from it. Can you image a furniture maker who crafts single-use chairs? As soon as someone stands up, the chair disappears?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m starting to see a solution to this problem, though. It&#39;s not going to be hooking up 15 different cameras around the school and recording every single thing that happens. Instead, I&#39;m starting the process of extracting key ingredients from class, and transforming them into a touchstones that students can come back to again and again to further their practice outside of that elusive produce-and-consume teaching moment. There&#39;s a lot more to say about this strategy, and I&#39;m really excited about refining those tools. They will look really different than a traditional class -- you have to trade the interactive spontaneity of a good class, for structures that create reproduceable learning and practice moments for students.&amp;Acirc;  I think I know what that means....stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Highlights from &#34;How Great Entrepreneurs Think&#34;</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/02/highlights-from-how-great-entrepreneurs-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 08:20:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/02/highlights-from-how-great-entrepreneurs-think/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Thinker&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.static.flickr.com/168/412158673_343bc90041_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;112&#34; height=&#34;168&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writing for Inc. Magazines Great Entrepreneur&#39;s series, Leigh Buchanan breaks down a fascinating study that pits successful entrepreneurs against career corporate managers in a thought experiment.&amp;Acirc;  The study strikes a big chord with me because so many of the things I think are necessary running a small, customer-focused service business are exactly the kinds of things the entrepreneurs describe doing&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-592&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; -- but here&#39;s the catch, by &#34;successful entrepreneurs&#34;, the author means: 15+ years of experience starting successful and unsuccessful ventures and at the time the study was done, the entrepreneurs were running companies with revenue between $200 million and $65 billion a year. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;That means the customer-focused iterative process mindset is very, very scalable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While, I definitely think you should go read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inc.com/magazine/20110201/how-great-entrepreneurs-think.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the full article&lt;/a&gt;, here are some of the highlights for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On where to Focus Your Energy:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Entrepreneurs fret less about competitors, Sarasvathy [the author of the study] explains, because they see themselves not in the thick of a market but on the fringe of one, or as creating a new market entirely. &#34;They are like farmers, planting a seed and nurturing it,&#34; she says. &#34;What they care about is their own little patch of ground.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
She contrasts the farming mentality to the corporate market share mentality -- what is the other guy doing and how can I get a piece of his pie? I&#39;ve often felt that the farming tendency is much more fruitful, because in the end you return to creating a really coherent experience for your clients. You&#39;re never actually going to be the other guy, so trying to mimic one or two pieces of what he&#39;s doing, you&#39;re going to miss something big and fall short. Plus, I really see more and more that it&#39;s a myth that the market is a zero sum game. There&#39;s lots and lots of room out there, and as Jason Fried once said &#34;there&#39;s a new class of freshman every year&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Testing vs. Guessing:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the best test of any product is to go to your target market and pretend like it&#39;s a real business. You&#39;ll find out soon enough if it is or not.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve seen this at every level from &#34;I want to open a new center&#34; down to &#34;I think I&#39;m going to teach this one exercise in class tonight&#34;. It&#39;s not that you sell people lies and shoddy products, it&#39;s that you can&#39;t get caught in the mind trap of making it perfect before you get your idea out there. Even if you get really honest feedback from a whole range of people, you&#39;ve gone from ideas to behavior, which is much more powerful, if you try to sell it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the contrast:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Corporate executives, by contrast, generally envisioned more traditional vendor-customer interactions, such as focus groups.....&#34;I would like to get from them...by meeting with them or getting their input on what they think of the limitation of existing programs....just kind of sit and listen to them telling me...what new features they&#39;d like. And I&#39;d just listen to them talk, talk, talk and then be thinking and develop something between what they want and what&#39;s possible technically.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What I really liked about this article, though, was that she made it clear that something like &#34;testing vs. guessing&#34; isn&#39;t a tactic that you should copy in your business operations, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;it&#39;s a mindset, or a way of being.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can&#39;t go out and survey customers and say, &#39;OK, what kinda car do you really want?&#39; I believe very much in living it. If you&#39;re gonna write a book about stevedores, go work as a stevedore for a period of time. My company was going to design and sell products for physical therapy, so I worked in rehab medicine for two years.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overall, I think I found this article so affirming personally because what I hear in these &#34;successful entrepreneurs&#34; is that a process is at the heart of what they do, not something static like an idea or a goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sarasvathy concluded that master entrepreneurs rely on what she calls &lt;a href=&#34;http://effectuation.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;effectual reasoning&lt;/a&gt;.  Brilliant improvisers, the entrepreneurs don&#39;t start out with concrete  goals. Instead, they constantly assess how to use their personal  strengths and whatever resources they have at hand to develop goals on  the fly, while creatively reacting to contingencies. By contrast,  corporate executives&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;those in the study group were also enormously  successful in their chosen field&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;use causal reasoning. They set a goal  and diligently seek the best ways to achieve it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The contrast between an endless, nourishing, and shifting process and a fixed, rigid, endpoint is a major mental shift that we try to make in energy arts practices, including meditation. It&#39;s fascinating to me that it cuts across all disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;image by &lt;a id=&#34;yui_3_3_0_1_1296651127747164&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/welshbaloney/&#34;&gt;welshbaloney&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Cycles</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 14:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m coming to another big teaching cycle in Trainerfly and I think this short clip of David Heinemeier Hansson speaking at Stanford&#39;s Entrepreneurship Corner is really useful to frame the mindset:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-574&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;single&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;302&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;config=http://ecorner.stanford.edu/embeded_config.xml%3Fmid%3D2361&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://ecorner.stanford.edu/swf/player-ec.swf&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;single&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;302&#34; src=&#34;http://ecorner.stanford.edu/swf/player-ec.swf&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; flashvars=&#34;config=http://ecorner.stanford.edu/embeded_config.xml%3Fmid%3D2361&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the point in the clip above is more about a strategy to take when you look at the &#34;big guys&#34;, but I really feel like the alternating cycles of &#34;spending&#34; and &#34;teaching&#34; are relevant here. We just went through a &#34;spending&#34; period where we were building out the technology behind Trainerfly. That was only possible because we went through a &#34;teaching&#34; period initially, where I learned what problems I wanted to solve with a software application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I&#39;m entering another &#34;teaching&#34; cycle as I share the fruits of the &#34;spending&#34; cycle, a viable software solution, with other peers in movement education. It gets even more interesting if you chart the smaller cycles within each of the major cycles.....hmmmm, where have I encountered that kind of thinking before??&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossfit&#39;s Brilliant use of Game Mechanics</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/04/crossfits-brilliant-use-of-game-mechanics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2011 06:51:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/04/crossfits-brilliant-use-of-game-mechanics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; Recently, TechCrunch featured an article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/25/scvngr-game-mechanics/&#34;&gt;the playdeck they use at SCVNGR&lt;/a&gt; that outlines the mechanics of gameplay. The article cites at TED talk by game designer Jane McGonigal, which I talk about &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-538&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was a little disappointed with McGonigal&#39;s conclusion, because she basically offered up the solution as specially-themed video games to leverage the power of game mechanics, or &#34;gameplay superpowers&#34;, to do good in the real world and incite behavior change. She presented a couple of case studies that her group ran and they showed some carry-over to behaviors later on. That&#39;s fine. I just think there&#39;s potential to go further. I don&#39;t think I was alone either. If you read the TED video comments, lots of people reply with &#34;but my son lives in the basement and only comes out to eat&#34; arguments. Not exactly the thriving social fabric McGonigal presents....&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I couldn&#39;t help think that there are better examples of hybrids between real life behavior and motivation that falls under the game mechanics principles. The example I want to look at today is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crossfit.com&#34;&gt;Crossfit&lt;/a&gt;. As a fitness movement, they do an amazing job with this blend. Now, I have to admit I don&#39;t have direct experience with Crossfit, so I&#39;m hoping someone who does will fill in even more detail here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Game Mechanics Defined&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I refer to &#34;game mechanics&#34; in this post, I&#39;m taking about the underlying elements that are repeatedly used across interactive electronic media to elicit emotional, motivating responses from the game players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the TechCrunch article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;SCVNGR&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s playdeck tries to break down the game mechanics into their  constituent parts.  Some elements are as basic as &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;achievements,&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;  &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;status,&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;virtual items.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;   But there are also more complex ones  such as the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;appointment dynamic&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; (a player must return at a specific  time and perform an action to get a reward, like in Farmville), &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;free  lunch&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; (a player gets something because of the efforts of other  people,like in Groupon), &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;fun once, fun always&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; (a simple action that  maintains a minimum level of enjoyment no matter how many times you do  it, like Foursquare&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s check-ins), and &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;cascading information theory  (give out information in the smallest dribblets possible to keep players  guessing and moving forward).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We&#39;re going to look at how these dynamics are used, intentionally or not (I don&#39;t know), in the user experience on Crossfit.com, at Crossfit affiliate gyms, and in the Crossfit Games. It&#39;s also important to look at overarching concepts in gameplay, that Jane McGonigal has articulated very clearly in her TED talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Game Mechanics in Crossfit&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I believe that the following mechanisms make the Crossfit user experience engaging and as a result, extremely popular. If you get confused about where I&#39;m using technical terms, refer back to &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/25/scvngr-game-mechanics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the TechCrunch article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Companion Gaming&lt;/strong&gt; -- the cross-platform approach is central to the idea of applying game mechanics from the virtual world to real world behavior. Crossfit does this by posting the &#34;workout of the day&#34; to Crossfit.com, allowing affiliate gyms to operate Crossfit locations, and even hosting an Olympics-style Crossfit Games. You can &#34;play&#34; in all these different ways, and your achievements in one venue is relevant to another. More on that below...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appointment Dynamic &lt;/strong&gt;-- at the heart of Crossfit.com is the &#34;Workout of the Day&#34;. Each day, a challenging workout is posted from Crossfit headquarters that sets the daily goal for everyone who participates. If you read the comments, where people post their workout times, you&#39;ll see a mix of dread and delight, which seems to capture the Crossfit spirit. So, all wrapped up in this daily challenge is also:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Achievement&lt;/strong&gt; -- posting your times to comments,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Countdown&lt;/strong&gt; -- workouts are often completed &#34;for time&#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pride&lt;/strong&gt; -- successful completion of the workout or beating your own previous time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Envy &lt;/strong&gt;-- daily workouts are often accompanied by pictures of other Crossfitters working out in various states of undress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy &lt;/strong&gt;-- leveraging public accountability, i.e. posting your achievement, to motivate future compliance&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These underlying mechanics add up to create what McGonigal refers to as the &#34;Social Fabric of Games&#34;. In other words, competition creates community. McGonigal captures the gamer spirit alive in the social fabric as an &#34;urgent optimism&#34; to toil in &#34;blissful productivity&#34; towards &#34;epic meaning&#34;. Again, watch the video to get her full explication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point though, you really need to ask two questions. First of all, you&#39;re probably wondering why these mechanics can be apparently more compelling than real life. I&#39;m not sure if they are or whether a virtual world just gives us a clear view into how they work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second question is, given how powerful these motivators are, how can I incorporate them into my training business? Take another look at Crossfit. I know I&#39;ve barely scratched the surface with this analysis. And I&#39;m not saying you should copy their model. But you should think long and hard about how they&#39;ve grown an online epicenter out into tens of thousands of real life participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, I don&#39;t think that just because you can identify these mechanisms, it makes their use disingenuous,b ut I will caution you with one more principle from the gamer&#39;s playdeck: &lt;strong&gt;Beware the Moral Hazard of Game Play&lt;/strong&gt;. The Moral Hazard is, again from TC, &#34;the risk that by rewarding people manipulatively in a game you remove the actual moral value of the action and replace it with an ersatz game-based reward.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s in this final warning, though, that I find the truly satisfying answer to McGonigal&#39;s problem  and why I love the Crossfit example so much. When you really do come up with an elegant blend of real-world and virtual cross-platform companion gaming, you create the best motivation for the healthiest action. That is what I believe all movement educators should strive for.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with the Old....Business Model</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 16:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Exit&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2245/2089485151_17f142a726_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s the end of the year and it&#39;s time to get out of old habits and mindsets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here&#39;s my prediction for the best business model for independent fitness and wellness pros, for the next DECADE. Yeah, I think it&#39;s going to take a few years to unfold, but the groundwork has been laid:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-514&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more brick-and-mortar businesses&lt;/strong&gt;. Trust me, I know what it&#39;s like to cut a $10,000 rent check each month. That&#39;s over with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more separation between in-person and on-line.&lt;/strong&gt; I read an article the other day that referred to &#39;90&#39;s style &#34;clicks-and-mortar&#34; business, e.g. Walmart.com for Walmart. You&#39;ve got to move past your website as a calling card for your services, even if you &#34;have really good content&#34;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more big barriers to scaling up your business.&lt;/strong&gt; This is great news. It&#39;s so easy to manage all the clients in your universe in a systematic way, through crm, email marketing, and interactive training apps like Trainerfly (ahem!), that the little guy or independent gal, can make it all by themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more one-size fits all products.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the same kind of dinosaur as a physical location. You might have some good reasons to put out video products (like standardizing a curriculum, for example), but you better have a way to tailor it to your clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more professional athlete fantasy.&lt;/strong&gt; You don&#39;t have to go pro or get sponsored or anything like that to make a decent living.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Welcome to the professional educator reality.&amp;Acirc;  I believe that the movement educator who is committed to honing a craft can make a real living. We all work really, really hard in our practice and now it&#39;s going to be possible to build a business around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at any public health statistics. Do you see a lack of movement in our society? Are we aging? Unhealthy? Totally divorced from the inherent human joys of movement? Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So those of us out there carrying the flag for better life through movement need to speak up. But we need to adapt too. We need to meet people where they are at, offer them chunks of wellness they can digest, and slowly change the conversation. And while we&#39;re at it, we need to make a living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is within reach in the next year or five years or ten years. You just need to start today with a little mental shift. Step into 2011 with some fresh perspective. You will be well rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exit photo courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/heathbrandon/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;heathbrandon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Business Thought Experiment</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 19:35:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m working strictly on a hunch here, but I think there&#39;s a connection between the sentiment I tried to express &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/03/technology-and-all-that-heavenly-glory/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; about not getting lost in the bells and whistles of technology, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/12/24/hybrid-startup/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; about &#34;hybrid businesses&#34;.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-501&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One Foot in the Virtual World, One Foot in the Real World&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to&amp;Acirc;  the author, Glenn Kelman, a hybrid business has &#34;one foot in the virtual world and one foot in the real world.&#34; However, &#34;this isn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t&amp;Acirc; the old &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;clicks-and-mortar&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; concept from the 1990s,  which put web glitter on an old-school business, building Walmart.com  for Walmart. A hybrid business is built entirely from scratch, to be  innovative in its online technology and its real-world operations.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m trying to envision how to adapt &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brooklinetaichi.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt; to the hybrid model or see how &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trainerfly&lt;/a&gt; fundamentally addresses this shift.&amp;Acirc;  Here are some thoughts along those lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right now, BTC is definitely in the &#34;clicks and mortar&#34; mindset. The purpose of the website is to tell people about classes and when they take place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trainerfly could fall into the same trap by simply mirroring the live training sessions, as a &#34;back-up copy&#34; of what happened in real life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of the more interesting possibilities I&#39;ve been exploring with Trainerfly and online learning have allowed me to open up live teaching &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;to people outside of my usual geographic reach&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The value proposition for trainers and their clients might be better in a hybrid.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact on Your Value Proposition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point deserves some illustration: think of the last time you or a friend joined a gym and got &#34;free&#34; personal training sessions with your new membership. If it&#39;s been a while, maybe you go through some exercises with the trainer and work out a plan. Great. But now here comes the awkward part. They offer you a $300 option or a $1,000 option. Everyone goes into high pressure mode, you squirm out, and the trainer loses another sale.&amp;Acirc;  Clearly, if high-pressure sales are involved, there&#39;s a dissonance between what you need and what the trainer is trying to offer you. Is there a middle-ground that works for both of you? I&#39;m guessing that if the trainer&#39;s only option is live training, then the answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sales terms, closing the sale came down to offering you an &#34;A or B offer&#34;, but the trainer had the wrong &#34;A or B&#34;. Both missed your real need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a hybrid live and online training model, I don&#39;t see how the trainer in this example (I don&#39;t know which side of the interchange you&#39;re likely to be on, probably both at some point), could offer much variety in terms of their &#34;A or B offer&#34;. The choice was only between more or fewer session, not a different type of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that&#39;s from a marketing and sales point of view. What about an educational point of view?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shifting Your Teaching Model&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The shift toward a hybrid business model is critically important for independent movement educators. We are constrained by one major factor: our limited teaching time. The problem is that you develop a body of knowledge that is vastly bigger than the mechanism for sharing it, one-on-one time with a client. Your students/clients can&#39;t absorb everything you put out in a live training session, but what if the hybrid model makes your knowledge more easily digestible? What if you can share all the information you&#39;ve refined a little bit at a time, in a way that decouples the actual sharing from your live time with clients? I think the hybrid model lies in that direction....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading Kelman&#39;s article, I&#39;m more and more convinced that this is the way to go for movement educators. I&#39;ve already tried to articulate what I&#39;ll now think of as &#34;hybrid strategies&#34; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/earn-an-extra-10000-this-year/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a related note, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/&#34;&gt;&#34;Enterprise of One&#34; &lt;/a&gt;theory here. It&#39;s the crumbling barriers of entry to business technology that are making all of this possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become an Enterprise of One </title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 09:04:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over at TechCrunch, Stephen Martin lays out his thesis about an interesting turning point for entrepreneurs in this economic climate. I could quote the piece at length, but I think this part is especially important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;These business mavericks live by a new dynamic of success &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; unique  individual strengths, expertise and credibility &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; fueled by today&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s  cultural and technological changes. In this new dimension of business  lies the secret to success in our transformed world of commerce. Armed  with a new viewpoint, and the tools to make a difference, these  entrepreneurs run their businesses based on the central principle that  once all of the barriers to entry, transaction costs and other hurdles  are stripped away by technology and cultural changes, an individual&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s  strengths and weaknesses are primarily what determine his or her  success.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve been trying to put my finger on something like this for a while and I think he says it really well. It&#39;s cheaper than ever to start a business and run a business because of all the technology small business owners can use to leverage their time.&amp;Acirc;  It&#39;s easier to communicate with lots and lots of people and instead of being buried in the back office, to quote Stephen again, &#34;the opportunities provided by the transformation to an online business  landscape...have left individual strengths, passions and  expertise as the only distinguishing factors remaining in an  individual&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s or business&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; success. Who you are as a person, and your  expertise and passions, are more important than ever. In fact, they  drive your own personal enterprise.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full article &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/12/27/entrepreneurs-great-reset/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find Your True Fans</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/21/find-your-true-fans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2010 09:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/21/find-your-true-fans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.static.flickr.com/30/54812349_b12966dcf7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;1,000 True Fans&#34; width=&#34;350&#34; height=&#34;256&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; If you&#39;ve never read Kevin Kelly&#39;s piece called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kk.org/thetechnium/archives/2008/03/1000_true_fans.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;1,000 True Fans&lt;/a&gt;, I suggest you hop on that link and read it. When you come back, you can read some of my thoughts on the issue, but I probably won&#39;t blow your mind the way Kelly will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, are you back? Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what I think stands out in his article for the aspiring &#34;Movement Education Professional&#34; (more on that term below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I don&#39;t know about you, but the long tail map is incredibly reassuring to me. I think whenever anyone is trying to run a small business, you look around and see &#34;the big guys&#34; and try to copy them. That&#39;s a totally unrealistic approach and going that route is totally disheartening. You can&#39;t behave like a big business at all: you don&#39;t have the same division of labor, you can&#39;t spend on advertising to build brand recognition, you can&#39;t fire an under-performing employee (what? cut off your left arm when sales tank???). You have to operate in a totally different way, but where is the model for how that&#39;s supposed to be done? Most of the people that would model for you, other successful small businesses, are too busy running their businesses!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So back to the long tail, Kelly says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am suggesting there is a home for creatives in between poverty and  stardom. Somewhere lower than stratospheric bestsellerdom, but higher  than the obscurity of the long tail. I don&#39;t know the actual true  number, but I think a dedicated artist could cultivate 1,000 True Fans,  and by their direct support using new technology, make an honest  living.&amp;Acirc;  I&#39;d love to hear from anyone who might have settled on such a  path.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As soon as you start looking at that in-between space, so many things open up. I like to think about this space when I&#39;m out in public. Sit on a busy street corner for 10 minutes and watch how many people go by. Do they all make a living? Do plenty of them make a comfortable living? Do you know them all? Yes. Yes. No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does that mean? &lt;strong&gt;It means that there is so much room in between for you to serve the needs of people who can pay for your service. &lt;/strong&gt;At Brookline Tai Chi, our database has over 10,000 names of people who have taken classes or inquired about classes at some point. You know what&#39;s amazing about that? Every 8 weeks, 30-50 &lt;em&gt;brand new&lt;/em&gt; people come through our door to start classes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the boring conclusion to all this is: &#34;there is a market out there for your services&#34;, but Kelly raises the stakes. It&#39;s not just a &#34;market&#34;. There are potentially raving, hard-core fans of what you do out there. You have to go find them and you have to find ways to engage them. I wrote in more detail about the &#34;universe&#34; of your fans &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/06/your-marketing-universe/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but on the Trainerfly blog, I just published &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2010/12/20/the-movement-education-professionals-manifesto/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&#34;The Movement Education Professional&#39;s Manifesto&#34;&lt;/a&gt;. The Manifesto is much more in line with the idea that passion driving a craft (in this case, your movement practice), should lead to engaging other people who get similarly excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think if you agree with premise of the Manifesto, about what movement means in your own life, and you&#39;ve taken the leap to teach professionally, then you&#39;ll see how important it is to take another big step and start finding your 1,000 True Fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/yourlocaldave/&#34;&gt;YourLocalDave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>