<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>small-business on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/categories/small-business/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in small-business on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/small-business/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Build Yourself a Pyramid</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/05/09/build-yourself-a-pyramid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2011 10:00:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/05/09/build-yourself-a-pyramid/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m not talking about a polygon with triangular faces or a marketing scam to rope your friends in. I&#39;m talking about The Pyramid Method, laid out by Cal Newport on his blog, Study Hacks. Newport tells the story of a friend of a friend&#39;s journey to becoming a professional hip-hop artist. The key, he claims, was that the friend, Chris, followed the Pyramid Method -- named for the hip-hop club, The Pyramid, where he honed his craft.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Brookline Tai Chi Fulfills Five Core Human Drives</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/25/how-brookline-tai-chi-fulfills-five-core-human-drives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2011 10:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/25/how-brookline-tai-chi-fulfills-five-core-human-drives/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s been on my mind a lot in the past month that Brookline Tai Chi is approaching its 20th anniversary. With a rough calculation, that also means that we are approaching having taught 10,000 students in that time span. I can&#39;t decide which one of those milestones is going to look better on the big banner out front. How about &#34;10,000 People Relaxed&#34;?
In light of reaching these major institutional marks, I&#39;ve also been wondering about the underlying mechanisms that have given the school such an amazing run so far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Posted from Trainerfly: Launching an Online Course</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2011 10:36:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</guid>
      <description>Check out this post from the Trainerfly blog. I talk to teachers and trainers all the time who want move beyond their live events, but the number of steps it takes, and the technology required to make it work seem overwhelming. Hopefully, I&#39;ve made a little dent in that perception!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 3</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 10:19:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</guid>
      <description>So far in this series we&#39;ve been talking about adapting your teaching style and the structure of your teaching business to fit the needs of your students. Now I want to look at a trait that all of the best teachers I&#39;ve studied with share, which is a work capacity they can turn on like a fire hose. If your work capacity only comes out like water from a dripping faucet, you won&#39;t be able to be &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 2</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2011 14:33:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/</guid>
      <description>In Part 1 of this series, we talked about the social nature of wanting to belong to something bigger than yourself as one possible drive for learning tai chi. The social drive is a major aid teachers can rely on to build their base of students. Another one, that we&#39;ll discuss here is our habitual drive, i.e. we are creatures of habit. That can be a good thing when it comes to maintaining a student base, but it is also the first major hurdle you have to clear as a teacher when it comes to getting new students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 1</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2011 10:42:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Over the weekend, Energy Arts Instructor Jess O&#39;Brien was in town, teaching at BTC. We got to spend some time together and talk about teaching, studying with different teachers, and trying to run a teaching business. One thing that we came back to again and again was how difficult it is to build up a student base. I think I know why.
People are Lazy, Social, and Creatures of Habit</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pros and Cons of Automation</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 09:32:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</guid>
      <description>Pro: My Car Broke Down and I Was Actually Happy about It
I guess I need to explain that a little more. I wasn&#39;t really happy that it broke down. I was on the way to Maine to teach the tai chi group in Farmington, so that sucked. And it was the clutch the completely died, so I knew it was going to be a few dollars to repair. But that was actually part of the silver lining.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Feedback from Trainerfly Beta</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 08:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</guid>
      <description>Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve gotten Trainerfly out into people&#39;s hands and I&#39;ve been learning some really interesting lessons. I think it was easy for me to get wrapped up in how I&#39;ve evolved it as a tool in my business over the last two years and lose perspective on how other people might be trying to add it into their business from scratch, with none of that prior history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Highlights from &#34;How Great Entrepreneurs Think&#34;</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/02/highlights-from-how-great-entrepreneurs-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 08:20:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/02/highlights-from-how-great-entrepreneurs-think/</guid>
      <description>Writing for Inc. Magazines Great Entrepreneur&#39;s series, Leigh Buchanan breaks down a fascinating study that pits successful entrepreneurs against career corporate managers in a thought experiment.&amp;Acirc; The study strikes a big chord with me because so many of the things I think are necessary running a small, customer-focused service business are exactly the kinds of things the entrepreneurs describe doing -- but here&#39;s the catch, by &#34;successful entrepreneurs&#34;, the author means: 15+ years of experience starting successful and unsuccessful ventures and at the time the study was done, the entrepreneurs were running companies with revenue between $200 million and $65 billion a year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Cycles</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 14:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m coming to another big teaching cycle in Trainerfly and I think this short clip of David Heinemeier Hansson speaking at Stanford&#39;s Entrepreneurship Corner is really useful to frame the mindset:

I know the point in the clip above is more about a strategy to take when you look at the &#34;big guys&#34;, but I really feel like the alternating cycles of &#34;spending&#34; and &#34;teaching&#34; are relevant here. We just went through a &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossfit&#39;s Brilliant use of Game Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/04/crossfits-brilliant-use-of-game-mechanics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2011 06:51:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/04/crossfits-brilliant-use-of-game-mechanics/</guid>
      <description>Background: Recently, TechCrunch featured an article about the playdeck they use at SCVNGR that outlines the mechanics of gameplay. The article cites at TED talk by game designer Jane McGonigal, which I talk about here.
I was a little disappointed with McGonigal&#39;s conclusion, because she basically offered up the solution as specially-themed video games to leverage the power of game mechanics, or &#34;gameplay superpowers&#34;, to do good in the real world and incite behavior change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with the Old....Business Model</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 16:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s the end of the year and it&#39;s time to get out of old habits and mindsets.
So, here&#39;s my prediction for the best business model for independent fitness and wellness pros, for the next DECADE. Yeah, I think it&#39;s going to take a few years to unfold, but the groundwork has been laid:
 No more brick-and-mortar businesses. Trust me, I know what it&#39;s like to cut a $10,000 rent check each month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Business Thought Experiment</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 19:35:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m working strictly on a hunch here, but I think there&#39;s a connection between the sentiment I tried to express here about not getting lost in the bells and whistles of technology, and this article about &#34;hybrid businesses&#34;.
One Foot in the Virtual World, One Foot in the Real World
According to&amp;Acirc; the author, Glenn Kelman, a hybrid business has &#34;one foot in the virtual world and one foot in the real world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become an Enterprise of One </title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 09:04:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</guid>
      <description>Over at TechCrunch, Stephen Martin lays out his thesis about an interesting turning point for entrepreneurs in this economic climate. I could quote the piece at length, but I think this part is especially important:
These business mavericks live by a new dynamic of success &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; unique individual strengths, expertise and credibility &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; fueled by today&#39;s cultural and technological changes. In this new dimension of business lies the secret to success in our transformed world of commerce.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find Your True Fans</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/21/find-your-true-fans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2010 09:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/21/find-your-true-fans/</guid>
      <description>If you&#39;ve never read Kevin Kelly&#39;s piece called 1,000 True Fans, I suggest you hop on that link and read it. When you come back, you can read some of my thoughts on the issue, but I probably won&#39;t blow your mind the way Kelly will.
Ok, are you back? Good.
Here&#39;s what I think stands out in his article for the aspiring &#34;Movement Education Professional&#34; (more on that term below).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>