<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-gates-dissolving-series on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/energy-gates-dissolving-series/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy-gates-dissolving-series on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/energy-gates-dissolving-series/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>When to Follow a Practice Recipe and When to Reflect on Your Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 09:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>In this video, we&#39;re talking about building up the skill of Outer Dissolving in your standing qigong practice.
When you start out, it pays to follow a recipe - a set of instructions that lead through a certain procedure physically, energetically, and with your mind. However, there are times you want to break away from the recipe and times you&#39;ll want to reflect on your experience verbally -- but there are good and bad ways to do both.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reporting Live from the Beach</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/12/reporting-live-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 10:38:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/12/reporting-live-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m on day 4 of daily practice by the ocean, but it&#39;s more than that. We&#39;re staying right on the beach, so I get to soak up the energy of the ocean pretty much all day long.
Now, I didn&#39;t used to have any sense for what &#34;the energy of the ocean&#34; meant and like pretty much everything else energetic, I&#39;m sure my sense for it will evolve even more, but I want to share my experiences from this week with you anyway.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Recipe for Rewarding Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/30/the-recipe-for-rewarding-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 09:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/30/the-recipe-for-rewarding-practice/</guid>
      <description>&#34;Is it better to structure your practice to stay with one energy gate, such as the crown, until you feel some dissolving happening there, or should you just keep moving through the gates week by week moving onto another gate?&#34;
Excellent questions like this one keep pouring in. Thank you for sharing your practice experiences with me. I know other folks who read the blog really appreciate it too.
I love hearing from you guys, especially when your questions are grounded in exploration, practice and thoughtful reflection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dissolving, Breathing, Structure, and Stillness: Follow-Up Q&amp;A</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/23/dissolving-breathing-structure-and-stillness-follow-up-qa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 08:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/23/dissolving-breathing-structure-and-stillness-follow-up-qa/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to everyone who reached out with questions about the first standing audio practice in the Energy Gates Dissolving series.
I want to share some of the questions with you here. Please let me know if you have any follow-up questions or comments or think there is anything the needs clarification. Hopefully we can approach this series together as an ongoing learning process!
What&#39;s the Difference between Outer Dissolving, Downward Dissolving, and Sinking?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting at the Crown of the Head</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/16/starting-at-the-crown-of-the-head/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 14:13:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/16/starting-at-the-crown-of-the-head/</guid>
      <description>If you read last week&#39;s post on standing qigong and the Energy Gates book, or better yet, you can stand comfortably &#34;just feeling&#34; for 15-20 minutes, you&#39;re probably ready to embark on the downward dissolving process.
This week, I want to help you get started.
I recorded a guided practice mp3 to get you through the first workout in the Energy Gates series: Feeling the Gate at the Crown of the Head.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>