<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mobility on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/mobility/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in mobility on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/mobility/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Arm Swing And The Force Transmission Problem</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 08:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of your practice goals should be to be able to make sense of other people&#39;s movement patterns. Learning how to watch someone move, and see what&#39;s going on, is going to give you really valuable information that you can then apply to your own practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following video clip, I demonstrate two different gait patterns, with different arm swings. If you can start to see how the arm swing differs between the two, you&#39;ll start to gain some valuable insight into how to assess and correct your own movement imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the clip and then we&#39;ll look at some of the implications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3165&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said at the beginning of the clip, your body adapts to postural changes instantaneously to find the most efficient way of dissipating force that comes into your skeletal structure. This principle was first explained to me by Dr. Eric Cobb, creator of &lt;a href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13500&#34;&gt;Z Health Performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you can see excessive (or deficient) movement in someone&#39;s whole-body pattern, you can pretty reliably draw the conclusion that they need some isolated movement tune-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But, the site of the abnormal movement is not the problem area.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always remember that principle. Was there something wrong with my left arm in the video clip? No, it started swinging more because the right arm was restricted. We changed the right arm and created excessive swing in the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there is a lot more to be said for how you begin to see the connections and determine what needs to move more or less to make the whole body move more efficiently. For now, though, I want you to try a little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Field Test Your Ability to See&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a title=&#34;APR 092 by chiolachic, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/chio/2432915922/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3091/2432915922_d36e45be2a_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;APR 092&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Brookline Tai Chi is located at mile 23 of the Boston Marathon. People run up and down Beacon Street all day long. As we were working on our ability to see these patterns, a friend and I would sit on the front steps of Brookline Tai Chi to watch runners and walkers come and go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a good spot with lots of running traffic and look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differences in swing between left and right arms from behind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How high each foot comes up behind the body -- can you see the sole of the shoe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Torso rotation -- is it more pronounced to one side?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excessive head movement in any particular direction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Stirring&#34; with the arm -- making a circle out to the side instead of coming straight back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Loops&#34; in the lower leg -- circles instead of straight up and down movement&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The challenge with seeing these patterns is that we very easily integrate this information and experience is as &#34;someone running.&#34; We don&#39;t stop to consciously parse the different parts of their movement. For the most part, it&#39;s a good thing that we take in chunks of information, instead of individual pieces. Think of how daunting it would be to have to record each data point and consciously put it together. You&#39;d never make it down the street!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, if you want to really hone your ability to see, correct, and improve movement patterns, you have to train to break the patterns back down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turn the Legs to Turn the Body</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 09:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you see a series of exercises, you can either look at what&#39;s common to all of them, or how they are different. In this video, I go through several variations of turning exercises, where I&#39;m using the connection between the legs and the spine to drive body movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people will look at the arms in each exercise and say, &#34;those are not the same movements&#34; and that&#39;s true, but they would be missing the most important part: &lt;strong&gt;how the legs turn the body&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3517&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GoqiuidbvGM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GoqiuidbvGM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Same Motor, Different Attachments&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In order to really see what&#39;s going on in this video, you need to think of a motor that can be fitted with different attachments. In our kitchen, for example, we have a mixer that can blend food together, make dough, whisk, grind meat, or cut pasta. The motor is the same in each case, but for every special application, you attach a different tool to the end of the motor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you watch the video above, imagine that I am doing exactly the same thing. The legs and the waist are the motor and the angle of the turn, the arm movements, and the plane that force is expressed along are all the various attachments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[nonmember]Inner Form members, &lt;a title=&#34;Member Login&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/member-login/&#34;&gt;log in&lt;/a&gt; to read the full breakdown of the video and get your practice assignment.[/nonmember]&lt;br /&gt;
[ismember]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Psoas Connection&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The easiest way to start to develop this connection is to understand how the psoas muscles connect the legs to the spine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, these big muscles run from the upper part of your thigh and attach to each side of your spine. They work like a steering mechanism. If you want to rotate the spine to the right, the psoas on the right contracts, pulling your spine that way. To turn left, the right side relaxes and the left side contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the beginning of this mechanism in the first exercise in the video, the Peg Board drill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned the Peg Board drill from Z Health founder Dr. Eric Cobb. The Peg Board concept is that as one heel pushes down, the other rises up, as if it were pushed from below by a peg. So we imagine standing on a &#34;peg board&#34; to do this exercise. The goal is to find the connection from one leg into the spine and through the pelvis to the other leg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next exercises expands on the Peg Board by adding more turning (0:12). Here, I&#39;m letting the pull through the leg turn the hips. You start the Peg Board looking a little like Elvis, but here you try to smooth it out. Think of the alternative. When you see people turn from the shoulders or even the hips, the body is not as smoothly integrated. What we develop from the Peg Board exercise is having a clear, connected, swiveling base of support. The rest of the body can come along for the ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next (0:16), let the pivot go through the legs completely, to bring the hips around through a 180 degree arc. With this full pivot, you begin to perform something that looks very much like foundation training in many Northern Chinese martial arts. The &#34;bow stance&#34; or &#34;gong bu&#34; is a commonly trained posture and now you can see how it is used to develop whole-body turning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, you can see the evolution of the psoas connection into whole-body turning from this simple 4-part progression. Next, we need to look at the arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Planes of Force&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Watch the way the arms move&amp;Acirc;  through the various exercises in the video. You will see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forward force, as in the first punching exercise (0:18)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Horizontal force, as in the bagua cutting exercise (0:36)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vertical force, as in the double teacup exercise (1:26)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combinations of force vectors like Cloud Hands and Rolling the Ball (2:02)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The cool thing about the leg power you develop this way is that you can express opposite force vectors simultaneously or with a slight change in intention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the bagua coiling exercise (1:10) is usually looked at as a drilling out with the fingers. However, if you pay attention to the elbow on the way back in, you can turn it into a pulling exercise instead. A similar thing happens with the teacup exercise. There is a powerful elbow drop hidden in the falling arm, but most people emphasize the hand or wrist coming in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi Cloud Hands is the ultimate test of your ability not to fixate on one particular force vector. The way it is organized, you slip through the four basic energies of Peng, Lu, Ji, and An, doing them in pairs. You have to find a way to clearly express each one, and then effortlessly change to the next. In my view, this is why &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora thinks of Cloud Hands as the ultimate practice integrator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The best way to develop this connection is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to get the hang of the Peg Board drill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the action of the legs in the Peg Board drill take you through bigger and bigger turning ranges until you get to 180 degrees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick one of your favorite exercises that fits this paradigm (standing qigong doesn&#39;t count for this exercise!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale back the exercise so that it doesn&#39;t feel like you are &#34;doing anything&#34; with the arms (very light &lt;a title=&#34;Three Swings from Opening the Energy Gates Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/three-swings-from-opening-the-energy-gates-qigong/&#34;&gt;First Swing &lt;/a&gt;works well here)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slowly work back up into the full shape of the movement, until you are reasonably confident that you are not using your arms to do the motion, but instead the movement of the legs and waist&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[/ismember]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read Faster, Move Better</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Eyercize is a free, web-based reading pacer that turns any text into a speed reading exercise. But, you can do more than just read faster using Eyercize. You can actually improve how you move, if you follow these simple training guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3457&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Part of the reason I&#39;m so excited about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eyercize.com&#34;&gt;Eyercize&lt;/a&gt; is how easy it is to use. Check out this video demo where I show you how to turn any web page into a eye training exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/rHKcP476yjY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/rHKcP476yjY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the creators of Eyercize explain on their site, most people probably haven&#39;t trained their reading skills since they first learned to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading faster, using the method that Eyercize is built on, relies on three interdependent skills. Basically, you read in chunks of letters. As your eye moves across the line, it takes a snapshot of a group of letters, which your brain processes, and then you move on to a new chunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading speed is determined by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The size of the chunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How quickly you jump from chunk to chunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much you keep moving forward, without going back to re-read the same chunk again&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eyercize trains you to expand the size of the chunk, move faster to the next chunk, and not go back and re-read the same chunk over again by moving the highlighter along at a set speed.&amp;Acirc;  If you really want to understand the technical details, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eyercize.com/home/tools&#34;&gt;add Eyercize to your bookmarks&lt;/a&gt;, hop over to the Wikipedia page about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eye_movement_in_language_reading&#34;&gt;Eye Movements in Reading&lt;/a&gt;, and read through it in the Eyercize reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Role of the Eyes in Movement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Saccadic movement, the technical term for the eyes moving rapidly side to side, like you do in reading, is one of the main visual skills that your brain uses to get information about your surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are unaware of just how much spatial and positional information we take in, but your body adopts a postural response based on the quality of information your visual system feeds your brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-3477&#34; title=&#34;Postural strain can come from lack of visual stamina&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/02/shutterstock_18400546-300x199.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lack of visual stamina can lead to postural strain.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;199&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can think about it as another case of &#34;garbage in, garbage out&#34;, but I prefer the positive statement that if you give your nervous system the best possible information, you get the best performance out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more, I&#39;ve written about &lt;a title=&#34;The Strange Link between Eyes and Movement&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/30/the-strange-link-between-eyes-and-movement/&#34;&gt;the link between eyes and movement&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/&#34;&gt;how the eyes influence flexibility&lt;/a&gt; (at 4:00 in the video) , and &lt;a title=&#34;2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/&#34;&gt;how poor eye movement can lead to neck pain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, though, the most important thing to know is that there is actually a bio-feedback test you can use to tell if new information is &#34;good information&#34; or &#34;garbage&#34;. In this case, when we are using a tool like Eyercize, we will use a bio-feedback test to tell when we&#39;ve hit the limit of productive eye work. More isn&#39;t always better. Especially with visual training, you can easily do too much in one sitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one of many bio-feedback tests we use in Z Health to determine if we should keep training or take a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Test Range of Motion Before and After&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Range of motion, using something as simple as a toe-touch, can tell you a lot about the state of your nervous system. You can also use shoulder flexion (like I demonstrate &lt;a title=&#34;What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) or neck rotation, which is especially instructive if you notice one side is a lot tighter than the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all about the little indicators that the fight-or-flight response is kicking in. If your nervous system perceives threat, it reigns in range of motion. Just think of the protective gesture of the &#34;fetal position&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our premise for this bio-feedback test is that if range of motion increase, and you feel looser and more flexible after performing the reading exercises, you have a green light to continue. As soon as you notice a decrease in your range of motion, stop, rest, and do something to restore the balance, like I recommend below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get your baseline for your reading practice session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand up straight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bend forward and try to touch your toes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice how far you go and which muscles feel tight first&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You&#39;re going to perform exactly the same exercise after you do 1 minute of speed reading with the pacer. Then retest your range of motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Red Light, Green Light&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Did you notice a change before and after 1 minute of speed reading? If not, double your time and try it again. Repeat this process until you notice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any change in range of motion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Postural changes while you read, like slumping in your chair or craning your neck&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you can comfortably do 2-3 minutes of speed reading with no noticeable change in posture or pre- and post-testing, then you are ready to increase the variables in the reader. Those are all the controls along the left side of the Eyercize interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Balance Foveal Work with Peripheral Work&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eyercize trains one of your foveal vision skills. &#34;Foveal&#34; means you are using the retina to focus on something. The opposite skill set is peripheral vision, and you can use peripheral vision work to give yourself a break from too much focusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a really simple peripheral drill you can do right at your desk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring your arms up in front of you and touch your hands together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start wiggling your index finger on each hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slowly move your arms apart and out to the sides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As your hands move away from each other, keep wiggling your fingers, but look straight ahead -- here&#39;s where you activate your peripheral vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue to track your wiggling fingers using only your peripheral vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can move your hands up and down independently in your peripheral field, but be sure to keep your eyes straight ahead&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a couple of minutes of peripheral work should be a nice balance to intense focus work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use Eyercize with posture in mind, you&#39;ll see some great results in reading speed and your overall quality of movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2011 08:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frozen shoulder is one of those terms that people accept with resignation and it seems like a plausible explanation...until you start to poke around in your own nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve ever been told you have a frozen shoulder, I urge you to look a little bit beyond the (overly) simple mechanical explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I&#39;m not diagnosing your shoulder from a YouTube video, but I just want you to ask a few more questions and try these two experiments:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2746&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do about a Frozen Shoulder&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you tried the experiments in the video and saw some changes in your shoulder movement, your best bet is to find someone who can assess your movement on a global (whole-body) level. This person, &lt;a title=&#34;Find a Z Health Trainer near you&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=1347&#34;&gt;like a certified Z Health instructor&lt;/a&gt;, for example, will be able to see what body parts are not moving when they should be and which ones are when they shouldn&#39;t be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can alleviate a lot of &#34;frozen&#34; anything in the body with this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&#39;t find an instructor near you, the next best thing is to begin a head-to-toe, full-body mobility program, &lt;strong&gt;focusing on everything else except your frozen shoulder &lt;/strong&gt;(&lt;a title=&#34;Z Health R-Phase Manual and DVD&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13446&#34;&gt;the Z Health R-Phase series is the best way to go about this&lt;/a&gt;). The number one rule you need to follow is &#34;never move into pain.&#34; Instead, you will re-educate your body and all its moving pieces, taking the burden off the parts that are already working too hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairly quickly (like, within a few good training sessions), you will see a change in how you move, 90% of the time. If you keep it up, you&#39;ll prevent further aggravation along these lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few more ideas if you&#39;re looking for other ways to &lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;GET MOVING&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Z Health Exercises for Stiff Joints in the Morning</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2011 08:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In just ten minutes of head-to-toe movement, you can get rid of stiff joints in the morning. What&#39;s the secret? There isn&#39;t one really...you just have to move every single joint. Z Health exercises for joint mobility give you an easy template to use to get this done, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this example of head-to-toe joint mobility: &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2581&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jCUM8kZ-etY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jCUM8kZ-etY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The metronome-like quality of the music got me. Sorry! You know why I like &lt;a title=&#34;Metronome Mobility&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/14/metronome-mobility/&#34;&gt;metronomes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you do a mobility flow like this, with the goal of loosening up your stiff joints, especially first thing in the morning, you want to follow these movement principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Movement Rules for Getting Rid of Stiff Joints in the Morning:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move Every Joint with Precision&lt;/strong&gt;: In the video above, I started with the fingers and worked back toward the spine, then down through the lower body. Each Z Health exercise is designed to target a specific joint. As much as possible, the rest of the body remains still while you isolate an individual joint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build Towards Flow:&amp;Acirc;  &lt;/strong&gt;When you&#39;re mastering the movement of any one joint, you&#39;ll start with straight-line movement, then do circles, and then progress to more flowing figure-8&#39;s. It&#39;s important to work in that order, because the linear movement almost always reveals places where you haven&#39;t developed good conscious control. You never find these places if you skip to figure-8&#39;s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never Move Into Pain: &lt;/strong&gt;Especially if you feel stiff in the morning, you might confuse &#34;waking up&#34; with &#34;being in pain.&#34; Never take yourself into painful ranges of motion. Instead, as you loosen up, your range of motion will increase. It&#39;s not unusual to notice a difference between the first and the third repetition in this regard. Remember: &lt;em&gt;being in pain will not alleviate your stiff joints&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With a morning mobility warm-up like this, you&#39;ll find yourself looser,&amp;Acirc;  more tuned-in to your body and ready to get moving. I often use the discipline of moving each body part head-to-toe as a way to trick myself into practicing more in-depth work when I&#39;m not really in the right frame of mind. Have you ever done that? Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress Reduction Techniques That Work in 5 Minutes or Less</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you have cultivated a daily practice that takes you into deep relaxation, it&#39;s helpful to have a set of stress reduction techniques &#34;that work in 5 minutes or less.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can pull these out during the day when you have a few minutes of downtime. If you are busy and really stressed out, these relaxation techniques can prevent your stress level from going through the roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try them and let me know what you think.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2540&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5 Minute Body Scan&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a few minutes of trying to tune into your body, instead of being stuck in your head, can help reduce the weight of some of the stress you are feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-2355&#34; title=&#34;basic standing qigong posture&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture-141x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; width=&#34;141&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standing posture pictured, here, do a 5-minute downward body scan, starting at the top of the head and working your way down, feeling height-by-height until you reach your feet.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First, set your posture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;place your feet hip-width apart, so your joints are aligned &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll feel the weight balanced evenly in each foot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lengthen the back of your neck, so the chin drops slightly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax your shoulders, as if the arms were slipping off the rib cage, to the left and right, not slouched forward or pulled back&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Next, settle in:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your breathing go smooth, so the turn-over from inhale to exhale feels natural and not forced&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Begin to scan:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bring your feeling awareness up to the crown of your head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;once you feel like you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve gathered your awareness to a single point, let your mind spread out through the crown of the head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give in to gravity and let your mind drop down the body, height-by-height, feeling front, sides, and back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your mind rest lightly on any sensations you feel as you scan, checking in, without trying to do anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work downward until you can feel your feet settle into the floor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more guidance on practicing this technique, check out &lt;a title=&#34;Settling in with Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;this article on Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt; (with a free guided-practice mp3 download).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Metronome Mobility&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This exercise is great for coordination and control and it&#39;s just distracting enough to let your nervous system reset its stress level by the time you are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s use this Z Health shoulder circle as an example for the metronome exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you feel comfortable performing the basic shoulder circle as in the video above, you&#39;ll need to set a metronome to 60 beats per minute. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a baseline for one repetition at your &#34;normal&#34; speed. How many beats?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, perform a circle at half your normal speed, or 2x as many beats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat this process, slowing down each time until the movement gets too choppy to be a smooth circle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now repeat the process getting faster each time instead of slower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you keep the rest of the body &#34;quiet&#34; -- you don&#39;t get any points for flailing around!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating this process for hip circles, ankle circles, or even finger/wrist/hand circles will work too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of metronome mobility as a stress reduction technique is to draw your mind and away from the mental and emotional pressures that are causing stress in the first place. Moving your body at different speeds provides novelty for your nervous system, which helps achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tai Chi Short Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; /&gt;When you do 5 minutes of tai chi, you have to change how you are practicing. You need to shift out of your normal &#34;training&#34; mindset, where you focus on little details, or work a principle over and over again until it clicks. That kind of deep practice mindset is great for 30 minutes or an hour of practice or more, but it&#39;s not going to do the trick in 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 5 minute practice for stress reduction, you need to focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moving smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making large, circular shapes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feeling the space around you, in your etheric field, not deep inside your body&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point, about putting your mind into your etheric field, might sound a little strange. What you are trying to do is clear the energetic layer around your body. Think of it as where you interface with the world. If you can sweep everything clean here, then the stress doesn&#39;t have the chance to soak into your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Got More Stress Reduction Techniques?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The thing that all these techniques have in common is that they are designed to recharge your nervous system through physical and energetic circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you accomplish this same goal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share your stress reduction techniques in the comments below.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Doctor, A Runner, and A Meditator Walk into A Bar...</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 10:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And they&#39;re all in pain!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the aches and pains of moving around, you might be in pain from your day job, your vigorous exercise routine, or even a mindfulness practice that doesn&#39;t involve any movement. Ever wonder why? &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2285&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is exactly the same in each case: in your pre-conscious mind, you are basically trying to outsource your own movement patterns, from a body part that should be doing the job, to one that&#39;s willing to, even though it isn&#39;t designed for that job!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that doesn&#39;t completely make sense, watch this video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/nFvmbc5At-U?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/nFvmbc5At-U?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those aches and pains might be caused by one big inappropriate act of outsourcing. If you think that&#39;s what&#39;s going on, you should definitely check out the Joint Mobility tips over on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;Get Moving&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Strange Link between Eyes and Movement</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/30/the-strange-link-between-eyes-and-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2011 08:42:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/30/the-strange-link-between-eyes-and-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I find this topic so interesting. When you start playing with the way eyes influence movement, you begin to unlock connections in the body that you had no other way of accessing. I&#39;ve seen some pretty strange stuff, from pain pretty much vanishing, big muscles magically unlocking, or people being able to run, jump, or lift in dramatically different ways....all from a couple of eye exercises. I know it sounds weird, and I was right there with you until I experienced it in my own practice and taught it to other. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/EpmtplrEn9I?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/EpmtplrEn9I?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;This course is now available for free.&lt;/a&gt; Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing the &#34;Foundations of Relaxation&#34; Series</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2011 07:48:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a tai chi teacher and movement coach, I get to meet a lot of people who want to relax, slow down and have more energy for the things they love to do in life.  But there&#39;s a very common misconception that I encounter and I think it leads people to spend too much time chasing the wrong things when it comes to a relaxation practice.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-606&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Hopefully, this series will begin to clarify what the best way to start a relaxation practice is and how to most efficiently get the results you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the big mistake: people think that lots of hand-waving choreography, preferably done in a pristine setting, often to calming music, is the best way to become more relaxed. They&#39;re wrong. It&#39;s the best way to have a temporary escape from 24/7 habits that are creating more stress in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that you can change these underlying habits. Even though they are pre-conscious, you can learn to recognize them, test them, and alter them. And I can show you how that all works. This series will save you a lot of time and money to seeking me out in person, or wasting time on the wrong things with another qualified instructor. You can make major progress on your own, if you focus on three areas that I&#39;ll tell you about below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am putting together home-study courses for each of these areas, because they are subjects where you can make progress on your own, without the close guidance of an instructor, once you have the right information and a good practice system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can boost your energy, save a lot of discomfort, and begin the process of moving through life more gracefully, if you focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You See&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-610&#34; title=&#34;Your Picture May Be Fuzzy&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/02/TV-Snow-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Your Picture May Be Fuzzy&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How you see the world may be a little distorted. The eyes, or more accurately, vision governs how you interpret the physical space around you and how you respond to it (i.e. your posture and balance) way more than most people realize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we think of &#34;seeing&#34; something, we see it or we don&#39;t. Vision is a much more comprehensive, integrative act. In other words, seeing is what your eyes do mechanically, but vision is how your brain interprets the world coming at you. And your body reacts to that interpretation constantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these reactions and relationships are rooted in evolutionary survival mechanics, buried deep in your pre-conscious mind. But don&#39;t worry, there are some really clear ways to test how your body and eyes are working together and demonstrate clearly when the picture is fuzzy, even if you don&#39;t realize it right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest benefit of improving your visual skills is that, when your brain gets more information, it can react more efficiently. A small eye movement will replace a big body movement and simply put, to get from A to B will take less energy, so you&#39;ll have more energy to spend on something else or you&#39;ll get there faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 6-week course, you&#39;ll learn how to systematically test and observe what your body is doing subconsciously and improve how your brain interprets visual information. As your visual skills improve, your body will literally recalibrate how it moves through space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You Breathe&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-611&#34; title=&#34;Try Breathing through a Straw&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/02/Snorkel-201x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Try Breathing through a Straw&#34; width=&#34;201&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next area that I wish every single person would work on before they come see me is their breathing. Poor breathing dramatically reduces your energy level, encourages you to stay stressed out, and even impacts your mood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t believe me? Try walking around for the rest of your day today breathing only out of a straw. See how much energy you have for even the simplest things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a cultural level, our largely sedentary lifestyle has a direct impact on our breathing mechanism. See, good breathing is all about fully activating the diaphragm, creating a vacuum effect that fills the lungs and simultaneously pressurizes the abdomen, massaging the internal organs. In slumped seated posture, you limit the movement of the diaphragm. And no, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;good posture&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; with shoulders back and chest up doesn&#39;t fix the breathing problem. In fact, the way most people hold &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;good posture&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; makes the breathing problem worse --- they are trying to fill the lungs by expanding the chest to create more volume. Not only is this less effective than diaphragmatic breathing, but it actually mimics hyperventilation and triggers a stress response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to break the stress cycle and give yourself an internal tune up, is to learn the proper way to breath with the diaphragm and develop a consistent practice. Information alone doesn&#39;t do you any good...you have to be smart about making new habits. In the course, I will teach you how to do both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You Walk&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-612&#34; title=&#34;Bricks&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/02/bricks-300x229.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bricks&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;229&#34; /&gt;When you teach movement 3-4 hours a day, you get to see a lot of different people&#39;s ingrained movement patterns and there are some striking common themes. Most people who want to learn tai chi, for example, begin by moving in exactly the opposite way prescribed by the Tai Chi Classics. In the Classics it says &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the movements should start in the feet, be powered by the legs, steered by the waist and expressed in the hands.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Instead, everything is about leading from the upper body, with little to no connection to the legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it&#39;s no coincidence that there is an abundance of back pain, knee injuries and general inability move around freely in our culture, right? Right......&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say it all starts in the feet. Try walking around with heavy bricks as feet and see how that feels. Maybe you feel a pinch in your hip right away, or a tug on the back. Maybe you&#39;re lucky enough to feel a crick all the way up in your neck. Lucky indeed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;feet&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; course, I will teach you how to open your feet again, even if you think your feet are too flat to work right or your hips are too stiff. &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;But I have these little plastic things that I put in my shoes....&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Ok, if I told you to wear a full-body cast for the rest of your life because your aches and pains mean all those parts weren&#39;t supposed to be moving around, would you take me up on that offer? I&#39;m not knocking some foot support, but if you&#39;ve read this far, I think you know that I&#39;m focused on helping you change movement habits to have more energy and less pain. Immobile feet are part of a movement habit....and re-mobilizing the tiny little bones in your feet is an important new project for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll learn how to re-awaken the feet with self-massage and mobility exercises that will have you moving lighter, faster, and with a better bounce in your step. Just like the other courses in this series, everything is laid out in a 6-week format that blends learning new concepts gradually with systematic follow-up practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my teachers, Dr. Eric Cobb always says, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the body you have is the one you&#39;ve earned through how you move.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; In these courses, I will teach you how to move differently in order to feel differently. Most people will never realize the degree to which their pre-conscious patterns are impacting how they go through their day, but you&#39;ll be tuned in to a whole different set of signs that will help you: cultivate more energy, move with more ease, and have less pain.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>