<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-arts on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/categories/energy-arts/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy-arts on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/categories/energy-arts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Bruce Frantzis&#39; New Taoist Meditation Circle</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/17/bruce-frantzis-new-taoist-meditation-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2011 09:11:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/17/bruce-frantzis-new-taoist-meditation-circle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just started working with Bruce&#39;s new meditation program. I&#39;m very excited to hear him framing this home-study series in terms of rhythms, pacing, and long term development. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-627&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Every couple of weeks he&#39;s putting out new guided practice recordings, which I think will be easy to follow-through on and fresh enough to keep people tuned into their practice. I&#39;ll let you know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/content/taoist-meditation-circle-subscription&#34;&gt;Taoist Meditation Circle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#34;Get out of your head and into your body.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating Your Energy Arts Instructor Profile</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/23/updating-your-energy-arts-instructor-profile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 08:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/23/updating-your-energy-arts-instructor-profile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This one is for the Energy Arts Certified Instructors. The new EA website allows you to change the details of your instructor profile when you have a registered account. I think having accurate and updated information is helpful, especially if you decide to become an active contributor on the forum.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-567&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0tfICVfuq54?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0tfICVfuq54?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ba Gua Program Product Launch</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/11/ba-gua-program-product-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 06:46:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/11/ba-gua-program-product-launch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been working with the team at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Energy Arts&lt;/a&gt; on various projects, but mainly in the capacity as a community coordinator. Currently, my focus is on helping them get a new community discussion forum off the ground, but I also had the chance to participate in the launch of their new Ba Gua Mastery Program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ba Gua Mastery Program is a home-study program with information on circle-walking for meditation and martial arts. They&#39;ve drawn from a live instructor training Bruce taught in 2009, and turned out CDs, DVDs, print manuals...the whole works! It&#39;s been a monumental effort and in the future I&#39;ll be discussing how we&#39;re going to blend live teaching with all these materials at BTC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now though, I want to talk about their launch strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks, they&#39;ve been building interest by sending out related content without trying to sell the program directly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-290&#34; title=&#34;offer&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2010/11/offer.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;478&#34; height=&#34;589&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a screen capture from one of the launch pages on their website.&amp;Acirc;  They&#39;ve added to it as they released new content, so I&#39;ve got back and highlighted what they put out in what order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first piece was a video of Bruce talking about his different Ba Gua teachers in China. On the video page, they included a &#34;pre-launch notification&#34; email list sign-up. In a follow-up email, they reported that over 2000 people opted-in to that list. Not bad, considering that all of the launch copy says they&#39;ll only be selling 250 copies of the program!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second piece was an interview I conducted with Bruce and Richard Taubinger, who is overseeing the launch. We discussed more of the details of the practice itself and why people should be interested in ba gua as an art. I&#39;m not sure about email sign-ups or interest in the interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the most direct approach, they gave away some sample material from the product itself, just before the launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure how long this page will be up for, but here is the launch page itself: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/bagua-mastery-program-launch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/bagua-mastery-program-launch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I really like how they gradually, but persistently built interest in the launch, drawing from a list they&#39;ve spent considerable time growing and finally putting just enough urgency around buying (only 250 copies!) that they will hopefully convince the right people to act on it. We&#39;ll see!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>