<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>feet on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/feet/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in feet on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/feet/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaxing Your Feet to Find Your Root</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/04/10/relaxing-your-feet-to-find-your-root/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 08:44:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/04/10/relaxing-your-feet-to-find-your-root/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you settle into your practice each day, you should always give yourself a couple of minutes to just feel and see where your body, your energy, and your awareness are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one sense, each practice session is about bringing the rhythms of each of those into harmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s why Tai Chi and qigong can be so powerfully restorative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you take a couple of minutes to just &#34;settle in,&#34; you&#39;ll discover several possible things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your overall energy level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What feels active and open.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What feels stuck or sluggish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific body parts that are calling out, in good or bad ways.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finding New Space in the Feet&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The other day, I was settling in to practice and the soles of the feet really stood out (sorry!) from everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the toes were hanging from the feet in a way that reminded me of this famous photo of workers having lunch on the beam of the Empire State building. Weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.afterimagegallery.com/nytconstructionworkers.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; alt=&#34;nytconstructionworkers&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2014/04/nytconstructionworkers-300x274.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;274&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what I think was going on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My ankles were relaxed, allowing the balls of the feet to connect to the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The spaces between the toes opened up, allowing the individual toes to release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could feel each toe &#34;hanging&#34; and connecting the ground too.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And why was that like the workers on the beam?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more I stood and moved with this feeling, the more the ball of the foot -- the beam -- became a support structure I could sink into. The more I sunk into the ball of the foot, the more the toes -- all the workers up there on the beam -- relaxed and let go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, and this is the part that would freak me out if I were ever anywhere near the top of the Empire State building, &lt;strong&gt;the more I relaxed the more it felt like there was infinite space for my feet to relax down into&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn&#39;t that what&#39;s so amazing about the photo? The way that the workers are so relaxed and grounded, but they&#39;re dangling over hundreds of feet of empty space?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating Your Own Big Sensations from Tiny Spaces&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, I don&#39;t want you to go try to reproduce this sensation. Remember, I didn&#39;t set out to do it either. There is a way to practice that makes it more likely that you will have similar experiences, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The more time I&#39;ve spent getting familiar with interior space, through &lt;a title=&#34;Energy Gates Dissolving Series&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt;, the more these spaces have opened up. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trick is to go in with the goal of feeling, not necessarily &#34;opening&#34; or &#34;releasing&#34; or &#34;sinking.&#34; Those are all techniques that evolve from feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you feel, then as the structure, space, and relationships between areas of the body become more familiar, and your overall intention of sinking or rising meld with the well-mapped areas, experiences like this one just seem to pour out from deep inside the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you bumped into anything like this in your own practice? I&#39;m always curious to hear!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>