<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>chi-gung on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/chi-gung/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in chi-gung on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/chi-gung/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 09:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>When you set out to develop your internal energy using standing postures, there are two main ways you can go about it: by feel or by form.
Now, there will be a lot of overlap in these two broad approaches, like aligning your body with gravity without collapsing internally and progressively releasing and relaxing as you stand, but when it comes to the role of the mind, form and feel can be very different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Itch to Move Your Chi</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 08:48:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>We tend to think about our energy level like the money we have in the bank. You wake up in the morning, look in your energetic wallet and say, &#34;I&#39;ve got a lot of energy today&#34; or &#34;Man, I need 7 cups of coffee.&#34;
Or, to put it another way, thanks to this New Yorker cartoon:

In qigong, we think about &#34;having energy&#34; a little bit differently. Often, it&#39;s not just how much or how little, but how well is your energy circulating?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend last night about standing qigong and different meditation traditions that we had both tried.
When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dragon and Tiger Exercises for Activating the Lower Tantien</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 07:32:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re borrowing a technique from Dragon and Tiger qigong to try and get a better sense of the lower tantien. The lower tantien (&#34;dan-tee-en&#34;) is the energetic center of your physical body, located just below your navel, on the central axis of the body. If you dropped a line down from the crown of the head, through the body, and out the bottom of the pelvis, it would pass through the lower tantien.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong is Packed with Internal Content</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</guid>
      <description>This summer, Bruce Frantzis will be teaching a Marriage of Heaven and Earth Instructor training. Heaven and Earth was the first instructor training I attended in 2004 and I can still remember what a profound effect learning to &#34;pulse&#34; had on me.
Within the Energy Arts system, Heaven and Earth is considered a bridge from the basic to more advanced practices.
We discussed how Heaven and Earth works in an early episode of Qigong Radio, but I wanted to share this explanation from Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel with you too:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.
Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refining Your Opening and Closing</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 07:00:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</guid>
      <description>I remember the first time I really got a sense for &#34;opening and closing&#34; my joints. We were on a qigong retreat and the person who was helping me probably spent 20 minutes &#34;pulsing&#34; my wrist, so that the fluids in the joint were moving in a smooth, even way, alternately creating more and less space between the bones.
When you pulse, you&#39;re manipulating the fluid flows inside your body so that the spaces inside your body compress and expand.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The True Value of Your Qigong Practice</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/30/the-true-value-of-your-qigong-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2012 08:40:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/30/the-true-value-of-your-qigong-practice/</guid>
      <description>We live in a culture where doing more, having more, and working harder are valued above pretty much everything else.
This is a dangerous attitude, a linear approach to life that denies the need for rest and renewal.
Of course, if you constantly push yourself, you know it will lead to burnout. If you operate as if you have an infinite capacity to do and never rest, sooner or later you will get the message in some form that it is time to slow down.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 09:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m sure you&#39;ve spent time looking around YouTube for qigong and tai chi videos. According to their website, people upload 24 hours of video to YouTube every minute! No doubt you&#39;ve seen some crazy stuff. So how do you sift through all of it and more importantly, are there any qigong videos on YouTube worth watching?
The good news is, of course there are. And I&#39;ve put together a list of 5 good ones to get you started.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Challenge of the Three Swings</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 09:03:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/</guid>
      <description>The Three Swings from Energy Gates are some of the most challenging exercises to do well in the entire Energy Arts curriculum. You have to relax, maintain good alignment, and coordinate stepping and turning while moving faster than most other qigong exercises.
Let&#39;s talk a little bit about why the Three Swings are important and what you need to integrate to do them well.
Getting Started with the Three Swings</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 10:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/</guid>
      <description>There is no other book I return to more for my qigong practice than Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body by Bruce Frantzis. It&#39;s the one I consistently recommend to students and anyone who emails the school to inquire about starting a qigong practice before they have access to a teacher.
Here&#39;s how to get the most out of it, whether or not you have someone who can give you regular feedback on your practice:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow and Stabilizing the Mind with Craig Barnes</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 08:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</guid>
      <description>Stability and flow seem to be at odds with each other. Stability can mean rigidity, or at least, it seems to conjure up something fixed, sturdy, and unmoving. Flow isn&#39;t any of those things. It&#39;s fluid and changing. So how does Energy Arts Senior Instructor Craig Barnes blend the two so seamlessly?

Recently, Craig taught a workshop about awakening energetic sensitivity, drawn from principles of Dragon and Tiger Qigong. We worked a lot on the opening of the set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Twice a Day</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 04:32:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</guid>
      <description>So, I know I&#39;m writing this on vacation where the most pressing decision we make each day is whether to hike, kayak, or swim, but I&#39;m going to go ahead anyway and recommend that you practice twice a day. Here&#39;s why...

What I Learned from a Month-Long Tai Chi Intensive
After a month in England, practicing 10 hours a day at the Short Form Instructor Training this summer, I have a renewed appreciation for daily practice rhythm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Balance Practicing Multiple Qigong Sets</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/23/how-to-balance-practicing-multiple-qigong-sets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2011 10:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/23/how-to-balance-practicing-multiple-qigong-sets/</guid>
      <description>This post is the first in a series of student practice questions that I&#39;d like to answer on the blog. The question is, &#34;given that I know and practice several different qigong sets and the tai chi form, how do I organize them into a coherent practice?&#34;
For my answer, check out this video, where I will either explain how learning which sets to practice, in what order, is like learning to taste wine, or I will actually drink the bottle of wine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personal Practice Journey</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/17/personal-practice-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 10:12:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/17/personal-practice-journey/</guid>
      <description>Having the luxury of a full month of training this summer has made me step back and reflect on my own personal practice over the last 13 years. I tried to put together some of what this process has been like for me and sum it up here. I&#39;m curious to know what you think. Have you gone through periods of practicing without a teacher? Have you had times where you&#39;ve made huge strides in your practice?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>