<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>chi-gung on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/chi-gung/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in chi-gung on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/chi-gung/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 09:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-2355 alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture.jpg&#34; width=&#34;159&#34; height=&#34;337&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you set out to develop your internal energy using standing postures, there are two main ways you can go about it: &lt;strong&gt;by feel or by form&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there will be a lot of overlap in these two broad approaches, like aligning your body with gravity without collapsing internally and progressively releasing and relaxing as you stand, but when it comes to the role of the mind, form and feel can be very different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Feeling Approach&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You stand &#34;by feel&#34; for a few different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a good period of feeling, taking stock, and getting comfortable is useful almost any time you do your standing practice. Because our initial orientation in standing is inward, and we&#39;re likely coming to it from a lot of outward-facing activity, taking 3, 5, or even 10 minutes to just stand and feel creates a nice buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve settled in to your practice, then any &#34;form&#34; work you do for the remainder of the standing session will be much more productive: you&#39;ll be quieter, more relaxed, and more tuned-in to your internal environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In fact, I recommend that you get to a comfortable baseline of just being able to settle, relax, and feel your body in a standing posture for 20 minutes before you move on to the form phase.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason to take the feeling approach is to fully appreciate the effects of your posture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;The posture pictured above is a neutral posture, also referred to as Wu Chi. As soon as you raise the arms or change the stance, the effect of the body position will begin to shape what you feel, physically and energetically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you pick a different posture, you automatically start doing a different form. You don&#39;t need to do anything special with the mind. Just feeling the new effects of a specific posture, compared to your Wu Chi baseline, can be enough to keep you occupied through much longer (2-hour!) standing sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, by taking the feeling approach, you can build your connection to the ground. As you stand, &lt;a title=&#34;3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;ask yourself these 3 questions&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Over time, you will become more rooted, relaxed, and connected&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moving into Standing Forms&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Once you have a solid baseline of feeling the body, you can begin to work on the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, most people are familiar with Tai Chi Forms or choreographed sequences in other martial arts, but what do we mean when we use the word &#34;form&#34; in this context?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t think of &#34;form&#34; as movements, but instead think of it as a procedure, then it starts to make more sense. And the value of having a procedure, or a repeatable process, is that you can begin to see how you&#39;re changing over time by performing it, both because you can use it as reference point and because doing it actually changes you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In standing, the form is going to be what you do with your awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here I want to warn you:&lt;/strong&gt; just like someone who follows the rote choreography of the Tai Chi form with no regard for softness, relaxation, and connection will be really stiff and awkward, if you follow the mind-forms without regard for the qualities you develop in the feeling approach, you will be stiff and awkward in your standing. You will just be going through a rigid mental checklist and the impact you will have on your energy and physical body will be limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you can introduce a pattern of progressively sinking the mind through the body, while you maintain relaxation, connection, and root, all of the qualities you began to develop in the feeling approach will be amplified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Your First Form: Downward Flow&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body, Bruce Frantzis teaches a standing qigong sequence that is designed to clear stagnant chi out of your energetic system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic process is a standing &#34;form&#34; where you begin at the crown of the head and move your mind downward through the body each time you practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the first level, an Energy Gates practice session is structured like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In (using the feeling method described above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downward Scan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stillness, Settling Again, or Storing Chi&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The more you practice Energy Gates, the more you will refine the Downward Scan piece. &lt;strong&gt;Specifically, you will go through stages of feeling your body to feeling your energy to sinking your energy and finally to dissolving your energy. &lt;/strong&gt;Bruce discusses each of these stages in depth &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;in the Energy Gates book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At each stage of this process, though, the form is the same. You start at the top and work your way down. Every time you go through the body this way, no matter at what layer, you are strengthening the downward current of energy, which has a powerful restorative effect over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often joke that the downward flow of chi in your body plays the same role as the downward flow of water in the plumbing system of your house. Not enough downward flow is a problem there, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Energy Gates Over Six Months&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you read the book or hear someone explain the Energy Gates process, it&#39;s easy to picture a whole bunch of dots all over the body that light up as you do your scan. In fact, learning to feel the gates themselves is a natural extension of just being able to feel the denser tissues of the body directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to tune the mind to a slightly different frequency, but all the time spent standing and feeling pays off here: you&#39;ve trained your mind to stay in one spot for extended periods without jumping around and without tensing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you set out to do a complete pass through all the gates, it roughly breaks down into a six-month project. There are 23 main places you&#39;ll want to work with and you could work with one per week (you can definitely spend longer on each gate, but this is just the basic formula). Here is the list from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/energy-gates-qigong&#34;&gt;the Energy Arts resource page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bai hui, or the crown of the head.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third eye, the eyes, the center of the ears and the temple. Also the four jaw points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where the tongue touches the roof of the mouth and the throat notch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The base of the skull and in between each of the cervical (neck) vertebrae down to the seventh cervical vertebra at the base of the neck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From where the tongue touches the roof of your mouth to the end of the breastbone, on a line about the width of your mouth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The four points of the shoulder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The elbows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The wrists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hands (all the points).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The joints where the ribs connect to the sternum, the spaces between the ribs, the joints where the ribs connect to the spine, the area between the shoulder blades and the spine. For women only: the gates of the breasts (directly behind the nipples).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The solar plexus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The whole of the belly, starting from the front and dissolving through the internal organs back to the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tantien and the mingmen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the points along the spine, from the occiput to the tailbone, paying special attention to the occiput, the seventh cervical vertebra, the vertebra in the center of the shoulder blades, the one at the base of the shoulder blades, mingmen and the tailbone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hip sockets, the pelvic bones, and the kwa (that is, the area inside the front crest of the hip bones).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The anus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The genitals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The perineum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The knees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ankles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The feet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Below the floor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Above the head.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, when you start working through the gates, the structure of your practice session will change from what we laid out earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in week 1, it could look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Crown of the Head - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Body - 3 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But week 11 would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel from the Crown of the Head down to the Solar Plexus - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Solar Plexus - 8 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Rest of the Body - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In other words, you should spend a substantial amount of time on whatever gate is the &#34;gate of the week.&#34; However, your practice session should always start with settling, finish with gathering, and have an easy flow down to the &#34;gate of the week&#34; and then from the &#34;gate of the week&#34; down into the ground after the main focus time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll notice that as you go through the process of the gates, your standing time can go from 15-20 minutes during the first few weeks up to 45-60 minutes towards the end of the process. If you can only manage 15-20 minutes and slowly adding more feels like too much of a strain, I recommend that you stick with the feeling method and not worry about the gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Is it Very Taoist?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here you might start to wonder about whether some of these guidelines for the form seem too rigid. How do you reconcile these recommendations with what you feel when you stand free-form?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And by the way, I&#39;m not saying that &#34;feeling&#34; is kindergarten and &#34;form&#34; is more advanced. In fact, you should cycle between periods of each as you practice over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guidelines and form serve a purpose. You need to work through the structure to develop certain things. Eventually, will you have a more intuitive feel for what you need and how much? Of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, though, Flannery O&#39;Connor captured the issue well, when she argued for a classical education: &#34;And if the student finds that this is not to his taste? Well, that is regrettable. Most regrettable. His taste should not be consulted; it is being formed.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However counter-intuitive it seems at first, the best feeling, the most relaxation, and the greatest internal stillness that I&#39;ve ever uncovered has come from the practice periods when I&#39;ve given over to a form to follow. Later on, I can bask in that energy and &#34;just feel&#34; and enjoy it, but to get there, it was a lot of little small, formal steps along the practice road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wherever you find yourself on the standing path now, I hope this helps orient you a little more. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Itch to Move Your Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 08:48:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We tend to think about our energy level like the money we have in the bank. You wake up in the morning, look in your energetic wallet and say, &#34;I&#39;ve got a lot of energy today&#34; or &#34;Man, I need 7 cups of coffee.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, to put it another way, thanks to this New Yorker cartoon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.condenaststore.com/-sp/If-we-re-all-just-energy-then-why-don-t-I-have-any-New-Yorker-Cartoon-Prints_i8481061_.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter  wp-image-4975&#34; alt=&#34;If we&#39;re all just energy, then why don&#39;t I have any?&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/12/Screen-Shot-2013-12-20-at-8.14.34-AM.png&#34; width=&#34;577&#34; height=&#34;445&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In qigong, we think about &#34;having energy&#34; a little bit differently. Often, it&#39;s not just how much or how little, but &lt;strong&gt;how well is your energy circulating?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good energetic circulation gives you a feeling of &#34;more,&#34; while stagnant or stuck energy feels draining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is such a different concept than most of us have, I&#39;ve often wondered about where these two ideas came from and where these two ways of seeing the world split. In this post, I&#39;m not going to give you a deeply researched exploration of the origins of the Taoist understanding of the world. I&#39;ll let &lt;a title=&#34;Straight Lines, Circles, and Spheres&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/11/straight-lines-circles-and-spheres/&#34;&gt;our practices&lt;/a&gt; stand as of evidence of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I want to share with you some of the writings of 20th century Western philosopher Hans Jonas. He wrote about the phenomenology of life and in his descriptions of biological processes, we get a really interesting connection to what many qigong practitioners come to realize: &lt;strong&gt;we have a fundamental need to circulate chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The Phenomenon of Life&lt;/span&gt;, Jonas is trying to reconcile the simplest forms of life with higher thought and our human experience of the mind. He tries to place them on a continuum and asks which one is for the sake of the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whatever the answer, one aspect of the ascending scale is that in its stages the &#34;mirroring&#34; of the world becomes ever more distinct and self-rewarding, beginning with the most obscure sensation somewhere on the lowest rungs of animality, even with the most elementary stimulation of organic irritability as such, in which somehow already otherness, world, and object are germinally &#34;experienced,&#34; that is, made subjective, and responded to (p.3).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My personal theory on the origins of qigong is that those early Taoists went exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They sat or stood in postures and listened, both inside themselves and to the natural world. &lt;strong&gt;As they got quieter and more perceptive, the heard the echoes of Jonas&#39; &#34;most obscure sensation.&#34;&lt;/strong&gt; The irritability that Jonas describes set them up against the world outside and framed their inner worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That irritability is the same itch you feel when you know you need to get your chi moving, circulating through you and passing back and forth between you, the natural world around you and the other people you interact with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things are flowing, in and out, up and down, towards and away, we feel good: &lt;strong&gt;connected to something outside ourselves but at the same time internally unified and integrated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like eating, breathing, and sleeping, circulating energy is a natural cycle that we can refine, enhance, and enjoy, but we need to pay attention to it on an ongoing, continuous basis to be healthy and feel whole.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-4629&#34; alt=&#34;help-browser&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/05/help-browser-150x150.png&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend last night about &lt;a title=&#34;Guide to Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; and different &lt;a title=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;meditation traditions&lt;/a&gt; that we had both tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many different reasons, on any given day, that we sought out the practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To clear our heads of racing thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To more deeply relax the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explore layers of the mind and emotions that aren&#39;t so obvious during our normal busy days.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It seems like we had really similar reasons to practice, but I was left wondering if it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; similar when we practice. What are the sensations that tell you you&#39;re on the right track? It seems like we want to end up in the same place, but are we taking the same road to get there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p4r3&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p4r3&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p4r3;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p4r3&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;554&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { r7p4r3 = new WufooForm();r7p4r3.initialize(options);r7p4r3.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dragon and Tiger Exercises for Activating the Lower Tantien</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 07:32:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re borrowing a technique from Dragon and Tiger qigong to try and get a better sense of the lower tantien. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lower tantien (&#34;dan-tee-en&#34;) is the energetic center of your physical body, located just below your navel, on the central axis of the body. If you dropped a line down from the crown of the head, through the body, and out the bottom of the pelvis, it would pass through the lower tantien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because this center is so deep inside the body, it is hard to feel. When you do find the energetic center of your body, though, you learn to realign your posture around it, feeling full and supported in a completely different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/-613On-w15U?list=UU4DJ7xUL-TWEBOgDp_ekI5Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this exercise, you want to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the palms, looking for the energetic sensation, as if you were pressing magnets together or pulling taffy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the energy get quiet once you stabilize the connection. Release, dissolve, and let go, without disconnecting the palms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat the first two steps, but with the palms facing the lower tantien.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, try to connect to this same internal alignment with the arms resting by your sides&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you find it, just hang out with the connection and don&#39;t try to do anything else!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong is Packed with Internal Content</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-4444 alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Paul Cavel performs the Marriage of Heaven and Earth&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/12/qi-gong-class-11.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;250&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This summer, Bruce Frantzis will be teaching a Marriage of Heaven and Earth Instructor training. Heaven and Earth was the first instructor training I attended in 2004 and I can still remember what a profound effect learning to &#34;pulse&#34; had on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the Energy Arts system, Heaven and Earth is considered a bridge from the basic to more advanced practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;how Heaven and Earth works in an early episode of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt;, but I wanted to share this explanation from &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; with you too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Heaven + Earth Works On So Many Levels&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As discussed in earlier issues, classically Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body Qigong is the foundation of the entire Water tradition since it initiates all neigong practice through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alignments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sinking chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissolving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bending and stretching techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic breathing methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Circulating chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaging the kwa as the leader of all motion&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Energy Gates softens the body and prepares the &#34;shell&#34; by creating a containment field with the body and its energy to develop more sophisticated neigong technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas Heaven + Earth takes the baton from Energy Gates and folds in the internal content learned there. So everything you learn and the skill you develop in each qigong system can and should be packed up and shipped off to the next set in the series. Yes, the arrangement will be completely unique, but you don&#39;t throw away or leave dormant any components while developing superior forms. For example, recall that Dragon + Tiger Medical Qigong is one of the three foundational practices in the neigong lattice. Dragon + Tiger&#39;s underlying technology develops the etheric field and wei chi, and thereby serves as a subcomponent of Heaven + Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as a more advanced practice than either Energy Gates or Dragon + Tiger, Heaven + Earth not only encompasses everything within these sets, but also further develops and upgrades each strand of neigong learned within them. This adds up to a serious amount of internal content&amp;mdash;even before material specific to Heaven + Earth is on the table. These include fundamental techniques like pulsing and developing the macrocosmic and microcosmic orbits of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as Heaven + Earth is a two-part, single exercise rather than a set of five, six or seven movements (like the other core practices in our system), its simplistic format encourages the internal rather than external focus needed to train deeper, more sophisticated neigong methods.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The excerpt above is from Paul&#39;s Inner Quest Newsletter, a monthly publication I highly recommend. Each month he writes in depth about a different aspect of learning and training neigong. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p5x7/&#34;&gt;You can download a free sample issue here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/q3tlLKD4YdM?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you download or listen to the episode below, you might also want to check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/bend-bow-spinal-qigong&#34;&gt;the description of Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong on EnergyArts.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/classes/chi-gung-bend-bow-introduction-bend-bow-and-shoot-arrow-december-1-2-late-fall-session&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be sure to check out Eric&#39;s Bend the Bow workshop, December 1 and 2, 2012 at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refining Your Opening and Closing</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 07:00:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I remember the first time I really got a sense for &#34;opening and closing&#34; my joints. We were on a qigong retreat and the person who was helping me probably spent 20 minutes &#34;pulsing&#34; my wrist, so that the fluids in the joint were moving in a smooth, even way, alternately creating more and less space between the bones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you pulse, you&#39;re manipulating the fluid flows inside your body so that the spaces inside your body compress and expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this is certainly not the normal way that we think about movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are trained in the &#34;pulleys and levers&#34; way of thinking. Contract this muscle to bend this joint (This is the logical conclusion of understanding movement based on dissection. When you cut back the skin and see muscles attached to bones.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you understood the body in terms of flows?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4113&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice opening and closing, you start to understand, on a visceral level, the flows that are constantly at work inside your body (and later you can more easily see them in the world all around you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulsing is a central skill in the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong. &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;In this early episode of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed why pulsing is the bridge to more advanced practice (see part 4 especially).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a more refined sense of how opening and closing works, you can also see the way it is integrated into movement in &lt;a title=&#34;5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/&#34;&gt;this progression of qigong videos.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, though, I want to show you a simple exercise you can use to fine-tune your sensitivity to opening and closing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/-y7o6ddHMCc?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you practice the simple exercise in the video, see if you can sense a similar kind of internal movement going on inside a full-body movement. At first this isn&#39;t easy to detect, but over time, you will become more sensitive to opening and closing on many different levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re curious about how to track opening and closing in more dynamic exercises, &lt;a title=&#34;Circles And Spheres in Qigong, Tai Chi, and Ba Gua&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/circles-and-spheres-in-qigong-tai-chi-and-ba-gua/&#34;&gt;check out this practice video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The True Value of Your Qigong Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/30/the-true-value-of-your-qigong-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2012 08:40:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/30/the-true-value-of-your-qigong-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We live in a culture where doing more, having more, and working harder are valued above pretty much everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a dangerous attitude, a linear approach to life that denies the need for rest and renewal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you constantly push yourself, you know it will lead to burnout. If you operate as if you have an infinite capacity to do and never rest, sooner or later you will get the message in some form that it is time to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the question is, how do we begin to value our energy as a cycle of work and rest instead of rest as the thing that distracts us from doing more work?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2950&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/33018637?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=e91c6b&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;300&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this video, &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/33018637&#34;&gt;The Myths of the Overworked Creative&lt;/a&gt;, Tony Schwartz articulates some of the different ways to, as he puts it &#34;ennoble renewal.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For qigong practitioners, listen to the way he frames the possibility for restful activities to be woven into daily work. I think you will see that a restorative energy practice will enhance everything that he recommends, especially when it comes to improving the quality of your rest.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Highlights from The Myths of the Overworked Creative&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Think about your energy like a natural resource:  &#34;the only resources that last are the ones we renew.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as you think about your energy as a precious resource (and here I would push qigong practitioners to think of energy in the everyday sense, beyond your practice):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can actively cultivate and develop more energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can renew your energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can learn to manage your energy more efficiently -- get more done in less time at a higher level of qulity, more sustainably&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You have 4 main sources of energy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;physical (quantity) -  the foundation of the others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;emotional (quality) - &#34;how do I feel when I&#39;m performing at my best&#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mental (focus) - attention is under siege&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spiritual (purpose) - energy of the human spirit -- serving something bigger than your needs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Myth of Doing More&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assume that the best way to get more done is to work more hours. The reality is that we work better when we build in intermitten renewal. We&#39;re not meant to operate like a digital device: high speed, long time, multiple programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&#34;Human beings are designed to pulse.&#34;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;Every system in the body pulses as it moves between spending and renewing energy. For some reason, we&#39;ve moved away from this pulse on a daily basis and we try to live linear lives.  We are violating the internal rhythm of our own body and the natural world around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, Schwartz places sleep at the center of daily renewal, citing some interesting research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As qigong practitioners, I think we would add that the rhythm of our practice helps keep the range between extreme work and rest more manageable. Work never burns up too much of your energy and rest becomes more nourishing, faster. Of course, I don&#39;t have any research to cite here, but I know when my practice is regular, the swings between work and rest feel smoother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else have you noticed about the way your practice changes your all-day energy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you get a chance to watch the entire video, let me know what you think the important lessons are here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 09:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure you&#39;ve spent time looking around YouTube for qigong and tai chi videos. According to their website, people upload 24 hours of video to YouTube &lt;em&gt;every minute&lt;/em&gt;! No doubt you&#39;ve seen some crazy stuff. So how do you sift through all of it and more importantly, are there any qigong videos on YouTube worth watching?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is, of course there are. And I&#39;ve put together a list of 5 good ones to get you started. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2522&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Practice with YouTube Qigong Videos&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you will see from the videos below, there is a blend of instructional content, guided practice, and demonstration. You have to get creative when you are borrowing from a source like online video to boost your practice. Sometimes you will just do a quick check-in. Sometimes you will sit and watch an entire lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&#39;t recommend trying to do your practice and darting back and forth to the computer at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the video has good audio guidance that can run in the background, great. Otherwise, just watch it once or twice and then go and practice. I&#39;ll try to point out key places in each video where you can see skilled practitioners demonstrating things they aren&#39;t necessarily talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This introduction to standing by Lam Kam Chuen is one of my favorite overviews of the practice. He talks a little bit about the background of the practice and gives just enough instruction to get you started. If you already have a standing practice, it&#39;s worth watching because you can revisit some of the overarching reasons to do this qigong method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/StandStillBeFit&#34;&gt;The entire channel&lt;/a&gt; is worth watching once you&#39;ve gone through the introductory clip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simple Circling Hands&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The natural transition from standing practice is to start repetitive movements. In standing, you tune into internal rhythms that only become obvious because there is no external movement. Circling Hands is a great bridge because your external movements are simple enough that you can let the internal rhythms drive them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch as &lt;a title=&#34;Q&amp;amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; performs Circling Hands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most important thing you can get from this YouTube qigong video is the way his whole body opens and closes, pulsing from the center, outward.&amp;Acirc; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exploring Internal Flows&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the next video, &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt; explains how to activate the two main energy flows that run your body: Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth. He teaches two different exercises to highlight these flows. Like Paul&#39;s demonstration above, if you practice these exercises you will begin to feel the &#34;pulls&#34; through the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth pointing out that while you may or may not be able to feel what he&#39;s describing right away, every teacher I&#39;ve ever had insists that you need to develop the internal sensitivity to these subtle movements through a standing or sitting practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transitioning into More Movement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Each mode of qigong practice gives you access to something different. &#34;Quiet&#34; practices like standing qigong or sitting meditation allow you to develop your internal awareness with as little physical coordination as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving practices do two things: they develop rhythm and they challenge your ability to maintain internal focus because of the ever-changing external conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these next two videos, we&#39;re going to introduce more movement, first by adding weight-shifting and turning, then by looking at the qigong set with the most complicated external form: Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try this &#34;Rolling the Ball&#34; exercise to see if you can maintain some of the internal awareness primed in the earlier qigong videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this last video isn&#39;t designed to be instructional or a follow-along practice. Instead, I want you to watch it and see if you can pick up some of the things we&#39;ve looked at in the other YouTube qigong videos in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see internal continuity? Opening and closing? Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth flows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The secret to training your eyes to see more subtle movement patterns is to look at someone&#39;s movements, in this case Tai Chi master &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, and try to feel inside your own body what he must be doing to create those movements.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this post gives you some ideas about how to use YouTube qigong videos to improve your own practice. Got any favorites that I&#39;ve left out? Be sure to let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Challenge of the Three Swings</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 09:03:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/11/Second-Swing.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-2437&#34; title=&#34;Second Swing&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/11/Second-Swing-e1321015385573.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;176&#34; height=&#34;386&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Three Swings from Energy Gates are some of the most challenging exercises to do well in the entire Energy Arts curriculum. You have to relax, maintain good alignment, and coordinate stepping and turning while moving faster than most other qigong exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s talk a little bit about why the Three Swings are important and what you need to integrate to do them well.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2436&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Started with the Three Swings&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the &lt;a title=&#34;10 Things Modern Athletes Can Learn from the Tai Chi Classics&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/27/10-things-modern-athletes-can-learn-from-the-tai-chi-classics/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Classics&lt;/a&gt;, it says, &#34;the motion should be rooted in the feet, released through the legs, controlled by the waist and manifested through the fingers.&#34; Think of practicing the swings as a way to test this concept. You will get much clearer feedback from the swings about how the motion you generate from the feet travels out to your fingertips than you will from solo form practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do the swings well, you need to do these three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relax Your Arms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sink Your Weight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Your Kwa&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you let the arms go completely and begin to turn from the kwa, you then focus on alternately sinking the weight down one leg and then the other. In that sense, the First Swing is a natural extension of what you do in your &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;Standing&lt;/a&gt; practice and then in Cloud Hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s new in the First Swing, though, is that you will begin to speed up the alternating sinking (that causes your weight shift from side to side), so that the arms begin to swing. Until you start building momentum, though, the arms should just hang by your sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s where the swings get interesting...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where the Swings Get More Complicated&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a series, each of the swings is designed to build on the previous one. Swing by swing there is more complexity in terms of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stepping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhythm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the First Swing, you fold the kwa to turn into the weighted leg. In the Second Swing, you unfold the kwa to turn away from the weighted leg. In the Third Swing, you add a vertical kwa pump to the stepping pattern of the Second. Each of these in changes in stepping alters the rhythm and the timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of moving from one to the next swing is to progressively build your internal connections, up through the spine and out the arms. In other words, you can see how each swing activates the internal connections in the body based on where the arms will go when you do the stepping correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the arm movement in each of the swings in this video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/7I1tBFlhOZU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/7I1tBFlhOZU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see how, swing-by-swing, the arms move higher. That is due to the stepping and shifting patterns described above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you practice the swings over time, your energy will rise and fall with the motion of the arms. You learn to bring it up and down the body effortlessly, smoothing out stuck points as you improve your shifting, timing, and stepping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re used to doing slow-motion qigong and tai chi practices, the swings can be very challenging because they are so dynamic. The payoff, though, is that you can take the feeling of integration that you get from being still or moving slowly and carry it over into more active practices. You still get &lt;a title=&#34;Repetition as Rhythm: Why Do 20 Reps?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/28/repetition-as-rhythm-why-do-20-reps/&#34;&gt;the benefits of repetition and rhythm&lt;/a&gt; doing the swings, so it really is a bridge between stillness and ever-changing movement. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 10:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is no other book I return to more for my qigong practice than &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body&lt;/span&gt; by Bruce Frantzis. It&#39;s the one I consistently recommend to students and anyone who emails the school to inquire about starting a qigong practice before they have access to a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s how to get the most out of it, whether or not you have someone who can give you regular feedback on your practice: &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2290&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/LhMF873nwkk?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/LhMF873nwkk?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever my students are getting ready to study with Bruce for the first time, I tell them, &#34;he teaches in chapter headings and book titles. It will be up to you to go back and write the paragraphs, sentence by sentence, as you do your own personal practice over the weeks and months after you study with him.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Energy Gates book isn&#39;t actually that different. As you can see from the video, there&#39;s a lot more in there than you want to practice initially. Here&#39;s how I recommend that you follow through on a personal practice, based on the information in the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Build a Solid Foundation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To help you get into a good rhythm with your standing practice (because I know how hard it can be sometimes), I created &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/standing-series/&#34;&gt;these guided practice mp3&#39;s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you go through the posts in the series, you will find 5-, 10-, and 20-minute practice sessions. Start with whichever one feels comfortable. Eventually you will find that your internal speed will slow to a rate that might require 30 minutes or an hour to complete one full head-to-toe scan. There&#39;s no rush to get there and no one will hand you a trophy when you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Follow the Energy Gates Schematic&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The logic of Energy Gates, from an energetic perspective, is that the standing practice clears stagnant energy out of your system. Think of it as an internal flush of whatever is stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means that after you complete the sinking into the feet (or below), you need to move. You can make a gradual transition into movement using Cloud Hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, Cloud Hands will be enough movement to get everything circulating strongly again. Eventually, adding the Swings builds up your internal connections in a more powerful way, but these are really hard to learn without a lot of ongoing feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, complete the clearing and circulating process with one final release: the Spine Stretch. As you learn to feel more and more of your back muscles, deep and in toward the spine, you will gain better control over the moving pieces. What this allows you to do is set up more full releases of any sense of holding in your nervous system. It can be a strong experience, so go slow and limit yourself to 2 or 3 each time you practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learn More When You Can&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you practice Sinking, Cloud Hands, and the Spine Stretch on your own as a regular practice, then you&#39;ll be in great shape for meeting with an instructor. Live and in person, you&#39;ll be able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get feedback on the dynamic alignments you need to maintain for the swings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be guided through the more subtle releasing techniques that allow you to dissolve energetic blockages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the importance of the gates for more precise movement and standing work&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Still, when you compare Energy Gates to any other set, the depth you can get out of these three exercises on your own is tremendous. Good luck in your practice!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow and Stabilizing the Mind with Craig Barnes</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 08:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2203&#34; title=&#34;Craig Barnes doing Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-3-199x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Craig Barnes doing Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; width=&#34;199&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;Stability and flow seem to be at odds with each other. Stability can mean rigidity, or at least, it seems to conjure up something fixed, sturdy, and unmoving. Flow isn&#39;t any of those things. It&#39;s fluid and changing. So how does Energy Arts Senior Instructor Craig Barnes blend the two so seamlessly?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2191&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Recently, Craig taught a workshop about awakening energetic sensitivity, drawn from principles of Dragon and Tiger Qigong. We worked a lot on the opening of the set. The goal was to &#34;fill up your chi&#34; before you start doing the movements, so that the body is awake and engaged and each movement is more alive and more connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specific method for waking up your energetic sensitivity begins with refining awareness of your physical body. How do you move each part under conscious control, in a smooth circular way? Craig is very skilled at leading a group through a gradual progression that brings each new piece online and then weaves it together with the previous pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What impressed me more, though, was the way he included &#34;stability points&#34;, while maintaining the flow of the teaching, which was also what he was teaching people to do in their practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps &#34;stability point&#34; is the wrong term. Certainly this was a &#34;point&#34; in time in the flow of practice, but what Craig teaches, as far as stabilizing the mind, has a more diffuse quality than &#34;point&#34; conveys. You miss it if you focus on all the little details of body mechanics. If you treat the components of your practice like a checklist, you never become internally connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stability of the mind, when Craig expresses it, becomes the ground for your practice. A stable mind is like a table, set for a great meal. The specific exercises are the plates and bowls and cups that get filled up with delicious food, but you need to set the table for the meal to come together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-medium wp-image-2204&#34; title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Sword Fingers&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-2-224x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Sword Fingers&#34; width=&#34;224&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Internalizing the paradox of stability and flow goes a step or two beyond &#34;setting the table&#34;, though. Dragon and Tiger is a great place to learn how to stabilize the mind in the flow of movements because, between each distinct movement pattern, there are transitional moves that you can repeat as much as you need to. In these transitions, it&#39;s much easier to return to stability, but you don&#39;t have to break the flow. You do something simple, like circle the arms back and forth around the waist, or pulse the hands in and out, which keeps up a smooth flow. Through the simple repetition, your mind can settle down again at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Dragon and Tiger is made for this kind of work, you can still go through this process in any qigong set, if you follow these rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start your practice with simple, repetitive movements that allow you to tune into the background or underlying stability of your mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tease out gradually bigger and bigger movements, without losing the stable ground feeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work up into larger flow patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take soft landings throughout the set that return you to something simple and repetitive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For tai chi people: this is why a phrase like Grasp Sparrow&#39;s Tail is repeated a dozen times in a long form.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Twice a Day</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 04:32:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I know I&#39;m writing this on vacation where the most pressing decision we make each day is whether to hike, kayak, or swim, but I&#39;m going to go ahead anyway and recommend that you practice twice a day. Here&#39;s why...&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1979&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/in5LGYtp8xw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/in5LGYtp8xw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Learned from a Month-Long Tai Chi Intensive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After a month in England, practicing 10 hours a day at &lt;a title=&#34;Movement Arts&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011&#34;&gt;the Short Form Instructor Training&lt;/a&gt; this summer, I have a renewed appreciation for daily practice rhythm. At the training, there were three distinct types of training sessions we would go through each day. In the mornings, we would practice in our groups. Most of the day, from 10am to 5pm was reserved for class time with Bruce. In the evenings, we would be free to practice again, ideally training the pieces of what we did in class that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During class time, we would have ten or twenty minutes to practice each new thing that Bruce introduced. That&#39;s fine to get an initial hit of each piece, but that brief exposure isn&#39;t the same thing as locking it in to your system. You have to take it two steps further. First, you have to expand that twenty minutes into forty-five minutes or an hour in the evening sessions. Then, after you eat and sleep and feel rested, you have to revisit the same material in a lighter way the next morning, trying to let the new material flow into your regular morning practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you look at the three pieces of each training day, you had integration of the previous day first thing in the morning, then new material during the bulk of the day, and finally a chance to really work on the new material in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the clearest way to see how this rhythm worked was to watch people not follow it! When people would blow off the evening training session, you could tell that the material wasn&#39;t soaking into their system the next day. Likewise, if they worked hard on pieces in the morning session (which they should have done the night before), they didn&#39;t have enough energy to get the most of out class that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I&#39;m Learning Practicing Twice a Day on Vacation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Going on vacation and having the free time to test this out again, I&#39;m even more convinced that you can learn a lot about your own practice rhythm by spreading out practice sessions throughout your day. The most surprising insight from the training was: &lt;strong&gt;the morning practice sessions were related more to the work I did the day before than they were to the two sessions following on the same day.&lt;/strong&gt; In other words, Tuesday morning practice was the completion of the training I did on Monday, not the warm-up for the rest of the training I was about to do on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the bigger pattern I wanted to test on vacation and it seems to be working really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you realize what this means, right? It means that eating, sleeping, and letting things settle down is an important part of learning. Or in other words, rest and integration complete hard work. We tend to think of work as an on/off switch. We&#39;re either working hard or being lazy. The lesson here is that rest and integration are the real opposites of hard work and that hard work doesn&#39;t pay off until you&#39;ve integrated it. Pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other cool thing about making this connection has been that now I feel like I&#39;m in one long training session. I used to think &#34;I practiced Monday, missed Tuesday, and Wednesday through Friday I did a little bit....I suck&#34;. Now, though, I think about chaining sessions of work, rest, and integration together and it gives the process much more continuity. You get out of an all-or-nothing mindset about your practice. To me, that seems to be much closer to making your practice a real part of the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Leave me a comment below and tell me about your practice cycles. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Balance Practicing Multiple Qigong Sets</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/23/how-to-balance-practicing-multiple-qigong-sets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2011 10:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/23/how-to-balance-practicing-multiple-qigong-sets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the first in a series of student practice questions that I&#39;d like to answer on the blog. The question is, &#34;given that I know and practice several different qigong sets and the tai chi form, how do I organize them into a coherent practice?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my answer, check out this video, where I will either explain how learning which sets to practice, in what order, is like learning to taste wine, or I will actually drink the bottle of wine. You&#39;ll have to watch the video to find out which one.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1839&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jAmrQtr9-UA?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jAmrQtr9-UA?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Got a practice question? &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/viewform?formkey=dFhvQkM4Vng1VWtsblZaQ25TdFJBa1E6MQ&#34;&gt;Ask me here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personal Practice Journey</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/17/personal-practice-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 10:12:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/17/personal-practice-journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having the luxury of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011&#34;&gt;full month of training&lt;/a&gt; this summer has made me step back and reflect on my own personal practice over the last 13 years. I tried to put together some of what this process has been like for me and sum it up &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/about/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;m curious to know what you think. Have you gone through periods of practicing without a teacher? Have you had times where you&#39;ve made huge strides in your practice? What was that like? Did the fruits of that period last a long time? Use the comments section below and let me know what it was like for you (or shoot me an email, but other people are probably curious too!).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>