<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>creativity on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/creativity/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in creativity on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/creativity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Cycles</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 14:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m coming to another big teaching cycle in Trainerfly and I think this short clip of David Heinemeier Hansson speaking at Stanford&#39;s Entrepreneurship Corner is really useful to frame the mindset:

I know the point in the clip above is more about a strategy to take when you look at the &#34;big guys&#34;, but I really feel like the alternating cycles of &#34;spending&#34; and &#34;teaching&#34; are relevant here. We just went through a &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epic Meaning, Sheep Knuckles, and The Institute for the Future</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2011 09:30:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</guid>
      <description>Jane McGonigal gives a fascinating talk about the &#34;superpowers&#34; cultivated by the game-playing masses (more than 500 million with another billion coming up in the next decade!). Obviously we all have the image of the gamer locked in his mother&#39;s basement, endlessly pawing away at an electronic reward system, like a hamster. McGonigal&#39;s takeaway is a little different though.
She emphasizes the motivation, inspiration, and social purpose built into game play.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make the Most of Phase-Based Activities</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/13/make-the-most-of-phase-based-activities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 13:29:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/13/make-the-most-of-phase-based-activities/</guid>
      <description>Check out this talk from 37Signals co-founder Jason Fried at TEDx Midwest, specifically at 5:13 when he starts comparing sleep and work:

It got me thinking about other &#34;phase-based&#34; activities, like Tai Chi or Qigong practice. Most productive practice happens when you can allow yourself to move through several stages of settling in and keep a continuous practice thread going for an hour or more.
Over the last 6 years of running 3 hour-long classes back-to-back-to-back, multiple times per week, I&#39;ve gotten a pretty good feel for these phases.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>