<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>technology on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/technology/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in technology on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Home Practice Challenge</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:19:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the recent practice survey we conducted at Brookline Tai Chi and experiments I&#39;ve been running in online learning, it&#39;s become clearer and clearer to me that most people need some external motivation when they are learning a new skill. That&#39;s not a judgment about willpower and motivation, it actually says more about the way we are wired for survival. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1523&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In Z Health, we always talk about the way that the nervous system is at once the most plastic system -- it can adapt to lots of different changes -- and also the most stable. The stability of the nervous system is a good thing from a survival and energy management point of view -- it doesn&#39;t cost you a lot of cognitive energy to get through your day if you run on habit. In that sense, the plasticity of the nervous system -- your ability to change and learn new things -- has to deal with the inertia of stability in your nervous system. When we are trying to learn new behaviors and forge new habits, these two things can be at odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&#39;ve seen and heard from my tai chi students, is that a little bit of external motivation goes a long way to spark the small changes you need to make on a daily basis to put new behavior in place. Last week, one of my students said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was liberating to think that 5 minutes of tai chi practice meant I could make progress, because until I thought about it that way, I avoided practice, assuming it was going to take 30 minutes or more.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, if you look at some studies on mental rehearsal and brain function, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1580438,00.html&#34;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;, you start to see that the cognitive component of learning new skills can be practiced in a much easier way than devoting hours and hours of grueling practice -- time that very few people I work with have to spare anyway. The smarter you get about your practice, the better you&#39;ll get at getting good at new things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#39;s my DIY Home Practice Challenge for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drill down into your practice until you get to a small chunk you can practice in 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick the easiest time of day to devote to your practice -- what&#39;s the perfect scenario for practicing this skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a recurring reminder in your calendar -- pick the medium that will be most accessible to get the reminder at the right time, i.e. on your desktop to interrupt your work, via email, or even text message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each day when you get the reminder, do your 5 minute practice, and then maybe take a minute or two to reflect on the success of what you just did or refine the scenario if necessary&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You will fail to build up this practice habit if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pick too big a skill to work on, e.g. I want to become a ballerina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are vague about when you are going to do it, e.g. I will practice it daily&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&#39;t get the reminder at the right time, e.g. I&#39;ll practice at noon each day, but my reminder comes in at 6pm&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I know those failures might sound obvious, and you should pick something pretty simple and obvious to begin with, but what I hope is that once you see the power in this simple approach, you&#39;ll start to tackle more complex and exciting skill building and begin to reflect on a lot of different experiences, in business, at work, in personal relationships, with the same desire to make incremental progress as you do with a hobby or healthy habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m always curious to hear how this goes for people, so send me an email or drop a comment below once you get set up and start hitting your daily targets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Posted from Trainerfly: Launching an Online Course</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2011 10:36:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2011/04/11/how-i-launched-my-first-online-course/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this post from the Trainerfly blog&lt;/a&gt;. I talk to teachers and trainers all the time who want move beyond their live events, but the number of steps it takes, and the technology required to make it work seem overwhelming. Hopefully, I&#39;ve made a little dent in that perception!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>xkcd: Let Go</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 08:43:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Be sure to mouse over for the original title text from the comic (Thanks, Nate!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/862/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; title=&#34;After years of trying various methods, I broke this habit by pitting my impatience against my laziness. I decoupled the action and the neurological reward by setting up a simple 30-second delay I had to wait through, in which I couldn&#39;t do anything else, before any new page or chat client would load (and only allowed one to run at once). The urge to check all those sites magically vanished--and my &#39;productive&#39; computer use was unaffected.&#34; src=&#34;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/let_go.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;518&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simplicity, Persuasion and Technology</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 08:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been reading/watching a lot of BJ Fogg&#39;s work lately. He studies &lt;a href=&#34;http://captology.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;the persuasive power of technology for positive behavior change&lt;/a&gt;. You&#39;ll recognize my interest here if you read some of my recent posts on game design mechanics and the potential to integrate technology into real world learning. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-557&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Check out his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/bjfogg&#34;&gt;Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; for some shorter videos that explain facets of his work &#34;in 60 seconds&#34;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s Dr. Fogg on simplicity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/2094487&#34;&gt;BJ Fogg on Simplicity&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/bjfogg&#34;&gt;BJ Fogg&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He makes a really important distinction around the 3:20 mark. We tend to think of simplicity as a feature of our technology, but he disagrees. Instead, he says &#34;simplicity is a perception we have of the experience in accomplishing the task&#34;. This means that you have to consider the person and the context if you want to facilitate behavior change, not just the information you are giving them, or the medium you are using to deliver the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, I&#39;ll write more about his 3-part behavior change model, summed up as &#34;putting hot triggers in the path of motivated people&#34; and try to explain how I see Motivation, Ability, and Triggers applied to teaching, business, and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all fascinating stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossfit&#39;s Brilliant use of Game Mechanics</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/04/crossfits-brilliant-use-of-game-mechanics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2011 06:51:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/04/crossfits-brilliant-use-of-game-mechanics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; Recently, TechCrunch featured an article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/25/scvngr-game-mechanics/&#34;&gt;the playdeck they use at SCVNGR&lt;/a&gt; that outlines the mechanics of gameplay. The article cites at TED talk by game designer Jane McGonigal, which I talk about &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-538&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was a little disappointed with McGonigal&#39;s conclusion, because she basically offered up the solution as specially-themed video games to leverage the power of game mechanics, or &#34;gameplay superpowers&#34;, to do good in the real world and incite behavior change. She presented a couple of case studies that her group ran and they showed some carry-over to behaviors later on. That&#39;s fine. I just think there&#39;s potential to go further. I don&#39;t think I was alone either. If you read the TED video comments, lots of people reply with &#34;but my son lives in the basement and only comes out to eat&#34; arguments. Not exactly the thriving social fabric McGonigal presents....&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I couldn&#39;t help think that there are better examples of hybrids between real life behavior and motivation that falls under the game mechanics principles. The example I want to look at today is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.crossfit.com&#34;&gt;Crossfit&lt;/a&gt;. As a fitness movement, they do an amazing job with this blend. Now, I have to admit I don&#39;t have direct experience with Crossfit, so I&#39;m hoping someone who does will fill in even more detail here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Game Mechanics Defined&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I refer to &#34;game mechanics&#34; in this post, I&#39;m taking about the underlying elements that are repeatedly used across interactive electronic media to elicit emotional, motivating responses from the game players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the TechCrunch article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;SCVNGR&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s playdeck tries to break down the game mechanics into their  constituent parts.  Some elements are as basic as &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;achievements,&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;  &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;status,&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;virtual items.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;   But there are also more complex ones  such as the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;appointment dynamic&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; (a player must return at a specific  time and perform an action to get a reward, like in Farmville), &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;free  lunch&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; (a player gets something because of the efforts of other  people,like in Groupon), &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;fun once, fun always&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; (a simple action that  maintains a minimum level of enjoyment no matter how many times you do  it, like Foursquare&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s check-ins), and &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;cascading information theory  (give out information in the smallest dribblets possible to keep players  guessing and moving forward).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We&#39;re going to look at how these dynamics are used, intentionally or not (I don&#39;t know), in the user experience on Crossfit.com, at Crossfit affiliate gyms, and in the Crossfit Games. It&#39;s also important to look at overarching concepts in gameplay, that Jane McGonigal has articulated very clearly in her TED talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Game Mechanics in Crossfit&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I believe that the following mechanisms make the Crossfit user experience engaging and as a result, extremely popular. If you get confused about where I&#39;m using technical terms, refer back to &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/08/25/scvngr-game-mechanics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the TechCrunch article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Companion Gaming&lt;/strong&gt; -- the cross-platform approach is central to the idea of applying game mechanics from the virtual world to real world behavior. Crossfit does this by posting the &#34;workout of the day&#34; to Crossfit.com, allowing affiliate gyms to operate Crossfit locations, and even hosting an Olympics-style Crossfit Games. You can &#34;play&#34; in all these different ways, and your achievements in one venue is relevant to another. More on that below...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appointment Dynamic &lt;/strong&gt;-- at the heart of Crossfit.com is the &#34;Workout of the Day&#34;. Each day, a challenging workout is posted from Crossfit headquarters that sets the daily goal for everyone who participates. If you read the comments, where people post their workout times, you&#39;ll see a mix of dread and delight, which seems to capture the Crossfit spirit. So, all wrapped up in this daily challenge is also:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Achievement&lt;/strong&gt; -- posting your times to comments,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Countdown&lt;/strong&gt; -- workouts are often completed &#34;for time&#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pride&lt;/strong&gt; -- successful completion of the workout or beating your own previous time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Envy &lt;/strong&gt;-- daily workouts are often accompanied by pictures of other Crossfitters working out in various states of undress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy &lt;/strong&gt;-- leveraging public accountability, i.e. posting your achievement, to motivate future compliance&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These underlying mechanics add up to create what McGonigal refers to as the &#34;Social Fabric of Games&#34;. In other words, competition creates community. McGonigal captures the gamer spirit alive in the social fabric as an &#34;urgent optimism&#34; to toil in &#34;blissful productivity&#34; towards &#34;epic meaning&#34;. Again, watch the video to get her full explication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point though, you really need to ask two questions. First of all, you&#39;re probably wondering why these mechanics can be apparently more compelling than real life. I&#39;m not sure if they are or whether a virtual world just gives us a clear view into how they work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second question is, given how powerful these motivators are, how can I incorporate them into my training business? Take another look at Crossfit. I know I&#39;ve barely scratched the surface with this analysis. And I&#39;m not saying you should copy their model. But you should think long and hard about how they&#39;ve grown an online epicenter out into tens of thousands of real life participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, I don&#39;t think that just because you can identify these mechanisms, it makes their use disingenuous,b ut I will caution you with one more principle from the gamer&#39;s playdeck: &lt;strong&gt;Beware the Moral Hazard of Game Play&lt;/strong&gt;. The Moral Hazard is, again from TC, &#34;the risk that by rewarding people manipulatively in a game you remove the actual moral value of the action and replace it with an ersatz game-based reward.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s in this final warning, though, that I find the truly satisfying answer to McGonigal&#39;s problem  and why I love the Crossfit example so much. When you really do come up with an elegant blend of real-world and virtual cross-platform companion gaming, you create the best motivation for the healthiest action. That is what I believe all movement educators should strive for.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epic Meaning, Sheep Knuckles, and The Institute for the Future</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2011 09:30:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-531&#34; title=&#34;gaming superpowers&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/01/gaming-superpowers-300x207.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;207&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jane McGonigal gives a fascinating talk about the &#34;superpowers&#34; cultivated by the game-playing masses (more than 500 million with another billion coming up in the next decade!). Obviously we all have the image of the gamer locked in his mother&#39;s basement, endlessly pawing away at an electronic reward system, like a hamster. McGonigal&#39;s takeaway is a little different though.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-528&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She emphasizes the motivation, inspiration, and social purpose built into game play. I think that&#39;s an interesting take. When I talked to an early pioneer of these games, he said that &#34;we knew they were addictive from the beginning&#34;, but it sounded like the dirty little secret that no one wanted to admit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I think the interesting question is whether the virtues of gaming (along the lines of motivation and engagement) can be transferred to real world activity without the addictive over-use that leads to unhealthy, sedentary life. Maybe as technology comes out of the basement and into the palm of your hand more readily, this is becoming a more reasonable goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, her talk is definitely worth watching (oh, and the sheep knuckles tie back nicely into Herodotus for a lesson on real world gaming!):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;446&#34; height=&#34;326&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;wmode&#34; value=&#34;transparent&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;bgColor&#34; value=&#34;#ffffff&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;vu=http://video.ted.com/talks/dynamic/JaneMcGonigal_2010-medium.flv&amp;amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/JaneMcGonigal-2010.embed_thumbnail.jpg&amp;amp;vw=432&amp;amp;vh=240&amp;amp;ap=0&amp;amp;ti=799&amp;amp;introDuration=15330&amp;amp;adDuration=4000&amp;amp;postAdDuration=830&amp;amp;adKeys=talk=jane_mcgonigal_gaming_can_make_a_better_world;year=2010;theme=what_s_next_in_tech;theme=the_rise_of_collaboration;theme=a_taste_of_ted2010;theme=design_like_you_give_a_damn;theme=art_unusual;theme=media_that_matters;event=TED2010;&amp;amp;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;bgcolor&#34; value=&#34;#ffffff&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;446&#34; height=&#34;326&#34; src=&#34;http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf&#34; flashvars=&#34;vu=http://video.ted.com/talks/dynamic/JaneMcGonigal_2010-medium.flv&amp;amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/JaneMcGonigal-2010.embed_thumbnail.jpg&amp;amp;vw=432&amp;amp;vh=240&amp;amp;ap=0&amp;amp;ti=799&amp;amp;introDuration=15330&amp;amp;adDuration=4000&amp;amp;postAdDuration=830&amp;amp;adKeys=talk=jane_mcgonigal_gaming_can_make_a_better_world;year=2010;theme=what_s_next_in_tech;theme=the_rise_of_collaboration;theme=a_taste_of_ted2010;theme=design_like_you_give_a_damn;theme=art_unusual;theme=media_that_matters;event=TED2010;&amp;amp;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;&#34; bgcolor=&#34;#ffffff&#34; wmode=&#34;transparent&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with the Old....Business Model</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 16:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Exit&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2245/2089485151_17f142a726_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s the end of the year and it&#39;s time to get out of old habits and mindsets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here&#39;s my prediction for the best business model for independent fitness and wellness pros, for the next DECADE. Yeah, I think it&#39;s going to take a few years to unfold, but the groundwork has been laid:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-514&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more brick-and-mortar businesses&lt;/strong&gt;. Trust me, I know what it&#39;s like to cut a $10,000 rent check each month. That&#39;s over with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more separation between in-person and on-line.&lt;/strong&gt; I read an article the other day that referred to &#39;90&#39;s style &#34;clicks-and-mortar&#34; business, e.g. Walmart.com for Walmart. You&#39;ve got to move past your website as a calling card for your services, even if you &#34;have really good content&#34;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more big barriers to scaling up your business.&lt;/strong&gt; This is great news. It&#39;s so easy to manage all the clients in your universe in a systematic way, through crm, email marketing, and interactive training apps like Trainerfly (ahem!), that the little guy or independent gal, can make it all by themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more one-size fits all products.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the same kind of dinosaur as a physical location. You might have some good reasons to put out video products (like standardizing a curriculum, for example), but you better have a way to tailor it to your clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No more professional athlete fantasy.&lt;/strong&gt; You don&#39;t have to go pro or get sponsored or anything like that to make a decent living.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Welcome to the professional educator reality.&amp;Acirc;  I believe that the movement educator who is committed to honing a craft can make a real living. We all work really, really hard in our practice and now it&#39;s going to be possible to build a business around that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at any public health statistics. Do you see a lack of movement in our society? Are we aging? Unhealthy? Totally divorced from the inherent human joys of movement? Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So those of us out there carrying the flag for better life through movement need to speak up. But we need to adapt too. We need to meet people where they are at, offer them chunks of wellness they can digest, and slowly change the conversation. And while we&#39;re at it, we need to make a living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is within reach in the next year or five years or ten years. You just need to start today with a little mental shift. Step into 2011 with some fresh perspective. You will be well rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exit photo courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/heathbrandon/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;heathbrandon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Business Thought Experiment</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 19:35:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m working strictly on a hunch here, but I think there&#39;s a connection between the sentiment I tried to express &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/03/technology-and-all-that-heavenly-glory/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; about not getting lost in the bells and whistles of technology, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/12/24/hybrid-startup/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; about &#34;hybrid businesses&#34;.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-501&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One Foot in the Virtual World, One Foot in the Real World&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to&amp;Acirc;  the author, Glenn Kelman, a hybrid business has &#34;one foot in the virtual world and one foot in the real world.&#34; However, &#34;this isn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t&amp;Acirc; the old &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;clicks-and-mortar&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; concept from the 1990s,  which put web glitter on an old-school business, building Walmart.com  for Walmart. A hybrid business is built entirely from scratch, to be  innovative in its online technology and its real-world operations.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m trying to envision how to adapt &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brooklinetaichi.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt; to the hybrid model or see how &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trainerfly&lt;/a&gt; fundamentally addresses this shift.&amp;Acirc;  Here are some thoughts along those lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right now, BTC is definitely in the &#34;clicks and mortar&#34; mindset. The purpose of the website is to tell people about classes and when they take place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trainerfly could fall into the same trap by simply mirroring the live training sessions, as a &#34;back-up copy&#34; of what happened in real life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of the more interesting possibilities I&#39;ve been exploring with Trainerfly and online learning have allowed me to open up live teaching &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;to people outside of my usual geographic reach&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The value proposition for trainers and their clients might be better in a hybrid.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact on Your Value Proposition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point deserves some illustration: think of the last time you or a friend joined a gym and got &#34;free&#34; personal training sessions with your new membership. If it&#39;s been a while, maybe you go through some exercises with the trainer and work out a plan. Great. But now here comes the awkward part. They offer you a $300 option or a $1,000 option. Everyone goes into high pressure mode, you squirm out, and the trainer loses another sale.&amp;Acirc;  Clearly, if high-pressure sales are involved, there&#39;s a dissonance between what you need and what the trainer is trying to offer you. Is there a middle-ground that works for both of you? I&#39;m guessing that if the trainer&#39;s only option is live training, then the answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sales terms, closing the sale came down to offering you an &#34;A or B offer&#34;, but the trainer had the wrong &#34;A or B&#34;. Both missed your real need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a hybrid live and online training model, I don&#39;t see how the trainer in this example (I don&#39;t know which side of the interchange you&#39;re likely to be on, probably both at some point), could offer much variety in terms of their &#34;A or B offer&#34;. The choice was only between more or fewer session, not a different type of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that&#39;s from a marketing and sales point of view. What about an educational point of view?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shifting Your Teaching Model&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The shift toward a hybrid business model is critically important for independent movement educators. We are constrained by one major factor: our limited teaching time. The problem is that you develop a body of knowledge that is vastly bigger than the mechanism for sharing it, one-on-one time with a client. Your students/clients can&#39;t absorb everything you put out in a live training session, but what if the hybrid model makes your knowledge more easily digestible? What if you can share all the information you&#39;ve refined a little bit at a time, in a way that decouples the actual sharing from your live time with clients? I think the hybrid model lies in that direction....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading Kelman&#39;s article, I&#39;m more and more convinced that this is the way to go for movement educators. I&#39;ve already tried to articulate what I&#39;ll now think of as &#34;hybrid strategies&#34; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/earn-an-extra-10000-this-year/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a related note, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/&#34;&gt;&#34;Enterprise of One&#34; &lt;/a&gt;theory here. It&#39;s the crumbling barriers of entry to business technology that are making all of this possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become an Enterprise of One </title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 09:04:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over at TechCrunch, Stephen Martin lays out his thesis about an interesting turning point for entrepreneurs in this economic climate. I could quote the piece at length, but I think this part is especially important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;These business mavericks live by a new dynamic of success &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; unique  individual strengths, expertise and credibility &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; fueled by today&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s  cultural and technological changes. In this new dimension of business  lies the secret to success in our transformed world of commerce. Armed  with a new viewpoint, and the tools to make a difference, these  entrepreneurs run their businesses based on the central principle that  once all of the barriers to entry, transaction costs and other hurdles  are stripped away by technology and cultural changes, an individual&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s  strengths and weaknesses are primarily what determine his or her  success.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve been trying to put my finger on something like this for a while and I think he says it really well. It&#39;s cheaper than ever to start a business and run a business because of all the technology small business owners can use to leverage their time.&amp;Acirc;  It&#39;s easier to communicate with lots and lots of people and instead of being buried in the back office, to quote Stephen again, &#34;the opportunities provided by the transformation to an online business  landscape...have left individual strengths, passions and  expertise as the only distinguishing factors remaining in an  individual&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s or business&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; success. Who you are as a person, and your  expertise and passions, are more important than ever. In fact, they  drive your own personal enterprise.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full article &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/12/27/entrepreneurs-great-reset/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning the Wheel</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2010 08:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Claude Hopkins, in &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Scientific Advertising&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Rapid stream ran by the writer&#39;s boyhood home. The stream turned a wooden wheel and the wheel ran a mill. Under that primitive method, all but a fraction of the streams&#39; potentiality went to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then someone applied scientific methods to that stream -- put in a turbine and dynamos. Now, with no more water, no more power, it runs a large manufacturing plant.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-470 alignleft&#34; title=&#34;falls&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2010/12/4121005703_2898edb080_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt; I love the image of harnessing more power from natural resources through better systems. Obviously, we&#39;re still taking about making a small business really churn, not powering a city from a hydro-electric plant, but the lesson is clear. If you&#39;re not using good systems in your small business, you&#39;re wasting potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&#39;d like to have it both ways, because the other part of the image that is so striking to me is the miller with the old wooden wheel. Every movement education professional that I know is really a craftsperson at heart. I just know there&#39;s a balance, though, between your craft and your business supporting a lifestyle you&#39;d like to live. That&#39;s what we&#39;re striving to find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/d-kav/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DaveKav&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technology and All that Heavenly Glory</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/03/technology-and-all-that-heavenly-glory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2010 09:31:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/03/technology-and-all-that-heavenly-glory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the process of building and launching &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trainerfly&lt;/a&gt;, I&#39;ve tried to keep the wisdom of Bruce Lee in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/sDW6vkuqGLg?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/sDW6vkuqGLg?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too many people are &#34;looking at the finger&#34; when they think of technology. What&#39;s the point of lightning fast communication and access to an abundance of information? It has to come back to people communicating. Otherwise, it just doesn&#39;t mean a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that the proliferation of fast, ubiquitous communication technology accelerates so much, that people finally get beyond the finger-fascination and can start looking at the moon -- in all its heavenly glory -- again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>