<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>technology on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/technology/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in technology on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Home Practice Challenge</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:19:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</guid>
      <description>From the recent practice survey we conducted at Brookline Tai Chi and experiments I&#39;ve been running in online learning, it&#39;s become clearer and clearer to me that most people need some external motivation when they are learning a new skill. That&#39;s not a judgment about willpower and motivation, it actually says more about the way we are wired for survival. In Z Health, we always talk about the way that the nervous system is at once the most plastic system -- it can adapt to lots of different changes -- and also the most stable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Posted from Trainerfly: Launching an Online Course</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2011 10:36:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</guid>
      <description>Check out this post from the Trainerfly blog. I talk to teachers and trainers all the time who want move beyond their live events, but the number of steps it takes, and the technology required to make it work seem overwhelming. Hopefully, I&#39;ve made a little dent in that perception!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>xkcd: Let Go</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 08:43:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</guid>
      <description>Be sure to mouse over for the original title text from the comic (Thanks, Nate!).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simplicity, Persuasion and Technology</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 08:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been reading/watching a lot of BJ Fogg&#39;s work lately. He studies the persuasive power of technology for positive behavior change. You&#39;ll recognize my interest here if you read some of my recent posts on game design mechanics and the potential to integrate technology into real world learning. 
(Check out his Youtube channel for some shorter videos that explain facets of his work &#34;in 60 seconds&#34;)
Here&#39;s Dr. Fogg on simplicity:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crossfit&#39;s Brilliant use of Game Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/04/crossfits-brilliant-use-of-game-mechanics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2011 06:51:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/04/crossfits-brilliant-use-of-game-mechanics/</guid>
      <description>Background: Recently, TechCrunch featured an article about the playdeck they use at SCVNGR that outlines the mechanics of gameplay. The article cites at TED talk by game designer Jane McGonigal, which I talk about here.
I was a little disappointed with McGonigal&#39;s conclusion, because she basically offered up the solution as specially-themed video games to leverage the power of game mechanics, or &#34;gameplay superpowers&#34;, to do good in the real world and incite behavior change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epic Meaning, Sheep Knuckles, and The Institute for the Future</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2011 09:30:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</guid>
      <description>Jane McGonigal gives a fascinating talk about the &#34;superpowers&#34; cultivated by the game-playing masses (more than 500 million with another billion coming up in the next decade!). Obviously we all have the image of the gamer locked in his mother&#39;s basement, endlessly pawing away at an electronic reward system, like a hamster. McGonigal&#39;s takeaway is a little different though.
She emphasizes the motivation, inspiration, and social purpose built into game play.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out with the Old....Business Model</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 16:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/31/out-with-the-old-business-model/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s the end of the year and it&#39;s time to get out of old habits and mindsets.
So, here&#39;s my prediction for the best business model for independent fitness and wellness pros, for the next DECADE. Yeah, I think it&#39;s going to take a few years to unfold, but the groundwork has been laid:
 No more brick-and-mortar businesses. Trust me, I know what it&#39;s like to cut a $10,000 rent check each month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Business Thought Experiment</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 19:35:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m working strictly on a hunch here, but I think there&#39;s a connection between the sentiment I tried to express here about not getting lost in the bells and whistles of technology, and this article about &#34;hybrid businesses&#34;.
One Foot in the Virtual World, One Foot in the Real World
According to&amp;Acirc; the author, Glenn Kelman, a hybrid business has &#34;one foot in the virtual world and one foot in the real world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become an Enterprise of One </title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 09:04:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/</guid>
      <description>Over at TechCrunch, Stephen Martin lays out his thesis about an interesting turning point for entrepreneurs in this economic climate. I could quote the piece at length, but I think this part is especially important:
These business mavericks live by a new dynamic of success &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; unique individual strengths, expertise and credibility &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; fueled by today&#39;s cultural and technological changes. In this new dimension of business lies the secret to success in our transformed world of commerce.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning the Wheel</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2010 08:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</guid>
      <description>Claude Hopkins, in Scientific Advertising:
A Rapid stream ran by the writer&#39;s boyhood home. The stream turned a wooden wheel and the wheel ran a mill. Under that primitive method, all but a fraction of the streams&#39; potentiality went to waste.
Then someone applied scientific methods to that stream -- put in a turbine and dynamos. Now, with no more water, no more power, it runs a large manufacturing plant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technology and All that Heavenly Glory</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/03/technology-and-all-that-heavenly-glory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2010 09:31:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/03/technology-and-all-that-heavenly-glory/</guid>
      <description>In the process of building and launching Trainerfly, I&#39;ve tried to keep the wisdom of Bruce Lee in mind:

Too many people are &#34;looking at the finger&#34; when they think of technology. What&#39;s the point of lightning fast communication and access to an abundance of information? It has to come back to people communicating. Otherwise, it just doesn&#39;t mean a thing.
I hope that the proliferation of fast, ubiquitous communication technology accelerates so much, that people finally get beyond the finger-fascination and can start looking at the moon -- in all its heavenly glory -- again.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>