<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>psychology on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/categories/psychology/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in psychology on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Yin and Yang of Problem Solving</title>
      <link>/2013/11/08/the-yin-and-yang-of-problem-solving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 09:46:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/08/the-yin-and-yang-of-problem-solving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-3831&#34; alt=&#34;following instructions&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/04/following-instructions.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;181&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;You know how you can be banging your head against a wall, trying to figure something out?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you sleep on it, take a shower, or go for a walk and suddenly a solution pops into your head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why this happens or how it works? So have I...and I don&#39;t know HOW it works, but I do know that we are practicing the exact same skill in qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s look at how it works in qigong, why you might be missing it, and how you can begin to recognize some of the same signs in other areas of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;20 Repetitions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
People often ask why we do qigong sets in certain numbers. Whenever I&#39;ve heard Bruce Frantzis answer that question, he tells a story about these elaborate experiments they run in the Taoist monasteries, over generations, with control groups and varying repetitions, to see what the optimal number of repetitions for each exercise is. I always feel bad for the monks who spent their lives doing a few too many of each exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think there&#39;s another reason to do somewhere around 20 reps of each exercises (in a typical qigong set). I tried to explain &lt;a title=&#34;Repetition as Rhythm: Why Do 20 Reps?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/28/repetition-as-rhythm-why-do-20-reps/&#34;&gt;how each group of reps feels to me in this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this context, what I want you to start to look for is the moment when, after a certain number of repetitionss, you cross a threshold where internal rhythms can take over. Your directed, intentional mind can flip from &#34;doing&#34; to &#34;following.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In those moments when the solution to your problem finally dawns on you, don&#39;t you feel the same way? Your mind is open and the solution comes in. You&#39;re not bearing down on the problem with intention (and tension) the same way when you were trying to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tension and Relaxation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, if these really are parallel processes, some interesting connections emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like you need a balance of doing and not doing, of tension and relaxation, or, as we&#39;ve been trained to think in qigong, yin and yang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For problem solving, most people focus on the yang moment of structure and intention, the active phase of &#34;working to solve the problem.&#34; Then, when we figure it out in the shower, &#34;out of nowhere,&#34; we beat ourselves up for not seeing it, or think we&#39;re stupid because now the solution is so obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But qigong teaches us that the yang phase is necessary to set up the yin phase. You have the prime the process actively before you can relax into the passive phase where a solution can emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often have you approached a problem with the intention to solve it, then equally valued and created the space, time, and distance to let the yin phase of problem solving happen? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we trained to let this happen the same way we train dissolving and sense our bodies, energies, and minds in qigong? &lt;em&gt;I know I could personally use more of this kind of practice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some more ideas on problem solving and letting solutions come to you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The True Value of Your Qigong Practice&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/30/the-true-value-of-your-qigong-practice/&#34;&gt;Tony Schwartz on Ennobling Rest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/&#34;&gt;Pushing Hands to find a Third Solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/24/transforming-conflict-with-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Honing Your Tai Chi Listening Skills in Everyday Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Student Practice Habits</title>
      <link>/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2011 08:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Donkey Kong from Arcade-Musuem.com&#34; src=&#34;http://www.arcade-museum.com/images/118/1181242103213.png&#34; alt=&#34;The Donkey Kong Model of Learning&#34; height=&#34;256&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What the heck does Donkey Kong have to do with the practice habits of tai chi students? It turns out the ladders and platforms in the video game are a perfect model for understanding the ecosystem of students practice habits. Let me explain the survey design and then I&#39;ll share some really fascinating results about how people engage Brookline Tai Chi to develop their tai chi practice.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1494&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Survey Design&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Last week we conducted a small practice survey to try to get a more accurate picture of what students do outside of class. We sent out a request to participate to about 2000 people on our email list, and 30 completed the survey in detail. I then divided the 30 into 3 groups, to test the difference between two types of daily reminders and a weekly follow-up. The initial survey, sent on a Sunday, asked people about &#34;typical&#34; practice habits: frequency, duration, and content. I followed up on Friday with the same set of questions, but instead of asking what people &#34;typically&#34; practice, I asked them what they specifically practiced &#34;last week&#34;. In between the initial Sunday survey and the follow-up Friday survey, 1/3 of participants received a daily email that said &#34;Thanks again for volunteering to help us develop better practice tools for our tai chi community. I&#39;m going to send you a little practice reminder every day this week and ask you about it at the end of the week. So...take a few minutes today to do some practice!&#34;. Another third got a similar email, but it included a link to a one-question survey: &#34;what did you practice today?&#34; The last third only got the Sunday and Friday surveys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who Participated in the Survey&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, in this case, we actually know just about everyone who participated in the survey, but that&#39;s a good thing. We&#39;re not trying to run a randomized, controlled, double-blinded study. We&#39;re trying to gain deeper insight into our students&#39; experience and develop tools for them that makes the practice more rewarding. So who participated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people were relatively new to learning tai chi and chi gung&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people have been doing home practice for 15 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people attend classes 3-5 times per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people don&#39;t live nearby the school or in Massachusetts (but they were tuned in enough to what we do to complete this survey, hmmm)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I was really excited to see that we got such a range of people interested in participating in this experience. It speaks to richness of our community that the request to &#34;help us develop better practice tools&#34; was embraced by people with so many different relationships to the school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the results started coming in, it looked to me that people fell into a few distinct categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Home Practicers vs. School Practicers vs. Blended Practice People&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skill Acquisition Mode vs. Practice Plateau Mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There was also a category of what I think of now as &#34;Super Practicers&#34;. Whereas most people reported on practice frequency as a number of days, these folks said &#34;daily&#34;. As I watched their survey results come in and read how they talked about their practice, it was clear that their practice is so ingrained into their lives, that practicing for them is just like eating or breathing. Surprisingly, the amount of time the Super Practicers reported varied from 10 minutes to 2 hours. It wasn&#39;t like the 10 minute Super Practicer was yearning to be in the 2 hour category, though. It was just that 10 minutes a day makes perfect sense for the role practice plays in their life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Skill Ladders and Practice Platforms&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ok, so here&#39;s where the Donkey Kong Model comes in. It was very clear that the students we surveyed fell into two different groups, which roughly matched up to how long they had been in their practice, but not completely. Some of the participants were actively engaged in learning new material, which is usually the choreography of a tai chi or chi gung set. The folks in this category who received daily email reminders to practice did more practice during the week than they thought they typically do. The folks in this category who only got the end-of-week follow-up did less practice than they reported initially.&lt;strong&gt; It seems clear from these results that when you are on the ladder of new skill acquisition, daily practice triggers help you get there faster.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, we have the people who are maintaining a regular, ongoing practice. For these folks, there was almost no change in reported practice, whether they received daily emails or the weekly survey. To these people, the reminders were more of an annoyance (they told me so!). The conclusion here isn&#39;t that the tool is not useful, it&#39;s that these folks don&#39;t need an external reminder to perform something that is internally motivated. More importantly, seeing very little change in the Practice Plateau group highlighted the impact of the daily reminders on the Skill Acquisition group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Donkey King Model is useful here, because over the course of your lifetime of practice, you don&#39;t just go through one Skill Acquisition Phase and one Practice Plateau. I like that image from the game of hanging out on a platform for a while, at a certain level of practice, before you embark on another climb up the skill ladder. From my own experience as a student and as a teacher, I think this is much more common. My intuition is that the daily reminder tool could be refined, if it&#39;s goal-specific enough, to be useful to anyone who is in a Skill Acquisition Phase, not just complete beginners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where Does Motivation Come From?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Where does motivation come from? I don&#39;t actually know for sure, but we learned some really interesting stuff about how people construct their practice. There seems to be a spectrum from internal to external sources of motivation. Again, this often correlated to how long people have been doing the practice, but not completely. Here&#39;s what I mean: when people first walk through the door to learn chi gung or tai chi, they need external motivation: they don&#39;t have the right information yet, they don&#39;t know what to practice, and they don&#39;t have any practice habits yet (for this art).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you climb one or two skill ladders, you start to feel the benefits of practice. You no longer practice &#34;because my doctor told me to&#34; or because &#34;I saw people doing it in the parks in China&#34;. Instead, the practice starts to satisfy you on some level. At this point, we see some branching. There are a small number of people who take one course and then go off and practice on their own forever. To me, they&#39;ve abandoned all of the external motivation we can provide, and made regular practice 100% internally driven. More often we see students who are happy to have the social support of classmates, a physical place to practice, and the guidance of an instructor -- all external motivators --- to keep their practice going. Many slot into this relationship with the school indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our instructors tells a funny story where a friend of hers, on hearing that she&#39;s been coming to classes for 15 years, said &#34;Don&#39;t you know it already?&#34; That&#39;s a perfect example of assuming that long term practice is one big skill ladder to climb. It&#39;s not. The practice plateaus along the way are not the same as the linear climb to skill acquisition and part of what a community like Brookline Tai Chi offers is not only external motivation, but external connection -- to people and a place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any progress we make developing practice tools for our students will have to consider all of these factors, internal and external motivators, phases of skill acquisition and even the satisfaction of practice plateaus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That brings me to the most surprising result in our survey. Many of the participants fell into the Super Practicer category, with extremely high internal motivation to practice, and in some cases no immediate geographic proximity to the school. By all appearances, this is the group who has moved on from everything we have to offer -- weekly classes, skill ladders, a space, people to practice with, instructor feedback . So why did so many of these folks respond to a request to develop practice tools for our community? In one sense, they appear to be the least connected to the day-to-day activities of the school and the least in need of help with practice, but they all responded to our request and gave a tremendous amount of insight into their practice habits. It&#39;s going to be a huge payoff for me when we finally figure out what makes these folks tick.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health Month Wrap-Up</title>
      <link>/2011/03/29/health-month-wrap-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 14:48:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/29/health-month-wrap-up/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As March comes to an end, I&#39;m wrapping up playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://healthmonth.com&#34;&gt;Health Month&lt;/a&gt;, an online game that helps you integrate new habits and change behavior. Here&#39;s my review of Health Month and a recap of what I experienced. I have to say, I don&#39;t think I really explored it to the fullest, but there were a couple of things I really liked about it and a couple of things I didn&#39;t connect with in the design.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-789&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, what didn&#39;t really work for me, then what I really like about this tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Point System&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Each day when you &#34;play your turn&#34;, you get a number of points for the rules you follow (set up at the beginning of the month) and lose points for the ones you don&#39;t. My problem was, the points didn&#39;t really have meaning for me. What was much more valuable for me was recognizing the connection between following the rules and how I felt, both in terms of succeeding in the task of following them, and in terms of how healthier habits made me feel physically. More on this below...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Social Aspect&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, you are supposed to be able to regain points and be held accountable by interacting with other people. I never connected in to this layer of the game, so it was hard to put weight behind the points or more public accountability. Maybe if I had started playing with someone I already knew, I would have found this aspect more compelling. It&#39;s probably pretty necessary to make these connections right away and I think there are ways to find people with similar rules or goals. I just never pulled the trigger on this piece of it because I wanted to ease into playing, but a couple of weeks in, I think not having that social pressure made it easier for me to ignore the game more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Having a Month&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I really like that the time frame is set as a month, for two reasons. First, the reset is right around the corner. Every month is a fresh start if you really get off track. Second, setting a goal for a behavior over a span like 30 days is much more manageable than saying you want to do something &#34;from now on&#34;, or as they call it at the Stanford Persuasive Technology Lab, adopting a &#34;Path Behavior&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s an explanation of the Fogg Behavior Model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/VqqJOMcd2zI?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/VqqJOMcd2zI?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s interesting though, that Dr. Fogg recently tweeted this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/bjfogg/status/35456115961638912&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Our data shows: People want to achieve Path Behaviors most. But they should really focus on Span Behaviors. www.behaviorgrid.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The difference between a &#34;span&#34; behavior and a &#34;path&#34; behavior is duration. &#34;From now on&#34; is too indefinite for most people to really master. When you limit the change you are aiming for to one month, though, you are creating a more manageable goal.&amp;Acirc;  Health Month makes you shoot for &#34;span&#34; behaviors by design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using Rules&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There was something that really clicked for me about formulating my Health Month goals as rules. Rules guide you from vague goals into concrete actions. I had to think through weekly situations and envision when I was going to follow my rules. The rules had to be crafted in ways I could reasonably follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a golden mean between doing things differently and doing them in a sustainable way. Fast changes, where you try to re-shape everything in your life, don&#39;t work. Imagine waking up one morning and deciding that your are going to do everything different, eat, exercise, work, interact. You can&#39;t do it. Part of that has to do with how weak our willpower really is. When you have to exercise a lot of self-control, you literally drain energy from your cognitive abilities (Chip and Dan Heath go through great examples of this and the concept of visualizing habits you want to ingrain ahead of time in &lt;a href=&#34;http://heathbrothers.com/switch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Switch&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the other extreme is not changing at all or changing the wrong things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that most of what you do should be driven by habit. That&#39;s the most efficient way to do things. But, you have to be thoughtful about the habits you want to create in life, and work hard at the systems and practices that are going to develop the habits you want. It&#39;s a strange mindset, I know. The cognitive work is in building the systems. Leave the rest to your nervous system&#39;s natural ability to adapt and make habits. I think Health Month helped me see this more clearly and I look forward to &#34;playing by the rules&#34; now even more!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Rules Are Lame</title>
      <link>/2011/03/07/my-rules-are-lame/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 08:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/07/my-rules-are-lame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, with one week of &lt;a href=&#34;http://healthmonth.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Health Month&lt;/a&gt; under my belt, I think one thing is clear: I picked some pretty lame rules for March! I mean, they&#39;re pretty plain and looking at some of the other options, I definitely could have picked something more interesting. I chose:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-680&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring lunch to work 3x per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track food at least 6x per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exercise at least 5x per week&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I picked those rules initially because I thought they would be easy to track and measure and because I had already been working on them in February. I wanted to get a feel for Health Month and use it to cement these new habits. It was definitely a safe, baby-sized step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, I started tracking food and exercise, to try to see if I had any daily or weekly patterns. That was the origin of my own February &#34;rules&#34;, pre-Health Month. I knew I didn&#39;t eat as well as I wanted to for the week when I failed to plan for mid-week lunches, hence the 3x per week bring lunch rule. Similarly, I knew it was harder to track food for me during the weekend, so instead of fighting weekend habits as much, I decided to tighten up during the week, when I had more flexibility and time to prepare anyway. For the exercise rule, I had been experimenting with a recurring Google calendar event, with an SMS reminder, to try to get something in Monday-Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, coming in to getting set up in Health Month for March, I figured I would&amp;Acirc;  just map these rules on to the new system to get a feel for how the Health Month triggers reinforced the behavior I was in the process of trying to adopt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know? When I put it that way, I don&#39;t feel as lame.....Haha. In fact, what I realize now, is that I&#39;m going to be even more motivated to put some really interesting rules in play for April. That should be fun!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signing the Contract</title>
      <link>/2011/03/04/signing-the-contract/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 08:38:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/04/signing-the-contract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-674&#34; title=&#34;Commitment&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/03/Commitment.bmp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;550&#34; height=&#34;413&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of playing Health Month is signing a contract to commit to follow your rules....and I was really surprised when I did it! &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-672&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;One of the things I&#39;m thinking about while playing is how this is different from simply tracking what you eat, when you work out, and even setting goals in other areas. I didn&#39;t think it was going to be a big deal to actually sign this commitment, but it was. I have to say, I got a little nervous before I clicked on my name there. How many electronic signatures or license agreements do you sign online all the time? But this felt just a little bit different and I think that&#39;s an ingenious feature!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>xkcd: Let Go</title>
      <link>/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 08:43:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/23/xkcd-let-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Be sure to mouse over for the original title text from the comic (Thanks, Nate!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/862/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; title=&#34;After years of trying various methods, I broke this habit by pitting my impatience against my laziness. I decoupled the action and the neurological reward by setting up a simple 30-second delay I had to wait through, in which I couldn&#39;t do anything else, before any new page or chat client would load (and only allowed one to run at once). The urge to check all those sites magically vanished--and my &#39;productive&#39; computer use was unaffected.&#34; src=&#34;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/let_go.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;518&#34; height=&#34;166&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March is Going to be Health Month</title>
      <link>/2011/02/21/march-is-going-to-be-health-month/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2011 09:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/21/march-is-going-to-be-health-month/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m pretty excited to try this one out. Health Month is a behavior change game where you set rules to follow each month and do daily tracking, with rewards and penalties for how well you follow them. I&#39;m just digging into it, but so far it looks like you can choose &#34;do more of this&#34; or &#34;do less of that&#34;.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-638&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I like the idea of limiting the scope of the goal to a month (what BJ Fogg calls a &#34;span&#34; behavior instead of a &#34;path&#34; behavior -- and says the key to long term change is focusing on span not path) and the immediate feedback from daily tracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m curious about the reward system, to see if it really is compelling and there also is some kind of social wrinkle where you can help and get help from other players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the site, here&#39;s how to play:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to play&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;definition_summary&#34;&gt;Are you new to Health Month?  Here&#39;s the quick and dirty.&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Health Month is all about making small improvements to your health,  one month at a time.  Players (that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s you!) can choose 1 or more rules  to try to stick to for a month from the many different dietary, fitness,  relationship, mental health, and financial health behaviors that are  currently in the game.  For first time players, 1-5 rules is a nice way  to start.  Choose rules that you want to work on, and try to make small  improvements to your current behavior rather than going cold-turkey,  whole-hog, or crazy-wombat.  You can always ratchet up the difficulty  next month,  once you get the hang of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are life points?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you commit to your rules, you start each month with 10 shiny  new life points.  The goal is to end the month with at least 1 life  point.  You lose a life point whenever you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t stick to one of your  rules, but don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t worry if you lose all of your life points &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s what  friends are for!  Friends and other players of Health Month have your  back when you need to be healed (this is a big part of why Health Month  totally rocks compared to other health plans and services).  This game  is NOT about making you feel guilty.  It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s  about helping you discover what works for your current lifestyle (do  more of that) and what doesn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t (skip it).  Also, if you accidentally  over-commit yourself and and lose all of your life points (I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve seen  some people go to -100 life points and more!  Maybe there should be an  award for being ambitious?), it just means you can take it a little  easier next month.  Life is long.  Small improvements will make a bigger  impact long term.  And, by the way, you can still play the game if you  are -100 life points&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar; everything still works as usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When do I play?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day, during the month that you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve committed to play, you can  come to the site and play your turn.  Spin the Wild Wheel if you feel  like adding an extra helping of whimsey to your game (don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t worry, most  of the outcomes are positive) or you can skip it and go straight to  filling out your daily scorecard without collecting $200.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do I do with fruit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you follow all of your rules for a day, you get a piece of fruit.   You can use fruit to heal other players who have lost life points.   It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s a good thing to do, because they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll remember you when you need to  be healed in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where are my friends?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow friends and team mates on Health Month to see a stream of how  everyone else is doing with their game (think Twitter or Facebook for  improving your life).  You&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re all in it together, and posting questions,  tips, fears, and challenges that you run into helps remind you that  things like this work better when they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re done with friends and family.   Don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t be afraid to invite them!  :)&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buried Psychological Nuggets</title>
      <link>/2011/02/05/buried-psychological-nuggets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2011 09:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/05/buried-psychological-nuggets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/mba-earn-more-money/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a long post&lt;/a&gt; from one of my favorite authors, Ramit Sethi. He often writes about putting ideas into action and I think this post is another great example, BUT, that&#39;s not what I want to highlight here.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-598&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I think this is my new favorite concept:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skepticism is not a strategy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to one of my top Earn1k students last week &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; she earned over $80,000 in 8 weeks &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; and she was talking about how much her entire viewpoint has changed. Once you realize that you can control your situation &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; how much you earn, how much you work, where you live, etc &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s amazing to look back at ourselves a few years ago&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;when we were skeptical and disbelieving that any of this could work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skeptics always have an excuse because it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s easier to be skeptical than to take the risk of trying something and possibly failing. Skeptics use codewords &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; much like racists do &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; to mask their fear and loathing of something different. For example, they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll say they don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have enough time (when everyone has the same 24 hours per day). They&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll complain about having &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;already tried that,&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; but when you dig in and ask them what they actually tried, they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll demur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s nothing I hate more than vocal skeptics &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; not only because they cheat themselves out of their own potential, but because they convince others that they can&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t do it, either.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can see this all over the place. It&#39;s another version of the Taoist saying that &#34;you become what you practice&#34;. You can literally watch skeptics develop a hard shell of denial as they try fewer and fewer new things. I&#39;m not necessarily blaming someone for this tendency, but I think it becomes a cycle that reinforces itself. That&#39;s why I love Ramit&#39;s writing: &#34;skepticism is not a strategy&#34; doesn&#39;t get into the blame, shame, or origin of the behavior, but it calls it out directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way he writes just draws such clean lines. Take this distinction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I write for the As, Bs, and Cs &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; but I systematically ignore one of them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine  the world has As, Bs, and Cs in  any field. In this one, the As are  already managing their money,  they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve read my book (and others), and  they&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re earning as much as they  need to lead the lifestyle they choose. They&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re already doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The  Bs are the greatest in number. They  have the potential to do something  great, but for whatever reason &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;  like actual barriers, self-imposed  barriers, or external  responsibilities &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; they &amp;Acirc; haven&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t achieved what  their potential first. &lt;em&gt;They can be reached if you communicate to them in the right way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The  Cs are a lost cause. Sure, they  might be salvageable to help, but  that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s not something I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m interested  in or capable of. This enrages  certain people who believe that we  should help everyone, but I live in  the world of practicality, not  utopia. If I have the chance to help an A  become an A+ in 3 months, or a  C become a B- in 3 years, who am I going  to choose? There are other  people who make it their life&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s work to work  with Cs, but it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s not me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And  so this is also applicable for you.  When I teach negotiation, or  interviewing, or automation, or even  earning more money, I teach you how  to focus on the right level of  analysis for you. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s ok not to please everyone. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d rather spend my  time hyper-focused on exactly your needs than try to serve everyone.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Great stuff! Here&#39;s that link again: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/mba-earn-more-money/&#34;&gt;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/mba-earn-more-money/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simplicity, Persuasion and Technology</title>
      <link>/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 08:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/20/simplicity-persuasion-and-technology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been reading/watching a lot of BJ Fogg&#39;s work lately. He studies &lt;a href=&#34;http://captology.stanford.edu/&#34;&gt;the persuasive power of technology for positive behavior change&lt;/a&gt;. You&#39;ll recognize my interest here if you read some of my recent posts on game design mechanics and the potential to integrate technology into real world learning. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-557&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Check out his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/bjfogg&#34;&gt;Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; for some shorter videos that explain facets of his work &#34;in 60 seconds&#34;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s Dr. Fogg on simplicity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/2094487&#34;&gt;BJ Fogg on Simplicity&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/bjfogg&#34;&gt;BJ Fogg&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He makes a really important distinction around the 3:20 mark. We tend to think of simplicity as a feature of our technology, but he disagrees. Instead, he says &#34;simplicity is a perception we have of the experience in accomplishing the task&#34;. This means that you have to consider the person and the context if you want to facilitate behavior change, not just the information you are giving them, or the medium you are using to deliver the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the coming weeks, I&#39;ll write more about his 3-part behavior change model, summed up as &#34;putting hot triggers in the path of motivated people&#34; and try to explain how I see Motivation, Ability, and Triggers applied to teaching, business, and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all fascinating stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>