<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>dragon-and-tiger on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/dragon-and-tiger/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in dragon-and-tiger on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/dragon-and-tiger/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dragon and Tiger Exercises for Activating the Lower Tantien</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 07:32:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re borrowing a technique from Dragon and Tiger qigong to try and get a better sense of the lower tantien. The lower tantien (&#34;dan-tee-en&#34;) is the energetic center of your physical body, located just below your navel, on the central axis of the body. If you dropped a line down from the crown of the head, through the body, and out the bottom of the pelvis, it would pass through the lower tantien.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Sensations That Arise When You Are Developing Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 07:24:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</guid>
      <description>In this episode of Qigong Radio, I answer some questions about different sensations readers have been experiencing when they practice.
In the Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong Instruction Manual, Bruce Frantzis lays out important guidelines for what kinds of &#34;chi reactions&#34; to expect. I want to show you how to apply these guidelines to your practice.
 Expect Chi Reactions
Dragon and Tiger is a powerful tool for awakening your body on physical, energetic, emotional, mental and spiritual levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving Your Energy to Soothe Your Mind</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/15/moving-your-energy-to-soothe-your-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2012 17:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/15/moving-your-energy-to-soothe-your-mind/</guid>
      <description>In this episode of Qigong Radio, I thought I was going to get a report about the Dragon and Tiger instructor training.
Yes, the six instructors who joined me for the episode talked about the training. If you missed Maui, you&#39;ll get a sense of what it was like.
But they also shared some true qigong gems with us, that I think you&#39;ll be able to apply to all of your energy practices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bill Ryan on Developing Energy Sensitivity</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 06:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/</guid>
      <description>When learning qigong or Tai Chi, people are often either more tuned into to energy or to their physical bodies. In this episode of Qigong Radio, I asked my first qigong and Tai Chi teacher, Energy Arts Senior Instructor and founder of Brookline Tai Chi, Bill Ryan to explain why this is.
More importantly, Bill teaches you how to navigate the experiences of developing your internal energy, regardless of how you first become aware of them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Lessons from Qigong Instructor Trainings</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/14/16-lessons-from-qigong-instructor-trainings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2012 08:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/14/16-lessons-from-qigong-instructor-trainings/</guid>
      <description>This June, my qigong teacher Bruce Frantzis will be offering a two-week Dragon and Tiger Qigong instructor training on Maui. Over the past 10 years, I&#39;ve attended most of the instructor trainings that he has offered, as well as many weekends and week-long retreats.
Being in an intensive learning environment at these events is great for your personal practice.
If you&#39;re thinking about teaching this material, though, you have to be smart about how you approach these trainings.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>