<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>dragon-and-tiger on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/dragon-and-tiger/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in dragon-and-tiger on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/dragon-and-tiger/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dragon and Tiger Exercises for Activating the Lower Tantien</title>
      <link>/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 07:32:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re borrowing a technique from Dragon and Tiger qigong to try and get a better sense of the lower tantien. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lower tantien (&#34;dan-tee-en&#34;) is the energetic center of your physical body, located just below your navel, on the central axis of the body. If you dropped a line down from the crown of the head, through the body, and out the bottom of the pelvis, it would pass through the lower tantien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because this center is so deep inside the body, it is hard to feel. When you do find the energetic center of your body, though, you learn to realign your posture around it, feeling full and supported in a completely different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/-613On-w15U?list=UU4DJ7xUL-TWEBOgDp_ekI5Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this exercise, you want to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the palms, looking for the energetic sensation, as if you were pressing magnets together or pulling taffy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the energy get quiet once you stabilize the connection. Release, dissolve, and let go, without disconnecting the palms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat the first two steps, but with the palms facing the lower tantien.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, try to connect to this same internal alignment with the arms resting by your sides&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you find it, just hang out with the connection and don&#39;t try to do anything else!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Sensations That Arise When You Are Developing Chi</title>
      <link>/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 07:24:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, I answer some questions about different sensations readers have been experiencing when they practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dragon-and-tiger-medical-qigong/&#34;&gt;Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong&lt;/a&gt; Instruction Manual, Bruce Frantzis lays out important guidelines for what kinds of &#34;chi reactions&#34; to expect. I want to show you how to apply these guidelines to your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Expect Chi Reactions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dragon and Tiger is a powerful tool for awakening your body on physical, energetic, emotional, mental and spiritual levels. As you practice these movements and begin to move your body in ways that may be different for you, energy and fluids in your body are stirred up and begin to move more vigorously. At some point you may experience reactions that may seem either positive or negative to you. These are called chi reactions: the body&#39;s response to the effects of energy beginning to flow more freely through previously blocked places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These reactions may show up immediately, hours after practicing, or even a day or two later. Although many people will not begin to feel either negative or positive reactions without practicing a lot, others, particularly if they have done other forms of personal development work, may notice reactions almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Positive Chi Reactions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Positive reactions can range from feeling less pain and having more energy to being more centered, relaxed and comfortable with your body. Some people report that they sleep much better; others report greater flexibility and balance. You may also notice that you are calmer and have fewer mood swings. You may experience an overall reduction in stress and tension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A transformative effect that most people consider positive, is an increase in and awareness of sexual energy. This is entirely normal as it is the most fundamental energy in your body, and practice of Dragon and Tiger will increase sexual energy. Finally, a transformative effect that confuses many people is what we call &#34;good pain.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dragon and Tiger is designed to gradually work more and more deeply into your body, to release muscles and other tissues and joints that have been restricted or blocked. When an area of your body that has been frozen begins to loosen and realign, more energy moves through that area than you are used to. But if the energy cannot flow freely or fully, you may experience temporary pain in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese medical theory of the body holds that pain in an area is a sign that the energy there is not flowing freely. You feel &#34;bad&#34; pain when an area is newly injured or hurt. In general, &#34;good&#34; pains tend to be temporary (lasting from a minute to at most a couple of days) and are usually dull, rather than sharp. As you practice you will learn to recognize such pains as signs of progress. Treat them with great care and keep within the 40 to 50 percent rule when you have pain, illness or injury (see p. 7). Back off practicing and be sure to consult your healthcare provider if you begin experiencing either significant pain or pain that does not go away quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Negative Chi Reactions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As your body wakes up on various levels, it may do so the same way as when aroused from a deep slumber &amp;mdash;cranky, sore and confused. You may experience some negative chi reactions. These can range from relatively mild but confusing aches, nausea, light-headedness, tingles, fatigue, unsteadiness, body temperature shifts or mood changes to strong emotional releases and mood swings to unusual dreams or shifts in perception. You may also experience physical discharges, such as stronger body odors or more frequent bowel movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As blocked and stagnant energy moves or leaves the body, energetic memories that are associated with the problem, stored in either your energy channels or physical tissue can awaken and cause you to relive the underlying and often repressed causes of the problem&amp;mdash;especially if you have a severe condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might experience what doctors refer to as a &#34;healing crisis.&#34; The term refers to that time during healing when a patient&#39;s body temporarily feels worse before it feels better. For example, when the body burns out infections, the patient often has a high fever. When the fever breaks, the symptoms of the disease pass. The fever may cause the patient to feel terrible, until the stored toxins or blocked energy are released. Afterwards the individual feels better as the illness passes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these reactions are common to many natural forms of healing and are often a sign that your body is cleansing itself. Many people have a healing crisis when they fast or switch to a cleansing or vegetarian diet. The practice of Dragon and Tiger may often trigger such effects; they are fairly normal reactions. What is important to remember is that these reactions are temporary and usually pass when your body begins to rebalance itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you begin to experience strong or uncomfortable sensations, immediately sit down, put your hands on your belly and gently breathe with your belly to ground and center yourself. Such sensations will usually pass within minutes. Then suspend or reduce your practice for a while. Start again by following the 20 percent or 40 percent rule and very gently explore your body&#39;s reactions to these practices. Remember that you are not alone in such experiences; almost everyone who practices will experience some of these reactions at some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the symptoms are intense, pull back your practice to 30 percent or 40 percent of what you consider your normal practice and consult with your teacher. Remember to drink plenty of water. Water helps accelerate the release of toxins. Taking some vitamin C also helps that process. Make sure you rest after practicing. Be sure to consult a healthcare professional immediately if you have any symptoms that might be a sign of a medical or psychological problem.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Listen to the episode to find out how to apply this principles to rising energy, activating the lower tantien, and differentiating between nerve flow, blood flood, and normal physical movement.&lt;br /&gt;
[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving Your Energy to Soothe Your Mind</title>
      <link>/2012/07/15/moving-your-energy-to-soothe-your-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2012 17:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/15/moving-your-energy-to-soothe-your-mind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;wp-image-4066 alignright&#34; title=&#34;Dejota Dragon and Tiger&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/07/Dejota-Dragon-and-Tiger-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dejota Apostol moving chi with Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, I thought I was going to get a report about the Dragon and Tiger instructor training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the six instructors who joined me for the episode talked about the training. If you missed Maui, you&#39;ll get a sense of what it was like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they also shared some true qigong gems with us, that I think you&#39;ll be able to apply to all of your energy practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4065&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relaxation in the West vs. Qigong perspective on relaxation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The way stagnant chi impacts your mind and how a tense mind freezes up your chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Dragon and Tiger helps relax the mind into a feeling state as opposed to a thinking state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How Dragon and Tiger&#39;s emphasis on chi circulation transforms other practices like Tai Chi and Ba Gua&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks to everyone who participated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/dorchester/ana-sorina-popa&#34;&gt;Ana Popa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/edgartown/eric-l-peters&#34;&gt;Eric Peters&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/edgartown/eileen-murphy&#34;&gt;Eileen Murphy&lt;/a&gt; from Boston.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/radford/paul-pallante&#34;&gt;Paul Pallante from Radford, Virginia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/san-jose/dejota-apostol&#34;&gt;Dejota Apostol from San Jose, California.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ensostudio.com/taichi.html&#34;&gt;Chris Cinnamon from Chicago.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
They all teach regularly in their local areas, so if you&#39;re looking for a live class to attend, but sure to check them out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bill Ryan on Developing Energy Sensitivity</title>
      <link>/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 06:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/30/bill-ryan-on-developing-energy-sensitivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-3850&#34; title=&#34;Bill Ryan Energy Arts Senior Instructor&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/04/Bill_LO_150w.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bill Ryan Energy Arts Senior Instructor&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When learning qigong or Tai Chi, people are often either more tuned into to energy or to their physical bodies. In this episode of Qigong Radio, I asked my first qigong and Tai Chi teacher, Energy Arts Senior Instructor and founder of Brookline Tai Chi, Bill Ryan to explain why this is.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3844&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, Bill teaches you how to navigate the experiences of developing your internal energy, regardless of how you first become aware of them. It turns out, you&#39;re probably already more tuned in than you think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are very sensitive to energy, Bill also has some great advice about how to become more grounded and balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen to the episode here and then &lt;a href=&#34;http://towardharmony.com/about_us/bill_ryan.html&#34;&gt;learn more about Bill and what he teaches at Toward Harmony Tai Chi and Qigong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks for supporting the Qigong Radio project. I know the audio quality isn&#39;t great &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt;...but if you enjoyed the content, consider making a small donation ($15 goes a long way!) to help us upgrade our equipment. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;cmd&#34; value=&#34;_s-xclick&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;hosted_button_id&#34; value=&#34;JM5L8XE2BBXM4&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_donateCC_LG.gif&#34; alt=&#34;PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/form&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Lessons from Qigong Instructor Trainings</title>
      <link>/2012/01/14/16-lessons-from-qigong-instructor-trainings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2012 08:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/14/16-lessons-from-qigong-instructor-trainings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Class by Brookline Tai Chi, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/brookline_tai_chi/1829912115/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2231/1829912115_838e5ddd20_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Class&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;This June, my qigong teacher Bruce Frantzis will be offering &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/store/events/events/dragon-and-tiger-medical-qigong-instructor-training#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=932cfb54&#34;&gt;a two-week Dragon and Tiger Qigong instructor training&lt;/a&gt; on Maui. Over the past 10 years, I&#39;ve attended most of the instructor trainings that he has offered, as well as many weekends and week-long retreats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in an intensive learning environment at these events is great for your personal practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re thinking about teaching this material, though, you have to be smart about how you approach these trainings. While getting certified is an important step in the teaching process, too many people see certification as an end point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the&amp;Acirc;  lessons I&#39;ve learned about what you should do, before, during, and after the training.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3319&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. They are the single best opportunity to invest in your own practice long-term.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material you will be exposed to will continue to reveal itself through practice for several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;I don&#39;t really know how to describe it in normal language, because it&#39;s not the typical linear learning process that most of us are used to. Think of the entire experience as one big experiment in farming. Bruce will be giving you seeds at the training, and if you water them with regular practice, all kinds of interesting things will emerge later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The training is not an end point in your learning process.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are people at these events who pay their money, get their seeds, and then start to daydream about all the brightly colored vegetables&amp;Acirc;  that will grow from the seeds someday. The go home and put the shiny package of seeds on their shelf, telling all their friends about the great vegetables they&#39;ll harvest soon, and showing everyone their packet of seeds. Six months later, they all but forget about the packet on the shelf and have returned to their regular lives. The seeds never get planted. Nothing grows and more importantly, they miss the chance to be nourished by what they would have harvested if they had truly approached this as a farming opportunity. That&#39;s the problem with treating the training as an end point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Be the farmer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going in to the training, you want to prepare your soil as best you can. You want your soil to be well-tilled so that the seeds have a fertile place to grow. If you show up at the training and you spend all your time hacking away at fresh ground, trying to learn the movements, you&#39;re missing the real learning opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. The more you are &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;re-learning&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;, not just learning, the better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what your current level of practice, when you get to the training, you will break down and refine everything you already know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Pay attention to how you are learning in addition to what you are learning.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do this stage well, you will go home with a clear progression to follow for your future practice and your future teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;how to learn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; dimension is like plotting the rows in your fields. If you mark everything off well, then your plants are more likely to thrive. Most people don&#39;t do this. They get caught up in little details or go off on a weird practice tangent, fixated on one new feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you need to alternate between deep focus and feeling, and big picture thinking and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Bruce will teach something in a hour that I have easily turned into a seven-week course at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructor trainings are designed to be comprehensive, but in a compressed time frame, that means you&#39;ll have to go back later and work out the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Take notes after class.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do the right kind of note-taking, you can glean the structures of how the material is organized, which is incredibly useful when you start teaching. In these trainings, I prefer to take notes at the end of each teaching block, not during the flow of class. When you&#39;re there and you are hearing something for the first time, try to feel it in your body and practice it. Then, your note-taking at the end of the morning or afternoon session will be a reflection on something you&#39;ve already experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Look for patterns in your notes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start paying attention to the patterns in your notebook, you can also start to see how Bruce teaches each piece and then layers new ones in. He has a very clear rhythm of introducing new material, then letting people absorb it, then letting people struggle with it and practice. The Senior Instructors are great at pointing the way to this level of information too. The hard part is that you are there to learn and absorb it yourself, so you have to get used to paying attention to multiple levels at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Be in sponge-mode.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At these trainings, you&#39;ll feel things you&#39;ve never been able to connect with before. When that happens, try to absorb as much of the feeling as you can. Don&#39;t over think it, but get good practice reps in while you can still feel what it is ultimately supposed to feel like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Don&#39;t get addicted to the master&#39;s help.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People get stuck here, being able to feel new things that are actually well beyond their current level of practice. When you leave, you have what I call &#34;the Bruce hangover&#34; because as you go home and practice, it really doesn&#39;t feel like it did when you were in his field. That can be frustrating, but you learn over time that you can work through the material and arrive at real integration. People get hung up on the shortcut of having a master put something in their bodies though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. Start over at the beginning. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;When you go home, the best thing to do for your personal practice is to go back to the very first thing Bruce taught and day one and start practicing from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12. Keep&amp;Acirc;  up your personal practice beyond teaching hours.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing about the relationship between teaching and personal practice is that you need both and they have to be separate. You can&#39;t rely on teaching time to be practice time. In the past, when I slipped on really having a separate personal practice, my teaching would suffer and I would feel like crap. At the times when I could keep my own practice going, on top of teaching, the teaching would really blossom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13. Keep your personal practice out of the classroom.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t teach whatever you are interested in at the moment. I think that&#39;s kind of selfish and myopic. Why would a beginner benefit from something that you are practicing, 5, 10, or 20 years in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14. Don&#39;t teach anything you can&#39;t clearly see going on in someone else&#39;s body or that you can&#39;t demonstrate on command if they put their hands on yours.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, you shouldn&#39;t be teaching anything you&#39;re trying to figure out yourself. In the most extreme case, if you have to stop and think about choreography, you shouldn&#39;t be teaching choreography. If I have to fumble around to get my joints pulsing, or I can only do it every 3rd time, I have no business teaching it to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material that you should teach to other people is material that you&#39;ve learned and integrated and you really own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15. Don&#39;t overestimate what your students are ready for.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, I see new teachers overestimate the depth of what their students can learn anyway. Practically, everyone starts teaching beginners. When you start your first class after the training, you have to teach people the moves. This just means that you have to keep all the really cool stuff you learned at the training under you hat until you&#39;ve developed students who are ready for that material. As you develop them, you&#39;re developing too, so it all works out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16. Teach and you will harvest.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve taught 15-20 hours a week of classes and private lessons for the last 7 years and I have to say that my personal practice has grown in some pretty awesome dimensions that I didn&#39;t anticipate. The hard work of keeping teaching and practice separate and keeping them both going really does pay off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you&#39;re seriously considering going, you have six months &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/store/products/featured/dragon-and-tiger-book-dvd-poster-package#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=932cfb54&#34;&gt;to get ready&lt;/a&gt;. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>