<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>harvard-medical-school on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/harvard-medical-school/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in harvard-medical-school on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/harvard-medical-school/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Obviously Tai Chi Improves Balance, But How Do You Explain It?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 14:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4716&#34; alt=&#34;don + sue 2&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/07/don-+-sue-2-e1373377188614-261x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;261&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We often talk about the way Tai Chi can &lt;a title=&#34;The Transformational Power of Tai Chi Body Mechanics&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/07/the-transformational-power-of-tai-chi-body-mechanics/&#34;&gt;improve your physical health and mental and emotional well-being&lt;/a&gt; from the point of view of the practitioner. But not everyone out there is as familiar with practical ways to use Tai Chi to support their health and wellness goals as you may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later this year, I&#39;m thrilled to have the chance to share Tai Chi with physicians in a course at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hmscme.com/activelives/faculty&#34;&gt;Harvard Medical School&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s always exciting to be able to present a combination of research and practice to knowledgeable caregivers, especially because in this case, the focus of the course is on promoting healthy, active lifestyles to their patients. What do you think I should share with them? If you have suggestions for what I should cover, please leave a note in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the mean time, I&#39;d like to invite you into a conversation about &lt;em&gt;how we talk about the benefits of our practice.&lt;/em&gt; As Brookline Tai Chi has been working with the Department of Public Health and other senior care agencies to spread practical implementation of &lt;a title=&#34;Dr. Fuzhong Li&#39;s Tai Chi Research&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dr-fuzhong-lis-tai-chi-research/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi falls prevention research&lt;/a&gt;, we find ourselves in a very different world, using new language and talking to new audiences about the benefits of Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent episode of Qigong Radio, Dr. Peter Wayne discussed the &lt;a title=&#34;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, a framework that he uses to define his Tai Chi research. We need more thoughtful ways like this to express the benefits of Tai Chi practice in an understandable way, without watering everything down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to keep the conversation moving in this direction, so I took the problem to one of my most eloquent teachers, Don Ethan Miller. As a result, Don and I have been working on a new program, called &lt;strong&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/strong&gt;, which will be out later this summer. In The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance, we set out to refine the language around Tai Chi balance concepts and, more importantly, get at the essence of what makes Tai Chi so good for improving balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we would like you to join in the conversation. Please join us for a discussion of The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance on Thursday, July 18, from 12-1pm EST. We will explore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The essential elements of a Tai Chi balance training program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to make sure you include these balance exercises in every practice session, whether your goal is falls prevention, becoming more relaxed and centered,  or training for competition-level Push Hands &lt;em&gt;(the secret is that it can be the same training!)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to share Tai Chi balance training with friends and family -- without making them feel like they have to take on a serious practice to get real benefits.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p3p1&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p3p1&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p3p1;(function(d, t) { var s = d.createElement(t), options = { &#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,  &#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p3p1&#39;,  &#39;autoResize&#39;:true, &#39;height&#39;:&#39;728&#39;, &#39;async&#39;:true, &#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,  &#39;ssl&#39;:true}; s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;; s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() { var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return; try { r7p3p1 = new WufooForm();r7p3p1.initialize(options);r7p3p1.display(); } catch (e) {}}; var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr); })(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 11:14:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft  wp-image-4644&#34; alt=&#34;HMS guide to Tai Chi&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/05/HMS-guide-to-Tai-Chi1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;120&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; In his new book, the Harvard Medical School Guide to Tai Chi, &lt;a title=&#34;Living between the Lab and the Classroom with Dr. Peter Wayne&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/&#34;&gt;Dr. Peter Wayne&lt;/a&gt; lays out the &#34;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; to help us understand the interface between traditional Tai Chi practice and the Western biomedical paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Research Director of the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, jointly based at Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, and the founder of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.treeoflifetaichi.com/instructors.html&#34;&gt;Tree of Life Tai Chi Center&lt;/a&gt;, Peter blends more than three decades of teaching experience with ongoing inquiry into what makes Tai Chi an effective medical intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, we explore the development of the 8 Active Ingredients and how help translate Tai Chi into a Western context&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi are:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awareness, Mindfulness, Focused Attention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intention, Belief, Expectation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic Structural Integration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active Relaxation of Mind and Body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aerobic Exercise, Musculoskeletal Strengthening, and Flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natural, Freer Breathing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Interaction and Community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embodied Spirituality, Philosophy, and Ritual&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I asked Peter to explain how he understands Tai Chi practice through these 8 ingredients and how they are related to each other. While there are many ways to explain what Tai Chi is, this framework has to explain Tai Chi to a Western medical audience, making each element of the practice related to biomedical and psychological principles rooted in evidence-based medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter tells us what was easy to convey and where the Tai Chi principles were more esoteric, but important to explain through the framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also makes the case for greater medical literacy amongst Tai Chi teachers and practitioners because, as Tai Chi research gets more sophisticated, the feedback loop between what gets studied and how Tai Chi is defined will get tighter and tighter. If you&#39;re concerned with the legacy of Tai Chi in the West, you need to be a part of this conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the podcast for all that and a great sense for Peter&#39;s insight, generosity, and caring as a practitioner and leader in the Tai Chi research field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>