<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>harvard-medical-school on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/harvard-medical-school/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in harvard-medical-school on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/harvard-medical-school/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Obviously Tai Chi Improves Balance, But How Do You Explain It?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 14:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</guid>
      <description>We often talk about the way Tai Chi can improve your physical health and mental and emotional well-being from the point of view of the practitioner. But not everyone out there is as familiar with practical ways to use Tai Chi to support their health and wellness goals as you may be.
Later this year, I&#39;m thrilled to have the chance to share Tai Chi with physicians in a course at Harvard Medical School.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 11:14:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>In his new book, the Harvard Medical School Guide to Tai Chi, Dr. Peter Wayne lays out the &#34;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; to help us understand the interface between traditional Tai Chi practice and the Western biomedical paradigm.
As the Research Director of the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, jointly based at Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, and the founder of the Tree of Life Tai Chi Center, Peter blends more than three decades of teaching experience with ongoing inquiry into what makes Tai Chi an effective medical intervention.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>