<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>teaching on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/teaching/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in teaching on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Gratitude for Immersive Learning</title>
      <link>/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 09:33:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-5033&#34; alt=&#34;Thank_You&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2014/04/Thank_You-e1397827802683-242x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;242&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night I taught my last two weekly classes at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next month, I&#39;ll be diving into &lt;a href=&#34;http://launchacademy.com/&#34;&gt;a new intensive learning experience&lt;/a&gt;, building software applications and learning about the web from a depth I&#39;ve only poked at up until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I have some really cool stuff planned for Immersion Week too, so I&#39;m not quite done yet!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s going to be a big change for me.  I don&#39;t quite know what to make of shedding a professional identity that I&#39;ve held for almost 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I don&#39;t quite know what to say to the students I&#39;ve worked so closely with over all this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I think about what&#39;s coming, I recognize a pattern that I&#39;ve repeated many times in my life. On many occasions now, I&#39;ve been able to dive into a pool that I couldn&#39;t swim in at first, and then somehow, float.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 10 years teaching weekly classes at Brookline Tai Chi, I feel ready to swim in a new pool and in a strange way, I&#39;m excited to be really out of my element, because I know that with the right structure, in the right environment, I will float back up to the surface buoyed by new skills and new perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ten Years Ago at Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I still remember walking across the room, not making eye contract with anyone, just shuffling out into the lobby to wait for students to come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was just a couple of weeks into my job as the new director of Brookline Tai Chi, in the summer of 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after that, many of our lead instructors left the school and while I was in the process of training to teach, I found myself with close to 20 hours a week of classes, not the 3 to 5 I had expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that being thrust into such a high volume of classes created one of the best learning environments I could have hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every night I would have 3 different classes, sometimes 4 on the weekends. That meant that each hour I had to do a complete reset, with a fresh new group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students would come in from whatever they had done all day and I had to &#34;land&#34; them, make the feel comfortable, relaxed and slowly tune them inward to become more present. I watch this arc, from scattered and tired, to relaxed and focused happen over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process, I learned how to more artfully make that transition myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we would get &#34;to work&#34; - the middle 20 - 30 minutes of class. In the work phase we would go into a form or a principle and really train it. Once you&#39;ve opened up, relaxed repetition is much easier, and more meaningful to your nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the hour, we would do an easy practice where the goal wasn&#39;t to keep squeezing in more and more information, but rather to feel integration, letting things settle and come to rest so that your body could more easily absorbs the training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, everything would go quiet&amp;hellip;.and then I would start all over again with the next group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did that for the last ten years, so 3 x 5 x 44 x 10 or over 6,000 times. When you factor in workshops and personal practice time, I&#39;m confident that I&#39;ve paid attention to this work-rest-integration cycle for well over 10,000 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Supportive Learning Environment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;m so grateful for the opportunity to have done this kind of learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to Brookline Tai Chi for its community and its structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to my teachers who gave me material to work on and also guided me through the meta layer of learning even more through teaching and sharing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful for all the students who were excited to learn with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to all of you reading this post who have indulged my sharing my teaching experiences on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even now, as I open a new chapter professionally, the combination of training, learning, and teaching will form the foundation for new endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve benefitted from my writing, podcasts, videos, or teaching in any form on this site, I want you to know that it&#39;s largely because of the opportunities I had to develop a teaching voice at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you will &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/thank-you-dan-retrospective-and-appeal-for-transition-contributions/&#34;&gt;consider supporting Brookline Tai Chi at this time&lt;/a&gt;, so that our learning community will continue to produce new teachers, who work hard to benefit all of us, and that as a group, we will always have a home base to return to for deep learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>