<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>rhythm on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/rhythm/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in rhythm on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/rhythm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhythm, Timing, and Intuition</title>
      <link>/2014/03/21/rhythm-timing-and-intuition/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 08:30:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/21/rhythm-timing-and-intuition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why is it that sometimes you feel confident, connected, and at ease and other times you get flustered, disoriented and nothing seems to come together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Greek poet Archilocus, &#34;we don&#39;t rise to the level of our expectations, we fall to the level of our training.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now does that mean that every possible situation you go through needs to be practiced, rehearsed, and trained? That seems a little overwhelming!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, when we practice Tai Chi and qigong, we are making the bet that they will infuse the rest of our lives with the calm, centered awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Training to Reveal Your Intuition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Lately, I&#39;ve been questioning how we learn and teach practices that are designed to connect us to our deeper channels of energy, awareness and being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are we over-thinking things?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came across a popular book from the 70s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://theinnergame.com/about-tim-gallwey/&#34;&gt;The Inner Game of Tennis&lt;/a&gt; and the author, Tim Gallwey, confirmed my suspicion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1971, while on sabbatical from a career in higher education, I took a job as tennis professional in Seaside, California. While teaching on the court one day, I realized that many of my instructions were being incorporated in the student&#39;s mind as a kind of &#34;command and control&#34; self-dialogue that was significantly interfering with both learning and performance. When I inquired further, I found there was a lot going on in the mind of my tennis students that was preventing true focus of attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then began to explore ways to focus the mind of the player on direct and non-judgmental observation of ball, body, and racquet in a way that would heighten learning, performance, and enjoyment of the process. With this new awareness, amateur tennis players seemed to naturally develop the instincts and physicality of much more experienced players without specific instruction.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
His techniques allowed people to bypass their verbal filters, where we normally try to communicate about learning, and tap directly into deeper, more intuitive ways of perceiving and performing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of bypassing your thinking brain, I&#39;d like you to take 5 minutes and watch the video below of Tai Chi Master Cheng Man Ching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t analyze it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the soundtrack of the video to help you feel the rhythm and timing of his steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then do your form or work on pushes or whatever other practice you enjoy, feeling for the same rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/fSYPOhSgiis?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By the way, I highly recommend you subscribe to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/mnpli&#34;&gt;Mario Napoli&#39;s Youtube Channel&lt;/a&gt;. He posts great archival footage and really interesting training videos of himself and his students.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refining Your Opening and Closing</title>
      <link>/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 07:00:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I remember the first time I really got a sense for &#34;opening and closing&#34; my joints. We were on a qigong retreat and the person who was helping me probably spent 20 minutes &#34;pulsing&#34; my wrist, so that the fluids in the joint were moving in a smooth, even way, alternately creating more and less space between the bones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you pulse, you&#39;re manipulating the fluid flows inside your body so that the spaces inside your body compress and expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this is certainly not the normal way that we think about movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are trained in the &#34;pulleys and levers&#34; way of thinking. Contract this muscle to bend this joint (This is the logical conclusion of understanding movement based on dissection. When you cut back the skin and see muscles attached to bones.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you understood the body in terms of flows?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4113&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice opening and closing, you start to understand, on a visceral level, the flows that are constantly at work inside your body (and later you can more easily see them in the world all around you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulsing is a central skill in the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong. &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;In this early episode of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed why pulsing is the bridge to more advanced practice (see part 4 especially).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a more refined sense of how opening and closing works, you can also see the way it is integrated into movement in &lt;a title=&#34;5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/&#34;&gt;this progression of qigong videos.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, though, I want to show you a simple exercise you can use to fine-tune your sensitivity to opening and closing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/-y7o6ddHMCc?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you practice the simple exercise in the video, see if you can sense a similar kind of internal movement going on inside a full-body movement. At first this isn&#39;t easy to detect, but over time, you will become more sensitive to opening and closing on many different levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re curious about how to track opening and closing in more dynamic exercises, &lt;a title=&#34;Circles And Spheres in Qigong, Tai Chi, and Ba Gua&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/circles-and-spheres-in-qigong-tai-chi-and-ba-gua/&#34;&gt;check out this practice video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The True Value of Your Qigong Practice</title>
      <link>/2012/07/30/the-true-value-of-your-qigong-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2012 08:40:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/30/the-true-value-of-your-qigong-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We live in a culture where doing more, having more, and working harder are valued above pretty much everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a dangerous attitude, a linear approach to life that denies the need for rest and renewal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you constantly push yourself, you know it will lead to burnout. If you operate as if you have an infinite capacity to do and never rest, sooner or later you will get the message in some form that it is time to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the question is, how do we begin to value our energy as a cycle of work and rest instead of rest as the thing that distracts us from doing more work?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2950&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/33018637?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=e91c6b&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;300&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this video, &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/33018637&#34;&gt;The Myths of the Overworked Creative&lt;/a&gt;, Tony Schwartz articulates some of the different ways to, as he puts it &#34;ennoble renewal.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For qigong practitioners, listen to the way he frames the possibility for restful activities to be woven into daily work. I think you will see that a restorative energy practice will enhance everything that he recommends, especially when it comes to improving the quality of your rest.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Highlights from The Myths of the Overworked Creative&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Think about your energy like a natural resource:  &#34;the only resources that last are the ones we renew.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as you think about your energy as a precious resource (and here I would push qigong practitioners to think of energy in the everyday sense, beyond your practice):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can actively cultivate and develop more energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can renew your energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can learn to manage your energy more efficiently -- get more done in less time at a higher level of qulity, more sustainably&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You have 4 main sources of energy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;physical (quantity) -  the foundation of the others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;emotional (quality) - &#34;how do I feel when I&#39;m performing at my best&#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mental (focus) - attention is under siege&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spiritual (purpose) - energy of the human spirit -- serving something bigger than your needs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Myth of Doing More&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assume that the best way to get more done is to work more hours. The reality is that we work better when we build in intermitten renewal. We&#39;re not meant to operate like a digital device: high speed, long time, multiple programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&#34;Human beings are designed to pulse.&#34;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;Every system in the body pulses as it moves between spending and renewing energy. For some reason, we&#39;ve moved away from this pulse on a daily basis and we try to live linear lives.  We are violating the internal rhythm of our own body and the natural world around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, Schwartz places sleep at the center of daily renewal, citing some interesting research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As qigong practitioners, I think we would add that the rhythm of our practice helps keep the range between extreme work and rest more manageable. Work never burns up too much of your energy and rest becomes more nourishing, faster. Of course, I don&#39;t have any research to cite here, but I know when my practice is regular, the swings between work and rest feel smoother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else have you noticed about the way your practice changes your all-day energy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you get a chance to watch the entire video, let me know what you think the important lessons are here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress Reduction Techniques That Work in 5 Minutes or Less</title>
      <link>/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you have cultivated a daily practice that takes you into deep relaxation, it&#39;s helpful to have a set of stress reduction techniques &#34;that work in 5 minutes or less.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can pull these out during the day when you have a few minutes of downtime. If you are busy and really stressed out, these relaxation techniques can prevent your stress level from going through the roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try them and let me know what you think.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2540&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5 Minute Body Scan&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a few minutes of trying to tune into your body, instead of being stuck in your head, can help reduce the weight of some of the stress you are feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-2355&#34; title=&#34;basic standing qigong posture&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture-141x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; width=&#34;141&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standing posture pictured, here, do a 5-minute downward body scan, starting at the top of the head and working your way down, feeling height-by-height until you reach your feet.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First, set your posture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;place your feet hip-width apart, so your joints are aligned &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll feel the weight balanced evenly in each foot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lengthen the back of your neck, so the chin drops slightly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax your shoulders, as if the arms were slipping off the rib cage, to the left and right, not slouched forward or pulled back&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Next, settle in:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your breathing go smooth, so the turn-over from inhale to exhale feels natural and not forced&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Begin to scan:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bring your feeling awareness up to the crown of your head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;once you feel like you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve gathered your awareness to a single point, let your mind spread out through the crown of the head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give in to gravity and let your mind drop down the body, height-by-height, feeling front, sides, and back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your mind rest lightly on any sensations you feel as you scan, checking in, without trying to do anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work downward until you can feel your feet settle into the floor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more guidance on practicing this technique, check out &lt;a title=&#34;Settling in with Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;this article on Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt; (with a free guided-practice mp3 download).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Metronome Mobility&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This exercise is great for coordination and control and it&#39;s just distracting enough to let your nervous system reset its stress level by the time you are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s use this Z Health shoulder circle as an example for the metronome exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you feel comfortable performing the basic shoulder circle as in the video above, you&#39;ll need to set a metronome to 60 beats per minute. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a baseline for one repetition at your &#34;normal&#34; speed. How many beats?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, perform a circle at half your normal speed, or 2x as many beats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat this process, slowing down each time until the movement gets too choppy to be a smooth circle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now repeat the process getting faster each time instead of slower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you keep the rest of the body &#34;quiet&#34; -- you don&#39;t get any points for flailing around!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating this process for hip circles, ankle circles, or even finger/wrist/hand circles will work too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of metronome mobility as a stress reduction technique is to draw your mind and away from the mental and emotional pressures that are causing stress in the first place. Moving your body at different speeds provides novelty for your nervous system, which helps achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tai Chi Short Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; /&gt;When you do 5 minutes of tai chi, you have to change how you are practicing. You need to shift out of your normal &#34;training&#34; mindset, where you focus on little details, or work a principle over and over again until it clicks. That kind of deep practice mindset is great for 30 minutes or an hour of practice or more, but it&#39;s not going to do the trick in 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 5 minute practice for stress reduction, you need to focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moving smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making large, circular shapes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feeling the space around you, in your etheric field, not deep inside your body&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point, about putting your mind into your etheric field, might sound a little strange. What you are trying to do is clear the energetic layer around your body. Think of it as where you interface with the world. If you can sweep everything clean here, then the stress doesn&#39;t have the chance to soak into your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Got More Stress Reduction Techniques?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The thing that all these techniques have in common is that they are designed to recharge your nervous system through physical and energetic circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you accomplish this same goal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share your stress reduction techniques in the comments below.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Challenge of the Three Swings</title>
      <link>/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 09:03:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/uploads/2011/11/Second-Swing.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-2437&#34; title=&#34;Second Swing&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/11/Second-Swing-e1321015385573.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;176&#34; height=&#34;386&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Three Swings from Energy Gates are some of the most challenging exercises to do well in the entire Energy Arts curriculum. You have to relax, maintain good alignment, and coordinate stepping and turning while moving faster than most other qigong exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s talk a little bit about why the Three Swings are important and what you need to integrate to do them well.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2436&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Started with the Three Swings&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the &lt;a title=&#34;10 Things Modern Athletes Can Learn from the Tai Chi Classics&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/27/10-things-modern-athletes-can-learn-from-the-tai-chi-classics/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Classics&lt;/a&gt;, it says, &#34;the motion should be rooted in the feet, released through the legs, controlled by the waist and manifested through the fingers.&#34; Think of practicing the swings as a way to test this concept. You will get much clearer feedback from the swings about how the motion you generate from the feet travels out to your fingertips than you will from solo form practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do the swings well, you need to do these three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relax Your Arms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sink Your Weight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open Your Kwa&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you let the arms go completely and begin to turn from the kwa, you then focus on alternately sinking the weight down one leg and then the other. In that sense, the First Swing is a natural extension of what you do in your &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;Standing&lt;/a&gt; practice and then in Cloud Hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s new in the First Swing, though, is that you will begin to speed up the alternating sinking (that causes your weight shift from side to side), so that the arms begin to swing. Until you start building momentum, though, the arms should just hang by your sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s where the swings get interesting...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where the Swings Get More Complicated&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a series, each of the swings is designed to build on the previous one. Swing by swing there is more complexity in terms of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stepping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhythm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the First Swing, you fold the kwa to turn into the weighted leg. In the Second Swing, you unfold the kwa to turn away from the weighted leg. In the Third Swing, you add a vertical kwa pump to the stepping pattern of the Second. Each of these in changes in stepping alters the rhythm and the timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of moving from one to the next swing is to progressively build your internal connections, up through the spine and out the arms. In other words, you can see how each swing activates the internal connections in the body based on where the arms will go when you do the stepping correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the arm movement in each of the swings in this video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/7I1tBFlhOZU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/7I1tBFlhOZU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see how, swing-by-swing, the arms move higher. That is due to the stepping and shifting patterns described above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you practice the swings over time, your energy will rise and fall with the motion of the arms. You learn to bring it up and down the body effortlessly, smoothing out stuck points as you improve your shifting, timing, and stepping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re used to doing slow-motion qigong and tai chi practices, the swings can be very challenging because they are so dynamic. The payoff, though, is that you can take the feeling of integration that you get from being still or moving slowly and carry it over into more active practices. You still get &lt;a title=&#34;Repetition as Rhythm: Why Do 20 Reps?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/28/repetition-as-rhythm-why-do-20-reps/&#34;&gt;the benefits of repetition and rhythm&lt;/a&gt; doing the swings, so it really is a bridge between stillness and ever-changing movement. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Twice a Day</title>
      <link>/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 04:32:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I know I&#39;m writing this on vacation where the most pressing decision we make each day is whether to hike, kayak, or swim, but I&#39;m going to go ahead anyway and recommend that you practice twice a day. Here&#39;s why...&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1979&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/in5LGYtp8xw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/in5LGYtp8xw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Learned from a Month-Long Tai Chi Intensive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After a month in England, practicing 10 hours a day at &lt;a title=&#34;Movement Arts&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011&#34;&gt;the Short Form Instructor Training&lt;/a&gt; this summer, I have a renewed appreciation for daily practice rhythm. At the training, there were three distinct types of training sessions we would go through each day. In the mornings, we would practice in our groups. Most of the day, from 10am to 5pm was reserved for class time with Bruce. In the evenings, we would be free to practice again, ideally training the pieces of what we did in class that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During class time, we would have ten or twenty minutes to practice each new thing that Bruce introduced. That&#39;s fine to get an initial hit of each piece, but that brief exposure isn&#39;t the same thing as locking it in to your system. You have to take it two steps further. First, you have to expand that twenty minutes into forty-five minutes or an hour in the evening sessions. Then, after you eat and sleep and feel rested, you have to revisit the same material in a lighter way the next morning, trying to let the new material flow into your regular morning practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you look at the three pieces of each training day, you had integration of the previous day first thing in the morning, then new material during the bulk of the day, and finally a chance to really work on the new material in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the clearest way to see how this rhythm worked was to watch people not follow it! When people would blow off the evening training session, you could tell that the material wasn&#39;t soaking into their system the next day. Likewise, if they worked hard on pieces in the morning session (which they should have done the night before), they didn&#39;t have enough energy to get the most of out class that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I&#39;m Learning Practicing Twice a Day on Vacation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Going on vacation and having the free time to test this out again, I&#39;m even more convinced that you can learn a lot about your own practice rhythm by spreading out practice sessions throughout your day. The most surprising insight from the training was: &lt;strong&gt;the morning practice sessions were related more to the work I did the day before than they were to the two sessions following on the same day.&lt;/strong&gt; In other words, Tuesday morning practice was the completion of the training I did on Monday, not the warm-up for the rest of the training I was about to do on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the bigger pattern I wanted to test on vacation and it seems to be working really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you realize what this means, right? It means that eating, sleeping, and letting things settle down is an important part of learning. Or in other words, rest and integration complete hard work. We tend to think of work as an on/off switch. We&#39;re either working hard or being lazy. The lesson here is that rest and integration are the real opposites of hard work and that hard work doesn&#39;t pay off until you&#39;ve integrated it. Pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other cool thing about making this connection has been that now I feel like I&#39;m in one long training session. I used to think &#34;I practiced Monday, missed Tuesday, and Wednesday through Friday I did a little bit....I suck&#34;. Now, though, I think about chaining sessions of work, rest, and integration together and it gives the process much more continuity. You get out of an all-or-nothing mindset about your practice. To me, that seems to be much closer to making your practice a real part of the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Leave me a comment below and tell me about your practice cycles. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Follow the 20-20-20 Rule for Better Breathing</title>
      <link>/2011/05/21/follow-the-20-20-20-rule-for-better-breathing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2011 07:50:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/21/follow-the-20-20-20-rule-for-better-breathing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Implementing a breathing practice that has an impact on your energy levels and actually chips away at stress can be tricky. It requires a blend of persistence and relaxation that can seem like a paradox at first. That&#39;s why I recommend the 20-20-20 Rule (which I made up) for better breathing.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1442&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I explain the 20-20-20 Rule in this clip, pulled from the breathing course in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;Foundations of Relaxation series&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/Nw8B-Y3_T2k?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/Nw8B-Y3_T2k?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bone Rhythm</title>
      <link>/2011/05/05/bone-rhythm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2011 08:57:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/05/bone-rhythm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bone Rhythm is a core concept taught in Z Health and I&#39;ve found it to be one of the single most important teaching tools I have when it comes to getting people moving. The idea is very simple, that each bone is a rigid structure and because of that, when one end moves, the other must move.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-944&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the question of how the other end moves is what matters here. When the two ends of the bone move correctly relative to each other, you have smooth, effortless movement. When they move in the wrong way, you force the joints to move improperly and your timing is off. You can apply this concept to any movement, using any bone in the body, which is a fascinating experiment, but let me start with a simple movement to illustrate the concept. Forgive me for the photos!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a basic squatting action. First, the downward phase:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-946&#34; title=&#34;Downward Phase of Squat&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/05/squat-down.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Downward Phase of Squat&#34; width=&#34;309&#34; height=&#34;222&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, rising up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-947&#34; title=&#34;Rising Up&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/05/rise-up.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Rising Phase of Squat&#34; width=&#34;309&#34; height=&#34;221&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to take any familiar movement and analyze it with the movement of a single bone in mind. This will often uncover stuck places in your body and you can use the right &#34;bone rhythm&#34; to unstick them. Have fun!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repetition as Rhythm: Why Do 20 Reps?</title>
      <link>/2011/04/28/repetition-as-rhythm-why-do-20-reps/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2011 10:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/28/repetition-as-rhythm-why-do-20-reps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/-wit-/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Taoist Skyline&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.static.flickr.com/90/235990150_3854d78690.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Taoist Skyline courtesy of wit&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;People often ask why we do chi gung sets in certain numbers. Whenever I&#39;ve heard Bruce Frantzis answer that question, he tells a story about these elaborate experiments they run in the Taoist monasteries, over generations, with control groups and varying repetitions, to see what the optimal number of repetitions for each exercise is. I always feel bad for the monks who spent their lives doing a few too many of each exercise.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-936&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my own personal experience, there is a subtle shift in feel as you go through, often, 20 repetitions of an exercise, that leaves you with just the right feeling at the end. Here&#39;s how I break it down when I practice to get the most out of each set:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reps 1-5&lt;/strong&gt;: You&#39;re just settling in to your practice, so these first few have to be lighter. You should focus on the shape of the movements with the arms, legs, or spine. Instead of trying to activate deep stretches, explore more superficial layers, like gentle stretches along big planes of fascia. You should make sure that the joints are moving smoothly and timed together properly (e.g. all of the leg joints are bending in unison as you squat)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reps 5-10: &lt;/strong&gt;Start looking for the natural pumps, pulses, and springs inside the body that are waking up. On any given day, one layer of the body is going to be more active than another. Sometimes you&#39;ll feel the joints and ligaments activate and you&#39;ll focus on bounce and spring. At other times, tissue turning or twisting will be very pronounced, so you&#39;ll emphasize the winding and unwinding. At other times still, energetic flows might be very obvious, so you can follow and amplify those. In this rep range, though, you are not trying to do anything to whatever is active in the body, you are only listening to discover what it is today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reps 10-15:&lt;/strong&gt; Once you&#39;ve tuned in to the most active system in your body, you start to &#34;turn up the volume&#34; on it. There are several strategies for doing this, but the simplest one is to have a clear passive and active phase mapped on to the movement. When we open and close the joints, for example, in a circling hands exercise, the best way to amplify the natural rhythm of the pulse is to actively close and then passively let the joint open (you can reverse this pattern too). By &#34;letting go&#34; for an entire phase of the movement, you are more relaxed throughout, and the natural capacity of your body has room to expand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reps 15-20:&lt;/strong&gt; On a good day, you&#39;ve found something to tune into, you&#39;ve amplified the natural pattern, and now you&#39;re cruising along. Somewhere in this range, you sit back and &#34;ride the rhythm&#34;. Instead of actively driving the process, your goal is to be able to let pattern run itself through your mind and body. Occasionally, you&#39;ll have to go back and amp it up like the earlier stage, but you&#39;re constantly testing to see if you can let go completely and let the pattern go on its own. This is often where lots of releasing and letting go happen, but you can&#39;t get sloppy and let the shape of the movements or your internal structure fall apart. That&#39;s why you are playing this edge between directing and letting go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration: &lt;/strong&gt;While we&#39;ve been talking about repetitions and doing exercises, you also need a little space to not do anything at the end. If you don&#39;t create so space to let you mind and body integrate at the end of a practice session, all the energy that you&#39;ve worked to build in the active phase of your practice gets blown off. You need a brief period to settle and store. Often, this can be one of the most relaxing parts of your practice, because you are also making a smooth transition back to the outside world.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Because each phase of these repetitions has a different feel and a different goal, I consider this a set-wide rhythm practice like &lt;a href=&#34;/tag/rhythm/&#34;&gt;the other ones we&#39;ve explored in this series&lt;/a&gt;. One of the benefits of teaching 15-20 hours a week over the past 6 years is that I regularly take groups of people through this particular version of rhythm training again and again, enough so that I have a clear feel for the pattern. I encourage you to look for the same one in your own practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metronome Mobility</title>
      <link>/2011/04/14/metronome-mobility/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 10:15:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/14/metronome-mobility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/mrs_logic/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Metronome&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2496/3714389346_95065e9777.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image courtesy of Mrs Logic&#34; width=&#34;192&#34; height=&#34;184&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/07/running-rhythm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous post in this series&lt;/a&gt;, we looked at how adhering to a particular rhythm, in that case running at 180bpm, can trigger the natural spring in the body and give you insight into &#34;stuck spots&#34; in your body that won&#39;t move at the right pace.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-884&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we want to explore the practice of changing rhythm deliberately as part of your movement practice. The value for sports or martial arts, where the ability to change speeds gives you a competitive advantage, should be pretty obvious. What might not be obvious is the value for &#34;real life&#34; and even less obvious is the method for systematically training speed -- which you can do joint-by-joint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Importance of a Single Joint&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For a little background on the issue of mobility and speed, I recommend you check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.begin2dig.com/2011/03/different-speeds-have-different.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; by Z Health trainer mc schraefel. In the article, she reviews a study on the effects that deliberately-induced knee pain have on gait. Here are some of the highlights from the study and her detailed review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design of the study was to fatigue the muscles around the knee in a precise way and measure, joint-by-joint how this fatigue (referred to as DOMS or delayed onset muscle soreness) impacted range of motion in the knee and in other joints. The authors of the study observed two different things. At slow speeds, they saw the decreased flexion in the knee -- which makes sense, right? Your knee is sore, so you move it less. At faster speeds, though, the knee looked like it moved normally, but you know what else they saw? Even though the knee looked like it was going through normal range of motion, the ankle, hip and pelvis all took on distorted movement patterns to apparently compensate for the fatigued knee. The basic effect of poor ankle movement was that study participants took a wider stance during gait, indicating compromised balance. The increased anterior tilt in the pelvis that was also observed puts more strain into the lower back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mc points out that these changes were almost immediate. She then asks, &#34;What happens when we move from an acute pain bout to something more chronic, and those adaptations become more chronic too? Those adaptations are going to stick around and cause their own compensations.&#34; Great question!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever someone comes in complaining about a &#34;bad knee&#34;, I ask them, &#34;when was the last time you saw a knee walking down the street all by itself?&#34; Now I have a research study to back me up! In all seriousness, though, the takeaway from this study is that the incredible interconnectedness of the body in motion means that you should seek out immobility anywhere and work to get it moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Metronome Mobility Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here&#39;s my favorite way to simultaneously test and train my mobility at different speeds. To do this exercise, you need a &lt;a href=&#34;http://lmgtfy.com/?q=metronome&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;metronome&lt;/a&gt;. You&#39;re going to set the metronome to something like 60 bpm and pick a body part. I recommend you start with something that&#39;s easy to move in a circle, like your arm from the shoulder, or a finger, or standing on one leg, the ankle of the foot you&#39;ve lifted off the ground (use a chair or the wall for support, this isn&#39;t a balance drill yet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, make a circle at a consistent, comfortable speed. Count the number of beats it takes to make the circle and repeat that count-circle 3 times in each direction. This is going to be your &#34;normal&#34; speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, you want to be able to slow &#34;normal&#34; down to half and half again. Half of normal will be your &#34;slow&#34; speed and half of slow is &#34;super slow&#34;. When most people go to slow and super slow, the circle starts to get choppy or flat. Discovering these rough parts is huge. If you can begin to smooth out the rough parts in your circle, you are building strength, coordination, and control. Work on a perfect super-slow circle at each joint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when you&#39;ve got a good handle at working on a joint at super slow speed, you should go back and double your normal speed. This approaches what we refer to in Z Health as &#34;sports speed&#34;. Becoming fluent with controlled movements of individual joints at faster speeds tends to unlock faster compound movements too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have four speeds to work with, you can incorporate the speeds into your regular training in a few different ways. To build coordination or more fluid movement, work movements in slow and super slow speed (tai chi, anyone?). To build strength and range of motion, take it up to sports speed. Experiment with the Z Health practice of training individual joints in sports-specific positions, working through a range of speeds. But don&#39;t just think &#34;sports&#34; here. Another Z Health tenant is that everyone is an athlete -- we all do similar squats, lunges, twists, and bends to different degrees and to get through life smoothly and with abundant energy, we need a fluent movement vocabulary as much as the professional athlete does. So if you sit at your desk all day, you&#39;ve got a sports-specific position to work in. Make sense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think about mc&#39;s study review, it was one under-performing joint that was altering the entire gait cycle. You need to go back and find those stuck joints in a systematic way. By getting comfortable at different speeds on a joint-by-joint basis, you are helping your body be more responsive to fatigue and soreness ahead of time and preparing yourself to move through life at all its different speeds. Happy Training!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running Rhythm</title>
      <link>/2011/04/07/running-rhythm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 09:15:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/07/running-rhythm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been clear to me from years of Tai Chi practice that finding the right rhythm in a movement &#34;unlocks&#34; the body. When I stumbled on to this video though, I was fascinated to see a similar theory being discussed in running.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-861&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/qRgTxa5ak8I?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/qRgTxa5ak8I?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the clip, he says that this particular rhythm, 180 beats per minute, helps you &#34;tap into the body&#39;s elastic mechanism.&#34; After I watched the clip (the other ones in the series are great, by the way), I turned my metronome up to 180 bpm and hit the road. Here&#39;s what happened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like other metronome work (which I&#39;ll discuss later in this series), having an external rhythm&amp;Acirc;  helps you feel the places you&#39;re stuck. When you&#39;re trying to hit the same rhythm again and again, you&#39;ll miss the beat or fatigue sooner in the places you&#39;re stuck than in other places. For example, if one hip is tighter than the other, you&#39;ll start to notice a lag on that side, while the other side doesn&#39;t feel like anything at all. Running to an external rhythm clarifies where you need to do additional isolation mobility work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the run, returning to the rhythm actually rejuvenated me. As I got tired, my stride got longer and&amp;Acirc;  slower, but the short, quick steps this rhythm demands made it easier to contain my center of gravity, and so instead of feeling like I had to reach and strain to keep going, it was more like re-establishing a &#34;bounce&#34;. Once I let the bounce go through my body, it got easier again. I think this is the beginning of &#34;tapping in to the body&#39;s elastic mechanism.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What continues to impress me about rhythm training is that adhering to a particular rhythm really can alter your form.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhythm as Relaxation</title>
      <link>/2011/03/31/rhythm-as-relaxation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2011 10:00:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/31/rhythm-as-relaxation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introducing a new series: &#34;Rhythm as Relaxation&#34;.&lt;/strong&gt; Across many different practices, which I&#39;ll go into one at a time, rhythm is a common thread. When you find the right rhythm in the practice, it gets easier, smoother, more connected, and as a result, more relaxing to perform and more energizing at the same time.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-802&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the practices I will explore in the series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tai Chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breathing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Five Element Theory&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;m going to argue that the practices on that list have more in common than not, when you look at them from a rhythm point of view.&amp;Acirc;  I always try to be careful not to conflate different things that have common elements, because then you usually miss the depth and richness of both, but I will try to show you how focusing on the rhythm in each activity will make it easier and more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>