<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>practice-tips on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/practice-tips/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in practice-tips on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/practice-tips/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Absolutely Anything in 2012</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 09:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Chess at Starbucks by radioflyer007, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/radioflyer007/4677003347/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1304/4677003347_3bcb440632.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chess at Starbucks&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;205&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;At this time of year, you hear a lot about New Year&#39;s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I was happy to see a lot of people saying &#34;New Year&#39;s resolutions don&#39;t work.&#34; We all know that&#39;s true from personal experience, but these folks were referencing a growing understanding about how learning and skill-building take place. Most of what we now know about how the nervous system works flies in the face of changing through the strength of your willpower alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I urge you to leave that mindset behind in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you should think about any changes, anything you want to learn, as slowing building a skill, with small steps you can practice, building like a snowball, until you&#39;re doing great new things without trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s how that works.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3160&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deliberate Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You often hear people say, &#34;practice makes perfect&#34;, but the reality is a little more complicated. One retort is &#34;practice makes permanent&#34;, which speaks to the way that your nervous system ingrains what you do over and over so that it becomes close to automatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you actually want to learn something new this year, you need get smart about how you build your new skills. The model that captures this the clearest is the deliberate practice model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deliberate practice has four components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need a framework for understanding what to practice -- this is where seeking out guidance from someone who has mastered that skill or taught others to do so is critical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to practice a very specific skill because you need a high degree of focus -- trying to juggle two or three new things at a time won&#39;t work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need immediate feedback on your practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to practice over and over and over again, a lot.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The irony for most of us is that we want to get better at something, so we just go out and do it. It&#39;s like trying to drive somewhere new without a map. You&#39;ll base your decisions, turn-by-turn, on old information about places you&#39;ve been before, which may work pretty well, but clearly won&#39;t get you there with the same directness as having a roadmap to guide you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, step one of any new deliberate practice endeavor that you seek out is to find the right map. Get good guidance, regular feedback, and keep practicing, biting off a little at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other thing you need to worry about, once you have the deliberate practice cycle down, is staying in a healthy &#34;learning zone&#34; as you take on new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recognizing Fight-or-Flight&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A natural part of trying to master any new skill is working beyond your current capacity. The problem is that pushing yourself too far into new territory will be counter-productive. When you exceed your limites, your body initiates the fight-or-flight response and you will no longer engage in productive learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the core Z Health training principles is learning to identify the onset of the stress response in any activity. When you recognize the signs of fight-or-flight, you learn to dial back your training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you may find:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your heart rate speeds up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your breathing gets heavy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your face becomes flushed or pale or alternates between them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your mouth dries up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You move toward the fetal position in subtle ways -- your shoulders hike up, your facial muscles contract, you draw your arms in to protect your body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You stop hearing what&#39;s going on around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get &#34;tunnel vision&#34; and lose your peripheral field.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you experience these things, or more likely, when someone points out to you that they are happening or you realize it in hindsight, you know you&#39;ve exceeded your capacity to integrate new information in that moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the poise and relaxation that comes through smart, modulated training in this boxing clip. Obviously, boxing can be a brutal sport, but watch the way that this training is structured, to stretch him in different ways, testing his visual skills, playing with his threat level and capacity to integrated movement information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that the training is done correctly because of how graceful and relaxed he is able to be under this kind of pressure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/2y5jB0uZOrM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/2y5jB0uZOrM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you work through this process, probably without an army of coaches, camera crews, and fans, you&#39;ll have to look back on the experience and break down how things came together and what you could do to decrease the threat level next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one of my favorite examples of this is a college football coach who plays crowd noise over the loudspeaker during practice sessions. He wants his players to simulate game conditions as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the gradual increase in game-like threat levels as they learn new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the coach introduces a new play in the locker room. He maps it out for the players and they get the idea. Next, they head to the field without pads on and with no defense trying to stop them. Little by little, the coach can introduce new elements that demand concentration, and most importantly from our point of view, integration of new information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can control a situation so that you can selectively increase the amount of information -- visual, auditory, spatial, or physical -- that you need to integrate to master a skill, then you will be able to learn anything in a smooth, steady manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&#39;s it going to be in 2012?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Man Who Did His Tai Chi Form 19,100 Times</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2011 07:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;I got an email the other day that was a little bit different than the usual requests for lessons. It read:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I learned the Short Form at Brookline Tai Chi under the tutelage of Bill Ryan back about 1996-1997. For seven years, I continued to do the short form three times every morning. Then for the past eight years or so, I have done the short form four times every morning.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;I keep a log of my centering practices, and have documentation that over the past 15 years, I have only missed doing my tai chi on three days, two when I was strapped down in hospital beds and unable to get up, and one day when I simply forgot to practice. (I practiced twice the next day.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Thus, I have done the short form now over 17,800 times.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;There were so many things that fascinated me about getting this email. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2966&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;First of all, it reinforced my belief that there&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s no such thing as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34;&gt;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;former student&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/a&gt;. As a teacher, this was a powerful reminder that you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t know the full extent of what you are giving your students and just how far they will take what they learn.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Then, consider this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He practices tai chi every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He practices several repetitions of the short form every time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He logs his practice every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;As you know from reading this blog, I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m a little obsessed with the idea of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;practice.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Clearly this man knew something about cultivating a practice. I wanted to know more about what motivated him to practice daily and record it with such diligence. So I asked him, but I wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t ready for the depth and thoughtfulness of his answer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3105&#34; title=&#34;Sandy Davis&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/12/IMG_0518-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sandy Davis runs Resilience Works&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;It turns out, I was talking to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;The Resilience Guy.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Sandy Davis runs a company called &lt;a href=&#34;http://resilienceworks.com/&#34;&gt;ResilienceWorks&lt;/a&gt;, dedicated to teaching people how to become more resilient, or as he puts it:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;CENTER&#34;&gt;&amp;Acirc; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: small;&#34;&gt;The more you invest wisely in your own vitality,&lt;br /&gt;
The more resilient you become, and&lt;br /&gt;
The easier it is to thrive.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Many of us come to movement arts like tai chi or qigong because of an innate desire to thrive, but Sandy has gone into great depth explaining the structures that make this process possible. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He advocates for &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Seven Simple Self-Care Structures&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; that make this possible:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Keep all your agreements.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Eat well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Sleep well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Have a daily centering practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Exercise aerobically on a regular basis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Have a daily creative practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Log your self-care results every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Now, when we talk about &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;practice&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; here, we often talk about 3 or 4 of these structures (mainly centering, exercise, and sleep). We often imply that a lot of what grabs you about something like tai chi is the creative expression you derive from continually refining it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;And certainly we talk about tracking your practice -- although I haven&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t yet met anyone else who has taken this habit to quite the same degree as Sandy -- he&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s missed three days of practice in the last 14 years, and he can prove it!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;So what is it about &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;keeping all your agreements&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; that adds to your store of energy? When I heard Sandy describe this particular structure, it broadened my sense of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what builds your energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what uses up your energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; in a way I had never considered. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.resilienceworks.com/resiliencemanual&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Resilience Manual&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s guide to developing these structures, he writes:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;There is much satisfaction to be had in knowing that you are someone who can be relied upon to keep your word. By consistently walking your talk, &lt;strong&gt;you can acquire a deep-seated self-confidence in your ability to successfully follow through&lt;/strong&gt; on whatever you agree to undertake. This includes faithfully attending to your own foundational self-care habits, as well as to faithfully doing your chosen daily self-care practices.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Alternatively, there is much disappointment to be had in knowing that you are someone who routinely fails to follow through on your commitments. Whenever you fail to keep your word, whenever you fail to do what you promised, whenever you do 95% of what you said you would do and leave the last 5% unfinished, in all these instances, you experience a loss of self-respect. Each of these failures, whether obvious and public, or miniscule and private, generates a measure of personal disappointment and/or discouragement. &lt;strong&gt;Such breakdowns cost you valuable energy. They undermine your self-confidence. And they get in the way of deepening your resilience-readiness. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;What I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve highlighted in bold above should be familiar language when you think about your movement practice. You are either moving in a way that builds and integrates your coordination and your energy, or in a way that saps both and leads to dis-integration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Many of us have a gut feeling that how we cultivate a movement practice spills over into other dimensions of life, but I think Sandy has clearly articulated exactly how that works in the above passage. The lesson is that doing your movement practice won&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t make you a better person, but &lt;em&gt;it is a template for how to move toward more wholeness in other areas of your life&lt;/em&gt;. In Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s language, both structures feed your resilience-readiness and the store of resilience that you naturally draw energy from, no matter what situation you are facing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;The linchpin to all of this, from Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s point of view, is the seventh structure, or the meta-structure of logging the results of the other six structures on a daily basis. In &lt;em&gt;The Resilience Manual,&lt;/em&gt; he makes several compelling arguments for keeping a daily practice log both to gain perspective and to sustain accountability to yourself. For me, the most compelling reason is the deep satisfaction this seventh structure generates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;A week or so after our lesson, Sandy e-mailed me to make a correction to the number of times he has done the short form (hence the title of this post):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;FYI, I re-checked the numbers, and it turns out that I have actually done the short form more than 19,100 times. It will be a treat to pass the 20,000 mark. At my current rate of four times each day, that will take me another seven-plus months. But who&#39;s counting?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Think about how great that must feel to realize that you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re actually a little closer to 20,000? And not because you can brag about a number, but because you know you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve made a serious ongoing investment in your own well-being.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Big thanks to Sandy for sharing his method with so much clarity and simplicity! His website has more information, including some useful free resources and more in-depth explanations of the daily self-care structures. Check them out here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://resilienceworks.com/download.asp&#34;&gt;ResilienceWorks.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oh, and we also agreed that Sandy should come in for a tune-up every 3,000 forms, not every 10,000 or 15,000!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress Reduction Techniques That Work in 5 Minutes or Less</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you have cultivated a daily practice that takes you into deep relaxation, it&#39;s helpful to have a set of stress reduction techniques &#34;that work in 5 minutes or less.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can pull these out during the day when you have a few minutes of downtime. If you are busy and really stressed out, these relaxation techniques can prevent your stress level from going through the roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try them and let me know what you think.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2540&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5 Minute Body Scan&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a few minutes of trying to tune into your body, instead of being stuck in your head, can help reduce the weight of some of the stress you are feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-2355&#34; title=&#34;basic standing qigong posture&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture-141x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; width=&#34;141&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standing posture pictured, here, do a 5-minute downward body scan, starting at the top of the head and working your way down, feeling height-by-height until you reach your feet.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First, set your posture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;place your feet hip-width apart, so your joints are aligned &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll feel the weight balanced evenly in each foot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lengthen the back of your neck, so the chin drops slightly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax your shoulders, as if the arms were slipping off the rib cage, to the left and right, not slouched forward or pulled back&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Next, settle in:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your breathing go smooth, so the turn-over from inhale to exhale feels natural and not forced&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Begin to scan:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bring your feeling awareness up to the crown of your head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;once you feel like you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve gathered your awareness to a single point, let your mind spread out through the crown of the head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give in to gravity and let your mind drop down the body, height-by-height, feeling front, sides, and back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your mind rest lightly on any sensations you feel as you scan, checking in, without trying to do anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work downward until you can feel your feet settle into the floor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more guidance on practicing this technique, check out &lt;a title=&#34;Settling in with Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;this article on Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt; (with a free guided-practice mp3 download).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Metronome Mobility&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This exercise is great for coordination and control and it&#39;s just distracting enough to let your nervous system reset its stress level by the time you are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s use this Z Health shoulder circle as an example for the metronome exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you feel comfortable performing the basic shoulder circle as in the video above, you&#39;ll need to set a metronome to 60 beats per minute. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a baseline for one repetition at your &#34;normal&#34; speed. How many beats?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, perform a circle at half your normal speed, or 2x as many beats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat this process, slowing down each time until the movement gets too choppy to be a smooth circle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now repeat the process getting faster each time instead of slower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you keep the rest of the body &#34;quiet&#34; -- you don&#39;t get any points for flailing around!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating this process for hip circles, ankle circles, or even finger/wrist/hand circles will work too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of metronome mobility as a stress reduction technique is to draw your mind and away from the mental and emotional pressures that are causing stress in the first place. Moving your body at different speeds provides novelty for your nervous system, which helps achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tai Chi Short Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; /&gt;When you do 5 minutes of tai chi, you have to change how you are practicing. You need to shift out of your normal &#34;training&#34; mindset, where you focus on little details, or work a principle over and over again until it clicks. That kind of deep practice mindset is great for 30 minutes or an hour of practice or more, but it&#39;s not going to do the trick in 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 5 minute practice for stress reduction, you need to focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moving smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making large, circular shapes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feeling the space around you, in your etheric field, not deep inside your body&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point, about putting your mind into your etheric field, might sound a little strange. What you are trying to do is clear the energetic layer around your body. Think of it as where you interface with the world. If you can sweep everything clean here, then the stress doesn&#39;t have the chance to soak into your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Got More Stress Reduction Techniques?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The thing that all these techniques have in common is that they are designed to recharge your nervous system through physical and energetic circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you accomplish this same goal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share your stress reduction techniques in the comments below.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Practice Partners You Should Avoid</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/17/4-practice-partners-you-should-avoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 08:29:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/17/4-practice-partners-you-should-avoid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The next time you go to class, watch out for these 4 practice partners. While they all start out with good intentions, if you hang out with them too much, you&#39;ll get sucked into their quirky habits and slow down your own progress. Don&#39;t say I didn&#39;t warn you!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2278&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Checklist Charlie&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Checklist Charlie is the tai chi student who is forever stuck in his own head. Every time he practices, instead of feeling his body, he recites a list of stuff he is supposed to be doing. For most people, &#34;soundtracking&#34; your way through the form is a legitimate learning phase, but Checklist Charlie is stuck there forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/eaJebVBzufY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/eaJebVBzufY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Intense Irene&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Intense Irene takes her practice way too far. At first, this is a good thing. She works hard and uncovers a lot of depth. Over time though, she goes too deeply into one thing and it distorts the rest of her practice, leaving her potentially injured, way too tense, and out of balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HAIzvee9Ga4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HAIzvee9Ga4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Workshop Wally&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Workshop Wally loves to collect pieces of his practice, like random pieces from a bunch of different puzzles. When he tries to fit them all together, it&#39;s a total disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GfKb18GTeoQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GfKb18GTeoQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Environmental Ernie&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;m not talking about your &#34;greenest&#34; student, I&#39;m talking about the one with no internal motivation to practice. Environmental Ernie relies on the external environment, fellow students, regular classes, instructor-led sessions, to do his practice. And I think that&#39;s fine! We can all learn from his laid-back ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ueAUIXDyVdE?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ueAUIXDyVdE?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kilimanjaro Made Easy</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 10:05:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2151&#34; title=&#34;Jen on Kilimanjaro&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/09/P1010499-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;Z-Health Master Trainer Jen Waak is a self-described &#34;recovering management consultant&#34;. These days, she helps other &#34;Keyboard Athletes&#34; improve and maintain their bodies and stay healthy even when they&#39;re stuck behind a desk all day. What surprised me about reading Jen&#39;s advice on &#34;what you should do at your desk&#34;, was that it sounded a lot like what she did last year to get ready for a climb up Mount Kilimanjaro.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1999&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here&#39;s what Jen had to say about her prep and training:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It was a year ago today that I left to climb Kilimanjaro. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m not a climber, I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t camp, and I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t like the cold. So why I thought this was a good idea I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll never know. I just knew it was something I needed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I got over the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what have I done?&#34; stage, it was time to start figuring out what it would take to summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I started researching the trip, and here is what I learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;40% of climbers don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t make the summit, and the vast majority of the succumb to hypoxia (altitude sickness) since a summit of 19,340 feet means there is about half of the oxygen at the summit than there is at sea level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was going to be traveling ~60 very hilly miles on foot over 9 days. No one day was going to be the gotcha &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; instead it was going to be the accumulated miles that would wear down my body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being comfortable in your gear is critically important since what you have with you is, well, what you have with you. And there&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s nothing like getting blisters and only 59 more miles to go.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In a situation like this, it would be really easy to get freaked out and not know where to start. But, using a framework I call the Energy Bank, I was able to fairly easily come up with a extremely doable training plan that made summiting downright easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Energy Bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Energy Bank is this idea that we all have a finite amount of energy to get through the day, and everything we do during the day &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; everything &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; either adds to or depletes our bank balance: the lighting in the room, your breathing patterns, the horrible morning commute, your uncomfortable desk chair, and that grande burrito you had for lunch. It all has an impact. And just like a bank balance the higher the average balance, the larger the margin of error before going bankrupt. As you can imagine, a large margin of error will serve someone well when attempting one of the Seven Summits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my goal in preparing for Kilimanjaro was to get my Energy Bank Balance high enough so that the trip wouldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t run the balance down to zero &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; focusing specifically on what I would encounter on the trip that would be more likely to result in large withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training for the Climb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Breathing:&lt;/strong&gt; I knew this was already a weak link for me - and given that it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s also the downfall of most climbers, this became my #1 priority. My first goal was to fix my breathing patterns at sea level during everyday activities. Once I had that mastered, I went on to practicing my breathing while in oxygen debt (as ultimately that was what I would encounter on Kilimanjaro). Since I live at sea level, I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t truly replicate the conditions on Kilimanjaro, but instead would sprint or run stairs and focus on my breathing during and after those activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision:&lt;/strong&gt; Another one of my weak links, I spent a great deal of time working on my visual skills. My depth perception isn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t great, which translates into me being tentative going down stairs. Since I had to travel 60 miles over hilly terrain, not being comfortable going up and down was going to be a BIG problem. So, I incorporated some basic convergence drills into my training so my eyes could re-learn to focus and my brain would re-learn depth perception. Like my breathing, first I worked on this during everyday activities, and then I moved on to working it into my running stairs, long hikes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Endurance:&lt;/strong&gt; Going and going over 9 days on rough terrain was something I didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have any experience in. Using the Energy Bank concept, I realized that if my body was already somewhat adapted to that it would be a lot easier. But, with a hectic schedule and living in the city, I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t exactly take off for 9 days to climb in the Cascades. Instead, I got the idea that if fatigued my legs the night before a long hike with either a run or stair session, that I would begin the adaptation process of going long distances on tired legs. So, I would either do a long stair session or a run one night and then the next morning go and hike 10+ miles with a 3,000 foot elevation gain (since that would most replicate the conditions I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d find on Kilimanjaro). I got in probably 3 or 4 of these back-to-back training sessions prior to Kilimanjaro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gear:&lt;/strong&gt; Remember that part where I said I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t climb or camp? Yeah, that meant that I had a buy and test a TON of gear for the trip. In the weeks leading up to the climb my week would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on a hike, discover I didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have the right gear (either through blisters, sweating sunscreen into my eyes, or dealing with lots of bugs. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d come home and take notes on what worked and what didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to REI and pick up what I was missing (and just cover my eyes while signing the credit card receipt)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on another hike and re-assess. Lather, rinse, repeat until I knew I had what I needed.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overkill? Maybe. But I had no blisters, no chafing, and at no point did I say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I wish I would have brought&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;Acirc;  Everything got tested on at least one 10+ mile hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery:&lt;/strong&gt; Early on in my physical training I got a bit ambitious and decided to run 4 miles down a mountain. That turned out to be one of the less bright things I could have done, as I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t go up and down stairs for several days after that. But it also highlighted something I hadn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t considered &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; that I could get sore. A phone call to fellow Master Trainer and endurance athlete Shannon Mauck revealed the world of recovery drinks to me. Yet another thing for me to test &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I needed to find something that I both liked the taste of and that would agree with my system. (Turns out I really like Accelerade.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did it Work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d have to give the entire experiment an unqualified, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;hell, yeah.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;Acirc;  My training wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t extreme &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I did 6 long hikes and then a couple of hours of running, sprinting, and stairs per week. I worked on my breathing and vision for a few minutes a day, and made a point of incorporating that practice while on my long hikes. And the entire trip up the mountain was a piece of cake for me &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d get into camp each night with extra energy to burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The biggest surprise:&lt;/strong&gt; The mental shift in who I am. I grew up a really sick little kid, and had never considered myself an athlete. And now I had accomplished that thousands of people cannot each year. I had to redefine who I am, and now think of myself as an athlete. Because everything is a skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you liked the way she managed her mountain climbing training, you&#39;ll definitely be interested in her insight into bringing more energy into your daily life: &lt;a href=&#34;http://keyboardathletes.com/yourenergybank/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Increase Your Energy Bank Balance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Your Practice All in Your Head?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/12/is-your-practice-all-in-your-head-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2011 09:15:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/12/is-your-practice-all-in-your-head-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you&#39;re sitting here reading this, I want you to try something. I want you to push yourself back away from your desk, let your arms hang by your sides, close your eyes and see how many fingers you can feel. Go ahead, try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now do the same thing again, but stand up and count your toes instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could you feel more fingers or toes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are you have much greater feeling access to your fingers. But how does the sensation of feeling a finger compare to the clarity of a thought you just had or an image you can generate in your head? If thoughts and images are much clearer than feeling sensations in your body, you might have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2106&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In this four-part series, I&#39;m going to show you how do deal with your practice &#34;being all in your head&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that a lot of us make a living with the power of our minds (that sounds much cooler than &#34;desk job&#34;, doesn&#39;t it?). We move ideas around and share them with other people. There&#39;s a lot of really wonderful stuff that happens as a result, but the last time I checked, we&#39;re not just brains in jars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, evolution has not caught up with you just existing as pure mental abstraction...and for the rest of your life it never will!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you will continue to exist as a mind inside a body, you have to bring the two into balance. Otherwise, as you know, the mind tends to float away from the body, like a poor little kid&#39;s balloon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you grab the balloon by it&#39;s string and reign it back in again? Here&#39;s my favorite method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don&#39;t Just Do Something, Stand There&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/mISML6ggKhg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/mISML6ggKhg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In standing qigong, you practice &#34;putting your mind inside your body&#34;. Think of most of the mental work that you do as the exact opposite. You get really good at letting your mind go wherever it wants to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stick with me over the next four weeks and I&#39;ll show you how to gradually encourage the mind to reconnect with the body. See, you can&#39;t force this process and to be honest, four weeks of practicing it is only the beginning. Think of the hours of mental churning you&#39;ve already accumulated. But we can start working towards a balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each week, I&#39;ll explain a different technique and include a guided practice mp3 that you can download and work with throughout the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first lesson is going to be a 5-minute practice on &#34;settling in&#34;. You can use it as a warm-up for tai chi or any other kind of movement practice where you want to be more grounded and connected to your body, or even as a break in your mental work (highly recommended!). Check back next week for the download, or even better, subscribe below and get each lesson delivered right to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Twice a Day</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 04:32:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I know I&#39;m writing this on vacation where the most pressing decision we make each day is whether to hike, kayak, or swim, but I&#39;m going to go ahead anyway and recommend that you practice twice a day. Here&#39;s why...&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1979&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/in5LGYtp8xw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/in5LGYtp8xw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Learned from a Month-Long Tai Chi Intensive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After a month in England, practicing 10 hours a day at &lt;a title=&#34;Movement Arts&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011&#34;&gt;the Short Form Instructor Training&lt;/a&gt; this summer, I have a renewed appreciation for daily practice rhythm. At the training, there were three distinct types of training sessions we would go through each day. In the mornings, we would practice in our groups. Most of the day, from 10am to 5pm was reserved for class time with Bruce. In the evenings, we would be free to practice again, ideally training the pieces of what we did in class that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During class time, we would have ten or twenty minutes to practice each new thing that Bruce introduced. That&#39;s fine to get an initial hit of each piece, but that brief exposure isn&#39;t the same thing as locking it in to your system. You have to take it two steps further. First, you have to expand that twenty minutes into forty-five minutes or an hour in the evening sessions. Then, after you eat and sleep and feel rested, you have to revisit the same material in a lighter way the next morning, trying to let the new material flow into your regular morning practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you look at the three pieces of each training day, you had integration of the previous day first thing in the morning, then new material during the bulk of the day, and finally a chance to really work on the new material in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the clearest way to see how this rhythm worked was to watch people not follow it! When people would blow off the evening training session, you could tell that the material wasn&#39;t soaking into their system the next day. Likewise, if they worked hard on pieces in the morning session (which they should have done the night before), they didn&#39;t have enough energy to get the most of out class that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I&#39;m Learning Practicing Twice a Day on Vacation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Going on vacation and having the free time to test this out again, I&#39;m even more convinced that you can learn a lot about your own practice rhythm by spreading out practice sessions throughout your day. The most surprising insight from the training was: &lt;strong&gt;the morning practice sessions were related more to the work I did the day before than they were to the two sessions following on the same day.&lt;/strong&gt; In other words, Tuesday morning practice was the completion of the training I did on Monday, not the warm-up for the rest of the training I was about to do on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the bigger pattern I wanted to test on vacation and it seems to be working really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you realize what this means, right? It means that eating, sleeping, and letting things settle down is an important part of learning. Or in other words, rest and integration complete hard work. We tend to think of work as an on/off switch. We&#39;re either working hard or being lazy. The lesson here is that rest and integration are the real opposites of hard work and that hard work doesn&#39;t pay off until you&#39;ve integrated it. Pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other cool thing about making this connection has been that now I feel like I&#39;m in one long training session. I used to think &#34;I practiced Monday, missed Tuesday, and Wednesday through Friday I did a little bit....I suck&#34;. Now, though, I think about chaining sessions of work, rest, and integration together and it gives the process much more continuity. You get out of an all-or-nothing mindset about your practice. To me, that seems to be much closer to making your practice a real part of the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Leave me a comment below and tell me about your practice cycles. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi for Weight Loss?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/08/tai-chi-for-weight-loss/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2011 08:24:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/08/tai-chi-for-weight-loss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People often ask me if tai chi is good for losing weight. If they&#39;re asking whether tai chi is a substitute for running or lifting weights, the answer is usually &#34;no&#34;. When someone has been really injury or hasn&#39;t exercised in a long time, tai chi can get you back on your feet and moving pain free. For these folks, tai chi can be a safe first step towards more demanding exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum, if you&#39;re into the martial side of tai chi, the answer is &#34;yes&#34;. You&#39;ll be training like a boxer, doing lots of heavy sparring, and weapons training becomes the equivalent of lifting weights. Most people aren&#39;t going down the martial tai chi road, training hours each day, so you need to look at the whole issue a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this explanation of stress on weight management, from Dr. Arya M. Sharma, Professor of Medicine &amp;amp; Chair in Obesity Research and Management at the University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1574&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stress has both a psychological and physiological impact on weight management as it affects a patient&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s eating and exercise behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physiologically, stress increases serum cortisol, which in turn affects appetite. Eating can be an appropriate response to stress as it decreases serum cortisol levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychologically, stressed individuals may find themselves more distractible with decreased ability to focus, concentrate and plan &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; abilities that are essential to lifestyle-based weight management. As well, individuals under stress may fall into more disorganized patterns of eating and miss meals or snacks, thereby allowing hunger to influence their eating decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching patients stress-reduction techniques, or directing them to appropriate stress-reduction resources may help with their weight-management efforts. Meditation, yoga, deep-breathing techniques, exercise and professional counselling can all be considered. (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drsharma.ca/obesity-best-weight-stress.html&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What I really like about this explanation is that you have to address stress on a psychological and physiological level to understand its full impact. As you begin to understand and identify the different facets of stress, you can adapt your behavior accordingly. It&#39;s not uncommon to write off our experiences as entirely psychological or entirely physiological, making us at fault in the first case and helpless in the second. It&#39;s so much more productive to try to understand the interplay of psychological and physiological forces at play in the stress -- and hopefully, relaxation -- cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that point of view, having a tai chi practice will teach you to recognize the signs of stress in your life and give you a way to process them before they take a psychological and physical toll. So what are you waiting for? Hurry up and relax!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Do I Sequence My Practice Sets for Qigong and Tai Chi?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/01/how-do-i-sequence-my-practice-sets-for-qigong-and-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2011 16:06:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/01/how-do-i-sequence-my-practice-sets-for-qigong-and-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I&#39;m going to practice several types of qigong and maybe some tai chi, does it matter what order I do things in? Or if I do one longer practice vs two shorter ones during the day?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2840&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_296&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=60324041&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/78e59884/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=60324041&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_296&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/78e59884/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=60324041&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=60324041&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Practice Qigong According to My Wife</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/18/how-to-practice-qigong-according-to-my-wife/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2011 08:57:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/18/how-to-practice-qigong-according-to-my-wife/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Simmering by EraPhernalia Vintage . . . (playin&#39; hooky ;o), on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/eraphernalia_vintage/3206968021/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3352/3206968021_60d9d7cec9_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Simmering&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I learned everything I know about practicing qigong from my wife. Or I should say, from watching my wife make magic in the kitchen! If you saw us cooking together, you&#39;d see her doing everything right and me doing everything wrong. When I started to practice qigong the way she cooks, my whole qigong world changed. Let me tell you how.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1725&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I do:&lt;/strong&gt; I read every recipe word for word and line by line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What she does: &lt;/strong&gt;She reads recipes like poetry and gets layers of meaning from the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Qigong Lesson: &lt;/strong&gt;At first, you need to learn your forms and the basics of your qigong set, but eventually, you have to get a feel for the whole, or you&#39;ll never get truly energized from the practice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I do: &lt;/strong&gt;I race back and forth from the counter to the cook book, thinking, &#34;was that a lemon or a lime?&#34;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What she does: &lt;/strong&gt;She stops and imagines a taste, thinking &#34;what kind of citrus will compliment these other ingredients? Maybe I&#39;ll use an orange instead&#34;....and she&#39;s usually right!&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Qigong Lesson: &lt;/strong&gt;You need to develop a feel for your energy flows so that you know what kind of practicing you need to do on any given day or any time of day. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I do: &lt;/strong&gt;I freak out when the timer goes off, because the recipe said 10 minutes, but it&#39;s been 12 or 13 and I can&#39;t tell if it&#39;s done yet.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What she does: &lt;/strong&gt;The recipe calls for a specific cook-time? She knows those are vague guidelines and she&#39;ll sniff, pinch, or push on the food to know exactly when it&#39;s ready.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Qigong Lesson: &lt;/strong&gt;The exercises you practice all have prescribed times and reps, but they&#39;re just there so that you learn what &#34;done&#34; feels like energetically.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you want your qigong practice to be as nourishing as a delicious, healthy meal, practice like my wife cooks: go a few layers deeper than your thinking mind and access your intuition. Learn to practice by feel. Otherwise, your practice will always be like reading out of a cookbook. When was the last time you got full from reading a recipe?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Day Better Breathing Challenge</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 10:17:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&#39;ve been talking a lot about two things, &lt;a title=&#34;Follow the 20-20-20 Rule for Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/21/follow-the-20-20-20-rule-for-better-breathing/&#34;&gt;improving your breathing&lt;/a&gt; to give you a &lt;a title=&#34;Disrupt the Stress Cycle with Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/26/disrupt-the-stress-cycle-with-better-breathing/&#34;&gt;major energy/relaxation boost&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a title=&#34;Building Better Practice Tools&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/&#34;&gt;developing tools&lt;/a&gt; that help you &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/?p=1494&#34;&gt;follow-through on your home practice&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve even created an online course with all the information you need to cultivate better breathing habits: &lt;a title=&#34;Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/courses/better-breathing/&#34;&gt;Better Breathing&lt;/a&gt;. The biggest lesson we learned as we talked to BTC students&amp;Acirc;  was that the best time to use reminders to trigger your practice was when you were invested in learning a new skill.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1510&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; When you&#39;re going through a period of sustained practice, integrating stuff you&#39;ve learned before, you need external tools less. However, when you shift back into learning mode and set a specific training goal, getting extra, regular motivation from an outside source can push you over the line from wanting to learn something to ingraining it as a habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to cultivate better breathing habits is a great example of skill building that benefits from extra stimulation. As I explain in the breathing course, there is a clear threshold with your breathing practice that you need to cross to make a lasting impact on your habits. In one sense, the secret to mastering better breathing habits is just putting in the time. The steps along the path to better breathing aren&#39;t always exciting or immediately gratifying, but crossing the breathing threshold puts you into a different world where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;each breath feels deep and nourishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your insides feel smooth and relaxed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you radiate a sense of well-being and easy-to-sustain energy throughout your day&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These are the kinds of things you only notice once you&#39;ve had them and lost them. The biggest challenge of cultivating these qualities is that you can&#39;t do it in one single act of will power. You need sustained, regular practice to take you over the threshold. The good news is that you can leverage external tools, instead of just will power, to carry you over the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s why I&#39;ve created the 30 Day Breathing Challenge. If you want to hit a new depth of practice in the next month, I will give you the tools to get there. For a limited time, I&#39;m giving away my online breathing course (normally $29), for free. All you have to do is sign-up for the 30-Day Challenge using the form below. I will send you daily practice reminders and weekly video instruction drawn from the course. In 30 days, you&#39;re going to see a major shift in your personal practice. Ready?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://eepurl.com/xORb&#34;&gt;Sign up for the 30 Day Challenge here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Quiet Awareness with Lee Burkins</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1656&#34; title=&#34;Lee Burkins Ba Gua&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/ABG1-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lee Burkins Ba Gua&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In June, between sessions at Brookline Tai Chi and during master classes with Bruce Frantzis, a small group of students got a special treat. Energy Arts Senior Instructor Lee Burkins was in town to train with Bruce, and on one of the nights off, he offered a special evening course on a topic he calls &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/blog/special-evening-mini-topic-lee-burkins&#34;&gt;&#34;Investing in Loss&#34;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I love about studying with someone like Lee is that he&#39;s a  practitioner whose art has soaked so deeply into his bones, that it  practically oozes out of his DNA. Everything he teaches seems so  obviously and natural when he explains it, but you&#39;ve never thought about  it before and never accessed it so effortlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second time he&#39;s taught at Brookline Tai Chi. The first  time, a couple of years ago, he did the same thing with the&amp;Acirc;  Ba Gua  Single Palm Change. Lee took a group of people, most of whom had never  done Ba Gua, and got them gliding around the room, finding the Ba Gua  step, and eventually even spontaneously twisting and turning into the  Single Palm Change. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1651&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our topic this year seemed more esoteric at first, so I was wondering if he&#39;d be able to do the same thing. What  the heck is &#34;Quiet Awareness&#34; and how do you let that run your physical  body? You could see that with many other teachers, this could have been a  2-hour theoretical lecture. Not with Lee. He snuck up on us with really  clear and simple physical exercises, just letting go of tension and  posture through movements. We let ourselves swirl around and find a  sloshing, fluid, sense of internal space. Once people had settled down  into deeper internal awareness, he showed us how to shape an internal  sense of letting go into a solid physical structure and full, alive, and  responsive physical movement. Obviously this is all a little hard to  explain in writing....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funniest moment though, was after everyone began to really get  what he was driving at, he said, &#34;ok, ok, you&#39;re doing it, so let me  give you something to feed your thinking mind too.&#34; See, the bigger  point he was driving at was that Quiet Awareness is a different mode for  your mind to be in, and you need that to understand your body, your  mind, and your energy. The internal arts are all about accessing this  mode and manifesting it. The problem is, most of us are trained to use a  different mode of awareness, i.e. the thinking mind. As a masterful  teacher, he recognized that, and with the gentle humor he always uses in  teaching, he graciously gave our thinking minds something to chew on  too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Here&#39;s the model he shared:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Leaves on river by rstrawser, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/14696088@N04/1544960560/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2395/1544960560_9e4ba9f9f8_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Leaves on river&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lee took the classic Chinese medicine phrase, &#34;the mind moves the chi  and the chi moves the blood&#34; and formulated it as &#34;the Quiet Awareness  moves the chi and the chi moves the fluids inside the body and therefore  the body as well&#34;. To really get this concept, he explained it like the  current in a river. Think of a leaf floating along in the river. That&#39;s  your body. When the current changes, that&#39;s like the chi shifting. It  shifts direction (inward to outward, up to down), because your Quiet  Awareness shifts first. The interesting part is the lag time between  the change of the current and movement of the leaf. Your Quiet Awareness  turns over, the chi follows, and so does the leaf, but as you are learning  to tune into this process, you can feel the leaf moving along the old  current pattern, even as the current is going a different direction.  Those are the circular transitions you feel in your form.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don&#39;t know if I quite captured what we did or what Lee was  aiming to teach, but if you ever do get a chance to work with him, take  it. He&#39;s a kind and generous teacher and the naturalness of his art form  that pours out is a real treasure. &lt;a href=&#34;http://coloradointernalarts.com/practitioners.htm&#34;&gt;Lee lives and teaches in Colorado&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In his own words: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I followed up with Lee to see if this recap came close to capturing what he was teaching. Here&#39;s how he describes the process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the mind&#39;s frequency to smoothly transition from  the&amp;Acirc; vibration&amp;Acirc; of the intellectual aspect to approach and begin to  connect with the vibration/frequency of the intuitive mind. Once you  &#39;experience&#39; this shift in frequency and are able to stay in this mode  (a posture of the mind), &#39;what is hidden will be revealed&#39;, ie, the  connection of the quiet awareness to the chi to the body (nerves,  fluids, and tissues).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Things Modern Athletes Can Learn from the Tai Chi Classics</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/27/10-things-modern-athletes-can-learn-from-the-tai-chi-classics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 09:58:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/27/10-things-modern-athletes-can-learn-from-the-tai-chi-classics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By training the principles of body-alignment and movement as described in the Tai Chi Classics, you can move with much more grace, fluidity, and power. Instead of wasting energy holding excess tension, relaxation can lead the way to more powerful movement. Here&#39;s what Yang Cheng-fu said about it a hundred years ago (the following is adapted from YANG&#39;S TEN IMPORTANT POINTS by Yang  Cheng-fu (1883 &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; 1936) as researched by Lee N. Scheele and published on  http://www.scheele.org/lee/classics.html. Scheele&#39;s translation is first and my notes are in italics following):&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1581&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.) Head upright to let the shen [spirit of vitality] rise to the top of the head.&lt;/strong&gt; Don&#39;t use li [external strength], or the neck will be stiff and the ch&#39;i [vital life energy] and blood cannot flow through. It is necessary to have a natural and lively feeling. If the spirit cannot reach the headtop, it cannot raise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you&#39;re sitting at your computer right now, what do your head and neck feel like? The beginning of effortless posture is how you hold your head. As it collapses down and forward, you begin a stress-inducing cascade of neck and shoulder pain, poor breathing, and bad posture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.) Sink the chest and pluck up the back.&lt;/strong&gt; The chest is depressed naturally inward so that the ch&#39;i can sink to the tan-t&#39;ien [field of elixir]. Don&#39;t expand the chest: the ch&#39;i gets stuck there and the body becomes top-heavy. The heel will be too light and can be uprooted. Pluck up the back and the ch&#39;i sticks to the back; depress the chest and you can pluck up the back. Then you can discharge force through the spine. You will be a peerless boxer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here&#39;s another posture tip. Lengthen the spine. It&#39;s the opposite of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;fetal position&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; fight or flight response (again, think stress). When you keep the chest relaxed and sunk, you naturally begin to breathe deeply with the diaphragm, getting a more efficient breath and actually nourishing the internal organs, literally massaging them with internal pressure changes. This is all the opposite of what happens to breath and posture when you hyperventilate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 3.) Sung [Relax] the waist.&lt;/strong&gt; The waist is the commander of the whole body. If you can sung the waist, then the two legs will have power and the lower part will be firm and stable. Substantial and insubstantial change, and this is based on the turning of the waist. It is said &#34;the source of the postures lies in the waist. If you cannot get power, seek the defect in the legs and waist.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now we&#39;re getting into some more esoteric terminology, but as a tai chi teacher, I&#39;ve found that many of my students have frozen hips. Start there. If you can&#39;t distinguish the movement of the legs, pelvis, and trunk, then your source of power and movement is seriously diminished. You should be able to internally and externally rotate each leg independently of hip movement and roll the pelvis around without moving the spine or legs. Once you can move all these parts independently, you can learn to lead movements with hip drive and powerful rotation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 4.) Differentiate between insubstantial and substantial.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the first principle in T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan. If the weight of the whole body is resting on the right leg, then the right leg is substantial and the left leg is insubstantial, and vice versa. When you can separate substantial and insubstantial, you can turn lightly without using strength. If you cannot separate, the step is heavy and slow. The stance is not firm and can be easily thrown of balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ever see someone get caught &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;flat-footed&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; on the court? The ability to distinguish where your weight is by feel, and quickly shift your center of gravity left and right is critical for reaction speed and movement. In tai chi, you learn to make this distinction completely clearly in slow motion, and then you gradually increase the speed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 5.) Sink the shoulders and drop the elbows.&lt;/strong&gt; The shoulders will be completely relaxed and open. If you cannot relax and sink, the two shoulders will be raised up and tense. The ch&#39;i will follow them up and the whole body cannot get power. &#34;Drop the elbows&#34; means the elbows go down and relax. If the elbows raise, the shoulders are not able to sink and you cannot discharge people far. The discharge will then be close to the broken force of the external schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This principle has to do with power-generation in tai chi, and may not be completely adaptable to your sport, but I will point this out: whenever you are in motion and you feel your shoulders start to creep towards your ears, you&#39;re experiencing the beginning of that fight or flight response. By training the physical opposite, you are sending your body the message that relaxation in motion is possible, and you&#39;re getting better at maintaining it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 6.) Use the mind instead of force.&lt;/strong&gt; The T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan Classics say, &#34;all of this means use I [mind-intent] and not li.&#34; In practicing T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan the whole body relaxes. Don&#39;t let one ounce of force remain in the blood vessels, bones, and ligaments to tie yourself up. Then you can be agile and able to change. You will be able to turn freely and easily. Doubting this, how can you increase your power?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body has meridians like the ground has ditches and trenches. If not obstructed the water can flow. If the meridian is not closed, the ch&#39;i goes through. If the whole body has hard force and it fills up the meridians, the ch&#39;i and the blood stop and the turning is not smooth and agile. Just pull one hair and the whole body is off-balance. If you use I, and not li, then the I goes to a place in the body and the ch&#39;i follows it. The ch&#39;i and the blood circulate. If you do this every day and never stop, after a long time you will have nei chin [real internal strength]. The T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan Classics say, &#34;when you are extremely soft, you become extremely hard and strong.&#34; Someone who has extremely good T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan kung fu has arms like iron wrapped with cotton and the weight is very heavy. As for the external schools, when they use li, they reveal li. When they don&#39;t use li, they are too light and floating. There chin is external and locked together. The li of the external schools is easily led and moved, and not too be esteemed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When he refers to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;force&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;li&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; in this principle, you should read it as &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;extra&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;unnecessary tension&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. Too many people have a silly fantasy about tai chi relying on magical chi and no force as an excuse for not training hard. The way you get to effortless power in tai chi is by refining you movements, stripping them of unnecessary tension, layer by layer. You do tai chi in slow motion so that your mind can search every inch of your insides and find the extra tension that is holding back your movements.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.) Coordinate the upper and lower parts of the body.&lt;/strong&gt; The T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan Classics say &#34;the motion should be rooted in the feet, released through the legs, controlled by the waist and manifested through the fingers.&#34; Everything acts simultaneously. When the hand, waist and foot move together, the eyes follow. If one part doesn&#39;t follow, the whole body is disordered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This description of force generation, coming from the ground and going up through the body and out the fingers is almost word for word how Curt Schilling described throwing a perfect pitch. Again, think of the basic practices of tai chi, the slow motion form work, as awareness training that lets you pay attention to these connections in a way you wouldn&#39;t be able to always going fast. Take any movement from your sport and try it in slow motion. Can you find these links?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8.) Harmonize the internal and external.&lt;/strong&gt; In the practice of T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan the main thing is the shen. Therefore it is said &#34;the spirit is the commander and the body is subordinate.&#34; If you can raise the spirit, then the movements will naturally be agile. The postures are not beyond insubstantial and substantial, opening and closing. That which is called open means not only the hands and feet are open, but the mind is also open. That which is called closed means not only the hands and feet are closed, but the mind is also closed. When you can make the inside and outside become one, then it becomes complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You hear people describe moments of flow, when time slows down, or the ball or the net looks huge and making the shot was inevitable. These moments are perfect examples of the inside and the outside becoming one. When the mind opens up and the internal and external are harmonized, you access a different kind of awareness. Tai Chi actually includes a systematic training method for getting you into that state, again and again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9.) Move with continuity.&lt;/strong&gt; As to the external schools, their chin is the Latter Heaven brute chin. Therefore it is finite. There are connections and breaks. During the breaks the old force is exhausted and the new force has not yet been born. At these moments it is very easy for others to take advantage. T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan uses I and not li. From beginning to end it is continuous and not broken. It is circular and again resumes. It revolves and has no limits. The original Classics say it is &#34;like a great river rolling on unceasingly.&#34; and that the circulation of the chin is &#34;drawing silk from a cocoon &#34; They all talk about being connected together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Try this exercise: with your index finger, draw a box in front of you and keep going around, with sharp corners and edges. Try to pay attention to your breathing at the same time. Now compare that to what it feels like to make a circle with your finger. See how much easier it is to tune into your breathing doing circular movement? Feel how the stop and start of linear movement briefly &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;freezes&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; your nervous system as you change directions. It&#39;s this simple practice of circular movement, repeated on deeper and deeper levels, that is the key to relaxation in tai chi.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.) Move with tranquility [Seek stillness in movement].&lt;/strong&gt; The external schools assume jumping about is good and they use all their energy. That is why after practice everyone pants. T&#39;ai Chi Ch&#39;uan uses stillness to control movement. Although one moves, there is also stillness. Therefore in practicing the form, slower is better. If it is slow, the inhalation and exhalation are long and deep and the ch&#39;i sinks to the tan-t&#39;ien. Naturally there is no injurious practice such as engorgement of the blood vessels. The learner should be careful to comprehend it. Then you will get the real meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Often, when people start learning tai chi, they think &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;ok, I&#39;m going to get this right&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;, as if doing the movement perfectly once was the end goal and they could stop there. That&#39;s the completely wrong way to think about it. In tai chi, you are setting up a state or a condition where all of the postural alignments, layers of relaxation, and continuity of movement can gel. Your goal is to experience that state, returning to it again and again, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;seeking stillness in movement&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. Daily practice, when you enter this state, becomes a major recharge and even when you are doing tai chi as a way to get better at something else, the nourishing, refreshing experience of doing the practice slowly becomes the goal itself. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Do You Have a Home Practice?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/15/why-do-you-have-a-home-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2011 09:20:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/15/why-do-you-have-a-home-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When we started asking our students at Brookline Tai Chi about their home practice, we got a really interesting range of habits and preferences. Since then, we&#39;ve been trying out different tools to help spark more home practice. Stepping back for a minute, I&#39;d really like to know more about why you practice. Take a minute drop me a line (filing out the form below is private and goes right to me, no one else).&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1610&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://spreadsheets.google.com/spreadsheet/embeddedform?formkey=dDlWY2Q4YXZuMXdBczhqdTBmOWktRmc6MA&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;1200&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34;&gt;Loading...&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Home Practice Challenge</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:19:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the recent practice survey we conducted at Brookline Tai Chi and experiments I&#39;ve been running in online learning, it&#39;s become clearer and clearer to me that most people need some external motivation when they are learning a new skill. That&#39;s not a judgment about willpower and motivation, it actually says more about the way we are wired for survival. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1523&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In Z Health, we always talk about the way that the nervous system is at once the most plastic system -- it can adapt to lots of different changes -- and also the most stable. The stability of the nervous system is a good thing from a survival and energy management point of view -- it doesn&#39;t cost you a lot of cognitive energy to get through your day if you run on habit. In that sense, the plasticity of the nervous system -- your ability to change and learn new things -- has to deal with the inertia of stability in your nervous system. When we are trying to learn new behaviors and forge new habits, these two things can be at odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&#39;ve seen and heard from my tai chi students, is that a little bit of external motivation goes a long way to spark the small changes you need to make on a daily basis to put new behavior in place. Last week, one of my students said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was liberating to think that 5 minutes of tai chi practice meant I could make progress, because until I thought about it that way, I avoided practice, assuming it was going to take 30 minutes or more.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, if you look at some studies on mental rehearsal and brain function, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1580438,00.html&#34;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;, you start to see that the cognitive component of learning new skills can be practiced in a much easier way than devoting hours and hours of grueling practice -- time that very few people I work with have to spare anyway. The smarter you get about your practice, the better you&#39;ll get at getting good at new things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#39;s my DIY Home Practice Challenge for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drill down into your practice until you get to a small chunk you can practice in 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick the easiest time of day to devote to your practice -- what&#39;s the perfect scenario for practicing this skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a recurring reminder in your calendar -- pick the medium that will be most accessible to get the reminder at the right time, i.e. on your desktop to interrupt your work, via email, or even text message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each day when you get the reminder, do your 5 minute practice, and then maybe take a minute or two to reflect on the success of what you just did or refine the scenario if necessary&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You will fail to build up this practice habit if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pick too big a skill to work on, e.g. I want to become a ballerina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are vague about when you are going to do it, e.g. I will practice it daily&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&#39;t get the reminder at the right time, e.g. I&#39;ll practice at noon each day, but my reminder comes in at 6pm&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I know those failures might sound obvious, and you should pick something pretty simple and obvious to begin with, but what I hope is that once you see the power in this simple approach, you&#39;ll start to tackle more complex and exciting skill building and begin to reflect on a lot of different experiences, in business, at work, in personal relationships, with the same desire to make incremental progress as you do with a hobby or healthy habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m always curious to hear how this goes for people, so send me an email or drop a comment below once you get set up and start hitting your daily targets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>