<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>qi on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/qi/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in qi on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/qi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Itch to Move Your Chi</title>
      <link>/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 08:48:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We tend to think about our energy level like the money we have in the bank. You wake up in the morning, look in your energetic wallet and say, &#34;I&#39;ve got a lot of energy today&#34; or &#34;Man, I need 7 cups of coffee.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, to put it another way, thanks to this New Yorker cartoon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.condenaststore.com/-sp/If-we-re-all-just-energy-then-why-don-t-I-have-any-New-Yorker-Cartoon-Prints_i8481061_.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter  wp-image-4975&#34; alt=&#34;If we&#39;re all just energy, then why don&#39;t I have any?&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/12/Screen-Shot-2013-12-20-at-8.14.34-AM.png&#34; width=&#34;577&#34; height=&#34;445&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In qigong, we think about &#34;having energy&#34; a little bit differently. Often, it&#39;s not just how much or how little, but &lt;strong&gt;how well is your energy circulating?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good energetic circulation gives you a feeling of &#34;more,&#34; while stagnant or stuck energy feels draining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is such a different concept than most of us have, I&#39;ve often wondered about where these two ideas came from and where these two ways of seeing the world split. In this post, I&#39;m not going to give you a deeply researched exploration of the origins of the Taoist understanding of the world. I&#39;ll let &lt;a title=&#34;Straight Lines, Circles, and Spheres&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/11/straight-lines-circles-and-spheres/&#34;&gt;our practices&lt;/a&gt; stand as of evidence of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I want to share with you some of the writings of 20th century Western philosopher Hans Jonas. He wrote about the phenomenology of life and in his descriptions of biological processes, we get a really interesting connection to what many qigong practitioners come to realize: &lt;strong&gt;we have a fundamental need to circulate chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The Phenomenon of Life&lt;/span&gt;, Jonas is trying to reconcile the simplest forms of life with higher thought and our human experience of the mind. He tries to place them on a continuum and asks which one is for the sake of the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whatever the answer, one aspect of the ascending scale is that in its stages the &#34;mirroring&#34; of the world becomes ever more distinct and self-rewarding, beginning with the most obscure sensation somewhere on the lowest rungs of animality, even with the most elementary stimulation of organic irritability as such, in which somehow already otherness, world, and object are germinally &#34;experienced,&#34; that is, made subjective, and responded to (p.3).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My personal theory on the origins of qigong is that those early Taoists went exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They sat or stood in postures and listened, both inside themselves and to the natural world. &lt;strong&gt;As they got quieter and more perceptive, the heard the echoes of Jonas&#39; &#34;most obscure sensation.&#34;&lt;/strong&gt; The irritability that Jonas describes set them up against the world outside and framed their inner worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That irritability is the same itch you feel when you know you need to get your chi moving, circulating through you and passing back and forth between you, the natural world around you and the other people you interact with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things are flowing, in and out, up and down, towards and away, we feel good: &lt;strong&gt;connected to something outside ourselves but at the same time internally unified and integrated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like eating, breathing, and sleeping, circulating energy is a natural cycle that we can refine, enhance, and enjoy, but we need to pay attention to it on an ongoing, continuous basis to be healthy and feel whole.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing Qigong Breathing Exercises -- Mp3</title>
      <link>/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 08:38:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4412&#34; alt=&#34;Better Breathing&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2012/11/032-300x225.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest question people ask me about standing qigong, especially when they hear about &lt;a title=&#34;Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/&#34;&gt;the 2-hour project&lt;/a&gt;, is &#34;what do you do, just stand there?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is actually a really delicate balance between &#34;doing&#34; and &#34;feeling&#34; when you stand. You learn lots of different techniques, like breathing, sinking, dissolving, and pulsing, but how you apply them internally when you are holding a static posture is a tricky topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you rev your engine too much -- activating &lt;a title=&#34;My Favorite Breathing Hack&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/30/my-favorite-breathing-hack/&#34;&gt;strong diaphragmatic breathing&lt;/a&gt; the entire time, for example -- then you miss the potential stillness in the posture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you zone out, and don&#39;t connect to internal sensations, you&#39;ll miss the potential for integration and you won&#39;t build any chi or walk away with the sense of organization that your standing qigong can provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you strike the balance between &#34;do&#34; and &#34;feel&#34; in your standing qigong practice? I&#39;ve put together two breathing exercise mp3 for you to listen to while you practice standing qigong to help you find that balance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/[Standing]%20Breathing%20to%20Activate%20the%20Back.mp3&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong -- Breathing to Activate the Back&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/[Standing]%20Breathing%20to%20Activate%20the%20Feet.mp3&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong -- Breathing to Activate the Feet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These are short, easy practice sessions that focus in on one skill each: you will learn how to use the breath as a guide for your awareness, activating sensation, without overriding the potential for stillness. As you practice, you will be able to apply this same skill to longer and longer standing qigong practice sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One more thing:&lt;/strong&gt; if you enjoy these workouts and find them useful, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr?cmd=_s-xclick&amp;amp;hosted_button_id=QQC5GSTJLQRUW&#34;&gt;considering making a small contribution here&lt;/a&gt;. Think of it as a drop-in class fee. If I know that a lot of people are finding these helpful as practice aides, I will create more of them in the future. Thanks for your feedback and support!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-4629&#34; alt=&#34;help-browser&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2013/05/help-browser-150x150.png&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend last night about &lt;a title=&#34;Guide to Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; and different &lt;a title=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;meditation traditions&lt;/a&gt; that we had both tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many different reasons, on any given day, that we sought out the practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To clear our heads of racing thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To more deeply relax the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explore layers of the mind and emotions that aren&#39;t so obvious during our normal busy days.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It seems like we had really similar reasons to practice, but I was left wondering if it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; similar when we practice. What are the sensations that tell you you&#39;re on the right track? It seems like we want to end up in the same place, but are we taking the same road to get there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p4r3&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p4r3&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p4r3;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p4r3&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;554&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { r7p4r3 = new WufooForm();r7p4r3.initialize(options);r7p4r3.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>