<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>standing-series on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/standing-series/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in standing-series on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/standing-series/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sinking Your Mind through Your Body</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 09:18:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you explore layers of relaxation through standing qigong, you&#39;ll hit a point where everything starts to feel fluid, as if you&#39;ve dug down deep enough to find a rich aquifer, filled with nourishing water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We describe the experience with words like &#34;sinking&#34; and &#34;soaking&#34; the mind into the body, and that&#39;s literally what&#39;s happening. Remember the qigong expression, &#34;your mind moves your chi and your chi moves your blood&#34;? When they say &#34;blood&#34;, they mean all the fluids in the body. When you truly start to fuse your mind and your body, your insides start to feel more wet, fluid, and connected.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2115&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last lesson on standing qigong, we worked on enlivening each section of your body, bringing awareness and increased sensation to each new place, from head to toe, with &lt;a title=&#34;Learning to Soften the Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/26/learning-to-soften-the-body/&#34;&gt;ten minutes of softening&lt;/a&gt;. Now we want to move even deeper into the body and explore how you can completely refresh your system by sinking your chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this guided practice session (download the mp3 below).&amp;Acirc;  In this 20-minute scan, you&#39;ll start the process of sinking your chi by letting your mind soak into your body at each height. As you go longer now, you will begin to recognize deeper relaxation patterns and find natural resolution of holding patterns in the body, without mental force:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/guides/Sinking_Chi.mp3&#34;&gt;Sinking 20-Minute Practice Mp3 (right click to save)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Soften the Body</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/26/learning-to-soften-the-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 09:17:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/26/learning-to-soften-the-body/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can encourage your body to relax just by paying attention to it the right way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using standing qigong, you can build up a relaxation feedback loop between your feeling awareness and the body&#39;s natural ability to soften when circulation improves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The qigong expression, drawn from Chinese medicine, is, &#34;your mind moves your chi and your chi moves your blood&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first lesson on standing qigong, we worked on creating a buffer between &#34;real life&#34; and &#34;practice time&#34; with &lt;a title=&#34;Settling in with Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;five minutes of settling in&lt;/a&gt;. Now we want to move a little deeper into the body and explore how increased you can trigger relaxation with increased feeling awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2114&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this guided practice session (download the mp3 below).&amp;Acirc;  In this 10-minute scan, you&#39;ll move beyond body alignment and the initial &#34;settle&#34;. As you go longer now, you will start to enliven each section of your body, bringing awareness and increased sensation to each new place, from head to toe, which naturally softens the tension you uncover:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Waking_Up_Feeling_Awareness.mp3&#34;&gt;Softening 10-Minute Practice Mp3 (right click to save)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up next in this series: We&#39;ll look at a powerful way to refresh yourself in a 20-minute recording on &#34;sinking your chi&#34;. I&#39;ll be posting these as weekly updates, so be sure you&#39;re on the email list below or check back with &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/standing-series/&#34;&gt;this bookmark&lt;/a&gt; to see the entire series.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Settling in with Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2011 09:17:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Do you include a &#34;settling-in&#34; phase each time you practice?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;If not, you&#39;re wasting time and energy resolving issues from your day when you could be going deeper into your practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;A settling-in phase acts as a buffer between your busy day and the place you&#39;d like your practice to take you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2113&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Standing qigong is one of the best buffers between &#34;real life&#34; and &#34;practice time&#34;. You could jump right into your tai chi form, but you&#39;d need to do 10 or 15 minutes of &#34;cold&#34; tai chi, with no warm-up, to arrive at the same place, ready to practice, after 5 minutes of standing and settling in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Check out this guided practice session (download the mp3 below).&amp;Acirc;  In this 5-minute scan, you&#39;ll align your body, release the first layer of accumulated tension from your day, and slow your mind down to a speed where your subsequent movement practice will be much more refreshing and restorative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Settling_In.mp3&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Settling In 5-Minute Practice Mp3&lt;/a&gt; (right click to save)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend that you start your practice off with a 5-minute settle every day for the next week. You&#39;ll also discover a little trick: on those days you don&#39;t feel like practicing, 5 minutes of guided scanning like this can prime your nervous system and get you over that &#34;no practice&#34; internal resistance. Try it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up next in this series: a 10-minute practice where I&#39;ll show you how to &#34;wake up your feeling awareness&#34;. After that, we&#39;ll look at a powerful way to refresh yourself in a 20-minute recording on &#34;sinking your chi&#34;. I&#39;ll be posting these as weekly updates, so be sure you&#39;re on the email list below or check back with &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/standing-series/&#34;&gt;this bookmark&lt;/a&gt; to see the entire series.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Your Practice All in Your Head?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/12/is-your-practice-all-in-your-head-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2011 09:15:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/12/is-your-practice-all-in-your-head-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you&#39;re sitting here reading this, I want you to try something. I want you to push yourself back away from your desk, let your arms hang by your sides, close your eyes and see how many fingers you can feel. Go ahead, try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now do the same thing again, but stand up and count your toes instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could you feel more fingers or toes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are you have much greater feeling access to your fingers. But how does the sensation of feeling a finger compare to the clarity of a thought you just had or an image you can generate in your head? If thoughts and images are much clearer than feeling sensations in your body, you might have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2106&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In this four-part series, I&#39;m going to show you how do deal with your practice &#34;being all in your head&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that a lot of us make a living with the power of our minds (that sounds much cooler than &#34;desk job&#34;, doesn&#39;t it?). We move ideas around and share them with other people. There&#39;s a lot of really wonderful stuff that happens as a result, but the last time I checked, we&#39;re not just brains in jars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, evolution has not caught up with you just existing as pure mental abstraction...and for the rest of your life it never will!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you will continue to exist as a mind inside a body, you have to bring the two into balance. Otherwise, as you know, the mind tends to float away from the body, like a poor little kid&#39;s balloon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you grab the balloon by it&#39;s string and reign it back in again? Here&#39;s my favorite method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don&#39;t Just Do Something, Stand There&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/mISML6ggKhg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/mISML6ggKhg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In standing qigong, you practice &#34;putting your mind inside your body&#34;. Think of most of the mental work that you do as the exact opposite. You get really good at letting your mind go wherever it wants to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stick with me over the next four weeks and I&#39;ll show you how to gradually encourage the mind to reconnect with the body. See, you can&#39;t force this process and to be honest, four weeks of practicing it is only the beginning. Think of the hours of mental churning you&#39;ve already accumulated. But we can start working towards a balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each week, I&#39;ll explain a different technique and include a guided practice mp3 that you can download and work with throughout the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first lesson is going to be a 5-minute practice on &#34;settling in&#34;. You can use it as a warm-up for tai chi or any other kind of movement practice where you want to be more grounded and connected to your body, or even as a break in your mental work (highly recommended!). Check back next week for the download, or even better, subscribe below and get each lesson delivered right to your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>