<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>standing-series on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/standing-series/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in standing-series on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/standing-series/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sinking Your Mind through Your Body</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 09:18:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/</guid>
      <description>As you explore layers of relaxation through standing qigong, you&#39;ll hit a point where everything starts to feel fluid, as if you&#39;ve dug down deep enough to find a rich aquifer, filled with nourishing water.
We describe the experience with words like &#34;sinking&#34; and &#34;soaking&#34; the mind into the body, and that&#39;s literally what&#39;s happening. Remember the qigong expression, &#34;your mind moves your chi and your chi moves your blood&#34;? When they say &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Soften the Body</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/26/learning-to-soften-the-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 09:17:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/26/learning-to-soften-the-body/</guid>
      <description>You can encourage your body to relax just by paying attention to it the right way.
Using standing qigong, you can build up a relaxation feedback loop between your feeling awareness and the body&#39;s natural ability to soften when circulation improves.
The qigong expression, drawn from Chinese medicine, is, &#34;your mind moves your chi and your chi moves your blood&#34;.
In the first lesson on standing qigong, we worked on creating a buffer between &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Settling in with Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2011 09:17:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>Do you include a &#34;settling-in&#34; phase each time you practice?
If not, you&#39;re wasting time and energy resolving issues from your day when you could be going deeper into your practice.
A settling-in phase acts as a buffer between your busy day and the place you&#39;d like your practice to take you.

Standing qigong is one of the best buffers between &#34;real life&#34; and &#34;practice time&#34;. You could jump right into your tai chi form, but you&#39;d need to do 10 or 15 minutes of &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Your Practice All in Your Head?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/12/is-your-practice-all-in-your-head-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2011 09:15:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/12/is-your-practice-all-in-your-head-2/</guid>
      <description>As you&#39;re sitting here reading this, I want you to try something. I want you to push yourself back away from your desk, let your arms hang by your sides, close your eyes and see how many fingers you can feel. Go ahead, try it.
Now do the same thing again, but stand up and count your toes instead.
Could you feel more fingers or toes?
Chances are you have much greater feeling access to your fingers.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>