<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>trainerfly-backstory on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/trainerfly-backstory/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in trainerfly-backstory on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/trainerfly-backstory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 12:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>Paul Cavel is an Energy Arts Senior Instructor based in London. He teaches regular weekly classes there, but he&#39;s also been traveling all over the UK and Europe for years teaching workshops, including annual week-long retreats in Crete. I talked to Paul a little bit about his background in Tai Chi, neigong, and Ba Gua and asked him for some practice advice for a group of students who just completed a series at BTC on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Posted from Trainerfly: Launching an Online Course</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2011 10:36:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</guid>
      <description>Check out this post from the Trainerfly blog. I talk to teachers and trainers all the time who want move beyond their live events, but the number of steps it takes, and the technology required to make it work seem overwhelming. Hopefully, I&#39;ve made a little dent in that perception!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Feedback from Trainerfly Beta</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 08:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</guid>
      <description>Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve gotten Trainerfly out into people&#39;s hands and I&#39;ve been learning some really interesting lessons. I think it was easy for me to get wrapped up in how I&#39;ve evolved it as a tool in my business over the last two years and lose perspective on how other people might be trying to add it into their business from scratch, with none of that prior history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Trainerfly Video Series</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/23/new-trainerfly-video-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 21:26:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/01/23/new-trainerfly-video-series/</guid>
      <description>I don&#39;t know if I&#39;m more excited about the video series, the fact that we&#39;re inches away from the private beta launch, or that I can embed all the videos in one of Viddler&#39;s &#34;vidgets&#34;. Check them out:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Pre-Launch in the Works</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/29/trainerfly-pre-launch-in-the-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 14:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/29/trainerfly-pre-launch-in-the-works/</guid>
      <description>I spent a fair amount of time today migrating, connecting, and updating. Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve been building out a wordpress front-end site for Trainerfly. My brother Sam has come through with some awesome illustration, including the logo and characters for the blog tutorials.
We had a funny debate about the use of flies on the site and got pretty carried away at one point. It started to look like &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Characters</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/20/trainerfly-characters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 05:18:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/20/trainerfly-characters/</guid>
      <description>Check out this draft of a character I&#39;m going to feature on the Trainerfly blog (my brother Sam is doing the design work):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Backstory: The Moodle Project</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/14/trainerfly-backstory-the-moodle-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2010 14:42:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/14/trainerfly-backstory-the-moodle-project/</guid>
      <description>This post is the second in a series I&#39;m doing on the backstory of how I came to develop a web-based software application called Trainerfly. You can read more about it here.
For about a year after I decided I need a way to manage all my clients&#39; programs, and share information with them privately, I wrestled with finding the right software. I tried private blogs, but at that time it was tons of work to partition information for each client.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Backstory: The Practice Problem</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 08:05:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m sure I&#39;m not alone here. Teachers in all disciples, if they need their students to practice to learn what they are teaching, will relate. I don&#39;t know if &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;movement educators&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; have it worse because people tend to think of all movement as &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;working out&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; -- something you go and do, not an art you have to practice.
In fact, one of my favorite concepts when you are talking about getting really good at something is called &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;deliberate practice&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>