<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>trainerfly-backstory on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/trainerfly-backstory/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in trainerfly-backstory on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/trainerfly-backstory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 12:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1529&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Paul Cavel is an Energy Arts Senior Instructor based in London. He teaches regular weekly classes there, but he&#39;s also been traveling all over the UK and Europe for years teaching workshops, including annual week-long retreats in Crete. I talked to Paul a little bit about his background in Tai Chi, neigong, and Ba Gua and asked him for some practice advice for a group of students who just completed a series at BTC on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little bit about how you got started studying these arts. Who were some of your first influential teachers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After a motorcycle accident in 1986, I started studying Yang style tai chi to heal my injuries. When the teacher left, the class naturally gravitated towards the Water method neigong practices as taught by my main teacher, Bruce Frantzis. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve been hooked ever since.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1528&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over the last 30 years, Bruce has taught in so many different places and formats. When and how did you first start studying with him?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first encounter with Bruce was in a London seminar on the spiraling energy body. Of course, that material really opened my eyes to what qigong could do! When I subsequently lived with Bruce some years later in 1994-1995, my passion for bagua was ignited in his weekly classes. I got in by the skin of my teeth as one of the last students he let into the class&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Since you&#39;ve studied with Bruce, have you had other influential teachers? Have you studied complementary arts that you bring into your teaching?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve attended the odd seminar with a reputable Chinese master or two, including a couple of months of early morning training in the park with a master in California. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve also attended events hosted by the Tai Chi Union of Great Britain where several teachers offer workshops. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve picked up the odd tidbit here and there from these courses. However, my direction is a product of Bruce&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s mentoring and the desire to follow the tenants of the genuine Water tradition as passed down by him. Bruce is my one and only teacher.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-1537  alignright&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel_SPC&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little bit about your teaching. Do you run regular classes? Workshops? Who are your students?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I teach full-time and offer various teaching formats, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Weekly classes and seminars in Kentish Town, London&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weekend seminars in England and Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weeklong retreats in Greece and Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corporate training and executive coaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private and small group lessons&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have students from all walks of life who practise for a wide variety of reasons. Some are looking for a system to maintain health and wellness while others are professionals who want an edge and/or a means for releasing stress. I also see many Energy Arts instructors who want to prepare for certification trainings or upgrade their practice and understanding of the material.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the three most important points that you would like other instructors to know about regarding your practice or your teaching or your business?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; My practice and my teaching are neigong-based. That is I focus on the strands of neigong that develop the body, chi and mind, and then integrate that material into Circle Walking, bagua, tai chi and meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m based in North London where I offer my full programme. The seminar series and retreats I teach in Europe are designed with a particular focus in mind to help students develop that particular aspect of practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I offer a lot of hands-on personal corrections, partner exercises and component practice sets with a systematic, progressive focus. My aim is to help students solidify their foundation and integrate the deeper aspects of neigong that ultimately intertwine to create the more complex movement forms of bagua and tai chi.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Some of my students have just finished a series on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth, where they learned to open and close the joints of the arms and legs. How should they continue to work on this practice on their own?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have opened up the pulse, the next step is to balance your  system. This is normally done through Circling Hands Qigong, an easy,  repetitive motion that allows the mind to focus on the content rather  that the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through practice of Circling Hands Qigong, the process is simple:  compare the pulse in the joint on the left side to the corresponding  joint on the right side of your body, and make them the same. This is  done by reducing the joint with the larger range to that of the joint  with the smaller range. Go through all the pairs, e.g. hands, feet,  elbows and knees. Next, compare each pair to all other pairs, e.g. hands  to feet, elbows to knees, shoulders to hips, and equalise any  imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reducing your range of motion to the joint with the smallest range, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dramatically soften the pulse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Release the nervous system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deepen the pulse in the joints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link the pulsing of the joints into one unified lattice, thereby amplifying the positive effects of the pulse.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more from Paul on the art of pulsing, check out this two-part series,&amp;Acirc;  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/1469/pulsing-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/1501/pulsing-bagua-zhang/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Posted from Trainerfly: Launching an Online Course</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2011 10:36:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2011/04/11/how-i-launched-my-first-online-course/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this post from the Trainerfly blog&lt;/a&gt;. I talk to teachers and trainers all the time who want move beyond their live events, but the number of steps it takes, and the technology required to make it work seem overwhelming. Hopefully, I&#39;ve made a little dent in that perception!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Feedback from Trainerfly Beta</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 08:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/estimmel/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-633&#34; title=&#34;megaphone&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/02/megaphone.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;megaphone by estimmel&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve gotten &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/&#34;&gt;Trainerfly&lt;/a&gt; out into people&#39;s hands and I&#39;ve been learning some really interesting lessons. I think it was easy for me to get wrapped up in how I&#39;ve evolved it as a tool in my business over the last two years and lose perspective on how other people might be trying to add it into their business from scratch, with none of that prior history.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-632&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Extra Layers&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you integrate a new business tool, you have a question of layers. In other words, if this is how I normally get something done, will the new tool add new layers of work, or remove them? And if it adds more work, is there another benefit that justifies the additional work. I got some strong feedback in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was amazingly clarifying for me to see the places where extra layers were not justified. Really specifically, the product is not strong enough right now to replace one-on-one communication if a trainer is using an email/youtube/spreadsheet system to get information to their clients. Why did I think I could compete with mature products from Google and Microsoft? Hahaha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if the communication issue is about hitting many people at different times with the same basic information, I think I have a winning solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Class, Deconstructed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The biggest thing that has been bugging me in the last 12-18 months on my own personal teaching front is summed up nicely by saying: &#34;teaching is a product that is consumed as it is produced&#34;. A little tear runs down my cheek at the end of every class, because I know that what happened in the last hour is lost forever in the ether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so maybe that&#39;s a little dramatic, but it bothers me that there&#39;s not a better way to preserve the moment, and from a business point of view, earn more money from it. Can you image a furniture maker who crafts single-use chairs? As soon as someone stands up, the chair disappears?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m starting to see a solution to this problem, though. It&#39;s not going to be hooking up 15 different cameras around the school and recording every single thing that happens. Instead, I&#39;m starting the process of extracting key ingredients from class, and transforming them into a touchstones that students can come back to again and again to further their practice outside of that elusive produce-and-consume teaching moment. There&#39;s a lot more to say about this strategy, and I&#39;m really excited about refining those tools. They will look really different than a traditional class -- you have to trade the interactive spontaneity of a good class, for structures that create reproduceable learning and practice moments for students.&amp;Acirc;  I think I know what that means....stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Trainerfly Video Series</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/01/23/new-trainerfly-video-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 21:26:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/01/23/new-trainerfly-video-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know if I&#39;m more excited about the video series, the fact that we&#39;re inches away from the private beta launch, or that I can embed all the videos in one of Viddler&#39;s &#34;vidgets&#34;. Check them out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_widget&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:D27CDB6E-AE6D-11cf-96B8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;320&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.viddler.com/simple_widget/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;wmode&#34; value=&#34;transparent&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;widgeturl=http%3A%2F%2Fvidgets.viddler.com%2Fwidgets%2Fcallback.php%3Fwidget_type%3Dplaylist%26title%3DTrainerfly+Tutorials%26source%3Duser%26user%3DTrainerfly%26tags%3DDemo%26sort%3Duploaded-asc%26max%3D12&amp;amp;autoplay=f&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;320&#34; src=&#34;http://www.viddler.com/simple_widget/&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; name=&#34;viddler_widget&#34; wmode=&#34;transparent&#34; flashvars=&#34;widgeturl=http%3A%2F%2Fvidgets.viddler.com%2Fwidgets%2Fcallback.php%3Fwidget_type%3Dplaylist%26title%3DTrainerfly+Tutorials%26source%3Duser%26user%3DTrainerfly%26tags%3DDemo%26sort%3Duploaded-asc%26max%3D12&amp;amp;autoplay=f&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Pre-Launch in the Works</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/29/trainerfly-pre-launch-in-the-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 14:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/29/trainerfly-pre-launch-in-the-works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-368&#34; title=&#34;Trainerfly Logo&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/LowerFacebook.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;280&#34; height=&#34;90&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; I spent a fair amount of time today migrating, connecting, and updating. Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve been building out a wordpress front-end site for Trainerfly. My brother Sam has come through with some awesome illustration, including the logo and characters for the blog tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a funny debate about the use of flies on the site and got pretty carried away at one point. It started to look like &#34;Planet of the Flies&#34;. Too much! I&#39;m hoping now the use of flies-in-action conveys just how much Trainerfly software can act &#34;like a fly on the wall of every training session&#34; for you and your clients. &lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-medium wp-image-369&#34; title=&#34;teacher&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/teacher-270x300.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;270&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m using the flies in karate uniforms to signify different &#34;belt levels&#34; of site users. When trainers start out using the app, they&#39;ll be focusing on &#34;White Belt&#34; stuff like adding clients, updating program info, and sharing resources. As they get more sophisticated, &#34;Blue Belt&#34; users focus on using Trainerfly to build value for their clients, to enhance their learning experience outside of one-on-one training. Finally, I hope to have a group of &#34;Black Belt&#34; trainers eventually, who will work on building new streams of revenue with Trainerfly, that where impossible with just live training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I explain more about the belt system on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2010/11/21/trainerfly-dojo-belt-levels/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the Trainerfly blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll post more updates on Trainerfly development progress as I go, but if this kind of thing is of interest to you, sign up for the pre-launch email list &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/pricing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you really want to help me out, become a fan of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Trainerfly/164834020218938&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trainerfly on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, or share this post with the FB buttons below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Characters</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/20/trainerfly-characters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 05:18:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/20/trainerfly-characters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out this draft of a character I&#39;m going to feature on the Trainerfly blog (my brother Sam is doing the design work):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-large wp-image-359&#34; title=&#34;master&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/master-971x1024.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;632&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Backstory: The Moodle Project</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/14/trainerfly-backstory-the-moodle-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2010 14:42:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/14/trainerfly-backstory-the-moodle-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post is the second in a series I&#39;m doing on the backstory of how I came to develop a web-based software application called Trainerfly. You can read more about it &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/category/trainerfly/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For about a year after I decided I need a way to manage all my clients&#39; programs, and share information with them privately, I wrestled with finding the right software. I tried private blogs, but at that time it was tons of work to partition information for each client. I tried creating a private social network for all my clients through &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ning.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ning&lt;/a&gt;, with the idea that I would message people with their individual updates and share videos inside the network, but it never quite had the right feel. Finally, short of building something from scratch, I found Moodle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.moodle.org&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-306&#34; title=&#34;moodle-logo&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/moodle-logo.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;46&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moodle stands for Modular Object Oriented Dynamic Learning Environment, in case you thought people just randomly came up with names for websites and programs on the internet! Basically, Moodle is an open-source online classroom software and it had everything I needed, including a huge development community, to get my clients set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of a school structure, you have students, courses, and teachers. What I was able to do was create a unique &#34;course&#34; in which I enrolled every client as a &#34;student&#34; and I was the teacher. The nice thing about Moodle is that teachers can do lots of behind the scenes stuff, like editing courses and sharing resources that follow them around the school and most importantly for my needs, control enrollment. That was the element I was missing before. Now, every client could log in and see their program information, inside a course, but they didn&#39;t have access to anyone else&#39;s information. And, I could share the same info over and over again with different clients, with the click of the mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-350&#34; title=&#34;student screen&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/student-screen2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;732&#34; height=&#34;363&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What you&#39;re looking at above is a screen cap from a typical student program.&amp;Acirc;  After my first session with a new client, I would log in to my Moodle installation on my website and create a new client profile, a new course for them and enroll them in that course. Then, I would write up a recap of what we covered. All together it would take me five minutes to set it up and fill in the details, once the system was set up. Eventually, I was also able to share video of the exercises with them, thanks to an agreement with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zhealth.net&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Z Health&lt;/a&gt; to test this system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After subsequent sessions, I would simply update this program section in their course with new information or new links to video, audio, or other type of files. Some trainers that I set up on this system also began to include interactive pieces, where their clients could write back to them through Moodle. Think of a regular classroom environment, with quizzes and reports and you can image the scope of things Moodle was able to do. In fact, I found it could do too much for what I needed, but more on that below...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was one other huge advantage that I want to point out of having a system like this in place. The typical trainer is juggling 20-30 clients at once throughout their training week. How do they stay organized when everyone has different goals and is working on different material? Well, for me, it became a simple matter of logging in to this system and calling up a particular client&#39;s program -- even if I hadn&#39;t seen them in 3 months, I could pick up right where we left off! Think about the confidence in me and the value they felt when they walked back into the room after a long absence and I could say, &#34;Joe, how&#39;s the right knee doing?&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s part of my program dashboard where I could call up anyone&#39;s program instantly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-large wp-image-309&#34; title=&#34;program screen&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/program-screen-1024x640.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for about a year this was working great with my clients. As I mentioned above, I brought the concept to Z Health and they were interested in sharing this with their whole community of trainers. The next time I went out to Phoenix, I presented what I had been working on to a group of about 30 Z trainers and from there, signed up half a dozen to test the system live with their clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll talk about the interesting things I learned from this &#34;beta test&#34; soon. Eventually, it led me to seek out someone to build brand new web app, from the ground up, based on the concept we proved in Moodle, but ultimately with a more user-friendly environment and scalable infrastructure. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Backstory: The Practice Problem</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 08:05:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure I&#39;m not alone here. Teachers in all disciples, if they need their students to practice to learn what they are teaching, will relate. I don&#39;t know if &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;movement educators&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; have it worse because people tend to think of all movement as &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;working out&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; -- something you go and do, not an art you have to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, one of my favorite concepts when you are talking about getting really good at something is called &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;deliberate practice&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. Geoff Colvin, explains the elements of deliberate practice in &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Talent is Overrated&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2006/10/30/8391794/index.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&#39;s a summary article he wrote on CNNMoney.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to implement deliberate practice strategies has been a major shift in how I train myself and that&#39;s another story entirely. As a professional movement educator, though, I had another problem: I most of my clients for one hour a week. Maybe if I&#39;m lucky we meet in a group class setting for 3 or 4 hours a week. How can I extend a practice model to them that involves hours of practice repetition, constant feedback, goal setting, and ever-evolving mental models of the practice in such a short amount of face-to-face time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to make the deliberate practice model work, I had to decide how to spend the precious little in-person time with my clients and inspire them to cover as many of the other elements as possible outside of our one-on-one time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which would you choose? Endless repetition? Refined feedback? Goal setting? Mental models?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, it turns out to be a blend. They need to lay the foundation between sessions for refinement by getting their reps in. We can talk goal setting any time, but lots of it comes down to an emotional understanding of where they want to be that is finally sharpened face-to-face. There is an initial hump when I start to work with someone where the conceptual framework for training needs to be established, but the mental models evolve based on what they experience through practice and what other resources I can send their way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you can see where I&#39;m heading at this point. In order to make the most of one-on-one time in person, and give my clients the best possible movement education, I needed to separate out the pieces of the whole training pie that could be automated, or at least frozen in time through asynchronous communication tools (haha, fancy term for things like email and blogs!). Later, I&#39;ll explain how I began to sift through what could be leveraged and what needed to be face-to-face, but the problem started to be clearer when I realized I would have to make this distinction: &lt;em&gt;can I share this later or do I need to address it face-to-face.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>