<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>product-launch on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/product-launch/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in product-launch on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/product-launch/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Cycles</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 14:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/31/teaching-cycles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m coming to another big teaching cycle in Trainerfly and I think this short clip of David Heinemeier Hansson speaking at Stanford&#39;s Entrepreneurship Corner is really useful to frame the mindset:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-574&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;single&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;302&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;config=http://ecorner.stanford.edu/embeded_config.xml%3Fmid%3D2361&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://ecorner.stanford.edu/swf/player-ec.swf&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;single&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;302&#34; src=&#34;http://ecorner.stanford.edu/swf/player-ec.swf&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; flashvars=&#34;config=http://ecorner.stanford.edu/embeded_config.xml%3Fmid%3D2361&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the point in the clip above is more about a strategy to take when you look at the &#34;big guys&#34;, but I really feel like the alternating cycles of &#34;spending&#34; and &#34;teaching&#34; are relevant here. We just went through a &#34;spending&#34; period where we were building out the technology behind Trainerfly. That was only possible because we went through a &#34;teaching&#34; period initially, where I learned what problems I wanted to solve with a software application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I&#39;m entering another &#34;teaching&#34; cycle as I share the fruits of the &#34;spending&#34; cycle, a viable software solution, with other peers in movement education. It gets even more interesting if you chart the smaller cycles within each of the major cycles.....hmmmm, where have I encountered that kind of thinking before??&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Trainerfly Video Series</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/23/new-trainerfly-video-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 21:26:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/01/23/new-trainerfly-video-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know if I&#39;m more excited about the video series, the fact that we&#39;re inches away from the private beta launch, or that I can embed all the videos in one of Viddler&#39;s &#34;vidgets&#34;. Check them out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_widget&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:D27CDB6E-AE6D-11cf-96B8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;320&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.viddler.com/simple_widget/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;wmode&#34; value=&#34;transparent&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;widgeturl=http%3A%2F%2Fvidgets.viddler.com%2Fwidgets%2Fcallback.php%3Fwidget_type%3Dplaylist%26title%3DTrainerfly+Tutorials%26source%3Duser%26user%3DTrainerfly%26tags%3DDemo%26sort%3Duploaded-asc%26max%3D12&amp;amp;autoplay=f&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;320&#34; src=&#34;http://www.viddler.com/simple_widget/&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; name=&#34;viddler_widget&#34; wmode=&#34;transparent&#34; flashvars=&#34;widgeturl=http%3A%2F%2Fvidgets.viddler.com%2Fwidgets%2Fcallback.php%3Fwidget_type%3Dplaylist%26title%3DTrainerfly+Tutorials%26source%3Duser%26user%3DTrainerfly%26tags%3DDemo%26sort%3Duploaded-asc%26max%3D12&amp;amp;autoplay=f&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Pre-Launch in the Works</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/29/trainerfly-pre-launch-in-the-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 14:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/29/trainerfly-pre-launch-in-the-works/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-368&#34; title=&#34;Trainerfly Logo&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2010/11/LowerFacebook.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;280&#34; height=&#34;90&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; I spent a fair amount of time today migrating, connecting, and updating. Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve been building out a wordpress front-end site for Trainerfly. My brother Sam has come through with some awesome illustration, including the logo and characters for the blog tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a funny debate about the use of flies on the site and got pretty carried away at one point. It started to look like &#34;Planet of the Flies&#34;. Too much! I&#39;m hoping now the use of flies-in-action conveys just how much Trainerfly software can act &#34;like a fly on the wall of every training session&#34; for you and your clients. &lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-medium wp-image-369&#34; title=&#34;teacher&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2010/11/teacher-270x300.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;270&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m using the flies in karate uniforms to signify different &#34;belt levels&#34; of site users. When trainers start out using the app, they&#39;ll be focusing on &#34;White Belt&#34; stuff like adding clients, updating program info, and sharing resources. As they get more sophisticated, &#34;Blue Belt&#34; users focus on using Trainerfly to build value for their clients, to enhance their learning experience outside of one-on-one training. Finally, I hope to have a group of &#34;Black Belt&#34; trainers eventually, who will work on building new streams of revenue with Trainerfly, that where impossible with just live training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I explain more about the belt system on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2010/11/21/trainerfly-dojo-belt-levels/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the Trainerfly blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll post more updates on Trainerfly development progress as I go, but if this kind of thing is of interest to you, sign up for the pre-launch email list &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/pricing/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you really want to help me out, become a fan of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Trainerfly/164834020218938&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trainerfly on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, or share this post with the FB buttons below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ba Gua Program Product Launch</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/11/ba-gua-program-product-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 06:46:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/11/ba-gua-program-product-launch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been working with the team at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Energy Arts&lt;/a&gt; on various projects, but mainly in the capacity as a community coordinator. Currently, my focus is on helping them get a new community discussion forum off the ground, but I also had the chance to participate in the launch of their new Ba Gua Mastery Program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ba Gua Mastery Program is a home-study program with information on circle-walking for meditation and martial arts. They&#39;ve drawn from a live instructor training Bruce taught in 2009, and turned out CDs, DVDs, print manuals...the whole works! It&#39;s been a monumental effort and in the future I&#39;ll be discussing how we&#39;re going to blend live teaching with all these materials at BTC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now though, I want to talk about their launch strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks, they&#39;ve been building interest by sending out related content without trying to sell the program directly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-290&#34; title=&#34;offer&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2010/11/offer.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;478&#34; height=&#34;589&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a screen capture from one of the launch pages on their website.&amp;Acirc;  They&#39;ve added to it as they released new content, so I&#39;ve got back and highlighted what they put out in what order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first piece was a video of Bruce talking about his different Ba Gua teachers in China. On the video page, they included a &#34;pre-launch notification&#34; email list sign-up. In a follow-up email, they reported that over 2000 people opted-in to that list. Not bad, considering that all of the launch copy says they&#39;ll only be selling 250 copies of the program!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second piece was an interview I conducted with Bruce and Richard Taubinger, who is overseeing the launch. We discussed more of the details of the practice itself and why people should be interested in ba gua as an art. I&#39;m not sure about email sign-ups or interest in the interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the most direct approach, they gave away some sample material from the product itself, just before the launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure how long this page will be up for, but here is the launch page itself: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/bagua-mastery-program-launch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/bagua-mastery-program-launch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I really like how they gradually, but persistently built interest in the launch, drawing from a list they&#39;ve spent considerable time growing and finally putting just enough urgency around buying (only 250 copies!) that they will hopefully convince the right people to act on it. We&#39;ll see!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>