<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>dr.-mark-cheng on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/dr.-mark-cheng/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in dr.-mark-cheng on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/dr.-mark-cheng/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How Dr. Mark Cheng is Bringing Tai Chi to the Fitness Community, Part 2</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/25/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2012 08:11:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/25/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-2/</guid>
      <description>In part 1 of this interview, we talked to Dr. Mark Cheng about how his background as an acupuncturist, martial artist, strength coach and PhD in Chinese Medicine has shaped his point of view about the broader subject of fitness and wellness.
Now he&#39;s going to explain his thinking behind developing a project, called Tai Cheng, which aims to introduce Tai Chi to a much larger fitness audience.

Here is Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Dr. Mark Cheng is Bringing Tai Chi to the Fitness Community, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/18/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2012 09:35:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/18/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Dr. Mark Cheng compares learning Tai Chi to studying a well-cut diamond, and as you&#39;ll see in the following conversation, his background as an acupuncturist, martial artist, strength coach and PhD in Chinese Medicine actually allows him to look at the broader subject of fitness and wellness in the same multi-faceted way. With the depth and range he brings to teaching movement, it&#39;s no wonder that he&#39;s leading the way to introducing Tai Chi to a much larger fitness audience and in the process, asking all Tai Chi people to step back and take a fresh look at their art.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>