<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>z-health on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/z-health/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in z-health on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/z-health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Arm Swing And The Force Transmission Problem</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 08:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</guid>
      <description>One of your practice goals should be to be able to make sense of other people&#39;s movement patterns. Learning how to watch someone move, and see what&#39;s going on, is going to give you really valuable information that you can then apply to your own practice.
In the following video clip, I demonstrate two different gait patterns, with different arm swings. If you can start to see how the arm swing differs between the two, you&#39;ll start to gain some valuable insight into how to assess and correct your own movement imbalances.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Absolutely Anything in 2012</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 09:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>At this time of year, you hear a lot about New Year&#39;s resolutions.
This year, I was happy to see a lot of people saying &#34;New Year&#39;s resolutions don&#39;t work.&#34; We all know that&#39;s true from personal experience, but these folks were referencing a growing understanding about how learning and skill-building take place. Most of what we now know about how the nervous system works flies in the face of changing through the strength of your willpower alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2011 08:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</guid>
      <description>Frozen shoulder is one of those terms that people accept with resignation and it seems like a plausible explanation...until you start to poke around in your own nervous system.
If you&#39;ve ever been told you have a frozen shoulder, I urge you to look a little bit beyond the (overly) simple mechanical explanation.
Obviously, I&#39;m not diagnosing your shoulder from a YouTube video, but I just want you to ask a few more questions and try these two experiments:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Z Health Exercises for Stiff Joints in the Morning</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2011 08:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</guid>
      <description>In just ten minutes of head-to-toe movement, you can get rid of stiff joints in the morning. What&#39;s the secret? There isn&#39;t one really...you just have to move every single joint. Z Health exercises for joint mobility give you an easy template to use to get this done, though.
Check out this example of head-to-toe joint mobility: 

The metronome-like quality of the music got me. Sorry! You know why I like metronomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Doctor, A Runner, and A Meditator Walk into A Bar...</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 10:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</guid>
      <description>And they&#39;re all in pain!
When it comes to the aches and pains of moving around, you might be in pain from your day job, your vigorous exercise routine, or even a mindfulness practice that doesn&#39;t involve any movement. Ever wonder why? 
The reason is exactly the same in each case: in your pre-conscious mind, you are basically trying to outsource your own movement patterns, from a body part that should be doing the job, to one that&#39;s willing to, even though it isn&#39;t designed for that job!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frozen Hips Are Too Common, But Avoidable</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/05/12/frozen-hips-are-too-common-but-avoidable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2011 08:35:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/05/12/frozen-hips-are-too-common-but-avoidable/</guid>
      <description>Update: We&#39;ve just released a new video-based course that shows you how to loosen up your hips and become stronger and more flexible!
[CSSBUTTON target=&#34;/fix-your-frozen-hips/&#34; color=&#34;66ff33&#34;]Check It Out[/CSSBUTTON]
Original Post:
I know the weather is getting warmer, but as I look around, all I see are frozen hips. We just aren&#39;t a squatting culture. We sit in chair, couches, cars. Look around the room you are in right now and see how all the furniture is designed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 3</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 10:19:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</guid>
      <description>So far in this series we&#39;ve been talking about adapting your teaching style and the structure of your teaching business to fit the needs of your students. Now I want to look at a trait that all of the best teachers I&#39;ve studied with share, which is a work capacity they can turn on like a fire hose. If your work capacity only comes out like water from a dripping faucet, you won&#39;t be able to be &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>