<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>z-health on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/z-health/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in z-health on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/z-health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Arm Swing And The Force Transmission Problem</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 08:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of your practice goals should be to be able to make sense of other people&#39;s movement patterns. Learning how to watch someone move, and see what&#39;s going on, is going to give you really valuable information that you can then apply to your own practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following video clip, I demonstrate two different gait patterns, with different arm swings. If you can start to see how the arm swing differs between the two, you&#39;ll start to gain some valuable insight into how to assess and correct your own movement imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the clip and then we&#39;ll look at some of the implications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3165&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said at the beginning of the clip, your body adapts to postural changes instantaneously to find the most efficient way of dissipating force that comes into your skeletal structure. This principle was first explained to me by Dr. Eric Cobb, creator of &lt;a href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13500&#34;&gt;Z Health Performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you can see excessive (or deficient) movement in someone&#39;s whole-body pattern, you can pretty reliably draw the conclusion that they need some isolated movement tune-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But, the site of the abnormal movement is not the problem area.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always remember that principle. Was there something wrong with my left arm in the video clip? No, it started swinging more because the right arm was restricted. We changed the right arm and created excessive swing in the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there is a lot more to be said for how you begin to see the connections and determine what needs to move more or less to make the whole body move more efficiently. For now, though, I want you to try a little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Field Test Your Ability to See&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a title=&#34;APR 092 by chiolachic, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/chio/2432915922/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3091/2432915922_d36e45be2a_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;APR 092&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Brookline Tai Chi is located at mile 23 of the Boston Marathon. People run up and down Beacon Street all day long. As we were working on our ability to see these patterns, a friend and I would sit on the front steps of Brookline Tai Chi to watch runners and walkers come and go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a good spot with lots of running traffic and look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differences in swing between left and right arms from behind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How high each foot comes up behind the body -- can you see the sole of the shoe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Torso rotation -- is it more pronounced to one side?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excessive head movement in any particular direction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Stirring&#34; with the arm -- making a circle out to the side instead of coming straight back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Loops&#34; in the lower leg -- circles instead of straight up and down movement&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The challenge with seeing these patterns is that we very easily integrate this information and experience is as &#34;someone running.&#34; We don&#39;t stop to consciously parse the different parts of their movement. For the most part, it&#39;s a good thing that we take in chunks of information, instead of individual pieces. Think of how daunting it would be to have to record each data point and consciously put it together. You&#39;d never make it down the street!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, if you want to really hone your ability to see, correct, and improve movement patterns, you have to train to break the patterns back down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Absolutely Anything in 2012</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 09:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Chess at Starbucks by radioflyer007, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/radioflyer007/4677003347/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1304/4677003347_3bcb440632.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chess at Starbucks&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;205&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;At this time of year, you hear a lot about New Year&#39;s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I was happy to see a lot of people saying &#34;New Year&#39;s resolutions don&#39;t work.&#34; We all know that&#39;s true from personal experience, but these folks were referencing a growing understanding about how learning and skill-building take place. Most of what we now know about how the nervous system works flies in the face of changing through the strength of your willpower alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I urge you to leave that mindset behind in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you should think about any changes, anything you want to learn, as slowing building a skill, with small steps you can practice, building like a snowball, until you&#39;re doing great new things without trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s how that works.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3160&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deliberate Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You often hear people say, &#34;practice makes perfect&#34;, but the reality is a little more complicated. One retort is &#34;practice makes permanent&#34;, which speaks to the way that your nervous system ingrains what you do over and over so that it becomes close to automatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you actually want to learn something new this year, you need get smart about how you build your new skills. The model that captures this the clearest is the deliberate practice model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deliberate practice has four components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need a framework for understanding what to practice -- this is where seeking out guidance from someone who has mastered that skill or taught others to do so is critical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to practice a very specific skill because you need a high degree of focus -- trying to juggle two or three new things at a time won&#39;t work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need immediate feedback on your practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to practice over and over and over again, a lot.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The irony for most of us is that we want to get better at something, so we just go out and do it. It&#39;s like trying to drive somewhere new without a map. You&#39;ll base your decisions, turn-by-turn, on old information about places you&#39;ve been before, which may work pretty well, but clearly won&#39;t get you there with the same directness as having a roadmap to guide you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, step one of any new deliberate practice endeavor that you seek out is to find the right map. Get good guidance, regular feedback, and keep practicing, biting off a little at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other thing you need to worry about, once you have the deliberate practice cycle down, is staying in a healthy &#34;learning zone&#34; as you take on new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recognizing Fight-or-Flight&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A natural part of trying to master any new skill is working beyond your current capacity. The problem is that pushing yourself too far into new territory will be counter-productive. When you exceed your limites, your body initiates the fight-or-flight response and you will no longer engage in productive learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the core Z Health training principles is learning to identify the onset of the stress response in any activity. When you recognize the signs of fight-or-flight, you learn to dial back your training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you may find:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your heart rate speeds up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your breathing gets heavy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your face becomes flushed or pale or alternates between them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your mouth dries up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You move toward the fetal position in subtle ways -- your shoulders hike up, your facial muscles contract, you draw your arms in to protect your body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You stop hearing what&#39;s going on around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get &#34;tunnel vision&#34; and lose your peripheral field.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you experience these things, or more likely, when someone points out to you that they are happening or you realize it in hindsight, you know you&#39;ve exceeded your capacity to integrate new information in that moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the poise and relaxation that comes through smart, modulated training in this boxing clip. Obviously, boxing can be a brutal sport, but watch the way that this training is structured, to stretch him in different ways, testing his visual skills, playing with his threat level and capacity to integrated movement information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that the training is done correctly because of how graceful and relaxed he is able to be under this kind of pressure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/2y5jB0uZOrM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/2y5jB0uZOrM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you work through this process, probably without an army of coaches, camera crews, and fans, you&#39;ll have to look back on the experience and break down how things came together and what you could do to decrease the threat level next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one of my favorite examples of this is a college football coach who plays crowd noise over the loudspeaker during practice sessions. He wants his players to simulate game conditions as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the gradual increase in game-like threat levels as they learn new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the coach introduces a new play in the locker room. He maps it out for the players and they get the idea. Next, they head to the field without pads on and with no defense trying to stop them. Little by little, the coach can introduce new elements that demand concentration, and most importantly from our point of view, integration of new information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can control a situation so that you can selectively increase the amount of information -- visual, auditory, spatial, or physical -- that you need to integrate to master a skill, then you will be able to learn anything in a smooth, steady manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&#39;s it going to be in 2012?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2011 08:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frozen shoulder is one of those terms that people accept with resignation and it seems like a plausible explanation...until you start to poke around in your own nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve ever been told you have a frozen shoulder, I urge you to look a little bit beyond the (overly) simple mechanical explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I&#39;m not diagnosing your shoulder from a YouTube video, but I just want you to ask a few more questions and try these two experiments:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2746&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do about a Frozen Shoulder&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you tried the experiments in the video and saw some changes in your shoulder movement, your best bet is to find someone who can assess your movement on a global (whole-body) level. This person, &lt;a title=&#34;Find a Z Health Trainer near you&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=1347&#34;&gt;like a certified Z Health instructor&lt;/a&gt;, for example, will be able to see what body parts are not moving when they should be and which ones are when they shouldn&#39;t be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can alleviate a lot of &#34;frozen&#34; anything in the body with this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&#39;t find an instructor near you, the next best thing is to begin a head-to-toe, full-body mobility program, &lt;strong&gt;focusing on everything else except your frozen shoulder &lt;/strong&gt;(&lt;a title=&#34;Z Health R-Phase Manual and DVD&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13446&#34;&gt;the Z Health R-Phase series is the best way to go about this&lt;/a&gt;). The number one rule you need to follow is &#34;never move into pain.&#34; Instead, you will re-educate your body and all its moving pieces, taking the burden off the parts that are already working too hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairly quickly (like, within a few good training sessions), you will see a change in how you move, 90% of the time. If you keep it up, you&#39;ll prevent further aggravation along these lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few more ideas if you&#39;re looking for other ways to &lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;GET MOVING&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Z Health Exercises for Stiff Joints in the Morning</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2011 08:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In just ten minutes of head-to-toe movement, you can get rid of stiff joints in the morning. What&#39;s the secret? There isn&#39;t one really...you just have to move every single joint. Z Health exercises for joint mobility give you an easy template to use to get this done, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this example of head-to-toe joint mobility: &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2581&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jCUM8kZ-etY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jCUM8kZ-etY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The metronome-like quality of the music got me. Sorry! You know why I like &lt;a title=&#34;Metronome Mobility&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/14/metronome-mobility/&#34;&gt;metronomes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you do a mobility flow like this, with the goal of loosening up your stiff joints, especially first thing in the morning, you want to follow these movement principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Movement Rules for Getting Rid of Stiff Joints in the Morning:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move Every Joint with Precision&lt;/strong&gt;: In the video above, I started with the fingers and worked back toward the spine, then down through the lower body. Each Z Health exercise is designed to target a specific joint. As much as possible, the rest of the body remains still while you isolate an individual joint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build Towards Flow:&amp;Acirc;  &lt;/strong&gt;When you&#39;re mastering the movement of any one joint, you&#39;ll start with straight-line movement, then do circles, and then progress to more flowing figure-8&#39;s. It&#39;s important to work in that order, because the linear movement almost always reveals places where you haven&#39;t developed good conscious control. You never find these places if you skip to figure-8&#39;s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never Move Into Pain: &lt;/strong&gt;Especially if you feel stiff in the morning, you might confuse &#34;waking up&#34; with &#34;being in pain.&#34; Never take yourself into painful ranges of motion. Instead, as you loosen up, your range of motion will increase. It&#39;s not unusual to notice a difference between the first and the third repetition in this regard. Remember: &lt;em&gt;being in pain will not alleviate your stiff joints&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With a morning mobility warm-up like this, you&#39;ll find yourself looser,&amp;Acirc;  more tuned-in to your body and ready to get moving. I often use the discipline of moving each body part head-to-toe as a way to trick myself into practicing more in-depth work when I&#39;m not really in the right frame of mind. Have you ever done that? Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Doctor, A Runner, and A Meditator Walk into A Bar...</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 10:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And they&#39;re all in pain!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the aches and pains of moving around, you might be in pain from your day job, your vigorous exercise routine, or even a mindfulness practice that doesn&#39;t involve any movement. Ever wonder why? &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2285&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is exactly the same in each case: in your pre-conscious mind, you are basically trying to outsource your own movement patterns, from a body part that should be doing the job, to one that&#39;s willing to, even though it isn&#39;t designed for that job!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that doesn&#39;t completely make sense, watch this video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/nFvmbc5At-U?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/nFvmbc5At-U?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those aches and pains might be caused by one big inappropriate act of outsourcing. If you think that&#39;s what&#39;s going on, you should definitely check out the Joint Mobility tips over on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;Get Moving&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frozen Hips Are Too Common, But Avoidable</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/12/frozen-hips-are-too-common-but-avoidable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2011 08:35:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/12/frozen-hips-are-too-common-but-avoidable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; We&#39;ve just released a new video-based course that shows you how to loosen up your hips and become stronger and more flexible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[CSSBUTTON target=&#34;/fix-your-frozen-hips/&#34; color=&#34;66ff33&#34;]Check It Out[/CSSBUTTON]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original Post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the weather is getting warmer, but as I look around, all I see are frozen hips. We just aren&#39;t a squatting culture. We sit in chair, couches, cars. Look around the room you are in right now and see how all the furniture is designed. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1381&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything i&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1672&#34; title=&#34;Lower Back Pain&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/07/shutterstock_2793192-199x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;199&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;s likely at an altitude that encourages sitting, right? Well the problem with that is if you sit all the time, you are really under-utilizing the movement of the ball and socket joint in your hips. When the hip joint freezes up, your body starts to treat the thigh and the pelvis as a unit. If they move as a unit, instead of as a ball and socket articulation, your knee joint or your spine has to compensate. What happens when your spine starts acting like a ball and socket joint? It gets twisted, contorted and jammed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is often a major reason people experience lower back pain. Lower back pain can be a frustrating experience whose source may be hard to pin down and whose remedy may seem elusive. But, if you start to understand pain a little differently and work with some core tai chi concepts, you can start to unravel your lower back pain. &lt;a title=&#34;How to Treat Lower Back Pain&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/06/how-to-treat-lower-back-pain/&#34;&gt;Read more about treating lower back pain here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Avoid Frozen Hips in the First Place&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to avoid frozen hips, here are some really simple mobility exercises you can do to remind your body to use the ball and socket action: &lt;a title=&#34;Fix Your Frozen Hips&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/fix-your-frozen-hips/&#34;&gt;Hip Mobility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 3</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 10:19:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/stephenagregory/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Dripping Faucet&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.static.flickr.com/69/165377377_6e9eabae34_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image courtesy of StephenAGregory&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;So far in this series we&#39;ve been talking about adapting &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;your teaching style&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the structure of your teaching business&lt;/a&gt; to fit the needs of your students. Now I want to look at a trait that all of the best teachers I&#39;ve studied with share, which is a work capacity they can turn on like a fire hose. If your work capacity only comes out like water from a dripping faucet, you won&#39;t be able to be &#34;big enough&#34; to encompass all of your students and their varying needs.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-894&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Work Ethic Isn&#39;t Work Capacity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first distinction I want to make here is between work ethic and work capacity. It&#39;s the difference between fire and water. Work ethic is a spark, the fire, that drives some of these teachers to be on the road 30 weeks a year, or fly half way around the world to learn from obscure masters. It&#39;s the drive that makes 14 hour days, 6 days seem like a worthwhile pursuit. But ultimately, it&#39;s not what makes these things possible. The spark initiates these crazy journeys, but along the way, work capacity gets built up. Work capacity is more like a habit, and when these guys get up in the morning to teach, it&#39;s like they turn on a faucet and get a steady stream of water to draw from all day long.  Again and again I watch my teaching mentors lead 5-8 hour workshops, continue teaching while every else takes a break for lunch, and then have 2-3 hours of meetings at the end of the day. Knowing them, there was probably a hour of personal practice going on before the teaching day began. So what is it that allows them to go for 12 or 14 hours when most of their students are worn out from the 5 hours of training in the middle?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Logging the Hours, Deliberately&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To say that they are used to teaching is a too simplistic. Yes, step one is to log the teaching hours. Any skill requires that you put in time. There are a couple more dimensions to building your work capacity and in this case we&#39;ll look at teaching for examples of what they are. I&#39;ve written about Geoff Colvin&#39;s deliberate practice model before &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, when I explained part of my motivation for building Trainerfly. Colvin outlines essential elements for getting better at any skill through practice.  When I look at my teaching mentors, they all follow this deliberate practice model in unique ways. Not only have they logged serious teaching hours, but they&#39;ve run the &#34;teaching chunks&#34; experiment, where you create feedback loops and reproduceable teaching moments that allow you to build a student base and your own work capacity simultaneously. Let&#39;s break their down approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bruce Frantzis&#39; Three City Model&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/bruces-frantzis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bruce&lt;/a&gt; has a prolific teaching record, spanning decades and many different format, from one-on-one lessons to workshops packed with 200 students, I think one of the most interesting models he&#39;s taught in is what I&#39;ll call the Three City Model. He did this in the Bay Area in the 1990&#39;s and in New Mexico before that. Some of his most successful certified instructors have also replicated this model. The basic strategy is to offer regular weekly classes in three locations that are near each other, but spread out. The distance criteria are that the locations are in distinct markets, but they are close enough to each other that really dedicated students could travel to any of the three sites to study more than once a week if they wanted. In the Bay Area, this was Berkeley, San Francisco, and Marin County. I&#39;ve contemplated this model in the Boston area, with sites in Cambridge, Boston, and Brookline, for example.  The geographic benefit is striking a balance between accessing a larger potential student base and catering to hard core students simultaneously. There is a financial benefit here too. You can weather the inevitable ups and downs in attendance at one site, because you have the other two.&amp;Acirc;  The benefit for the teacher, though, is that you can experiment with what you teach and how you present it. Separate sites give you the chance to have a more controlled experiment than if you just decided to try a new approach each week at a single site. You can watch two groups evolved over six months or a year and see if a better way to teach emerges on a lot of different levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dr. Eric Cobb, The Constant Presenter&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Whenever I attend a Z Health training, I&#39;m always impressed with the way &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zhealth.net/about-z-health&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Cobb&lt;/a&gt; shifts gears between group teaching and working one-on-one with clients before the seminar begins, during the breaks, and often at the end of the day. He does it as effortlessly as turning up the water pressure on a faucet. The flow is on from the moment he enters the room, cranked up for the group, then down to just the right volume for someone he&#39;s never worked with before and then back up for everyone at once.  I know the he spent years in clinical practice before he started teaching Z Health publicly, and you can see the fine-tuned empathy that comes from years of working one-on-one. There is also something very particular about his rapport with a group that feels like it&#39;s built on all the one-on-one relationships in the room.  When you look at his current teaching schedule, you see over 20-30 events a year, often in the same 3-4 topics. Some of these groups are only 10-12 people and some are capped at 50 attendees. He&#39;s also presented the core concepts of Z Health at professional gatherings, conferences and through the lens of group coaching. Once again, this is the deliberate practice model in action: take the same key concepts and present them in as many different venues as possible -- individual, small group, big group, written, recorded on video.  By teaching anywhere and to everyone, two very interesting things happen. The first is you hone your message and make it scalable (i.e. you know it so well, you know how to present just the right amount of it, from the right perspective, to the right people). The second is sort of a fortunate by-product and that is that you gradually recruit people who also believe in your message. I call that a by-product because most people assume they deserve to have a massive, faithful following as soon as they have an idea in their heads. The message from all of these teachers is exactly the opposite: if you get a big enough fire hose going for long enough, the faithful will follow. Lots of people have ideas. Untested, unhoned ideas are worthless. When you see Dr. Cobb tirelessly flying around the country to successfully build a business and nonchalantly acknowledging that he would likely keep that up for another 5 years to keep on building, you realize that building work capacity is the secret ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bill Ryan&#39;s Healing/Teaching Blend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the traits that all three of these teachers have in common is that they are all gifted hands-on healers. I can attest to this from being under their hands personally, but it was also a key tool they used for developing their businesses early on and growing a dedicated following of students. I&#39;m not sure anyone has blended the two with the intensity Bill Ryan did while he was building up Brookline Tai Chi in the 1990&#39;s, though.  On top of founding, running, and teaching daily at Brookline Tai Chi, Bill relied on private lessons and bodywork to keep the school running and cultivate a core of students at a punishing rate. When I trained with him to take over the operations of the school, he was in a quieter mode, but he would still be there from 10am-10pm almost every day. I&#39;m not sure I ever even saw him stop and eat in those 12 hours bursts...and this was when he was transitioning out. The bigger point here is not about keeping crazy work hours. The point is that by working intensely one-on-one and transitioning to group classes, the different skills each teaching scenario require begin to blend, and that&#39;s a good thing.  When Bill was training me to teach tai chi, we would practice how to give form corrections as hands-on adjustments. We would each start on opposite sides of the room and Bill would say &#34;I&#39;ll meet you in the middle.&#34; By the time I was fumbling through the second or third student, Bill would show up next to me, having corrected 9 or 10. He developed fast eyes and fast hands that could make meaningful corrections, largely due to the number of hours doing private bodywork. While I wasn&#39;t a trained bodyworker, he encouraged me to do as many private lessons as I could. He swore by them as a way to hone your teaching, just because you had more space and time to play with adjustments and get immediate feedback from students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Create Deliberate Practice Moments&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What I&#39;ve learned from these guys is that you create the opportunities to hone your teaching. I don&#39;t see where they are today and think &#34;I want to be up on stage teaching 150 people&#34;. I think about their process and how I can create the teaching moments to steadily grow my capacity.  Bruce likes to talk about the &#34;20 year overnight success&#34; when he&#39;s talking about learning tai chi, but as a teacher who now attracts hundreds of students to a single event, he&#39;s a model for this same approach in teaching. He often points out how this message doesn&#39;t really come across in our culture, unless you really look for it. He&#39;ll talk about a sports movie, with a little kid throwing the ball around in his backyard, who by the next scene is transformed into the World Series-winning major league pitcher. What&#39;s the message there? Hang on to a distant dream and it will magically happen? That&#39;s why I initially wanted to make the decision between work ethic and work capactiy.  The ethic, the idea, the spark -- that&#39;s important and necessary, but it&#39;s the inspiration. Each of these teachers has taken their unique inspiration or aspiration and slowly, over time, developed the capacity to steadily build toward that image. You need a slow, steady fuel to make that journey, more like a flowing river than a short burst of flame.&amp;Acirc;  So take any opportunity you can get to deliberately develop your work capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>