<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi-mastery-program on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi-mastery-program/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi-mastery-program on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/tai-chi-mastery-program/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dust Off Your Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/12/06/dust-off-your-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2013 08:59:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/12/06/dust-off-your-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>It looks like Energy Arts is releasing another set of The Tai Chi Mastery Program. This is a short message to those of you who have the program sitting on your bookshelf, collecting dust, or still pristinely packaged: Let&#39;s open it up and get to work!
Now, if you&#39;re not familiar with this program, take a look at this:
That&#39;s a lot of DVDs!
What&#39;s Inside The Tai Chi Mastery Program?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</guid>
      <description>After teaching thousands of people of all ages and physical abilities over the last eight years, it is clear to me that there is one technique in Tai Chi that is more powerful than all others.
My main teacher, Bruce Frantzis, introduced me to this technique and taught me how to use all its variations, under different conditions. He has encouraged all his instructors to pass along this technique because it is practically a lost art.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Eight Energies of Tai Chi and the Physical Attributes of Roll Back</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 13:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</guid>
      <description>As part of the Tai Chi Mastery Program, Bruce Frantzis recently published a report called &#34;The Eight Principles of Tai Chi Chuan.&#34; The report is full of detail about stages of training 8 different energies of Tai Chi, laid out in clear and straightforward language.
But I always have a problem with writing like this....
On the one hand, it is invaluable for anyone who wants to understand the bigger context of their Tai Chi practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Calm Your Mind Through Movement</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 08:45:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</guid>
      <description>Movement can be a powerful tool for creating a calm mind, but only when you follow some very specific rules.
Tai Chi was designed with these specific movement rules because the goal is to take you from tense to relaxed and from relaxed to vital and strong.
When my Tai Chi teacher, Bruce Frantzis explains the learning progression for Tai Chi, he makes it clear that when your primary focus is on the mind, and your goal is to calm your mind, you must follow this progression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Tai Chi Is Like Listening To Your Favorite Song</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/08/20/good-tai-chi-is-like-listening-to-your-favorite-song/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2012 11:16:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/08/20/good-tai-chi-is-like-listening-to-your-favorite-song/</guid>
      <description>When you really find the groove with your Tai Chi practice, it&#39;s like listening to a piece of music.
The rhythms, riffs, and notes phase in and out, sometimes blending, and sometimes really standing out on their own, and even though there&#39;s a lot going on, you can soak it all in at once.
Can you practice Tai Chi the same way?
This isn&#39;t just an analogy, there&#39;s a major lesson buried in here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 08:23:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>From the outside, standing qigong can look calm, peaceful and meditative.
On the inside, if you don&#39;t ask yourself these 3 essential questions, standing can be grueling. Your muscles ache, you tremble and sweat, and in burning discomfort you strain to see how much longer you must endure.
It doesn&#39;t have to be torture, though, if you adopt the right mindset as you practice.

Over the years, I have learned many different standing qigong techniques from my teacher Bruce Frantzis, but when I practice what he&#39;s taught about mindset and attitude in standing qigong, I&#39;ve had some of my biggest breakthroughs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaxing Your Eyes in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/06/04/relaxing-your-eyes-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2012 13:57:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/06/04/relaxing-your-eyes-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>The eyes are the gateway to your nervous system.
This is a theme that my teacher Bruce Frantzis weaves into many different Tai Chi and qigong teachings that he gives.
Relaxing the nervous system is one of the central goals of Tai Chi practice. With a relaxed nervous system you are more aware of your reactions, thoughts, emotions, and really, your entire internal environment.
One of the best ways to begin to tune into the state of your nervous system is by learning to feel your eyes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming a Giant Rooted Spring in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/05/14/becoming-a-giant-rooted-spring-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 09:22:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/05/14/becoming-a-giant-rooted-spring-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>When you relax into the turning of the waist and feel how it connects to the legs, you begin a process of rooting while moving that creates a dynamic and springy stability. Kind of a paradox, right?
You feel like a giant spring, anchored to the floor even though you&#39;re moving around, that is constantly being wound up and then released.
The key to cultivating this connection is how you relax through your turning, so let&#39;s start off by getting clear on what we mean when we say relaxation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Intensive 9 Months Later</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/04/04/tai-chi-intensive-9-months-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 06:54:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/04/04/tai-chi-intensive-9-months-later/</guid>
      <description>When you spend a month training Tai Chi 10-12 hours a day, what happens when you go home? What does it feel like several months later when your life has returned to normal? Is it a let down? Do you need to be inspired again to continue your training?
What have you continued to discover about your practice? How has the intensive training infused your teaching?
I sat down with several Energy Arts Tai Chi instructors to discuss these issues for Episode 3 of Qigong Radio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Push Hands and The Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 07:19:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re hosting Bruce Frantzis for a Push Hands Intensive this week at Brookline Tai Chi. The training is being filmed and it will become the Push Hands module of the Tai Chi Mastery Program, due out later this year.
Here are my thoughts so far on how the Push Hands component fits in with what we did this past summer in Brighton:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What did we do all day in Brighton?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/21/what-did-we-do-all-day-in-brighton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2011 10:18:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/21/what-did-we-do-all-day-in-brighton/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s a little peek into our daily training routine in Brighton. You can see there was lots of partner work, holding postures and form practice. Of course, it was very serious the whole time! Thanks to Aimo for the photos. Click here for all the photos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Form Training Final Update</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 12:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m heading home to Boston tomorrow, but I&#39;ve already begun looking through my notes and thinking about what I will personally practice and what I&#39;ll be able to share with my students in classes this coming year. Here are some of my initial thoughts:

How Material is Woven together over a Month:
 Day to day we&#39;re looking at really small specific pieces but now going back through my notes, I can start to see different threads that run throughout the duration of the month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update from the Beach</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>Week 3 wraps up and testing is right around the corner. What was Bruce&#39;s big message as we prepare for testing? Work your ass off and cram all night for the big test? Not quite. You might be surprised. Check it out:

A Lesson about Integration:
The biggest thing that Bruce is emphasizing in the last couple days of class is that with this stage of the training, a month long training, you need integration time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 of the Short Form Instructor Training</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 09:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s my Week 2 update. Some big milestones this week: group 1 finished the form and group 2 has been languishing in the purgatory that is holding static postures. Check it out:

Inner Form vs. Outer Form
 In the two groups, we&#39;re doing very different things. The group one just finished the form this week. So on Thursday after they finished it, we came in Friday, and it was a really interesting dividing line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am Learning at the Wu Tai Chi Instructor Training</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 01:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re a week into the Wu Tai Chi short form instructor training in Brighton, UK, with Lineage Holder Bruce Frantzis. So far we&#39;ve been completely rebuilding our forms, working on Tai Chi leg power, and exploring the meditative aspects of the art. Check it out:

On Rebuilding Your Form:
It&#39;s crazy when you come at these things, you&#39;re completely rebuilding your Tai Chi form. We&#39;re about two-thirds of the way through the form and it feels so different.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>