<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi-mastery-program on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/tai-chi-mastery-program/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi-mastery-program on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/tai-chi-mastery-program/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dust Off Your Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/12/06/dust-off-your-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2013 08:59:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/12/06/dust-off-your-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It looks like Energy Arts is releasing another set of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/tai-chi-mastery-program#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=82cf549a&#34;&gt;The Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;. This is a short message to those of you who have the program sitting on your bookshelf, collecting dust, or still pristinely packaged: &lt;strong&gt;Let&#39;s open it up and get to work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Now, if you&#39;re not familiar with this program, take a look at this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter  wp-image-4332&#34; alt=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#39; Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/10/Tai-Chi-Mastery-Program.png&#34; width=&#34;576&#34; height=&#34;565&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;That&#39;s a lot of DVDs!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&#39;s Inside The Tai Chi Mastery Program?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It all started back in 2011 when we spent a month in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011/&#34;&gt;England training the Wu Style Short Form with Bruce&lt;/a&gt;. Everyday for 8 hours or more, we worked on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choreography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relaxation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push Hands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meditation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more...&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here&#39;s what it was like to completely rebuild my Tai Chi practice at this training:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/HoXz88Vyxe0?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These events are always transformative, but what has been so cool is having the Mastery Program as a resource. And in the year since the initial release, I&#39;ve been working hard to create practice resources for you that make it even easier to learn Tai Chi using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/tai-chi-mastery-program#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=82cf549a&#34;&gt;Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Want to learn more about how to use the Tai Chi Mastery Program to build your Chi in 2014?  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-m11egdjc17es6rb&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/m11egdjc17es6rb&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var m11egdjc17es6rb;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;m11egdjc17es6rb&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;342&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;host&#39;:&#39;wufoo.com&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { m11egdjc17es6rb = new WufooForm();m11egdjc17es6rb.initialize(options);m11egdjc17es6rb.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After teaching thousands of people of all ages and physical abilities over the last eight years, it is clear to me that there is one technique in Tai Chi that is more powerful than all others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis Tai Chi Resources&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis-tai-chi-resources/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, introduced me to this technique and taught me how to use all its variations, under different conditions. He has encouraged all his instructors to pass along this technique because it is practically a lost art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just this week, he released &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/tai-chi/the-insiders-guide-to-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;The Insider&#39;s Guide to Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, where he describes Tai Chi&#39;s most powerful technique in detail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upon recognizing what your own qi feels like, you begin two separate phases that synergistically work with each other. The first is centered on your central nervous system. Having gained the experience of putting your mind (awareness) into your muscles, you now learn to put it into your nerves. Relaxing and releasing the nerves themselves enables you to recognize the constant buzz that runs through your entire nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are not aware of this ever-present stressful buzz because it has become so normal. This buzz is a sure sign that your nervous system is either beginning to rev up (like a car going from 0-60 miles per hour in a few seconds), or even worse, has been locked habitually into a constant rev. This rev or buzz is how stress seeps through and hardens into your body. You now focus on ways to re-soften this nervous buzz inside you and progressively relax and release it from your nerves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a growing capacity to relax, you move into the second phase. Here you want to release the more-subtle nervous buzz of blocked qi inside all your body&#39;s tissues. Progressively, step-by-step, you find and release the rev in your joints, blood flow, spinal system, internal organs and glands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each stage of releasing the rev from your bodily systems makes your body more awake. This takes you into more subtle and powerful experiences of what it means and feels like for your body to be fully alive.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The enlivening technology of Tai Chi -- not what is visible on the outside, but what you do on the inside, with your mind, your chi, and in your nervous system -- holds the potential to transform the way you feel throughout the day, every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time I get a clear hit of just how to release a new layer, or relax to a new level, it blows me away and makes me hope that you can find a way to experience it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Eight Energies of Tai Chi and the Physical Attributes of Roll Back</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 13:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;a title=&#34;Your Guide to the Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/your-guide-to-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;, Bruce Frantzis recently published a report called &#34;The Eight Principles of Tai Chi Chuan.&#34; The report is full of detail about stages of training 8 different energies of Tai Chi, laid out in clear and straightforward language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I always have a problem with writing like this....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, it is invaluable for anyone who wants to understand the bigger context of their Tai Chi practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re not careful, though, you can fall into a Tai Chi trap (see below after the video).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Physical Attributes of Roll Back&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the report, Bruce details each of the different energies and one of the sections that jumped out at me was the chapter on &#34;Lu&#34; or &#34;Roll Back.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roll Back is Tai Chi&#39;s signature yielding or softening energy. Bruce lays out an excellent progression for training Roll Back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I demonstrate the five points he makes about the &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; aspects of Roll Back:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/PL8TPEu3TWw?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Tai Chi Trap&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, when you read the report, Bruce lays out the physical aspects of Roll Back, then the energetic ones. Once he explains the physical aspects, he says,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the early stages of learning Roll Back, your movements will be large and obvious, both in your joints and in your waist. Over time, however, as your physical movements become more refined and circular, they can become extremely small, so tiny, in fact, that they are virtually invisible to the eye of someone untrained in observing subtlety of movement.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;And here&#39;s the trap: you read about subtlety and refinement and energetics that seem superhuman and because you are a well-trained, sophisticated thinker, you choose to imagine that you can do the subtle version right away.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bruce just gave you a road map, but you think you&#39;re already at your destination because you can read the map and picture the destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that&#39;s not how a journey really works and that&#39;s not how growth occurs in your Tai Chi practice. Especially when it gets to the subtle energetics, you have to work your way into them slowly over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Big Road Map: The Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bruce is about to release a huge road map for a lifelong journey through Tai Chi. My biggest fear is that people will buy the map and fantasize about the destinations, but never actually begin the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who does want to go on that journey, though, I&#39;m getting ready to go with you and I&#39;d be happy to be your guide along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To get the rest of my guided tour of the Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/strong&gt; (including &#34;The Eight Energies of Tai Chi Chuan&#34; report from Bruce), &lt;a title=&#34;Your Guide to the Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/your-guide-to-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;visit this page and sign up&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bon Voyage!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Calm Your Mind Through Movement</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 08:45:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/10/P10001922.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2313&#34; title=&#34;Repulse Monkey&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/10/P10001922-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tai Chi in Gloucester, MA&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Movement can be a powerful tool for creating a calm mind, but only when you follow some very specific rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi was designed with these specific movement rules because the goal is to take you from tense to relaxed and from relaxed to vital and strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my Tai Chi teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt; explains the learning progression for Tai Chi, he makes it clear that when your primary focus is on the mind, and your goal is to calm your mind, you must follow this progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relax Your Muscles and Your Mind&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
At the first stage, you go for the big obvious stuff. Most of us are more tuned into muscular contraction and mental tension than to constrictions in our soft tissues or jammed joints. Start with what you can feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you are learning basic exercises and a broad-stroke version of the Tai Chi form, focus on relaxing your muscles and begin to catch yourself in moments of mental tension. Learn to let go of each one as you move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By training yourself to find these moments in motion, you begin to make relaxation a habit that will follow you into daily activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Find Your Shape&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you go through the Tai Chi form for the first time, you are sketching the basic shape that will be filled in in detail later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, don&#39;t overstretch, don&#39;t contract too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to feel basic alignments, like centering the weight in your feet as you shift and turn and squat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the cadence of the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By following these movement rules, you are building a physical container. The more unified this container becomes, the more you can run your mind through your body. Following all of the rhythms and flows of the form with your awareness leads to the same kind of letting go for your mind that we began to work in with the muscles in the first stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Layer By Layer&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you relax your mind and your body, you can go deeper. Your mind penetrates deeper into the space inside your body and as a result, your body is knit together in a stronger way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You learn to make deep internal connections that optimize how you move and how you respond to your surroundings. You have more energy.You can interact with your internal environment in a smoother way too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how relaxation leads to strength.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Tai Chi Is Like Listening To Your Favorite Song</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/08/20/good-tai-chi-is-like-listening-to-your-favorite-song/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2012 11:16:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/08/20/good-tai-chi-is-like-listening-to-your-favorite-song/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you really find the groove with your Tai Chi practice, it&#39;s like listening to a piece of music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rhythms, riffs, and notes phase in and out, sometimes blending, and sometimes really standing out on their own, and even though there&#39;s a lot going on, you can soak it all in at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you practice Tai Chi the same way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#39;t just an analogy, there&#39;s a major lesson buried in here. Can you spot it?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4135&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/1HzXjw6zu8c?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Takeaway:&lt;/strong&gt; Whenever you find yourself &#34;thinking&#34; your way through your Tai Chi practice, remember what it&#39;s like to listen to great music. Approach the internal principles of Tai Chi just like you would settle in for your favorite song. When you can truly listen to your practice the same way, you know you&#39;ve begun integrating Tai Chi on a deep level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out more practice tips like this in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 08:23:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3864&#34; title=&#34;Stake Standing&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/05/Stake-Standing-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong as Prep for Meditation&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the outside, standing qigong can look calm, peaceful and meditative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the inside, if you don&#39;t ask yourself these 3 essential questions, standing can be grueling. Your muscles ache, you tremble and sweat, and in burning discomfort you strain to see how much longer you must endure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&#39;t have to be torture, though, if you adopt the right mindset as you practice.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4015&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have learned many different standing qigong &lt;em&gt;techniques&lt;/em&gt; from my teacher &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, but when I practice what he&#39;s taught about &lt;em&gt;mindset&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; in standing qigong, I&#39;ve had some of my biggest breakthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summer 2011, at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011/&#34;&gt;Wu Style Short Form Instructor training&lt;/a&gt;, he emphasized the role of standing qigong in developing internal connections in Tai Chi practice. We did work on the particular energetic techniques of different Tai Chi postures, but the bigger lessons of &#34;what to watch for&#34; and &#34;what you want to experience&#34; have been even more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote about the challenges and payoffs of an intensive environment like this for &lt;a href=&#34;http://imos-journal.net/?p=3486&#34;&gt;Into Mountains, Over Streams&lt;/a&gt; when I returned. Specifically, I described the way standing helps you find internal stability in your form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p id=&#34;internal-source-marker_0.8767203545320106&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Tai Chi has many methods for tuning you in to the inner form. My personal favorite was holding standing postures. It can be grueling work on a physical level. Even when you adjust to the physical discomfort, standing still for extended periods of time forces you to confront your own internal environment. Nothing is moving on the outside, so your attention focuses on the inside.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Holding postures to open specific energy lines in the body is very much a science. We began that study by exploring nine of the postures from the short form, holding each one for twenty to thirty minutes. Throughout this process, I could feel everything from the surfaces of my body, down through the layers of twisted tissue. I became acutely aware of how my bones and joints were aligned. Eventually I got access to the specific flow pattern each posture is designed to highlight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I often describe the sensation of &#34;getting&#34; a posture as feeling your internal gears clicking. The posture gels in a way that you would never experience if you always just go through the form. Until you spend time in each posture, you miss a whole hidden side of internal connectedness. When we asked Master Frantzis how to systematically train these postures after the training was over, he recommended working on each posture for 2 months and then changing to the next one in the series. It&#39;s amazing to feel your insides shift and change over one twenty minute standing session, but coming back to a posture each day for two months gives you a completely different level of insight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Before the training, I had always thought about posture holding as a timed goal, like, &#34;Okay, I&#39;m going to hold this one for twenty, this one for thirty, this one longer, longer.&#34; One of the key points that Master Frantzis  made was that you should focus on the feeling of stability in each posture, not on the clock. Once you hit it for that place in the posture, everything opens up and becomes connected in a way that gives the posture a unique flavor. That&#39;s the key moment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Once everything clicks, a practitioner wants to maintain the moment for as long as they can. When you lose it; you shrink out of it; you start to collapse a little bit; something gets off.  This is game we play with each posture. How do you connect to it and reliably re-create that feeling again and again? That&#39;s the goal of the first stage of posture holding. After you reach this stage, you start to work of experiencing the same connections as you move into and out of this posture in your form. Eventually you can string the whole form together this way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Other people joke that the fastest way clear a room full of people who want to learn Tai Chi is to just make them close their eyes and hold a posture. It&#39;s definitely a matter of personal preference! To me, posture holding is a way to feel more connected and more integrated and really develop a feel for letting things come together without forcing them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Adopting the Right Mindset for Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;At first, searching for internal stability this way can be frustrating. Even once you&#39;ve gotten a sense for it, you can&#39;t always reproduce it reliably. However, if you ask yourself these three questions as you practice, you odds of getting there again and again will get much better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;As you stand, ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is gravity going through me? (Not getting stuck somewhere)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are my nerves relaxing and releasing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there warmth?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can ask yourself this question about any part of your body or everywhere at once. If you wash over yourself with this questions again and again as you stand, you will adopt the right alignment of your body, mind, and energy and increase your chances of finding internal stability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaxing Your Eyes in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/06/04/relaxing-your-eyes-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2012 13:57:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/06/04/relaxing-your-eyes-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The eyes are the gateway to your nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a theme that my teacher &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt; weaves into many different Tai Chi and qigong teachings that he gives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relaxing the nervous system is one of the central goals of Tai Chi practice. With a relaxed nervous system you are more aware of your reactions, thoughts, emotions, and really, your entire internal environment.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3974&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best ways to begin to tune into the state of your nervous system is by learning to feel your eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relaxing Your Eyes in Tai Chi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ty7CmoTk8nA?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ty7CmoTk8nA?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did an expanded lesson on this same technique, using partners, at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011/&#34;&gt;Wu Short Form Instructor training&lt;/a&gt;, so I hope this practice is also included in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the &#34;eye-check&#34; as a way to start your practice each day, then as a periodic check during your practice session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you too focused on getting something right? Your eyes will tense up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you found your root and maintained nice, sinking energy throughout? You&#39;ll keep your soft eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s to relaxed practicing!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming a Giant Rooted Spring in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/05/14/becoming-a-giant-rooted-spring-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 09:22:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/05/14/becoming-a-giant-rooted-spring-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you relax into the turning of the waist and feel how it connects to the legs, you begin a process of rooting while moving that creates a dynamic and springy stability. Kind of a paradox, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You feel like a giant spring, anchored to the floor even though you&#39;re moving around, that is constantly being wound up and then released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to cultivating this connection is how you relax through your turning, so let&#39;s start off by getting clear on what we mean when we say relaxation. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3897&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, people conflate relaxation with just slumping on the couch. In Tai Chi, we actually mean, &#34;moving in a way that doesn&#39;t constrict your nervous system and even more, having a sense of continuously releasing the nerves as you practice.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/29/qigong-radio-episode-2-developing-your-soft-tissue-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel gave some great advice on the progression from turning to twisting to spiraling for Qigong Radio.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are relaxing into more and more leg and waist turning, your goal is to get connected all the way to the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s an example:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/HolPGfI3KVc?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Mastery program&lt;/a&gt;, Bruce explains how letting this turning penetrate the legs actually protects the joints of the legs and lower spine.&lt;/strong&gt; You must simultaneously relax the nerves and the tissue to allow for turning, but also keep space in all the joints, &lt;em&gt;so the turning movements pass through the joints.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the key points to develop this quality in your practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turning from the waist should eventually feel like it directly screws the foot into the floor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turning must go through both legs in all stances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for sections of the leg that stop turning because these freeze points will put pressure on the joints in that area (thigh or lower leg on the knee, for example, or hips/glutes on the lower spine).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can practice this continuously in the Tai Chi form or &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/&#34;&gt;in a variety of other movement patterns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Intensive 9 Months Later</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/04/04/tai-chi-intensive-9-months-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 06:54:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/04/04/tai-chi-intensive-9-months-later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34; wp-image-3752&#34; title=&#34;Energy Arts Tai Chi Instructors at Push Hands&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/04/Photo-Mar-30-2-27-16-PM-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you spend a month training Tai Chi 10-12 hours a day, what happens when you go home? What does it feel like several months later when your life has returned to normal? Is it a let down? Do you need to be inspired again to continue your training?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have you continued to discover about your practice? How has the intensive training infused your teaching?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sat down with several Energy Arts Tai Chi instructors to discuss these issues for Episode 3 of Qigong Radio. Here&#39;s what they had to say. Since we were all together for a Push Hands training, designed to be a follow-up to the Short Form training, we also talked about the ways we were seeing connections between the two topics.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3751&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to these guys for participating: Senior Instructors &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.balancedenergyarts.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Jamie Dibdin from Brighton, UK&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/edgartown/eric-l-peters&#34;&gt;Eric Peters from Martha&#39;s Vineyard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/harpers-ferry/aaron-green&#34;&gt;Aaron Green from Washington, DC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://taichi.studioyugen.com/&#34;&gt;Scott Huette from Eugene, OR&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ensostudio.com/taichi.html&#34;&gt;Chris Cinnamon from Chicago&lt;/a&gt;, Thomas Herrington from Maui, Chris Redmond from California, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/london/lucy-amis&#34;&gt;Lucy Amis from London&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/manchester/alexander-daniel-connor&#34;&gt;Alex Connor from Manchester, UK&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;Acirc;  &lt;a href=&#34;http://taichi-shiatsu.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Peter Ling&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/instructors/taichi-qigong/pforzheim/franz-heutschy&#34;&gt;Franz Heutschy from Pforzheim, Germany&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zendokan.de/&#34;&gt;Olaf Rolving from Muelhiem, Germany&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichievi.byethost13.com/jeannehome/index.htm&#34;&gt;Jeanne Houde&lt;/a&gt;, and local instructors Ana Popa, Janak Sanariya, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.natehribar.com&#34;&gt;Nate Hribar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Push Hands and The Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 07:19:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re hosting Bruce Frantzis for a Push Hands Intensive this week at Brookline Tai Chi. The training is being filmed and it will become the Push Hands module of the Tai Chi Mastery Program, due out later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are my thoughts so far on how the Push Hands component fits in with what we did &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011/&#34;&gt;this past summer in Brighton&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0XaK4Gy7fDc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0XaK4Gy7fDc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What did we do all day in Brighton?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/21/what-did-we-do-all-day-in-brighton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2011 10:18:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/21/what-did-we-do-all-day-in-brighton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1885&#34; title=&#34;Group Corrections&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/08/Group-correction-300x200.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a little peek into our daily training routine in Brighton. You can see there was lots of partner work, holding postures and form practice. Of course, it was very serious the whole time! Thanks to Aimo for the photos. &lt;a title=&#34;Short Form Instructor Training Photos&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/short-form-instructor-training-photos/&#34;&gt;Click here for all the photos. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Form Training Final Update</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 12:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m heading home to Boston tomorrow, but I&#39;ve already begun looking through my notes and thinking about what I will personally practice and what I&#39;ll be able to share with my students in classes this coming year. Here are some of my initial thoughts:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1827&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ZkLnAA8ejb8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ZkLnAA8ejb8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Material is Woven together over a Month:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Day to day we&#39;re looking at really small specific pieces but now going back through my notes, I can start to see different threads that run throughout the duration of the month. It&#39;s almost like you don&#39;t even notice some of the nuances as in the moment, but like we&#39;ll look at something about the legs in Tai Chi from the first day and then we came back to it four or five days later and then we look at it again, and when you actually line up the pieces side by side, what you start to see is that...versus looking at it from like sort of looking at a ball, you look at it from one side and then the next time you look at it from this angle, then you look at it from this angle. And by taking this kind of spherical approach to it, looking at different facets of the subject, you start to develop a sense for the whole. And it&#39;s not the progression that he always teaches and it&#39;s not linear. It&#39;s not one, two, three, four, five. It&#39;s look at it this way, look at it that way and it&#39;s sort of up to you to put the pieces together to create the whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Handling Stress on a Whole New Level&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;They&#39;re all are these layers to that and progressions that I&#39;ll be able to lay out for my students, but personally for me I think one of the most exciting ones that I&#39;ll be able to bring to people is some really specific technical information about burnout and stress and no, I mean, if you think about Tai Chi in general, that&#39;s kind of what it&#39;s known for. It&#39;s a relaxation practice and it looks calming in that way. Everybody&#39;s first impression of it is that it is gentle and relaxing, but we actually got in much deeper into the technical stuff and the form that actually makes the softness of Tai Chi really work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;s not always contrasted to the couch potato model of relaxation where we live in this culture where we think, okay just go, go, go, go, go 24/7 and when you want to relax, pass out on the couch in front of the TV. So we have these two extremes. Tai chi is sort of an antidote to stress. It works on relaxation but it&#39;s a little more complicated than that. It&#39;s not... relaxation isn&#39;t just a flop. Relaxation has to do much more with your capacity to put energy out and take energy in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there&#39;s some really interesting technical stuff in terms of being able to absorb and nourish the body that is really Tai Chi&#39;s strong suit that you&#39;re not going to get in this kind of fast paced go, go, go, very Yang, very revved up kind of mentality. Instead, Tai Chi has a way of building the nervous system and building the body up so that it can rest, absorb and regenerate and we looked at some really specific ways to highlight in the form to make sure that happens for people.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update from the Beach</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 3 wraps up and testing is right around the corner. What was Bruce&#39;s big message as we prepare for testing? Work your ass off and cram all night for the big test? Not quite. You might be surprised. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1823&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/BQcg7CR5F78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/BQcg7CR5F78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Lesson about Integration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing that Bruce is emphasizing in the last couple days of class is that with this stage of the training, a month long training, you need integration time. And we talk about this all the time in regular weekly classes. We talk about in a given practice session, whether it&#39;s an hour or 20 minutes or whatever, you always have this sort of startup time where you just get warmed up. And then from there you go into the work period, where you just kind of crank and crank and crank, and that&#39;s when your system is the most open. You can get a lot done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the biggest mistake people make is that they do that hard charge all the way to the end. The secret to all of these energy practices, to really get your energy to smoothed out and then get into your nervous system in the best possible way, is that you need to have integration. So, we talk about it all the time. That&#39;s how we try to do each practice session. So, to me, it&#39;s really cool to watch this month-long work and hear Bruce talk about that and emphasize that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Yesterday he talked a lot about what to do on the day off, in terms of even just mentally rehearsing the form, going through and trying to feel it through your body without doing the movements. So there&#39;s a lot of interesting stuff about mental rehearsal that we talked about, but also just to let it kind of soak into your system. And I find when students can recognize that integration phase as a legitimate part of the practice, then you take it to a whole deeper level, because you recognize rest as an important part of hard work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And I think there are a lot of ways that we&#39;ve lost that idea culturally and a lot of ideas of success and hard work don&#39;t really acknowledge the resting and integration phase as an important piece of it. So even though we&#39;ve come through intensive month-long training, as we&#39;re rounding into the final stretch, rest and integration and relaxation is a key piece to learning all this stuff. And to me that&#39;s very cool. So that&#39;s what we&#39;re up to this week.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 of the Short Form Instructor Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 09:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my Week 2 update. Some big milestones this week: group 1 finished the form and group 2 has been languishing in the purgatory that is holding static postures. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1816&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/FpsecDulvWc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/FpsecDulvWc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inner Form vs. Outer Form&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;In the two groups, we&#39;re doing very different things. The group one just finished the form this week. So on Thursday after they finished it, we came in Friday, and it was a really interesting dividing line. Bruce made the big distinction between, on the one hand, on Thursday we finished the shape and the form, that&#39;s sort of the container. He said, &#34;Now, everything that we&#39;re going to do has to do with internal content.&#34; So he made this distinction all the time. He talked about the bottle versus the wine you put inside it and we even have an article at Brookline Tai Chi that we put out from, I think, it&#39;s from 1989 Tai Chi Magazine. The title of the article is &#34;The Inner Form is the Key to Health.&#34; And in the article, Bruce talks about all the different internal content things that should be going on that to be Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And I find this working with beginners all the time is such a huge hurdle to get them over. Because people know Tai Chi by looks like in the outside, they see the shapes and the movements, and they see it flowing and graceful and relaxed, but it&#39;s really hard unless you&#39;re used to looking at it, to see what&#39;s going on inside. But Bruce always makes this big point, it actually what goes on inside that makes Tai Chi actually effective. It makes it not just choreography but it makes it work to improve your health, we&#39;re going to do meditation and martial arts. If you don&#39;t have the internal content, it&#39;s like driving a car without an engine. So it&#39;s interesting to hear him talk about for a group that&#39;s just finishing the container of the form. Now, to start to see what he started out with. And as far as internal content for them and how we&#39;re going to build that up. So that&#39;s a cool inflection point in the halfway point for the first group.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Finding Internal Stability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the second group we&#39;ve been holding postures. And so we&#39;ve gone through now, I think, eight of the postures and the form, and building out from twenty, twenty-five, thirty minutes. And this is one of my favorite methods - the posture holding and you see up here, look at some other posing here, you see me messing around with 30 minutes in one posture or something else like that, I&#39;ve always liked it in the standing practice. It was the thing that kind of, for me, made the difference of what&#39;s in the outside and &#34;Hey, if you stand still and start to just feel into the body, there&#39;s this whole internal landscape you can start to explore.&#34; And that was the thing that always got me excited about Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&#39;m very happy that we&#39;ve been going through and holding posture by posture. What it is about it, is that if you get into each posture and the form, each of them because of the physical constraints, higher twisting, one way twisting, the other way, whether the posture&#39;s more extended, or whether the posture is more condensed, all of these things add up to determine in a specific posture how you manifest the energy of that posture. And so by holding it, you start to feel those internal gears kind of click and lock together in a way that you just if you&#39;re always just going through the form doing whatever, you totally missed that aspect. Sometimes you noticed really where you&#39;re tense, where things are stuck. But once you get each one of these things, it has kind of like a threshold where it clicks in. And I&#39;ve always thought about it in terms of, &#34;Okay, I&#39;m going to hold this one for twenty, this one for thirty, this one longer, longer.&#34; But one of the key points that Bruce made was that once you hit a certain stability point for that posture, everything opens up and lights up. The pathways light up or this connection lights up that gives the posture a unique flavor. That&#39;s the key moment. And then you wanted to maintain that for as long as you can. And inevitably you lose it, you shrink out of it, you start to collapse a little bit, something gets off. And this is game of like, &#34;Okay, how do I connect to it?&#34; Reliably create that effective posture and then stabilize it. And once you can stabilize it for a long time, then you move into this thing where the quality, the posture becomes integrated into your form and to how you move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to me, I don&#39;t know, it&#39;s a fascinating process. Other people joke that the fastest way clear Tai Chi class and get everybody to flee out of the room is to just make them close their eyes and hold the posture. So it&#39;s definitely a matter of personal preference. But I mean it&#39;s really cool, that&#39;s what we&#39;ve been focusing on all week.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am Learning at the Wu Tai Chi Instructor Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 01:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re a week into the Wu Tai Chi short form instructor training in Brighton, UK, with Lineage Holder Bruce Frantzis. So far we&#39;ve been completely rebuilding our forms, working on Tai Chi leg power, and exploring the meditative aspects of the art. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2964&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HoXz88Vyxe0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HoXz88Vyxe0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Rebuilding Your Form:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s crazy when you come at these things, you&#39;re completely rebuilding your Tai Chi form. We&#39;re about two-thirds of the way through the form and it feels so different. When you&amp;Acirc;  run through the whole thing one time, you get up to what we&#39;ve done so far and it feels brand new, like a completely different moves. And then you get to the last thing we&#39;ve done, you come around to the last move that you finished and you go back to your old form and it has a totally different feeling.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Yin and Yang of Tai Chi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contrast is that the biggest thing that he took from the London trainings into the Tai Chi training was this idea. He talks about it in terms of Yin and Yang, in terms of soft and hard, or in the sitting practice, it&#39;s about how do you go deep inside the body. You find this internal space and then let go of anything you find that&#39;s stuck. But there&#39;s an interesting contrast, it&#39;s not just let go and relax and collapse because the quality of mind it takes is that you have to sort of go inside, find and hold your awareness on something and persist with this awareness. That&#39;s a stronger quality. So this is interesting, this is Yin and Yang blend of getting your mind onto something and holding it there, giving it shape and containing this feeling. But then the other side it to completely let go, completely relaxing. So that&#39;s the Yin and Yang of the dissolving process. And we&#39;ve expanded that idea where he&#39;s talking about the energies in the Tai Chi form, the way we working on Tai Chi, the forming energies to the form, that balance of finding it, holding it and adding this kind of consistent, persistent meditative awareness as you do Tai Chi, is mirrored in the sort of the Yang aspects of the Tai Chi form. And then that letting go, softening, releasing, relaxing and just completely not holding on anything is there&#39;s the Yin qualities to the form, that have that same thing. So through Peng, Lu, Ji and An, each one of those from a meditative point of view can figure into how you&#39;re doing, making your Tai Chi form a true meditation practice, not just relaxation practice. So there&#39;s really great stuff there.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>