<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>1000-true-fans on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/1000-true-fans/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in 1000-true-fans on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/1000-true-fans/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Find Your True Fans</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/21/find-your-true-fans/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2010 09:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/21/find-your-true-fans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.static.flickr.com/30/54812349_b12966dcf7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;1,000 True Fans&#34; width=&#34;350&#34; height=&#34;256&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; If you&#39;ve never read Kevin Kelly&#39;s piece called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kk.org/thetechnium/archives/2008/03/1000_true_fans.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;1,000 True Fans&lt;/a&gt;, I suggest you hop on that link and read it. When you come back, you can read some of my thoughts on the issue, but I probably won&#39;t blow your mind the way Kelly will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, are you back? Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what I think stands out in his article for the aspiring &#34;Movement Education Professional&#34; (more on that term below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I don&#39;t know about you, but the long tail map is incredibly reassuring to me. I think whenever anyone is trying to run a small business, you look around and see &#34;the big guys&#34; and try to copy them. That&#39;s a totally unrealistic approach and going that route is totally disheartening. You can&#39;t behave like a big business at all: you don&#39;t have the same division of labor, you can&#39;t spend on advertising to build brand recognition, you can&#39;t fire an under-performing employee (what? cut off your left arm when sales tank???). You have to operate in a totally different way, but where is the model for how that&#39;s supposed to be done? Most of the people that would model for you, other successful small businesses, are too busy running their businesses!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So back to the long tail, Kelly says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am suggesting there is a home for creatives in between poverty and  stardom. Somewhere lower than stratospheric bestsellerdom, but higher  than the obscurity of the long tail. I don&#39;t know the actual true  number, but I think a dedicated artist could cultivate 1,000 True Fans,  and by their direct support using new technology, make an honest  living.&amp;Acirc;  I&#39;d love to hear from anyone who might have settled on such a  path.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As soon as you start looking at that in-between space, so many things open up. I like to think about this space when I&#39;m out in public. Sit on a busy street corner for 10 minutes and watch how many people go by. Do they all make a living? Do plenty of them make a comfortable living? Do you know them all? Yes. Yes. No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does that mean? &lt;strong&gt;It means that there is so much room in between for you to serve the needs of people who can pay for your service. &lt;/strong&gt;At Brookline Tai Chi, our database has over 10,000 names of people who have taken classes or inquired about classes at some point. You know what&#39;s amazing about that? Every 8 weeks, 30-50 &lt;em&gt;brand new&lt;/em&gt; people come through our door to start classes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the boring conclusion to all this is: &#34;there is a market out there for your services&#34;, but Kelly raises the stakes. It&#39;s not just a &#34;market&#34;. There are potentially raving, hard-core fans of what you do out there. You have to go find them and you have to find ways to engage them. I wrote in more detail about the &#34;universe&#34; of your fans &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/06/your-marketing-universe/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but on the Trainerfly blog, I just published &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2010/12/20/the-movement-education-professionals-manifesto/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&#34;The Movement Education Professional&#39;s Manifesto&#34;&lt;/a&gt;. The Manifesto is much more in line with the idea that passion driving a craft (in this case, your movement practice), should lead to engaging other people who get similarly excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think if you agree with premise of the Manifesto, about what movement means in your own life, and you&#39;ve taken the leap to teach professionally, then you&#39;ll see how important it is to take another big step and start finding your 1,000 True Fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/yourlocaldave/&#34;&gt;YourLocalDave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>