<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ba-gua on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/ba-gua/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in ba-gua on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/ba-gua/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Qigong Radio Episode 2: Developing Your Soft Tissue with Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/29/qigong-radio-episode-2-developing-your-soft-tissue-with-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2012 06:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/29/qigong-radio-episode-2-developing-your-soft-tissue-with-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>In episode 2 of Qigong Radio, I sat down with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel to discuss what it feels like to work with soft tissue -- muscle, fascia, and ligaments -- in the internal arts.
We discussed the different stages of practice and one of my favorite topics: adopting the right mindset so that the progress you make in your body isn&#39;t outpaced by what you think you&#39;re doing in your mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why You Should Not Worry About Breathing in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/19/why-you-should-not-worry-about-breathing-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/19/why-you-should-not-worry-about-breathing-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>In this Inner Form office hours clip, Nate asked me about a specific issue on breathing in the Marriage of Heaven and Earth qigong.
If your main focus is Tai Chi, then I would recommend that you pretty much ignore breathing as you practice, but you should focus on opening up the body enough to facilitate deep, even, smooth breathing.
In the following clips, we look at how opening up the body will lead to deeper breathing, what stages you will go through in this process, and finally, I show him a specific technique for keeping the deep internal connections loose as he does the Marriage of Heaven and Earth qigong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Yin and Yang of Learning and Teaching the Internal Arts</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/07/the-yin-and-yang-of-learning-and-teaching-the-internal-arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2012 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/07/the-yin-and-yang-of-learning-and-teaching-the-internal-arts/</guid>
      <description>This is a guest post from my friend and fellow instructor, Paul Cavel. I asked Paul to talk a little bit about his experience teaching all over Europe and what he&#39;s learned after nearly 20 years doing it. There are some great insights here about the internal energy arts that you can apply to your own practice, whether you teach or not. Take note when he talks about practice mindset!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making More Space Inside Your Body</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/05/making-more-space-inside-your-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/03/05/making-more-space-inside-your-body/</guid>
      <description>One of the most counter-intuitive feelings in qigong, Tai Chi, or Ba Gua is the way that making more space inside the body allows you open more outwardly as well.
In these two Inner Form office hours video clips, I show Brendan how making more space in the kwa and shoulder&#39;s nest can help her take a more connected step in her circle walking practice and develop a more fluid single palm change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turn the Legs to Turn the Body</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 09:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/</guid>
      <description>When you see a series of exercises, you can either look at what&#39;s common to all of them, or how they are different. In this video, I go through several variations of turning exercises, where I&#39;m using the connection between the legs and the spine to drive body movement.
Most people will look at the arms in each exercise and say, &#34;those are not the same movements&#34; and that&#39;s true, but they would be missing the most important part: how the legs turn the body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twisting Through the Legs</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/02/13/twisting-through-the-legs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/02/13/twisting-through-the-legs/</guid>
      <description>Twisting, especially the legs, is one of those techniques that sounds really cool, but it easy to overdo. Going slow and steady with twisting can help everything loosen up.
My advice: at first work on feeling what naturally happens rather than trying to make something happen. Develop sensitivity.
In this &#34;office hours&#34; clip, we look at twisting the legs in Cloud Hands and troubleshoot some of her stuck spots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Quiet Awareness with Lee Burkins</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</guid>
      <description>In June, between sessions at Brookline Tai Chi and during master classes with Bruce Frantzis, a small group of students got a special treat. Energy Arts Senior Instructor Lee Burkins was in town to train with Bruce, and on one of the nights off, he offered a special evening course on a topic he calls &#34;Investing in Loss&#34;.
What I love about studying with someone like Lee is that he&#39;s a practitioner whose art has soaked so deeply into his bones, that it practically oozes out of his DNA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 12:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>Paul Cavel is an Energy Arts Senior Instructor based in London. He teaches regular weekly classes there, but he&#39;s also been traveling all over the UK and Europe for years teaching workshops, including annual week-long retreats in Crete. I talked to Paul a little bit about his background in Tai Chi, neigong, and Ba Gua and asked him for some practice advice for a group of students who just completed a series at BTC on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ba Gua Program Product Launch</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/11/ba-gua-program-product-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 06:46:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/11/11/ba-gua-program-product-launch/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;ve been working with the team at Energy Arts on various projects, but mainly in the capacity as a community coordinator. Currently, my focus is on helping them get a new community discussion forum off the ground, but I also had the chance to participate in the launch of their new Ba Gua Mastery Program.
The Ba Gua Mastery Program is a home-study program with information on circle-walking for meditation and martial arts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>