<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-gates-dissolving-series on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/energy-gates-dissolving-series/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy-gates-dissolving-series on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/energy-gates-dissolving-series/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>When to Follow a Practice Recipe and When to Reflect on Your Practice</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 09:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this video, we&#39;re talking about building up the skill of Outer Dissolving in your standing qigong practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start out, it pays to follow a recipe - a set of instructions that lead through a certain procedure physically, energetically, and with your mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are times you want to break away from the recipe and times you&#39;ll want to reflect on your experience verbally -- but there are good and bad ways to do both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/wv2eex86CCE?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reporting Live from the Beach</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/12/reporting-live-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 10:38:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/12/reporting-live-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2014/02/D0D3E67C-7A7E-4922-89F3-85A0FA4D143B1392219396.012004.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;margin: 5px; border: 0px none;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2014/02/D0D3E67C-7A7E-4922-89F3-85A0FA4D143B1392219396.012004.jpg&#34; width=&#34;158&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I&#39;m on day 4 of daily practice by the ocean, but it&#39;s more than that. We&#39;re staying right on the beach, so I get to soak up the energy of the ocean pretty much all day long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I didn&#39;t used to have any sense for what &#34;the energy of the ocean&#34; meant and like pretty much everything else energetic, I&#39;m sure my sense for it will evolve even more, but I want to share my experiences from this week with you anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately we&#39;ve been talking about two ways of practicing standing qigong: &lt;a title=&#34;Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;by form or by feel&lt;/a&gt;. This week I&#39;ve been using both and both methods have revealed interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First By Feel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Holding the same posture for the same amount of time when you stand gives you the opportunity to &#34;just feel.&#34; By having a consistent baseline, the posture and duration, you can compare the feel from one day to the next to reveal new internal space and sensations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice by a huge natural power source like the ocean, though, you can also discover &#34;activity&#34; that varies day to day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy of the ocean works like a giant amplifier this way. When you settle in and get quiet, you can connect to it and get a big signal boost. In other words, the volume gets turned up on all the internal sensations you typically listen for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has been so exciting about practice this week is that the thing that gets amplified and really stands out is different each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day it was the lower tantien directing energy down through the legs and stabilizing the lower body. The next day, I found more space and expansiveness through the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the very first day, a stuck spot I had been working with for a few months began to open up and continued to unwind itself as I sat by the ocean after practice. Thanks, Ocean!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I tell you about practice experiences like this, it&#39;s not that I want you to go out and search for these specific ones. You can&#39;t. You might encounter them, but I didn&#39;t set out with an agenda to experience them ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;You have to open your awareness to see what naturally emerges and your reward is the surprise of discovery.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Doing the Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, this all might sound like spontaneous practice, but there&#39;s an important role for the form here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember how I framed &#34;just feel&#34; practice? Set the same conditions as much as possible, then be surprised by the contrast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get the boost from a natural power source like the ocean, you can go back into the form and have extra juice for feeling, sinking, and dissolving, as you work through the body in a systematic way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of you have been sending me questions about sinking versus dissolving lately and I&#39;ve been thinking a lot about the best way to capture the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we go through the process of working on the Gates, you use both techniques in each practice session, dissolving the &#34;&lt;a title=&#34;Energy Gates Dissolving Series&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;gate of the week&lt;/a&gt;,&#34; then sinking down through the rest of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, you have the opportunity to contrast the two techniques every time you practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissolving is lighter, sinking saturates your tissues and gets heavy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissolving breaks things apart, sinking pulls them down through your body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissolving is letting go without forcing, so is sinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases you have to rest your mind in one place and let the process unfold, but dissolving and sinking happen on different frequencies. Don&#39;t ask me what kind of frequencies. I can tell you that model captures my experience, but I don&#39;t honestly know if that&#39;s an analogy or what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I do know from practicing by the ocean this week, though, is that when you get a Great Amplifier for your form, you build stronger internal connections, go deeper, release more and if you listen just right, you figure out new things about old patterns that you can hopefully bring back with you to your regular practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Recipe for Rewarding Practice</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/30/the-recipe-for-rewarding-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 09:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/30/the-recipe-for-rewarding-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4998&#34; alt=&#34;Mixing all the elements of a good qigong practice.&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2014/01/iStock_000019067988Small-200x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&#34;Is it better to structure your practice to stay with one energy gate, such as the crown, until you feel some dissolving happening there, or should you just keep moving through the gates week by week moving onto another gate?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent questions like this one keep pouring in. Thank you for sharing your practice experiences with me. I know other folks who read the blog really appreciate it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love hearing from you guys, especially when your questions are grounded in exploration, practice and thoughtful reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check this next one out too. I don&#39;t think I&#39;ve ever articulated the process of sinking chi as clearly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#34;I&#39;m basically aiming to keep my attention on each section of my body as I go down until I feel it has gone sung and has the sense that&#39;s its as relaxed as I&#39;m capable of - as well as the sensation that it has filled with qi (like the sponge analogy). Then I try to feel the leading edge of that fullness until it seeps down to the next section. Does this sound like I&#39;m sinking or dissolving? Or am I somewhere in between perhaps?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you see the common thread in both of these questions? &lt;strong&gt;Both of these questions are about &#34;practice recipes.&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice Recipes for Skill Acquisition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve been reading about learning models a little more lately and I wanted to share the Dreyfus Model of Skill Acquisition with you. If you have the time, these slides give a great overview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&#34;border: 1px solid #CCC; border-width: 1px 1px 0; margin-bottom: 5px; max-width: 100%;&#34; src=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/3462945&#34; height=&#34;356&#34; width=&#34;427&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a title=&#34;Dreyfus Model Of Skills Acquisition&#34; href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/cynthiajoffrion/dreyfus-model-of-skills-acquisition&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dreyfus Model Of Skills Acquisition&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/cynthiajoffrion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;cynthia joffrion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The big takeaway is that any time you are building a new skill, it helps to block everything else out and use a set of context-free rules to hone the skill....or in other words, follow a recipe!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Did you notice that experts fall back on rules, recipes, and analysis when things get too complex too?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice recipes help you separate signal from noise, what&#39;s important from what&#39;s irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the five stages in this model, you&#39;ll notice that at a certain point rules are replaced by patterns, then by decisions and intuition. As skills become ingrained, we subconsciously integrate more information than could possibly be explained and reduced to binary rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice Recipes in Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To apply this model to our standing practice, we need to adopt a novice mindset every time we practice a new way of standing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start out by asking yourself, &#34;if I want to build this skill, what rules should I follow?&#34; Practicing this way will give you &lt;strong&gt;focus and freedom&lt;/strong&gt;: you won&#39;t worry about a million different things and you&#39;ll be able to give your energy over to one or two simple tasks.&lt;br /&gt;
So if we return to the initial question and think about recipes, what do you notice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is it better to structure your practice to stay with one energy gate, such as the crown, until you feel some dissolving happening there, or should you just keep moving through the gates week by week moving onto another gate?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;This question is equivalent to saying, &#34;I like my bread a little crispier and browner, I think I&#39;m going to leave it in the over for a few more minutes.&#34; The recipe says 25 minutes, but you&#39;re making a choice to leave it in for 30. And that&#39;s fine!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;The person who asked this question is right on the edge of following the recipe to the letter and exploring, improvising and practicing &#34;to taste.&#34; I&#39;ve worked with a lot of people who don&#39;t play this edge enough. Either they lock themselves rigidly into a form or always go by feel. I don&#39;t think either of those is a good choice.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instead, you should run through the recipe many times, to really understand the steps and start to see the potential for variation&lt;/strong&gt;, like &#34;I could stay at this gate longer and feel more going on.&#34; Then, when you&#39;ve found a place to go deeper, break away from the recipe and really explore.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;In this case, any of gate, if it&#39;s a really productive area for you, could be a 2-week, 3-week, or month-long project.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;In the &lt;a title=&#34;Energy Gates Dissolving Series&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;Standing Dissolving Series&lt;/a&gt;, I&#39;m giving you weekly recipes to follow and taking you through a whole process, which you could also look at as one 6-month-long recipe to follow.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My recommendation in this case is to follow the recipe until you feel confident and comfortable without it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;Deeply Ingrained Recipes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Re-read the second question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m basically aiming to keep my attention on each section of my body as I go down until I feel it has gone sung and has the sense that&#39;s its as relaxed as I&#39;m capable of - as well as the sensation that it has filled with qi (like the sponge analogy). Then I try to feel the leading edge of that fullness until it seeps down to the next section. Does this sound like I&#39;m sinking or dissolving? Or am I somewhere in between perhaps?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In addition to being a great description of &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;sinking chi&lt;/a&gt;, I want you to notice that it&#39;s also an interesting blend of a clearly structured recipe, but also something that&#39;s done completely by feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get to this stage with a particular skill, where you&#39;re feeling your way through it in a consistent pattern instead of thinking it through like a list of instructions, you&#39;re ready to layer new skills on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this case, instead of following the leading edge and the seeping sensation, you tune in more to the energy &#34;behind&#34; the area that&#39;s releasing, without leaving that area. Hanging out here, with a listening attitude, sensing what unfolds next, will lead you into dissolving.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/standing-qigong-question/&#34;&gt;Do you have a Standing Qigong practice question? Ask me here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dissolving, Breathing, Structure, and Stillness: Follow-Up Q&amp;A</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/23/dissolving-breathing-structure-and-stillness-follow-up-qa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 08:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/23/dissolving-breathing-structure-and-stillness-follow-up-qa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34; id=&#34;docs-internal-guid-38f4178b-bf43-c313-f159-173b20fcce07&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4992&#34; alt=&#34;Stillness of a Mountain Lake&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2014/01/iStock_000013351742Small-300x170.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;170&#34; /&gt;Thanks to everyone who reached out with questions about the first standing audio practice in the Energy Gates Dissolving series.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I want to share some of the questions with you here. Please let me know if you have any follow-up questions or comments or think there is anything the needs clarification. Hopefully we can approach this series together as an ongoing learning process!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#39;s the Difference between Outer Dissolving, Downward Dissolving, and Sinking?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This first question is a clarification about 3 different types of standing practices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;She asks,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;So we are getting acquainted with the the gates in this series in the context of downward dissolving, not outer dissolving.  Is that correct?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I also have a question about the progression of the standing practice.  Just for the sake of having the big picture, it would be useful to understand when to transition one&#39; practice from each stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;From sinking to downward dissolving&lt;br /&gt;
From downward dissolving to awareness of energy gates&lt;br /&gt;
From awareness to energy gates to outer dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Is this the correct sequence and what are the markers that you are ready to move into the next phase?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I like the way she lays out the stages, around sinking, awareness, and dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Technically, dissolving a general area and working on a specific gate are both methods of outer dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;As far as deciding which to know or knowing where you are at, these stages of practice are cyclical. You&#39;ll get to a point on any given day or go through periods of practice where one way of standing may call to you more than another.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;In this series, I&#39;m going to be emphasizing awareness of the gates with the hope that it turns into dissolving the gates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;In my experience there is a tendency to try to force the dissolving process to happen based on the concept, so I try to encourage people to discover the process more naturally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If you rest your mind in one area of the body and hold that area in your awareness with the intent to let go (paradox!), then naturally the energy that&#39;s binding it will begin to release. The release goes through phases with &#34;ice&#34;, &#34;water&#34; and &#34;gas&#34; being good landmarks for recognizing and talking about those phases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Does the Weight Fall through the Feet?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Here&#39;s an alignment question that gets a little confusing when you compare the standing we&#39;re doing to other practices where we play with varying the pressure in the feet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The only question I have is regarding letting the weight fall to the center of the feet (rather than the heel).  I understand how this is appropriate for the dissolving part of this standing.  But since, in Dragon and Tiger, Vol.2, pg. 24, Bruce talks about the Shi mian point causing energy to descend down the body, I was wondering if the weight should be more on the heel during the latter part of this standing when we do more of the sinking chi than the dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This is an interesting case where we look at several layers of the body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Yes, it&#39;s true that shifting ball to heel helps get energy going up and down. In this case, though, we&#39;re working on a slightly different set of structural alignments, where we want the OVERALL feeling of weight falling through the structure of the pelvis, legs, and feet to be the primary goal. Eventually, these two different techniques are layered on top of each other, even though they seem to be at odds right now - that&#39;s a common qigong experience!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Should I Breath during Standing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I received several questions about breathing - natural breathing, reverse breathing, breathing connected to energy flows, etc. To this list I would also add any techniques like lengthening, pulsing, twisting - generally anything you would do along pathways, with soft tissues, or joints.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The short answer is: at this point in the process, don&#39;t focus on any of that stuff!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If we break it down a little more, you will want to go through all of these techniques, and more. But here&#39;s the thing: there&#39;s a tradeoff between a specific focus, like your breath, and the overall container that you create by &#34;holding&#34; the posture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;It&#39;s always felt like two different volume knobs. If you turn up the volume on your breathing, at a certain point, you&#39;ll drown out your sensitivity to other things. On the other hand, if you get just the right volume on the breath, you&#39;ll find a harmony with the mind and your feel for the whole posture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;When you do practice a specific neigong element like breathing or lengthening or pulsing, work it for a few minutes, then stop. And feel. And see if what you&#39;ve set up is primed to go on its own and, with minimal effort, integrate with the whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Techniques for Closing the Practice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Another student asked about methods for closing the practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;You referred to &#39;gathering&#39; . Can you describe that? Is that just maintaining the form at the end of a practice session and feeling the energy?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
At the end of your practice session, especially if you&#39;ve done a &#34;form&#34; like a downward scan, you want to reserve at least a minute or two (sometimes 5 or 10) to just let the inside of your body and your energy go quiet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;There are specific techniques for storing chi in the lower tantien, and we&#39;ll get to those later, but at the very least, you want to create a layer of quiet between the activity of your practice and whatever you go about doing once you finish the practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The best part of adding this buffer in at the end: &lt;strong&gt;you begin to recognize stillness at other times during the &#34;active&#34; phase of your standing session.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the key to really good dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your Questions and Next Steps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Hopefully you found these questions helpful. Was there anything else you were wondering about during your standing practice?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If so, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/standing-qigong-question/&#34;&gt;drop me a line here&lt;/a&gt; and I do my best to answer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If you missed this first workout on the Crown of the Head and want to get started with the standing series, you can &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/AEcQ&#34;&gt;download it directly here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Ready for the next audio? &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/YSOn&#34;&gt;Download it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Also, &lt;a title=&#34;Energy Gates Dissolving Series&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;check back with this page&lt;/a&gt; where I will be adding a new workout each week. I recommend you do them in order if you decide to take on the dissolving process as part of your practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting at the Crown of the Head</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/16/starting-at-the-crown-of-the-head/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 14:13:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/16/starting-at-the-crown-of-the-head/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4985&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong Workouts&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2014/01/StandingNoName-01-300x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you read &lt;a title=&#34;Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;last week&#39;s post on standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;the Energy Gates book&lt;/a&gt;, or better yet, you can stand comfortably &#34;just feeling&#34; for 15-20 minutes, you&#39;re probably ready to embark on the downward dissolving process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I want to help you get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recorded a guided practice mp3 to get you through the first workout in the Energy Gates series: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/AEcQ&#34;&gt;Feeling the Gate at the Crown of the Head&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, in this phase, you want each practice session to have a clear structure, so that you release stuck energy in a systematic way. Here is my advice from the last post on &#34;the form&#34; of an Energy Gates standing session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in week 1, it could look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Crown of the Head - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Body - 3 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But week 11 would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel from the Crown of the Head down to the Solar Plexus - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Solar Plexus - 8 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Rest of the Body - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In other words, you should spend a substantial amount of time on whatever gate is the &#34;gate of the week.&#34; However, your practice session should always start with settling, finish with gathering, and have an easy flow down to the &#34;gate of the week&#34; and then from the &#34;gate of the week&#34; down into the ground after the main focus time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll notice that as you go through the process of the gates, your standing time can go from 15-20 minutes during the first few weeks up to 45-60 minutes towards the end of the process. If you can only manage 15-20 minutes and slowly adding more feels like too much of a strain, I recommend that you stick with the feeling method and not worry about the gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you&#39;re just setting out on this process, you&#39;re probably thinking, &lt;strong&gt;&#34;how am I supposed to be relaxed, feel into my body, and become more sensitive to my chi if I have to remember all these details??&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is exactly why I created &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/AEcQ&#34;&gt;this follow-along audio practice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out and let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>