<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>marriage-of-heaven-and-earth on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/marriage-of-heaven-and-earth/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in marriage-of-heaven-and-earth on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/marriage-of-heaven-and-earth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong is Packed with Internal Content</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-4444 alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Paul Cavel performs the Marriage of Heaven and Earth&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/12/qi-gong-class-11.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;250&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This summer, Bruce Frantzis will be teaching a Marriage of Heaven and Earth Instructor training. Heaven and Earth was the first instructor training I attended in 2004 and I can still remember what a profound effect learning to &#34;pulse&#34; had on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the Energy Arts system, Heaven and Earth is considered a bridge from the basic to more advanced practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;how Heaven and Earth works in an early episode of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt;, but I wanted to share this explanation from &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; with you too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Heaven + Earth Works On So Many Levels&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As discussed in earlier issues, classically Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body Qigong is the foundation of the entire Water tradition since it initiates all neigong practice through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alignments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sinking chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissolving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bending and stretching techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic breathing methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Circulating chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaging the kwa as the leader of all motion&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Energy Gates softens the body and prepares the &#34;shell&#34; by creating a containment field with the body and its energy to develop more sophisticated neigong technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas Heaven + Earth takes the baton from Energy Gates and folds in the internal content learned there. So everything you learn and the skill you develop in each qigong system can and should be packed up and shipped off to the next set in the series. Yes, the arrangement will be completely unique, but you don&#39;t throw away or leave dormant any components while developing superior forms. For example, recall that Dragon + Tiger Medical Qigong is one of the three foundational practices in the neigong lattice. Dragon + Tiger&#39;s underlying technology develops the etheric field and wei chi, and thereby serves as a subcomponent of Heaven + Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as a more advanced practice than either Energy Gates or Dragon + Tiger, Heaven + Earth not only encompasses everything within these sets, but also further develops and upgrades each strand of neigong learned within them. This adds up to a serious amount of internal content&amp;mdash;even before material specific to Heaven + Earth is on the table. These include fundamental techniques like pulsing and developing the macrocosmic and microcosmic orbits of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as Heaven + Earth is a two-part, single exercise rather than a set of five, six or seven movements (like the other core practices in our system), its simplistic format encourages the internal rather than external focus needed to train deeper, more sophisticated neigong methods.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The excerpt above is from Paul&#39;s Inner Quest Newsletter, a monthly publication I highly recommend. Each month he writes in depth about a different aspect of learning and training neigong. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p5x7/&#34;&gt;You can download a free sample issue here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refining Your Opening and Closing</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 07:00:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I remember the first time I really got a sense for &#34;opening and closing&#34; my joints. We were on a qigong retreat and the person who was helping me probably spent 20 minutes &#34;pulsing&#34; my wrist, so that the fluids in the joint were moving in a smooth, even way, alternately creating more and less space between the bones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you pulse, you&#39;re manipulating the fluid flows inside your body so that the spaces inside your body compress and expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this is certainly not the normal way that we think about movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are trained in the &#34;pulleys and levers&#34; way of thinking. Contract this muscle to bend this joint (This is the logical conclusion of understanding movement based on dissection. When you cut back the skin and see muscles attached to bones.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you understood the body in terms of flows?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4113&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice opening and closing, you start to understand, on a visceral level, the flows that are constantly at work inside your body (and later you can more easily see them in the world all around you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulsing is a central skill in the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong. &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;In this early episode of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed why pulsing is the bridge to more advanced practice (see part 4 especially).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a more refined sense of how opening and closing works, you can also see the way it is integrated into movement in &lt;a title=&#34;5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/&#34;&gt;this progression of qigong videos.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, though, I want to show you a simple exercise you can use to fine-tune your sensitivity to opening and closing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/-y7o6ddHMCc?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you practice the simple exercise in the video, see if you can sense a similar kind of internal movement going on inside a full-body movement. At first this isn&#39;t easy to detect, but over time, you will become more sensitive to opening and closing on many different levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re curious about how to track opening and closing in more dynamic exercises, &lt;a title=&#34;Circles And Spheres in Qigong, Tai Chi, and Ba Gua&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/circles-and-spheres-in-qigong-tai-chi-and-ba-gua/&#34;&gt;check out this practice video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>