<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>marriage-of-heaven-and-earth on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/marriage-of-heaven-and-earth/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in marriage-of-heaven-and-earth on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/marriage-of-heaven-and-earth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong is Packed with Internal Content</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</guid>
      <description>This summer, Bruce Frantzis will be teaching a Marriage of Heaven and Earth Instructor training. Heaven and Earth was the first instructor training I attended in 2004 and I can still remember what a profound effect learning to &#34;pulse&#34; had on me.
Within the Energy Arts system, Heaven and Earth is considered a bridge from the basic to more advanced practices.
We discussed how Heaven and Earth works in an early episode of Qigong Radio, but I wanted to share this explanation from Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel with you too:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refining Your Opening and Closing</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 07:00:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2012/08/13/refining-your-opening-and-closing/</guid>
      <description>I remember the first time I really got a sense for &#34;opening and closing&#34; my joints. We were on a qigong retreat and the person who was helping me probably spent 20 minutes &#34;pulsing&#34; my wrist, so that the fluids in the joint were moving in a smooth, even way, alternately creating more and less space between the bones.
When you pulse, you&#39;re manipulating the fluid flows inside your body so that the spaces inside your body compress and expand.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>