<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>practice on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/practice/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in practice on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/practice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Returning to an Old, Familiar Practice</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 09:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s easy to get caught in a linear, progress-oriented way of thinking about your practice.
What&#39;s new? What can I learn next? Am I improving...all the time.
You get so caught up in doing it right and refining every little detail that you can lose sight of the what&#39;s really great about practice in the first place...the restoration, integration, and feeling of wholeness you can walk away with each time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaxing Your Feet to Find Your Root</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2014/04/10/relaxing-your-feet-to-find-your-root/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 08:44:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2014/04/10/relaxing-your-feet-to-find-your-root/</guid>
      <description>When you settle into your practice each day, you should always give yourself a couple of minutes to just feel and see where your body, your energy, and your awareness are.
In one sense, each practice session is about bringing the rhythms of each of those into harmony.
That&#39;s why Tai Chi and qigong can be so powerfully restorative.
So, if you take a couple of minutes to just &#34;settle in,&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Yin and Yang of Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/11/08/the-yin-and-yang-of-problem-solving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 09:46:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/11/08/the-yin-and-yang-of-problem-solving/</guid>
      <description>You know how you can be banging your head against a wall, trying to figure something out?
Then, you sleep on it, take a shower, or go for a walk and suddenly a solution pops into your head.
Have you ever wondered why this happens or how it works? So have I...and I don&#39;t know HOW it works, but I do know that we are practicing the exact same skill in qigong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update on Quantity vs. Quality and the Struggle for Perfect Practice</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/06/19/update-on-quantity-vs-quality-and-the-struggle-for-perfect-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 07:32:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/06/19/update-on-quantity-vs-quality-and-the-struggle-for-perfect-practice/</guid>
      <description>A few months ago we talked about the signs of progress in your qigong practice. For so many of us, the issue of &#34;progress&#34; is central to qigong or Tai Chi practice, since we are driven by the desire to get it right, to solve a problem like a health issue, or to reach an amorphous and elusive spiritual goal.
But what if we completely abandoned the idea of outcomes and perfection in practice?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend last night about standing qigong and different meditation traditions that we had both tried.
When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Intrinsic Practice Motivation</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 09:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</guid>
      <description>For the last couple of years, I&#39;ve been teaching regular workshops in Farmington, Maine. When I went up again last week, I had a fascinating conversation with one of the students. She was telling me how the core group had been coming along and that other people have come in and out of practicing with them. She said, &#34;you know, it&#39;s not really for everyone.&#34;
Now, I don&#39;t know if that jumps out at you as a significant statement, but as a Tai Chi teacher, it&#39;s something I&#39;ve been thinking about for years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 09:53:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>I get the question all the time, or at least it&#39;s always implied, &#34;When am I going to get it?&#34; Or, &#34;how do I know if I&#39;m getting good at this?&#34;
Now, let&#39;s unpack a little bit of what&#39;s behind this question and then I want to share some different ways that I think you can answer this question on your own, without even asking your teacher.
Practice Goals
I&#39;m on a training trip this weekend out in New Mexico with Robert Tangora.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>