<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>paul-cavel on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/paul-cavel/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in paul-cavel on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/paul-cavel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Chasing Secrets and Shortcuts in Taoist Energy Arts</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/23/chasing-secrets-and-shortcuts-in-taoist-energy-arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2013 16:19:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/23/chasing-secrets-and-shortcuts-in-taoist-energy-arts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1537&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you set out to learn Taoist Energy Arts like Tai Chi, qigong, or meditation, you come across the lore of masters with supernatural abilities or techniques too deadly to teach openly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or more insidious, we grasp after images of unattainable perfection, always slightly beyond reach, unless we just find the right technique or are initiated into a secret practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even if we&#39;ve given up silly kung fu fantasies of flying through the bamboo reeds, on a subtle level we still chase ideas and dreams that only live in the mental realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality - and I&#39;m not trying to disappoint you, but stay with me because the reality is deeply rewarding, meaningful, and rich too - is that Taoist Energy Arts must be lived-through and practiced-through to be truly discovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Paul Cavel and I explore the disconnect you can sometimes feel in the day-to-day of your practice and the idea of where you ought to be in your practice - it&#39;s not because you must be a chosen one or special to get it, but rather, because you can&#39;t directly perceive or experience energy when you operate solely on the mental realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll give you some guidelines for how to recognize when you slip back into the mental realm of fantasy practice and talk about the struggles, as a student and as a teacher, of communicating your practice experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul also shares specific neigong techniques that will keep you present, engaged, and help you cultivate a direct experience of your natural internal energy, that can be applied to any energy practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn more from Paul about the best way to study Taoist Practices by signing up for his newsletter here (includes a free guide to getting started with Taoist Energy Arts):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;http://forms.aweber.com/form/68/1737149068.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2013 07:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; explains the 3 different layers of neigong practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beginner or Foundational Practices&lt;/strong&gt; -- Dragon and Tiger, Opening the Energy Gates, and Heaven and Earth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intermediate or Power-Production Practices&lt;/strong&gt; -- Spiraling Energy Body and Bend the Bow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced or Integration Practices&lt;/strong&gt; -- Gods Playing in the Clouds&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter  wp-image-4491&#34; alt=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/01/for_danny-1024x483.jpg&#34; width=&#34;717&#34; height=&#34;338&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Paul explains what to focus on at each level and how your learning spiral takes you back through them over time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I found Paul&#39;s explanation of the relationships between the sets particularly useful. Specifically, understanding &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;Energy Gates&lt;/a&gt; as direct preparation for &lt;a title=&#34;Spiraling Energy Body Qigong with Isaac Kamins&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/28/spiraling-energy-body-qigong-with-isaac-kamins/&#34;&gt;Spiraling&lt;/a&gt; -- first you clear the downward flow of chi, then you strengthen the upward flow. Similarly, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/heaven-and-earth/&#34;&gt;Heaven and Earth&lt;/a&gt; you learn to expand the body (through opening/closing the joints and lengthening the soft tissue) before you really go into deep internal compression in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/bend-the-bow/&#34;&gt;Bend the Bow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we discussed the meaning of &#34;integration,&#34; Paul explained how neigong is the basis for Taoist meditation and where neigong shows up inside your meditation practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the episode, we talk about the great training resources available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://paulcavel.com&#34;&gt;PaulCavel.com&lt;/a&gt;, including the Inner Quest Journal (&lt;a title=&#34;Recommended Products&#34; href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p5x7/&#34;&gt;download a free issue here&lt;/a&gt;). If you get the chance, please let Paul know how much we all appreciate the high quality material he is putting out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong is Packed with Internal Content</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:24:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/24/why-the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong-is-packed-with-internal-content/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-4444 alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Paul Cavel performs the Marriage of Heaven and Earth&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/12/qi-gong-class-11.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;250&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This summer, Bruce Frantzis will be teaching a Marriage of Heaven and Earth Instructor training. Heaven and Earth was the first instructor training I attended in 2004 and I can still remember what a profound effect learning to &#34;pulse&#34; had on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the Energy Arts system, Heaven and Earth is considered a bridge from the basic to more advanced practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;how Heaven and Earth works in an early episode of Qigong Radio&lt;/a&gt;, but I wanted to share this explanation from &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; with you too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Heaven + Earth Works On So Many Levels&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As discussed in earlier issues, classically Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body Qigong is the foundation of the entire Water tradition since it initiates all neigong practice through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alignments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sinking chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissolving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bending and stretching techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic breathing methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Circulating chi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaging the kwa as the leader of all motion&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Energy Gates softens the body and prepares the &#34;shell&#34; by creating a containment field with the body and its energy to develop more sophisticated neigong technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas Heaven + Earth takes the baton from Energy Gates and folds in the internal content learned there. So everything you learn and the skill you develop in each qigong system can and should be packed up and shipped off to the next set in the series. Yes, the arrangement will be completely unique, but you don&#39;t throw away or leave dormant any components while developing superior forms. For example, recall that Dragon + Tiger Medical Qigong is one of the three foundational practices in the neigong lattice. Dragon + Tiger&#39;s underlying technology develops the etheric field and wei chi, and thereby serves as a subcomponent of Heaven + Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as a more advanced practice than either Energy Gates or Dragon + Tiger, Heaven + Earth not only encompasses everything within these sets, but also further develops and upgrades each strand of neigong learned within them. This adds up to a serious amount of internal content&amp;mdash;even before material specific to Heaven + Earth is on the table. These include fundamental techniques like pulsing and developing the macrocosmic and microcosmic orbits of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as Heaven + Earth is a two-part, single exercise rather than a set of five, six or seven movements (like the other core practices in our system), its simplistic format encourages the internal rather than external focus needed to train deeper, more sophisticated neigong methods.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The excerpt above is from Paul&#39;s Inner Quest Newsletter, a monthly publication I highly recommend. Each month he writes in depth about a different aspect of learning and training neigong. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p5x7/&#34;&gt;You can download a free sample issue here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More of the Best Qigong on YouTube</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/09/more-of-the-best-qigong-on-youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2012 08:18:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/09/more-of-the-best-qigong-on-youtube/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My friend Jess makes a point of studying with as many different teachers as he can. His goal isn&#39;t to dabble in a lot of different styles or systems. He is faithful and dedicated to his main practice, but he knows that each time he gets exposed to a new system, he learns something about his own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See if you can glean one new thing from each of these qigong videos from YouTube to refine and improve your practice today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you enjoy these videos, you should also check out this article on &lt;a title=&#34;5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/&#34;&gt;5 Important YouTube Qigong Videos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3769&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Practice Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This video is from Taoist Meditation teacher Bruce Frantzis. He discusses the often-overlooked foundation of Taoist meditation: building a strong link between your mind and your body. When you do this, you can run energy through your system in a more stable way, enabling you to go further in your meditation practice. To me, this is a compelling reason to develop your qigong practice. What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;274&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/4MHPc24k0IY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/4MHPc24k0IY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;274&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Build Stability and Structure&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Part of what allows you to build a safe container for moving more and more energy is the actual structure of the movements. In this video, Energy Arts instructor Paul Cavel demonstrates the &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&lt;/a&gt; with clear structure. Pay particular attention to the two main flows of the movement, Heaven-to-Earth and Center-to-Periphery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;274&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/9ZkMwzEsumQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/9ZkMwzEsumQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;274&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Follow Your Energy to Build Flow&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In this last video, which you&#39;ll have to go to YouTube to watch since I can&#39;t embed it, Tai Chi Grandmaster Feng Zhiqiang demonstrates a qigong set where you can see his main emphasis is &lt;strong&gt;feeling and following his own energy&lt;/strong&gt;. Once you&#39;ve trained your structure, doing this kind of practice makes the flows go much deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you watch his qigong practice, here is an example of his Chen Style Tai Chi, so you know that he can manifest very clear structure and form (look at those legs!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fXRDwm0ioX8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fXRDwm0ioX8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, compare that to the qigong set &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-5X5pBx8nUE&#34;&gt;in this YouTube clip&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Qigong Radio Episode 2: Developing Your Soft Tissue with Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/29/qigong-radio-episode-2-developing-your-soft-tissue-with-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2012 06:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/29/qigong-radio-episode-2-developing-your-soft-tissue-with-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft  wp-image-3729&#34; title=&#34;QigongRadio300&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/03/QigongRadio300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;210&#34; height=&#34;210&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In episode 2 of Qigong Radio, I sat down with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel to discuss what it feels like to work with soft tissue -- muscle, fascia, and ligaments -- in the internal arts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed the different stages of practice and one of my favorite topics: adopting the right mindset so that the progress you make in your body isn&#39;t outpaced by what you think you&#39;re doing in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you&#39;ll appreciate the clarity of Paul&#39;s explanations and I want you to know that this topic is a direct reply to feedback I received on &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;Episode 1, about the Marriage of Heaven and Earth&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3707&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Yin and Yang of Learning and Teaching the Internal Arts</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/07/the-yin-and-yang-of-learning-and-teaching-the-internal-arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2012 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/07/the-yin-and-yang-of-learning-and-teaching-the-internal-arts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a guest post from my friend and fellow instructor, Paul Cavel. I asked Paul to talk a little bit about his experience teaching all over Europe and what he&#39;s learned after nearly 20 years doing it. There are some great insights here about the internal energy arts that you can apply to your own practice, whether you teach or not. Take note when he talks about practice mindset!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3549&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1537&#34; title=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been traveling around Europe teaching internal arts in England, France, Germany and Greece since 1995, as well as training with my teacher almost every year in the United States since 1994. Through these experiences, I&#39;ve had the opportunity to meet people of many different backgrounds and observe how cultural influences can give them unique perspectives on most any subject, including their neigong training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, more than any cultural differences, I see that the real challenges come from the Western mindset being so radically different to the Eastern approach. I know for me, as a Westerner learning ancient Eastern arts, the initial hurdle was to figure out the methodology underlying the great content I was training, so I could see the bigger picture--the proverbial light at the end of the tunnel. There are 16 neigong, each with many, many layers of complexity, and dozens of forms to learn in any one system, so understanding how each can be integrated into the whole within the linear Western model for learning can be a bit tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students who achieve real and sustainable results from their practice are those who approach their training with patience, dedication and consistency. Perhaps most importantly, they have the willingness to work towards balance in all aspects of their being, rooting out weaknesses rather than only playing to their strengths--tenants consistent with an Eastern learning strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;East Meets West&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some people approach their practice as though they have &#34;been there, done that,&#34; but from an Eastern perspective, that would be completely missing the point. Instead, it&#39;s about the depth and range of your skill set and how you can apply it in every conceivable way--not just in your practice, but in life. The students who catch onto this style will, over time, automatically weave in mechanics that create flowing forms and circulate blood and chi more profoundly. These are the factors that influence health and well-being, and give the most experienced practitioners the ability to achieve seemingly superhuman results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find a tai chi class in almost every major city across the Western world, but few schools teach the deep internal content that underlies and powers up these forms as originally propagated in the East. Many schools have resorted to a linear teaching style to suit the average Westerner, but the Eastern approach has always been a circular progression: that is you learn a technique and practise it for awhile, developing your skill to the extent you can over several weeks to months. When you reach a plateau and your practice seems to stop evolving, you move on to other techniques, integrating everything you&#39;ve learned within your forms (qigong sets, tai chi styles or bagua palm changes). Later, you return to the original technique, once again singling out that thread and further refining it. Although, upon revisiting the technique, your increased awareness--in body, mind and chi--contributes to an upgrade in your overall understanding and execution of the technique. This circular learning process creates a multiplying, self-sustaining positive feedback loop in your practice and the results you can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Structure-Flow Continuum&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Most students approach their practice from one of two ends of the spectrum: either from the perspective of flow or structure. That is there are those who gravitate towards the integrity of the movement form (i.e. successful execution of component pieces that combine to create a physical form) and others who focus on the flow, or the overall quality of motion within any given form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the point of view of teaching the internal arts, it is helpful to know where a student&#39;s talent lies--either in flow or structure. Initially, using their natural ability, you can focus on that stream of information to help them gain some momentum. Once they gain some skill in that which comes easier for them, then a good teacher will use this momentum to redress the balance by focusing on exercises that will develop the opposite end of the continuum. This approach allows students to see the bigger picture with their talent being the driver of their success. As anyone who trains with an emphasis on internal power development knows, it is the balance between form and flow that is at the crux of all matters relating to how much benefit any one person will get from their practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life as a Traveling Teacher&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Teaching in different cultures for nearly two decades tuned me into the fact that, as a teacher, I cannot be attached to one style or method of presenting material as each culture, city, class, group or individual will have a slightly unique disposition. Although any given culture might be predisposed to start from a particular perspective, the magic of the internal arts is in the details and how they seamlessly integrate with all others. So there really is no starting line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circular progression of learning is about building up and breaking down component pieces in endless weaves and patterns, essentially looking at every possible angle to create a well-integrated, balanced form. This kind of assimilation is what allows students to overcome obstacles and achieve their goals, regardless of where they begin. From the perspective of teaching, I&#39;ve not found anything more rewarding than helping students come to this realization and take on a long-term outlook towards their training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1529&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/strong&gt; is a certified sports massage therapist, personal trainer and senior instructor of internal arts and Taoist meditation master Bruce Frantzis. Since 1987, Paul has studied the Energy Arts System in-depth, including qigong, tai chi, bagua zhang, Longevity Breathing therapy, qigong tui na energy healing and meditation. In 1995, with the encouragement of his teacher, he began offering an integrated health, fitness and stress-management solution to exercise and strengthen the body while releasing blockages -- in mind-body-energy -- that help people realize their true human potential. Find Paul blogging at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/&#34;&gt;www.CircleWalking.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 09:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure you&#39;ve spent time looking around YouTube for qigong and tai chi videos. According to their website, people upload 24 hours of video to YouTube &lt;em&gt;every minute&lt;/em&gt;! No doubt you&#39;ve seen some crazy stuff. So how do you sift through all of it and more importantly, are there any qigong videos on YouTube worth watching?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is, of course there are. And I&#39;ve put together a list of 5 good ones to get you started. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2522&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Practice with YouTube Qigong Videos&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you will see from the videos below, there is a blend of instructional content, guided practice, and demonstration. You have to get creative when you are borrowing from a source like online video to boost your practice. Sometimes you will just do a quick check-in. Sometimes you will sit and watch an entire lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&#39;t recommend trying to do your practice and darting back and forth to the computer at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the video has good audio guidance that can run in the background, great. Otherwise, just watch it once or twice and then go and practice. I&#39;ll try to point out key places in each video where you can see skilled practitioners demonstrating things they aren&#39;t necessarily talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This introduction to standing by Lam Kam Chuen is one of my favorite overviews of the practice. He talks a little bit about the background of the practice and gives just enough instruction to get you started. If you already have a standing practice, it&#39;s worth watching because you can revisit some of the overarching reasons to do this qigong method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/StandStillBeFit&#34;&gt;The entire channel&lt;/a&gt; is worth watching once you&#39;ve gone through the introductory clip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simple Circling Hands&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The natural transition from standing practice is to start repetitive movements. In standing, you tune into internal rhythms that only become obvious because there is no external movement. Circling Hands is a great bridge because your external movements are simple enough that you can let the internal rhythms drive them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch as &lt;a title=&#34;Q&amp;amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; performs Circling Hands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most important thing you can get from this YouTube qigong video is the way his whole body opens and closes, pulsing from the center, outward.&amp;Acirc; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exploring Internal Flows&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the next video, &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt; explains how to activate the two main energy flows that run your body: Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth. He teaches two different exercises to highlight these flows. Like Paul&#39;s demonstration above, if you practice these exercises you will begin to feel the &#34;pulls&#34; through the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth pointing out that while you may or may not be able to feel what he&#39;s describing right away, every teacher I&#39;ve ever had insists that you need to develop the internal sensitivity to these subtle movements through a standing or sitting practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transitioning into More Movement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Each mode of qigong practice gives you access to something different. &#34;Quiet&#34; practices like standing qigong or sitting meditation allow you to develop your internal awareness with as little physical coordination as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving practices do two things: they develop rhythm and they challenge your ability to maintain internal focus because of the ever-changing external conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these next two videos, we&#39;re going to introduce more movement, first by adding weight-shifting and turning, then by looking at the qigong set with the most complicated external form: Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try this &#34;Rolling the Ball&#34; exercise to see if you can maintain some of the internal awareness primed in the earlier qigong videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this last video isn&#39;t designed to be instructional or a follow-along practice. Instead, I want you to watch it and see if you can pick up some of the things we&#39;ve looked at in the other YouTube qigong videos in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see internal continuity? Opening and closing? Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth flows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The secret to training your eyes to see more subtle movement patterns is to look at someone&#39;s movements, in this case Tai Chi master &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, and try to feel inside your own body what he must be doing to create those movements.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this post gives you some ideas about how to use YouTube qigong videos to improve your own practice. Got any favorites that I&#39;ve left out? Be sure to let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 12:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1529&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Paul Cavel is an Energy Arts Senior Instructor based in London. He teaches regular weekly classes there, but he&#39;s also been traveling all over the UK and Europe for years teaching workshops, including annual week-long retreats in Crete. I talked to Paul a little bit about his background in Tai Chi, neigong, and Ba Gua and asked him for some practice advice for a group of students who just completed a series at BTC on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little bit about how you got started studying these arts. Who were some of your first influential teachers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After a motorcycle accident in 1986, I started studying Yang style tai chi to heal my injuries. When the teacher left, the class naturally gravitated towards the Water method neigong practices as taught by my main teacher, Bruce Frantzis. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve been hooked ever since.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1528&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over the last 30 years, Bruce has taught in so many different places and formats. When and how did you first start studying with him?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first encounter with Bruce was in a London seminar on the spiraling energy body. Of course, that material really opened my eyes to what qigong could do! When I subsequently lived with Bruce some years later in 1994-1995, my passion for bagua was ignited in his weekly classes. I got in by the skin of my teeth as one of the last students he let into the class&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Since you&#39;ve studied with Bruce, have you had other influential teachers? Have you studied complementary arts that you bring into your teaching?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve attended the odd seminar with a reputable Chinese master or two, including a couple of months of early morning training in the park with a master in California. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve also attended events hosted by the Tai Chi Union of Great Britain where several teachers offer workshops. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve picked up the odd tidbit here and there from these courses. However, my direction is a product of Bruce&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s mentoring and the desire to follow the tenants of the genuine Water tradition as passed down by him. Bruce is my one and only teacher.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-1537  alignright&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel_SPC&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little bit about your teaching. Do you run regular classes? Workshops? Who are your students?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I teach full-time and offer various teaching formats, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Weekly classes and seminars in Kentish Town, London&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weekend seminars in England and Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weeklong retreats in Greece and Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corporate training and executive coaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private and small group lessons&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have students from all walks of life who practise for a wide variety of reasons. Some are looking for a system to maintain health and wellness while others are professionals who want an edge and/or a means for releasing stress. I also see many Energy Arts instructors who want to prepare for certification trainings or upgrade their practice and understanding of the material.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the three most important points that you would like other instructors to know about regarding your practice or your teaching or your business?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; My practice and my teaching are neigong-based. That is I focus on the strands of neigong that develop the body, chi and mind, and then integrate that material into Circle Walking, bagua, tai chi and meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m based in North London where I offer my full programme. The seminar series and retreats I teach in Europe are designed with a particular focus in mind to help students develop that particular aspect of practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I offer a lot of hands-on personal corrections, partner exercises and component practice sets with a systematic, progressive focus. My aim is to help students solidify their foundation and integrate the deeper aspects of neigong that ultimately intertwine to create the more complex movement forms of bagua and tai chi.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Some of my students have just finished a series on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth, where they learned to open and close the joints of the arms and legs. How should they continue to work on this practice on their own?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have opened up the pulse, the next step is to balance your  system. This is normally done through Circling Hands Qigong, an easy,  repetitive motion that allows the mind to focus on the content rather  that the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through practice of Circling Hands Qigong, the process is simple:  compare the pulse in the joint on the left side to the corresponding  joint on the right side of your body, and make them the same. This is  done by reducing the joint with the larger range to that of the joint  with the smaller range. Go through all the pairs, e.g. hands, feet,  elbows and knees. Next, compare each pair to all other pairs, e.g. hands  to feet, elbows to knees, shoulders to hips, and equalise any  imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reducing your range of motion to the joint with the smallest range, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dramatically soften the pulse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Release the nervous system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deepen the pulse in the joints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link the pulsing of the joints into one unified lattice, thereby amplifying the positive effects of the pulse.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more from Paul on the art of pulsing, check out this two-part series,&amp;Acirc;  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/1469/pulsing-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/1501/pulsing-bagua-zhang/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>