<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pain on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/pain/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in pain on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/pain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Desire Pain as a Tai Chi Exercise</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/01/learning-to-desire-pain-as-a-tai-chi-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 12:41:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/01/learning-to-desire-pain-as-a-tai-chi-exercise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In response to &lt;a title=&#34;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/24/transforming-conflict-with-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, many of you sent me stories of situations where you were forced into a tense encounter and you had to draw on your practice to get you through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After, you feel relief and you can move on, but sometimes the idea slips through that, &#34;hey, I&#39;m a little better able to handle this kind of thing because of the way I faced it.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you actually started to seek out challenging encounters because you sensed their transformative effect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is exactly what psychologists Phil Stutz and Barry Michels teach in their book, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thetoolsbook.com/&#34;&gt;The Tools,&lt;/a&gt; and it has some surprising Tai Chi parallels.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4205&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Watch this short video clip about &#34;The Reversal of Desire&#34; which is their technique for facing pain that will move you out of your comfort zone and into new growth:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/kWZaQgDeHYM?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, by itself, this is a fascinating idea, that you seek out pain as transformation. But as we discussed in the podcast, I want you to go beyond ideas and into practical, physical manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s what&#39;s so exciting about your Tai Chi practice. It&#39;s not a metaphor for transformation. You&#39;re playing with the very material that will shift and change through practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How the Reversal of Desire is like an Interactive Tai Chi Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The steps that the authors teach in their tool are very similar to the physical experience you have in Tai Chi when you neutralize your own fear response and move towards the resolution of a confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s how the tool works just like Tai Chi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, you call out to the pain, you face it. In Tai Chi, the first stage of the encounter is face-to-face and the first hurdle you have to overcome is your impulse to &#34;freeze up&#34; in response to the threat. The connection here is that you literally experience this freezing in the front of your body, like &#34;a deer frozen in the headlights&#34;. Either you activate the front with enough sensitivity to pass to the second step, or you revert to the fear response, which plays out in a yin or yang way: you collapse or you tense up. The tool is similarly training your sensitivity and priming you to move into the encounter.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, you move through a cloud of pain. They want you to feel it all around you. In the Tai Chi encounter, you do something similar. You have to let the other person&#39;s energy move through you (rooting) or past you (neutralizing). In both cases, step two you are completely enveloped by the energy of the threat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the final step of the tool, you visualize being spit out by the cloud of pain and you feel it at your back. In your Tai Chi response, once you can feel your back engaged, loose, flexible, and connected to your root, you have pretty much resolved the incoming threat and your best response arises.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In both cases, stepping up to the encounter without running away and letting it wash through your system, allows you to come out the other side, engaged, connected, and ultimately stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, you are training to allow the most natural response to arise, something you most likely hadn&#39;t planned, ruminated on, or conceived of, but that emerges because of the interaction. You get to a new place, because you have grappled with pain you would have otherwise fled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other tools in the book address different dimensions of the question, &#34;how do I turn my challenges into courage, compassion, and creativity?&#34; There certainly are more parallels to Tai Chi to explore. What sets &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thetoolsbook.com/&#34;&gt;The Tools&lt;/a&gt; apart is the emphasis on teaching exercises that you have to practice over and over again to build new responses. They are not after theoretical understanding, they want to cultivate an embodied response. Sound familiar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are some of the encounters you&#39;ve had lately where your practice either did or did not factor in to how you resolved the situation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p6q5/&#34;&gt;Please take this anonymous, two-minute survey, so that we can how we talk about the potential for Tai Chi to transform conflict. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arm Swing And The Force Transmission Problem</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 08:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of your practice goals should be to be able to make sense of other people&#39;s movement patterns. Learning how to watch someone move, and see what&#39;s going on, is going to give you really valuable information that you can then apply to your own practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following video clip, I demonstrate two different gait patterns, with different arm swings. If you can start to see how the arm swing differs between the two, you&#39;ll start to gain some valuable insight into how to assess and correct your own movement imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the clip and then we&#39;ll look at some of the implications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3165&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said at the beginning of the clip, your body adapts to postural changes instantaneously to find the most efficient way of dissipating force that comes into your skeletal structure. This principle was first explained to me by Dr. Eric Cobb, creator of &lt;a href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13500&#34;&gt;Z Health Performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you can see excessive (or deficient) movement in someone&#39;s whole-body pattern, you can pretty reliably draw the conclusion that they need some isolated movement tune-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But, the site of the abnormal movement is not the problem area.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always remember that principle. Was there something wrong with my left arm in the video clip? No, it started swinging more because the right arm was restricted. We changed the right arm and created excessive swing in the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there is a lot more to be said for how you begin to see the connections and determine what needs to move more or less to make the whole body move more efficiently. For now, though, I want you to try a little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Field Test Your Ability to See&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a title=&#34;APR 092 by chiolachic, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/chio/2432915922/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3091/2432915922_d36e45be2a_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;APR 092&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Brookline Tai Chi is located at mile 23 of the Boston Marathon. People run up and down Beacon Street all day long. As we were working on our ability to see these patterns, a friend and I would sit on the front steps of Brookline Tai Chi to watch runners and walkers come and go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a good spot with lots of running traffic and look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differences in swing between left and right arms from behind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How high each foot comes up behind the body -- can you see the sole of the shoe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Torso rotation -- is it more pronounced to one side?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excessive head movement in any particular direction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Stirring&#34; with the arm -- making a circle out to the side instead of coming straight back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Loops&#34; in the lower leg -- circles instead of straight up and down movement&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The challenge with seeing these patterns is that we very easily integrate this information and experience is as &#34;someone running.&#34; We don&#39;t stop to consciously parse the different parts of their movement. For the most part, it&#39;s a good thing that we take in chunks of information, instead of individual pieces. Think of how daunting it would be to have to record each data point and consciously put it together. You&#39;d never make it down the street!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, if you want to really hone your ability to see, correct, and improve movement patterns, you have to train to break the patterns back down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2012 09:03:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my students says that in medical school they were taught how to explain their clinical observations in a way that made them sound more official. For example, if you see something once, you can say that &#34;in my experience...&#34; The second time you&#39;ve observed the same phenomenon, you can say that &#34;in case after case....&#34; Finally, if you&#39;re seeing something more than two times, you&#39;ve seen it &#34;in a series of cases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, last week, in case after case of neck-related pain and discomfort, the cause of the pain came down to one simple movement principle: substitution.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2949&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In this video, I explain how the nervous system bridges the gap between what you ask your body to do and performing that task by any means it can. Practically, this can result in the wrong body part moving for one that doesn&#39;t respond to the call of the nervous system, or &#34;substitution.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chronic substitution leads to pain, discomfort, and sets the stage for injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Specific Causes of Neck Pain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the case of neck pain, you&#39;ll often see under-performing eyes or stuck vertebrae force the neck into excess movement:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/KsBX4eHvtTo?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/KsBX4eHvtTo?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to avoid these causes of neck pain:&lt;/strong&gt; Tune up your eyes (&lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;try my free visual training course&lt;/a&gt;) and do a full-body movement inventory on a regular basis (&lt;a title=&#34;Recommended Products&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/products/&#34;&gt;check out the Z Health R-Phase set&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2011 08:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frozen shoulder is one of those terms that people accept with resignation and it seems like a plausible explanation...until you start to poke around in your own nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve ever been told you have a frozen shoulder, I urge you to look a little bit beyond the (overly) simple mechanical explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I&#39;m not diagnosing your shoulder from a YouTube video, but I just want you to ask a few more questions and try these two experiments:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2746&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do about a Frozen Shoulder&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you tried the experiments in the video and saw some changes in your shoulder movement, your best bet is to find someone who can assess your movement on a global (whole-body) level. This person, &lt;a title=&#34;Find a Z Health Trainer near you&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=1347&#34;&gt;like a certified Z Health instructor&lt;/a&gt;, for example, will be able to see what body parts are not moving when they should be and which ones are when they shouldn&#39;t be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can alleviate a lot of &#34;frozen&#34; anything in the body with this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&#39;t find an instructor near you, the next best thing is to begin a head-to-toe, full-body mobility program, &lt;strong&gt;focusing on everything else except your frozen shoulder &lt;/strong&gt;(&lt;a title=&#34;Z Health R-Phase Manual and DVD&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13446&#34;&gt;the Z Health R-Phase series is the best way to go about this&lt;/a&gt;). The number one rule you need to follow is &#34;never move into pain.&#34; Instead, you will re-educate your body and all its moving pieces, taking the burden off the parts that are already working too hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairly quickly (like, within a few good training sessions), you will see a change in how you move, 90% of the time. If you keep it up, you&#39;ll prevent further aggravation along these lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few more ideas if you&#39;re looking for other ways to &lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;GET MOVING&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Doctor, A Runner, and A Meditator Walk into A Bar...</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 10:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And they&#39;re all in pain!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the aches and pains of moving around, you might be in pain from your day job, your vigorous exercise routine, or even a mindfulness practice that doesn&#39;t involve any movement. Ever wonder why? &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2285&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is exactly the same in each case: in your pre-conscious mind, you are basically trying to outsource your own movement patterns, from a body part that should be doing the job, to one that&#39;s willing to, even though it isn&#39;t designed for that job!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that doesn&#39;t completely make sense, watch this video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/nFvmbc5At-U?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/nFvmbc5At-U?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those aches and pains might be caused by one big inappropriate act of outsourcing. If you think that&#39;s what&#39;s going on, you should definitely check out the Joint Mobility tips over on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;Get Moving&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Treat Lower Back Pain</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/06/how-to-treat-lower-back-pain/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 09:53:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/06/how-to-treat-lower-back-pain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1672&#34; title=&#34;Lower Back Pain&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/07/shutterstock_2793192-199x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;139&#34; height=&#34;210&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Lower back pain can be a frustrating experience whose source may be hard to pin down and whose remedy may seem elusive. I hope that as you read through this article, you can start to understand the nature of pain a little differently. I&#39;ll also show you some tai chi concepts that can help you unravel your lower back pain, and more importantly, how to search for a solution for your individual situation. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1671&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Do You Define Pain?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to fix something, you have to know what it is, right? When I ask most people to define pain, I usually hear &#34;Pain hurts&#34; or &#34;Pain means I&#39;m injured&#34;. If you think pain means you&#39;re injured, and you&#39;ve tried every possible thing to fix yourself, then you&#39;re setting yourself up for some serious frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at how the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iasp-pain.org/Content/NavigationMenu/GeneralResourceLinks/PainDefinitions/default.htm&#34;&gt;International Society for the Study of Pain&lt;/a&gt; defines pain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;An unpleasant sensory and emotional experience associated with actual or  potential tissue damage, or described in terms of such damage.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Do you see an &#34;equals&#34; sign between pain and injury? Do you even see injury as a necessary part of what creates the experience of pain? The researchers at the forefront of pain science understand that pain is a lot more complex than &#34;I&#39;m broken therefore I hurt&#34;. So let&#39;s break down this complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off we have &#34;unpleasant sensory and emotional experience&#34;. That&#39;s how I feel about my alarm clock when it goes off in the morning. And that&#39;s how you should think about the experience of pain. Your alarm clock is designed to jolt you out of sleep and into action, just like the pain experience. &#34;Hey, you, do something different&#34;. In the case of your alarm clock, it&#39;s because you have to get up and get to work, so why does your body set off an alarm in the case of pain?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, let&#39;s look at part 2: &lt;em&gt;because of actual or potential tissue damage&lt;/em&gt;. Actual or potential. Does that mean you&#39;re already broken? Maybe. But pain can also be an early warning signal, alerting you to a threat, before there is damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &#34;associated&#34; part is interesting too, because, especially in chronic pain situations, you can&#39;t dismiss associations people may have on a lot of different levels -- not just mechanical, but emotional as well. Context and association influence the pain experience. &lt;a href=&#34;http://articles.latimes.com/1991-03-08/local/me-2534_1_back-injury&#34;&gt;The classic example in this case is a 1991 study of Boeing employees, that showed a strong correlation between back pain and job dissatisfaction.&lt;/a&gt; Researchers tried to control for physical and genetic factors and found that the emotional state of employees, both on the job and in their home lives, had a huge impact on whether they reported back pain. Lead researcher Dr. Stanley Bigos, said &#34;people don&#39;t hurt as much if they have something better to do&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My personal pet peeve:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; I just need to point out here that people tend to take the experiential component of pain too far, and write off others in pain by saying &#34;It&#39;s all in your head&#34;. Yes, actually, if you look at it from a neurological point of view, that&#39;s largely true. But I also think it&#39;s an incredible disservice to dismiss the experience of pain for that reason. It&#39;s a gross oversimplification. We&#39;ll do much better to say, &#34;Let&#39;s decode this signal, find out what the signal means, or whether the signaling mechanism itself may even be broken, and get you out of pain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Tai Chi Helps Treat Lower Back Pain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/home.php#!/zhealth&#34;&gt;Z Health&lt;/a&gt; mantra is pain is all about &#34;signals and interpretation&#34;. If you want to get out of pain, you have to understand what the pain signals are trying to tell you and one way to do that is to build up greater context for interpreting them. This is where Tai Chi comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason that Tai Chi is done in slow motion is largely so that you can take the time to feel your way through your own body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/QExDRp6pAjg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;200&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/QExDRp6pAjg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you slow down, and start feeling different moving parts, your brain starts &#34;mapping&#34; your body differently, that is, it devotes more space to each individual part, instead of lumping things together. Why that matters for movement-related pain is that poor differentiation in your movement map means that the wrong body parts are being pulled and moved at the wrong times. Eventually, if your lower back is doing the job your hip joint was designed to do, and you can&#39;t tell the difference, you are going to tweak it. It&#39;s a bit like using a screwdriver to pound in nails, or trying to saw wood with a hammer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice in the video above, all the twisting and turning of the body is done from the hip joints, while the spine stays straight. Tai Chi does this to create very specific internal pressures in more advanced practices, but at the beginning level, it&#39;s a great way to ease up on torquing the lower back, and re-learn how to move from the hips. Before you get into the turning movements, though, you should try this more straightforward (haha!) squatting exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-946 &#34; title=&#34;Downward Phase of Squat&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/05/squat-down-300x215.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Downward Phase of Squat&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;215&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clearer the rotating sensation is in the ball and socket joint of the hip, the better. It should be equally clear on the way up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-947&#34; title=&#34;Rising Up&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/05/rise-up-300x214.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Rising Phase of Squat&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;214&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you learn more tai chi, the pivots, shifts, and turns get more complex, which opens the hips up to a much greater degree. Most of the students I teach, who come in with sedentary 9-5 jobs have completely frozen hips, and they move in a way that substitutes incorrect spinal movement for proper hip movement. When you begin to relearn the correct hip movement, you don&#39;t have to tell yourself &#34;stopping moving your spine wrong&#34;. Instead, with more information to draw on, your body naturally corrects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the moving parts, your bones, joints, tendons, and ligaments are like the factory workers at Boeing. They &#34;don&#39;t hurt as much if they have something better to do&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;For the Astute Reader&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, some of you reading this will probably say, &#34;hey, you gave us this whole rap at the beginning that pain isn&#39;t about tissue damage, it&#39;s about signaling, then you proceed to give us a mechanical solution to lower back pain in the tai chi example. What gives?&#34; Good question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re still operating under the assumption that the source of the pain is not the cause of the pain. This is a pretty radical shift when you think about a typical response to back pain: stretch it out or get surgery. On a mechanical level, you need to understand individual body parts in the context of all the other moving parts in the system. The site of actual tissue damage from repetitive movement only exposes the weak point in the system. &lt;a title=&#34;Frozen Hips Are Too Common, But Avoidable&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/12/frozen-hips-are-too-common-but-avoidable/&#34;&gt;&#34;Frozen hips&#34;&lt;/a&gt; causing knee and back pain is the clearest example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a broader sense, I urge you to make the shift from single-point to contextual thinking about pain. That&#39;s the whole point of the IASP definition above. Yes, there may be mechanical factors, but there may also be emotional factors or other sensory factors that contribute to the pain experience. Your pain experience is a highly individual combination of all of them and ultimately, you have to investigate it for yourself.&amp;Acirc;  At Brookline Tai Chi, we get more and more students referred by physicians for balance and chronic pain issues. The ones who walk in the door thinking that they&#39;ll take a &#34;dose of tai chi&#34; like a pill don&#39;t last very long. On the other hand, the ones who get excited about &lt;em&gt;exploring&lt;/em&gt; tai chi start to develop more and more powerful tools for addressing their chronic conditions. How do you separate the educational component from the therapeutic component in this case? The more we understand pain, the more you realize you don&#39;t have to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8 Reasons You Can&#39;t Get Out of Pain</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/02/8-reasons-you-cant-get-out-of-pain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2011 10:05:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/02/8-reasons-you-cant-get-out-of-pain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-161 alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Neck Pain&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2009/11/shutterstock_1257249-300x199.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Get out of pain!&#34; width=&#34;210&#34; height=&#34;139&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. You&#39;re lazy&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Think about your daily movement patterns. How much variety is there? If you drive to work to sit at a desk and then relax by coming home and watching TV, you&#39;re living your life essentially seated in front of a screen. You need to change up the patterns: stand, run, twist, bend and move, not just your body but your eyes and head too.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1016&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. You eat crap &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;What you eat has an impact on your pain levels from the point of view of your total energy system. If your diet is causing inflammation, you are spending way too much energy on dealing with your food because you&#39;re fighting what you put into your body. Experiment with adding more anti-inflammatory foods into your diet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. You&#39;re an emotional wreck &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Your emotional state impacts your pain levels. If you go around angry, depressed, and upset all the time, you are more likely to be in pain. Put on your favorite music, hang out with friends, laugh and see how even small tweaks can impact your mood and your pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. You have terrible posture &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Chronic postural abnormalities can cause more pain because you&#39;re forcing your body to compensate in ways it&#39;s not designed to do. Don&#39;t think of posture as how you consciously hold your body, though. Posture is the result of how you move, on a sub-conscious level. Go back to point #1. If you don&#39;t have a varied diet of daily movement, your posture will suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. You don&#39;t sleep well &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We tend to underestimate the value of a good night&#39;s sleep. If you have trouble sleeping, you need to spend more time preparing for it each night. You might even need a couple of hours of lead time to begin to wind down. Cut off visual stimulation and find ways to feel your body, not feed your brain.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. You&#39;re stressed out &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Researchers are blaming stress for exacerbating disease left and right. Stress lowers all your defense mechanisms and makes you more susceptible to illness. Pain is not an exception to this phenomenon. Look for ways to eliminate stress.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. You have old injuries &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;I put this way down on the list because most people think &#34;Pain = Injury&#34;. It doesn&#39;t.&amp;Acirc;  The body is really good at shutting down isolated parts to let them heal when the trauma initially occurs. The problem is that there is not reflexive mechanism for opening them back up after. Instead, you accumulate a series of shut down pieces and everything around them works to compensate. Go back and systematically open things up and you will lighten the load on everything else.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. You&#39;re obsessed with being in pain &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Seriously, who reads a list called &#34;8 Reasons You Can&#39;t Get Out of Pain&#34;? The more you are fixated on pain, the more you will be in pain. You become what you practice, so use these tips to practice pain-free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I hope you know from reading this that I&#39;m being a little heavy-handed here. Some of these things apply to you and some do not. The bigger point is that I want you to move away from the notion that &#34;Pain = Broken or Injured&#34;. It really doesn&#39;t. As much as I hate the connotations of saying &#34;pain is all in your head&#34;, from the point of view of your nervous system, it is. That doesn&#39;t mean pain isn&#39;t real. What it does mean though, is that treating pain is about talking to your nervous system (&#34;your head&#34;), not dealing with a specific piece of injured tissue. And you can talk to the nervous system on a lot of different levels. All of the factors outlined above could contribute to the experience of pain -- pain is highly contextual and highly individual. If you really want to get out of pain,stop hunting for the one little broken piece and take a much broader view of your pain experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>