<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>joint-mobility on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/joint-mobility/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in joint-mobility on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/joint-mobility/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic Training: Focus on Your Kwa Squat</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 07:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every six months or so, one of our Senior Instructors at Brookline Tai Chi tells me that he&#39;s had an amazing revelation about how to do the kwa squat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kwa squat is one of the very first things we teach, he&#39;s been doing Tai Chi for 40 years, and he gets new insight into it all the time. Amazing, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tai Chi and Back Pain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the reasons we get so interested in this exercise is its power to relieve pressure on the spine and open up important joints of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, our teacher &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis Tai Chi Resources&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis-tai-chi-resources/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt; explains how Tai Chi works on the spine, including the effects of squatting, tucking, &lt;a title=&#34;My Favorite Breathing Hack&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/30/my-favorite-breathing-hack/&#34;&gt;breathing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;sinking your chi&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a title=&#34;Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/&#34;&gt;Bend the Bow&lt;/a&gt; techniques done in Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/OA6ao4UyiiA?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though there are many different ways to open the spine in Tai Chi, let&#39;s focus on one of the core: &lt;strong&gt;the kwa squat&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a saying in Tai Chi, which surely applies to all arts, that &#34;high level skill is just high level basics.&#34; The deeper you go with the fundamentals, the better you get. So let&#39;s revisit the basics of the kwa squat. Specifically, we&#39;ll look at how this leads to a healthier spine and integrates the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Kwa Squat&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first three levels of using the kwa will get you in the game for the more sophisticated variations you use in Tai Chi. They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Folding the kwa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bending and Stretching from the kwa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pump the kwa&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/gevaFsGiYg0?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we&#39;re not really a squatting culture in the West, most people have a steep motor-learning curve when they try their first kwa squat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our hips tend to be frozen and we&#39;ll jam into the knees to try to lower the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-946 aligncenter&#34; alt=&#34;Downward Phase of Squat&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/05/squat-down-300x215.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;215&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In a proper squat,  the hip joint (green dot) moves back and down, while the knee joint (red dot), rotates in place. You can also track the femur movement (white line). &lt;em&gt;The knee doesn&#39;t move forward in space.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get a feel for the basic version by placing your knees up against the seat of a chair. When you squat, the chair shouldn&#39;t move at all. If you press into the chair, you are pressing into your knees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you will probably feel like you&#39;re sticking your butt out. That&#39;s a good thing for this exercise and it will lead us to a key difference between a Tai Chi kwa squat and the kind of squat you would use to lift heavy weight, like in a deadlift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Tai Chi kwa squat, you keep the spine straight, so the pelvis hangs like an anchor from the bottom of the spine. One of the reasons this is done is to create more space in the lumbar spine. As your sensitivity and control increase in this exercise, you can even begin to use the pulsing of the kwa to create a gentle opening at the sacroiliac joint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; alt=&#34;source: Wikipedia&#34; src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/91/Sacroiliac_joint.svg/500px-Sacroiliac_joint.svg.png&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;188&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Opening the sacroiliac joint makes the connection between the legs and spine much stronger, increases overall flexibility in the hips, and makes your movements much smoother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process of developing this fine motor control, you need to pass through several levels of releasing and relaxing muscles and coordination. For more practice ideas, you might want to review these posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;How to Get More Flexible without Adding Stretching to Your Practice&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/06/how-to-get-more-flexible-without-adding-stretching-to-your-practice/&#34;&gt;How to Get More Flexible without Stretching&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Femur Bone Rhythm&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/femur-bone-rhythm/&#34;&gt;Femur Bone Rhythm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Hip Mobility&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/hip-mobility/&#34;&gt;Hip Mobility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Qigong Radio Episode 2: Developing Your Soft Tissue with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/29/qigong-radio-episode-2-developing-your-soft-tissue-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Developing Soft Tissue in the Internal Arts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you focus on developing this core skill, all the other qigong and Tai Chi movements that you learn are designed to multiply out the benefits. If you skip over the basics, though, the other movements just become fancy hand-waiving. Always revisit your basic training!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arm Swing And The Force Transmission Problem</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 08:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of your practice goals should be to be able to make sense of other people&#39;s movement patterns. Learning how to watch someone move, and see what&#39;s going on, is going to give you really valuable information that you can then apply to your own practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following video clip, I demonstrate two different gait patterns, with different arm swings. If you can start to see how the arm swing differs between the two, you&#39;ll start to gain some valuable insight into how to assess and correct your own movement imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the clip and then we&#39;ll look at some of the implications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3165&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said at the beginning of the clip, your body adapts to postural changes instantaneously to find the most efficient way of dissipating force that comes into your skeletal structure. This principle was first explained to me by Dr. Eric Cobb, creator of &lt;a href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13500&#34;&gt;Z Health Performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you can see excessive (or deficient) movement in someone&#39;s whole-body pattern, you can pretty reliably draw the conclusion that they need some isolated movement tune-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But, the site of the abnormal movement is not the problem area.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always remember that principle. Was there something wrong with my left arm in the video clip? No, it started swinging more because the right arm was restricted. We changed the right arm and created excessive swing in the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there is a lot more to be said for how you begin to see the connections and determine what needs to move more or less to make the whole body move more efficiently. For now, though, I want you to try a little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Field Test Your Ability to See&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a title=&#34;APR 092 by chiolachic, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/chio/2432915922/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3091/2432915922_d36e45be2a_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;APR 092&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Brookline Tai Chi is located at mile 23 of the Boston Marathon. People run up and down Beacon Street all day long. As we were working on our ability to see these patterns, a friend and I would sit on the front steps of Brookline Tai Chi to watch runners and walkers come and go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a good spot with lots of running traffic and look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differences in swing between left and right arms from behind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How high each foot comes up behind the body -- can you see the sole of the shoe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Torso rotation -- is it more pronounced to one side?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excessive head movement in any particular direction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Stirring&#34; with the arm -- making a circle out to the side instead of coming straight back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Loops&#34; in the lower leg -- circles instead of straight up and down movement&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The challenge with seeing these patterns is that we very easily integrate this information and experience is as &#34;someone running.&#34; We don&#39;t stop to consciously parse the different parts of their movement. For the most part, it&#39;s a good thing that we take in chunks of information, instead of individual pieces. Think of how daunting it would be to have to record each data point and consciously put it together. You&#39;d never make it down the street!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, if you want to really hone your ability to see, correct, and improve movement patterns, you have to train to break the patterns back down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Get More Flexible without Adding Stretching to Your Practice </title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/06/how-to-get-more-flexible-without-adding-stretching-to-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/06/how-to-get-more-flexible-without-adding-stretching-to-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve been reading this blog for a while, you know I love a challenging practice problem. One of our Inner Form members wrote to me and said, &#34;I need more flexibility, but I don&#39;t have time to add a whole other stretching routine to my current practice. What can I do?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have good news if you&#39;ve been mulling over a similar practice problem. It all comes down to how you understand flexibility.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3403&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this quick practice video I shot the other morning. You&#39;ll see one way that I blend joint-by-joint mobility, qigong, and Cloud Hands:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/sazLaIUxpbY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/sazLaIUxpbY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Understand the Brakes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Most people think of flexibility as a fixed degree of stretch in your muscles. If you didn&#39;t have a chance to read my recent post on &lt;a title=&#34;What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/&#34;&gt;Frozen Shoulder&lt;/a&gt;, you should go back and check that out. The quick version is that your nervous system will throw the brakes on range of motion any time it perceives a threat to your safety. The problem is not with the particular muscle tissue. You actually have a communication problem going on with the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So you have to find a better way to talk to your nervous system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Z Health, we look at an information hierarchy that governs how your nervous system processes input. The most valuable information comes from the visual system, then your inner ear, and finally from the positional information it gets from where your joints are in space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to assess how your nervous system is integrating these three sources of information and work out the different ways that you are receiving conflicting reports. Confusing information results in the threat level going up and things like range of motion going down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He wrote me asking for a shortcut to flexibility and I&#39;m ready to write a novel about the nervous system. Sorry! Hang in there.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, there is a process you can go through to clear up all the different ways that your nervous system is confused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the flexibility issue specifically, the easiest thing to rule out at first is how all the joints are moving. You&#39;ve heard me say this before, but a head-to-toe scan, mobilizing each and every joint, takes less than 15 minutes, so there&#39;s no reason not to do it. What you&#39;ll discover are &#34;hidden stuck spots&#34; that were impeding range of motion through this whole nervous system confusion process. A joint-by-joint inventory clears them up, your nervous system is able to more smoothly integrate positional information, and as a result it releases the brakes, giving you more range of motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you progress, you work into more complicated positions, test bigger ranges of motion, play with different speeds and expand the range of safe, clean movement your body is comfortable with. In other words, your flexibility increases!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the &#34;morning mobility&#34; video again. &lt;em&gt;What you&#39;re seeing is how I&#39;ve learned to integrate the mobility drills that open me up the most into my warm-ups for Tai Chi practice, without spending tons of time on them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Tutorial on Hip Mobility&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/tutorial-on-hip-mobility/&#34;&gt;In this Inner Form tutorial, I answer Dara&#39;s question about hip flexibility specifically and teach a five-minute mobility practice that he can integrate into his regular Tai Chi practice.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2012 09:03:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my students says that in medical school they were taught how to explain their clinical observations in a way that made them sound more official. For example, if you see something once, you can say that &#34;in my experience...&#34; The second time you&#39;ve observed the same phenomenon, you can say that &#34;in case after case....&#34; Finally, if you&#39;re seeing something more than two times, you&#39;ve seen it &#34;in a series of cases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, last week, in case after case of neck-related pain and discomfort, the cause of the pain came down to one simple movement principle: substitution.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2949&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In this video, I explain how the nervous system bridges the gap between what you ask your body to do and performing that task by any means it can. Practically, this can result in the wrong body part moving for one that doesn&#39;t respond to the call of the nervous system, or &#34;substitution.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chronic substitution leads to pain, discomfort, and sets the stage for injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Specific Causes of Neck Pain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the case of neck pain, you&#39;ll often see under-performing eyes or stuck vertebrae force the neck into excess movement:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/KsBX4eHvtTo?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/KsBX4eHvtTo?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to avoid these causes of neck pain:&lt;/strong&gt; Tune up your eyes (&lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;try my free visual training course&lt;/a&gt;) and do a full-body movement inventory on a regular basis (&lt;a title=&#34;Recommended Products&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/products/&#34;&gt;check out the Z Health R-Phase set&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2011 08:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frozen shoulder is one of those terms that people accept with resignation and it seems like a plausible explanation...until you start to poke around in your own nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve ever been told you have a frozen shoulder, I urge you to look a little bit beyond the (overly) simple mechanical explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I&#39;m not diagnosing your shoulder from a YouTube video, but I just want you to ask a few more questions and try these two experiments:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2746&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do about a Frozen Shoulder&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you tried the experiments in the video and saw some changes in your shoulder movement, your best bet is to find someone who can assess your movement on a global (whole-body) level. This person, &lt;a title=&#34;Find a Z Health Trainer near you&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=1347&#34;&gt;like a certified Z Health instructor&lt;/a&gt;, for example, will be able to see what body parts are not moving when they should be and which ones are when they shouldn&#39;t be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can alleviate a lot of &#34;frozen&#34; anything in the body with this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&#39;t find an instructor near you, the next best thing is to begin a head-to-toe, full-body mobility program, &lt;strong&gt;focusing on everything else except your frozen shoulder &lt;/strong&gt;(&lt;a title=&#34;Z Health R-Phase Manual and DVD&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13446&#34;&gt;the Z Health R-Phase series is the best way to go about this&lt;/a&gt;). The number one rule you need to follow is &#34;never move into pain.&#34; Instead, you will re-educate your body and all its moving pieces, taking the burden off the parts that are already working too hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairly quickly (like, within a few good training sessions), you will see a change in how you move, 90% of the time. If you keep it up, you&#39;ll prevent further aggravation along these lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few more ideas if you&#39;re looking for other ways to &lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;GET MOVING&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Z Health Exercises for Stiff Joints in the Morning</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2011 08:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In just ten minutes of head-to-toe movement, you can get rid of stiff joints in the morning. What&#39;s the secret? There isn&#39;t one really...you just have to move every single joint. Z Health exercises for joint mobility give you an easy template to use to get this done, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this example of head-to-toe joint mobility: &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2581&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jCUM8kZ-etY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jCUM8kZ-etY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The metronome-like quality of the music got me. Sorry! You know why I like &lt;a title=&#34;Metronome Mobility&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/14/metronome-mobility/&#34;&gt;metronomes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you do a mobility flow like this, with the goal of loosening up your stiff joints, especially first thing in the morning, you want to follow these movement principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Movement Rules for Getting Rid of Stiff Joints in the Morning:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move Every Joint with Precision&lt;/strong&gt;: In the video above, I started with the fingers and worked back toward the spine, then down through the lower body. Each Z Health exercise is designed to target a specific joint. As much as possible, the rest of the body remains still while you isolate an individual joint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build Towards Flow:&amp;Acirc;  &lt;/strong&gt;When you&#39;re mastering the movement of any one joint, you&#39;ll start with straight-line movement, then do circles, and then progress to more flowing figure-8&#39;s. It&#39;s important to work in that order, because the linear movement almost always reveals places where you haven&#39;t developed good conscious control. You never find these places if you skip to figure-8&#39;s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never Move Into Pain: &lt;/strong&gt;Especially if you feel stiff in the morning, you might confuse &#34;waking up&#34; with &#34;being in pain.&#34; Never take yourself into painful ranges of motion. Instead, as you loosen up, your range of motion will increase. It&#39;s not unusual to notice a difference between the first and the third repetition in this regard. Remember: &lt;em&gt;being in pain will not alleviate your stiff joints&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With a morning mobility warm-up like this, you&#39;ll find yourself looser,&amp;Acirc;  more tuned-in to your body and ready to get moving. I often use the discipline of moving each body part head-to-toe as a way to trick myself into practicing more in-depth work when I&#39;m not really in the right frame of mind. Have you ever done that? Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Doctor, A Runner, and A Meditator Walk into A Bar...</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 10:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/14/a-doctor-a-runner-and-a-meditator-walk-into-a-bar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And they&#39;re all in pain!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the aches and pains of moving around, you might be in pain from your day job, your vigorous exercise routine, or even a mindfulness practice that doesn&#39;t involve any movement. Ever wonder why? &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2285&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is exactly the same in each case: in your pre-conscious mind, you are basically trying to outsource your own movement patterns, from a body part that should be doing the job, to one that&#39;s willing to, even though it isn&#39;t designed for that job!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that doesn&#39;t completely make sense, watch this video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/nFvmbc5At-U?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/nFvmbc5At-U?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those aches and pains might be caused by one big inappropriate act of outsourcing. If you think that&#39;s what&#39;s going on, you should definitely check out the Joint Mobility tips over on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;Get Moving&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frozen Hips Are Too Common, But Avoidable</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/12/frozen-hips-are-too-common-but-avoidable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2011 08:35:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/12/frozen-hips-are-too-common-but-avoidable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; We&#39;ve just released a new video-based course that shows you how to loosen up your hips and become stronger and more flexible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[CSSBUTTON target=&#34;/fix-your-frozen-hips/&#34; color=&#34;66ff33&#34;]Check It Out[/CSSBUTTON]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original Post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know the weather is getting warmer, but as I look around, all I see are frozen hips. We just aren&#39;t a squatting culture. We sit in chair, couches, cars. Look around the room you are in right now and see how all the furniture is designed. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1381&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything i&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1672&#34; title=&#34;Lower Back Pain&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/07/shutterstock_2793192-199x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;199&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;s likely at an altitude that encourages sitting, right? Well the problem with that is if you sit all the time, you are really under-utilizing the movement of the ball and socket joint in your hips. When the hip joint freezes up, your body starts to treat the thigh and the pelvis as a unit. If they move as a unit, instead of as a ball and socket articulation, your knee joint or your spine has to compensate. What happens when your spine starts acting like a ball and socket joint? It gets twisted, contorted and jammed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is often a major reason people experience lower back pain. Lower back pain can be a frustrating experience whose source may be hard to pin down and whose remedy may seem elusive. But, if you start to understand pain a little differently and work with some core tai chi concepts, you can start to unravel your lower back pain. &lt;a title=&#34;How to Treat Lower Back Pain&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/06/how-to-treat-lower-back-pain/&#34;&gt;Read more about treating lower back pain here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Avoid Frozen Hips in the First Place&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to avoid frozen hips, here are some really simple mobility exercises you can do to remind your body to use the ball and socket action: &lt;a title=&#34;Fix Your Frozen Hips&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/fix-your-frozen-hips/&#34;&gt;Hip Mobility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>