<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/energy/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/energy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Embrace the Cold to Feel Your Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/07/embrace-the-cold-to-feel-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 08:48:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/07/embrace-the-cold-to-feel-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2014/03/iStock_000034767246Small-291x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Winter tree in the mountains&#34; width=&#34;291&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-5018&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been such a cold winter in the Northeastern US this year, that even Niagara Falls has frozen over. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every night, students come in to class shivering, that is, once they&#39;ve resolved to venture out in the cold and the dark. And many haven&#39;t even been up for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I want to tell you about an important practice lesson you can learn from all this cold. You will develop a better feel for the chi of your etheric body and stay warmer in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, when you step out into frigid temperatures, your reaction is to tense up, contract your body, and shiver to keep warm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should do the opposite. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a short qigong practice you can use to relax, warm-up, and even improve your sensitivity to the energy that runs your physical body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embrace the Cold&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand, with your arms by your sides, legs relaxed and weight balanced through the feet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the cold air around you and how it&#39;s making contact with your body, through all your layers of clothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice any reaction to contract or withdraw.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gently, from the outer edges of the body, expand to meet the cold, reversing the tendency to tense up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the contact between your body and the cold air around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With time, expand the mind into the space around the body, feeling out into the cold, as if you were sensing for temperature. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when we tell people to extend their minds beyond their bodies, that can often seem strange, esoteric, or even impossible, but we do this naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt someone walk up behind you? Can you feel the heat without touching the fire? I hope so!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to sense the chi in your etheric field requires the same kind of sensory activation that you use for many mundane activities. When you embrace this winter&#39;s cold, you have another great opportunity to enhance your senses and expand your awareness of chi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kilimanjaro Made Easy</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 10:05:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2151&#34; title=&#34;Jen on Kilimanjaro&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/09/P1010499-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;Z-Health Master Trainer Jen Waak is a self-described &#34;recovering management consultant&#34;. These days, she helps other &#34;Keyboard Athletes&#34; improve and maintain their bodies and stay healthy even when they&#39;re stuck behind a desk all day. What surprised me about reading Jen&#39;s advice on &#34;what you should do at your desk&#34;, was that it sounded a lot like what she did last year to get ready for a climb up Mount Kilimanjaro.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1999&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here&#39;s what Jen had to say about her prep and training:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It was a year ago today that I left to climb Kilimanjaro. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m not a climber, I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t camp, and I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t like the cold. So why I thought this was a good idea I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll never know. I just knew it was something I needed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I got over the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what have I done?&#34; stage, it was time to start figuring out what it would take to summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I started researching the trip, and here is what I learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;40% of climbers don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t make the summit, and the vast majority of the succumb to hypoxia (altitude sickness) since a summit of 19,340 feet means there is about half of the oxygen at the summit than there is at sea level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was going to be traveling ~60 very hilly miles on foot over 9 days. No one day was going to be the gotcha &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; instead it was going to be the accumulated miles that would wear down my body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being comfortable in your gear is critically important since what you have with you is, well, what you have with you. And there&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s nothing like getting blisters and only 59 more miles to go.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In a situation like this, it would be really easy to get freaked out and not know where to start. But, using a framework I call the Energy Bank, I was able to fairly easily come up with a extremely doable training plan that made summiting downright easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Energy Bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Energy Bank is this idea that we all have a finite amount of energy to get through the day, and everything we do during the day &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; everything &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; either adds to or depletes our bank balance: the lighting in the room, your breathing patterns, the horrible morning commute, your uncomfortable desk chair, and that grande burrito you had for lunch. It all has an impact. And just like a bank balance the higher the average balance, the larger the margin of error before going bankrupt. As you can imagine, a large margin of error will serve someone well when attempting one of the Seven Summits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my goal in preparing for Kilimanjaro was to get my Energy Bank Balance high enough so that the trip wouldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t run the balance down to zero &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; focusing specifically on what I would encounter on the trip that would be more likely to result in large withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training for the Climb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Breathing:&lt;/strong&gt; I knew this was already a weak link for me - and given that it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s also the downfall of most climbers, this became my #1 priority. My first goal was to fix my breathing patterns at sea level during everyday activities. Once I had that mastered, I went on to practicing my breathing while in oxygen debt (as ultimately that was what I would encounter on Kilimanjaro). Since I live at sea level, I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t truly replicate the conditions on Kilimanjaro, but instead would sprint or run stairs and focus on my breathing during and after those activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision:&lt;/strong&gt; Another one of my weak links, I spent a great deal of time working on my visual skills. My depth perception isn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t great, which translates into me being tentative going down stairs. Since I had to travel 60 miles over hilly terrain, not being comfortable going up and down was going to be a BIG problem. So, I incorporated some basic convergence drills into my training so my eyes could re-learn to focus and my brain would re-learn depth perception. Like my breathing, first I worked on this during everyday activities, and then I moved on to working it into my running stairs, long hikes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Endurance:&lt;/strong&gt; Going and going over 9 days on rough terrain was something I didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have any experience in. Using the Energy Bank concept, I realized that if my body was already somewhat adapted to that it would be a lot easier. But, with a hectic schedule and living in the city, I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t exactly take off for 9 days to climb in the Cascades. Instead, I got the idea that if fatigued my legs the night before a long hike with either a run or stair session, that I would begin the adaptation process of going long distances on tired legs. So, I would either do a long stair session or a run one night and then the next morning go and hike 10+ miles with a 3,000 foot elevation gain (since that would most replicate the conditions I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d find on Kilimanjaro). I got in probably 3 or 4 of these back-to-back training sessions prior to Kilimanjaro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gear:&lt;/strong&gt; Remember that part where I said I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t climb or camp? Yeah, that meant that I had a buy and test a TON of gear for the trip. In the weeks leading up to the climb my week would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on a hike, discover I didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have the right gear (either through blisters, sweating sunscreen into my eyes, or dealing with lots of bugs. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d come home and take notes on what worked and what didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to REI and pick up what I was missing (and just cover my eyes while signing the credit card receipt)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on another hike and re-assess. Lather, rinse, repeat until I knew I had what I needed.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overkill? Maybe. But I had no blisters, no chafing, and at no point did I say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I wish I would have brought&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;Acirc;  Everything got tested on at least one 10+ mile hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery:&lt;/strong&gt; Early on in my physical training I got a bit ambitious and decided to run 4 miles down a mountain. That turned out to be one of the less bright things I could have done, as I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t go up and down stairs for several days after that. But it also highlighted something I hadn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t considered &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; that I could get sore. A phone call to fellow Master Trainer and endurance athlete Shannon Mauck revealed the world of recovery drinks to me. Yet another thing for me to test &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I needed to find something that I both liked the taste of and that would agree with my system. (Turns out I really like Accelerade.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did it Work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d have to give the entire experiment an unqualified, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;hell, yeah.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;Acirc;  My training wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t extreme &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I did 6 long hikes and then a couple of hours of running, sprinting, and stairs per week. I worked on my breathing and vision for a few minutes a day, and made a point of incorporating that practice while on my long hikes. And the entire trip up the mountain was a piece of cake for me &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d get into camp each night with extra energy to burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The biggest surprise:&lt;/strong&gt; The mental shift in who I am. I grew up a really sick little kid, and had never considered myself an athlete. And now I had accomplished that thousands of people cannot each year. I had to redefine who I am, and now think of myself as an athlete. Because everything is a skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you liked the way she managed her mountain climbing training, you&#39;ll definitely be interested in her insight into bringing more energy into your daily life: &lt;a href=&#34;http://keyboardathletes.com/yourenergybank/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Increase Your Energy Bank Balance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing the &#34;Foundations of Relaxation&#34; Series</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2011 07:48:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a tai chi teacher and movement coach, I get to meet a lot of people who want to relax, slow down and have more energy for the things they love to do in life.  But there&#39;s a very common misconception that I encounter and I think it leads people to spend too much time chasing the wrong things when it comes to a relaxation practice.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-606&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Hopefully, this series will begin to clarify what the best way to start a relaxation practice is and how to most efficiently get the results you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the big mistake: people think that lots of hand-waving choreography, preferably done in a pristine setting, often to calming music, is the best way to become more relaxed. They&#39;re wrong. It&#39;s the best way to have a temporary escape from 24/7 habits that are creating more stress in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that you can change these underlying habits. Even though they are pre-conscious, you can learn to recognize them, test them, and alter them. And I can show you how that all works. This series will save you a lot of time and money to seeking me out in person, or wasting time on the wrong things with another qualified instructor. You can make major progress on your own, if you focus on three areas that I&#39;ll tell you about below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am putting together home-study courses for each of these areas, because they are subjects where you can make progress on your own, without the close guidance of an instructor, once you have the right information and a good practice system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can boost your energy, save a lot of discomfort, and begin the process of moving through life more gracefully, if you focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You See&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-610&#34; title=&#34;Your Picture May Be Fuzzy&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/02/TV-Snow-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Your Picture May Be Fuzzy&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How you see the world may be a little distorted. The eyes, or more accurately, vision governs how you interpret the physical space around you and how you respond to it (i.e. your posture and balance) way more than most people realize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we think of &#34;seeing&#34; something, we see it or we don&#39;t. Vision is a much more comprehensive, integrative act. In other words, seeing is what your eyes do mechanically, but vision is how your brain interprets the world coming at you. And your body reacts to that interpretation constantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these reactions and relationships are rooted in evolutionary survival mechanics, buried deep in your pre-conscious mind. But don&#39;t worry, there are some really clear ways to test how your body and eyes are working together and demonstrate clearly when the picture is fuzzy, even if you don&#39;t realize it right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest benefit of improving your visual skills is that, when your brain gets more information, it can react more efficiently. A small eye movement will replace a big body movement and simply put, to get from A to B will take less energy, so you&#39;ll have more energy to spend on something else or you&#39;ll get there faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 6-week course, you&#39;ll learn how to systematically test and observe what your body is doing subconsciously and improve how your brain interprets visual information. As your visual skills improve, your body will literally recalibrate how it moves through space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You Breathe&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-611&#34; title=&#34;Try Breathing through a Straw&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/02/Snorkel-201x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Try Breathing through a Straw&#34; width=&#34;201&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next area that I wish every single person would work on before they come see me is their breathing. Poor breathing dramatically reduces your energy level, encourages you to stay stressed out, and even impacts your mood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t believe me? Try walking around for the rest of your day today breathing only out of a straw. See how much energy you have for even the simplest things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a cultural level, our largely sedentary lifestyle has a direct impact on our breathing mechanism. See, good breathing is all about fully activating the diaphragm, creating a vacuum effect that fills the lungs and simultaneously pressurizes the abdomen, massaging the internal organs. In slumped seated posture, you limit the movement of the diaphragm. And no, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;good posture&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; with shoulders back and chest up doesn&#39;t fix the breathing problem. In fact, the way most people hold &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;good posture&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; makes the breathing problem worse --- they are trying to fill the lungs by expanding the chest to create more volume. Not only is this less effective than diaphragmatic breathing, but it actually mimics hyperventilation and triggers a stress response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to break the stress cycle and give yourself an internal tune up, is to learn the proper way to breath with the diaphragm and develop a consistent practice. Information alone doesn&#39;t do you any good...you have to be smart about making new habits. In the course, I will teach you how to do both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You Walk&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-612&#34; title=&#34;Bricks&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/02/bricks-300x229.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bricks&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;229&#34; /&gt;When you teach movement 3-4 hours a day, you get to see a lot of different people&#39;s ingrained movement patterns and there are some striking common themes. Most people who want to learn tai chi, for example, begin by moving in exactly the opposite way prescribed by the Tai Chi Classics. In the Classics it says &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the movements should start in the feet, be powered by the legs, steered by the waist and expressed in the hands.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Instead, everything is about leading from the upper body, with little to no connection to the legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it&#39;s no coincidence that there is an abundance of back pain, knee injuries and general inability move around freely in our culture, right? Right......&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say it all starts in the feet. Try walking around with heavy bricks as feet and see how that feels. Maybe you feel a pinch in your hip right away, or a tug on the back. Maybe you&#39;re lucky enough to feel a crick all the way up in your neck. Lucky indeed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;feet&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; course, I will teach you how to open your feet again, even if you think your feet are too flat to work right or your hips are too stiff. &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;But I have these little plastic things that I put in my shoes....&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Ok, if I told you to wear a full-body cast for the rest of your life because your aches and pains mean all those parts weren&#39;t supposed to be moving around, would you take me up on that offer? I&#39;m not knocking some foot support, but if you&#39;ve read this far, I think you know that I&#39;m focused on helping you change movement habits to have more energy and less pain. Immobile feet are part of a movement habit....and re-mobilizing the tiny little bones in your feet is an important new project for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll learn how to re-awaken the feet with self-massage and mobility exercises that will have you moving lighter, faster, and with a better bounce in your step. Just like the other courses in this series, everything is laid out in a 6-week format that blends learning new concepts gradually with systematic follow-up practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my teachers, Dr. Eric Cobb always says, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the body you have is the one you&#39;ve earned through how you move.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; In these courses, I will teach you how to move differently in order to feel differently. Most people will never realize the degree to which their pre-conscious patterns are impacting how they go through their day, but you&#39;ll be tuned in to a whole different set of signs that will help you: cultivate more energy, move with more ease, and have less pain.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>