<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>robert-tangora on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/robert-tangora/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in robert-tangora on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/robert-tangora/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi for Self Massage of Your Internal Organs</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/01/tai-chi-for-self-massage-of-your-internal-organs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 07:25:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/01/tai-chi-for-self-massage-of-your-internal-organs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most people are familiar with the benefits of basic Tai Chi: relaxation, better balance, relief from stiff joints. As you get more internally connected and learn to listen to the inside of your body as you practice, there are whole other layers of benefits, hidden beneath the surface of the graceful, flowing movements typically associated with Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this video, Robert Tangora explains one of the more interesting ones, that is rarely taught with the precision he is outlining: how to use specific Tai Chi movements to target and massage individual organs in your body, like your liver, spleen, heart, and lungs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/7a9MZIXYsu4?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you&#39;ve watched the video and understand some of the basic principles, let&#39;s discuss what you need to do to prepare for this level of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Internal Lengthening&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First of all, if you think in terms of &#34;stretching&#34; from a Western, muscle-based approach to movement, the whole idea of massaging your internal organs through movement is ridiculous. You can&#39;t fit the concept into that paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, Tai Chi relies on &#34;lengthening&#34; the soft tissues of the body, essentially releasing to create movement. If you adopt this approach, then as the limbs are lengthened away from the body, you actually feel more space being created inside the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tai Chi, this starts with the principle of &#34;elbows away from the spine,&#34; where you sink the elbows down, pulling the tips toward the floor and away from your body simultaneously. It&#39;s all done gently, so that the soft tissue of the shoulders and upper back are elongated. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, this feeling travels through the whole back, connected the arm movements to the hips. Finally, as Robert mentions in the video, you practice with the intent of connecting the entire body to the feet. Every inch of the body is lengthened out, like smoothing out the wrinkles on a bed sheet, and pulled towards the feet, so that the power of the body is unified and grounded at the same time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Opening and Closing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Another dimension of Tai Chi movement that doesn&#39;t square with the typical Western movement paradigm is the method of &#34;opening and closing&#34; the body. Instead of pulleys and levers, Tai Chi treats the body as a series of interconnected fluid pumps. The hydraulic power of these pumps is what creates strength in Tai Chi, but on the outside it looks like relaxation, because everything remains smooth and fluid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin activating these pumps, you learn a basic &#34;bend and stretch&#34; rhythm in your form. Following a simple cadence, you alternately bend all the limbs, and then stretch them back out, working to synchronize their movement as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the rhythm become smoother, you tune into the joints themselves and feel how Tai Chi movements can compress and release all your joints through the alternating bend and stretch. The pumping of the joints lubricates them and leaves your muscles feeling relaxed and loose too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refining the opening and closing of the joints also makes you aware of other space inside the body that can open and close as well. Working to unify the shrinking and expanding of every space you can feel inside your body in harmony is a challenging practice, both physically, energetically, and in terms of what you are asking your feeling awareness to do. Training your awareness to move in continuous, circular waves can be as calming for the mind as pumping the joints is for your body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of organ massage, the first step is to develop the ability to feel your entire abdomen opening and closing in sync with the openings and closings of the rest of the body. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Precise Targeting&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Next, you need to learn to &#34;listen&#34; to the way that different movements work back into your body at different vectors. Every angle of the arms and legs relative to the spine creates different pulls and forces that have the potential to create healthy pressures inside your body. The opposite is to tug and pull in a harmful way through over-extending, which is why you need to develop internal sensitivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three main ways to develop the right kind of precision with your internal sensitivity. Usually, just repeating your Tai Chi form won&#39;t get you there. There are too many changes, too quickly, for  you to be able to pay attention the right way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you can build precise internal listening through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standing Postures:&lt;/strong&gt; all you do is focus on the waves of your mind, your energy, and shifting body alignments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repetitive Movement Drills:&lt;/strong&gt; every Tai Chi form has movements that repeat like Brush Knee Twist Step or Parting Wild Horse&#39;s Mane, which can be chained together and repeated so that you can tune into their unique patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two-Person Exercises:&lt;/strong&gt; Co-operative partner exercises and martial applications teach you about precise alignment and internal connection, because if you&#39;re off, they don&#39;t work&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whichever method you use, you are learning to dial in deeper and deeper connection, while shedding excessive effort. Over time, small tweaks to your stance, awareness, or energy will reflect through your whole system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Knitting the Pieces Together&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Generating internal organ massage in a sophisticated Tai Chi technique. You should be comfortable performing all three of the skills above before you even attempt it. Honestly, it won&#39;t make much sense otherwise and you&#39;ll probably trick yourself into thinking that clenching and relaxing your abdomen is organ massage. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you do get a sense for the length, pumps, and vectors, this exercise can be incredibly energizing. By releasing the space in your abdomen and smoothly moving pressures through the whole cavity, you free lots of bound energy. You finish your practice feeling relaxed and refreshed on a deep level.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master Wang Hao Da on Zhong Ding or Central Equilibrium</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/31/master-wang-hao-da-on-zhong-ding-or-central-equilibrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 06:57:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/31/master-wang-hao-da-on-zhong-ding-or-central-equilibrium/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In issue 48 of Qi Magazine, there is an article about Wu Style Tai Chi Master Wang Hao Da. The article describes Master Wang&#39;s early training and his desire to interact with as many different people as possible to refine his art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The description of Zhong Ding, or Central Equilibrium, drawn from the article, explains much of what organized Master Wang&#39;s teaching and personal practice, as described to me by one of my teachers, &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi Instructor Robert Tangora&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: Arial; font-size: small;&#34;&gt;Correct central equilibrium {Zhong Ding} is the basis for everything else in Taijiquan. One must focus with their complete intention {Yi} to differentiate that which is external and separate from one&#39;s centre. The centre is the key; it must remain straight and hidden, concentrated, deep inside the body constantly changing, spiraling into the earth for the most part. One must gather all the Qi {energy} to your centre. It is this structure that is the basis for internal power {Nei Jing} or Zhong Ding Jing, and essential for good health and longevity. The Dantien {lower abdomen} is alive! Not only does the Dantien push down inside the open hips but also it turns, spirals, bounces, and shoots; inside the structure is always full, always condensed. When you play the Taiji form you are performing the interaction of your Zhong Ding and Dantien. This hidden internal play moves the outside, not necessarily the entire body like a single lump of wood, rather by gathering everything to your centre, your outside body follows the direction of this internal command. It is because your inside works so intensively that you receive the health benefit of Taiji. If one only works externally and has strong skin and muscles but weak organs, vessels, and bones, then the outside may thrive while internally you are dying.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can read the full article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.susanamatthews.com/GeorgeXu/Wang%20Hao%20Da%20Article.htm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you understand the importance Master Wang placed on Zhong Ding, you can begin to understand the nature of his unique-looking form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/9QqUGNjMuZw?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sharp bursts sprinkled throughout the form are caused by the sudden release of energy from his Zhong Ding. The rest of the time he is actively gathering into the Zhong Ding, focusing his mind there and letting all the physical movement feed the sense of gathering and storing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked on &lt;a title=&#34;Exercises from The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/09/exercises-from-the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands/&#34;&gt;a basic version of this exercise&lt;/a&gt; in preparation for Tai Chi Cloud Hands.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Cloud Hands Fall Workshop</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 17:31:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4081&#34; title=&#34;Robert Tangora Tai Chi Cloud Hands&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/07/DSC_0067-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are in the process of finalizing the details of a Tai Chi Cloud Hands workshop with Robert Tangora this fall in Boston, from October 26-28.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As preparation for the workshop, I will be teaching a fall course at Brookline Tai Chi, covering the basic mechanics of Cloud Hands, as well as the prep exercises from Robert&#39;s newly published book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m really looking forward to taking everyone at Brookline Tai Chi through these exercises and at the same time, working with members of the Inner Form coaching program to improve their Cloud Hands practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4080&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, I just shared a 25-minute follow-along practice mp3 with the Inner Form members, guiding them through a set of Cloud Hands prep exercises. This is the same kind of coaching I give people in live classes each week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more it amazes me just how many different ways we are able to refine and improve qigong and Tai Chi practice. Of course, people have been teaching themselves the basics from books for years, but I think we&#39;ve entered age where getting feedback and guidance remotely is getting much more sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, there are elements of the practice that will only be transmitted in person, but think of how much more we are able to share this way, through video, audio, email, and written discussion -- across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It amazes me that people continue to find this site, reach out, and connect with each other about something so personal, so individual, and so fundamental to their sense of well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And I&#39;m grateful that I get to share in that with all of you!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, ok, so back to the workshop announcement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&#39;re in Boston and you want to prep for Tai Chi Cloud Hands with Robert Tangora in October, be sure you&#39;re on &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/contact-us/chi-mail&#34;&gt;the Brookline Tai Chi mailing list&lt;/a&gt; when we announce the new course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you plan to come to Boston for the workshop, you should probably join &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/contact-us/chi-mail&#34;&gt;the BTC email list too&lt;/a&gt;, so you&#39;ll get all the details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&#39;re already a member of the Inner Form section of this site, be sure to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/forum/cloud-hands-challenge/prep-exercises-mp3/&#34;&gt;download your practice mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a Tai Chi practice (budding or established) and you&#39;re looking for other dedicated practitioners who will share ideas with you, give you feedback and motivate you to keep up your practice, you should join us in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/&#34;&gt;the Inner Form section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exercises from The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/09/exercises-from-the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 07:03:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/09/exercises-from-the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the toughest parts of learning movement exercises from a book is knowing what goes in between each still photo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s why I&#39;m very excited that Robert Tangora has put out an overview video of all the exercises that he teaches in the &lt;a title=&#34;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands by Robert Tangora&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/&#34;&gt;Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4030&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/rbxbLQIjpYI?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use this video as a companion guide to the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this book is such an excellent resource, that I&#39;m urging every serious Tai Chi and qigong practitioner that I know to find a way to work it into theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the months of July, August, and September, I&#39;m dedicating a portion of my daily practice time to the material in Robert&#39;s book. I&#39;m calling it the 90-Day Cloud Hands Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why I&#39;m Excited about The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve studied with Robert for several years, mainly when he comes to Boston to teach seminars, and we&#39;ve worked on several different pieces of his system -- this book ties them all together. I wish I had had this from the beginning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is also a road map for infusing your Tai Chi practice will all of the main principles found in the complete Energy Arts curriculum &lt;strong&gt;(see below, I want to share my notes on this with you)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He&#39;s collected simple (but profound, and not necessarily easy) exercises that lay out all the building blocks for your Cloud Hands practice and described them in the book. And now we have the video reference to go with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re looking for a way to boost your personal practice, no matter where you&#39;re coming from with it, setting a 90-day goal of honing one skill, or repeatedly delving into one set of exercises can be a great way to do it. 90 days is enough time to really immerse yourself, but also short enough so it doesn&#39;t feel endless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book and video just coming out is the perfect trigger to set you off on a 90-day challenge of your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My Personal Practice Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Since I&#39;m in the process of weaving the Cloud Hands material together with my normal Energy Arts practice, I started mapping out the links I was seeing between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just rough outlines I&#39;ve put together. Think &#34;work in progress&#34;, &#34;musings&#34;, or &#34;scratchpad.&#34; I&#39;m not claiming anything definitive!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, if you&#39;d like to check them out, drop your email in the form below and I&#39;ll send you my notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&#34;width: 100%;&#34; src=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/embed/m7p7s5/&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;261&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands by Robert Tangora</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 07:00:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/06/18/the-internal-structure-of-cloud-hands-by-robert-tangora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3991&#34; title=&#34;Robert Tangora Cloud Hands&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/06/DSC_0074-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands by Robert Tangora&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi Instructor Robert Tangora&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&#39;s&lt;/a&gt; new book, &lt;strong&gt;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/strong&gt;, has just been published.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last October, &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;I spoke to Robert about why he chose this topic for a Tai Chi book&lt;/a&gt; and what he hoped to communicate to people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on that interview, working with him live doing his Cloud Hands training, and the meticulous way he approaches learning, teaching, and Tai Chi, I have no doubt that this book is going to the top of my recommended reading list next to &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;Energy Gates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3990&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://tangora-cloud-hands.kickofflabs.com/?kid=BXEF&#34;&gt;Robert is offering up a free sample chapter from the book as a preview.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&#39;ve downloaded the chapter, he&#39;ll send you a link to the book on Amazon and while you&#39;re waiting for it in the mail, do what I did: &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora Tai Chi Cloud Hands Interview&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi-cloud-hands-interview/&#34;&gt;re-watch the whole interview I did with him.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inner Form members:&lt;/strong&gt; this is going to be a juicy topic for us to discuss more. While you&#39;re waiting for the &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;, the material in this book could easily fill all your free hours with rich, rewarding practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I Learned from Robert Tangora about Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/14/what-i-learned-from-robert-tangora-about-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/14/what-i-learned-from-robert-tangora-about-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, we hosted &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt; at Brookline Tai Chi for an introduction to Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong. Prior to the workshop, I had put together a few thoughts on what it feels like to work with the spine in Tai Chi and qigong. This weekend definitely helped me refine my sense for what Spinal Qigong can do, so I wanted to share some of those lessons with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3578&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/_1hMPWIbTiY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/_1hMPWIbTiY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundational practices I describe in the video prepare you to work with the more sophisticated connections you access in Bend the Bow. &lt;strong&gt;One of the main goals of spinal qigong is to link the arms and legs by connecting them to the spine.&lt;/strong&gt; By learning to use the spine as a bow that can store and release energy, you learn to move the arms and legs &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the spine, not just &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the spine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Targeting the Spine in Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We used an exercise very similar to the one Robert demonstrates at 4:00 in this video to begin to feel the way that the arms and legs connect to the spine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;410&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;410&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of qigong principles that apply to working with the spine, Robert made it very clear that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first level of any qigong practice is all about coordinating moving parts. You need to practice slowly and careful, with the goal of synchronizing the timing of the movements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once timing is there, you being to build internal connections, i.e. it becomes possible to have the sense of one part leading another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to develop a clear sense of how the big muscles of the back connect to the arms and legs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Through partner feedback, you can start to discern how the arms and legs &#34;pull&#34; on the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You refine how the limbs pull on the spine in order to balance the left and right side of the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your body is open enough, spinal qigong can give an incredibly balanced, whole-body feel to all your movement.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Since the workshop, I&#39;ve used this exercise as a daily warm-up and it has been spilling over into my Tai Chi practice nicely. Everything feels more linked together. I&#39;m working on a post right now about breathing and some of the conclusions are the same: once deep internal connections are in place, the circular nature of these movements opens you up continuously as you practice. That is a huge contrast from linear stretching, which feel like you&#39;re flicking a switch on and off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my biggest takeaway about Spinal Qigong (at the moment, of course!) is that you need to approach it like every other qigong exercise that is designed to open up your body, but there definitely are some unique experiences that come up working with the spine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 09:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure you&#39;ve spent time looking around YouTube for qigong and tai chi videos. According to their website, people upload 24 hours of video to YouTube &lt;em&gt;every minute&lt;/em&gt;! No doubt you&#39;ve seen some crazy stuff. So how do you sift through all of it and more importantly, are there any qigong videos on YouTube worth watching?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is, of course there are. And I&#39;ve put together a list of 5 good ones to get you started. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2522&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Practice with YouTube Qigong Videos&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you will see from the videos below, there is a blend of instructional content, guided practice, and demonstration. You have to get creative when you are borrowing from a source like online video to boost your practice. Sometimes you will just do a quick check-in. Sometimes you will sit and watch an entire lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&#39;t recommend trying to do your practice and darting back and forth to the computer at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the video has good audio guidance that can run in the background, great. Otherwise, just watch it once or twice and then go and practice. I&#39;ll try to point out key places in each video where you can see skilled practitioners demonstrating things they aren&#39;t necessarily talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This introduction to standing by Lam Kam Chuen is one of my favorite overviews of the practice. He talks a little bit about the background of the practice and gives just enough instruction to get you started. If you already have a standing practice, it&#39;s worth watching because you can revisit some of the overarching reasons to do this qigong method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/StandStillBeFit&#34;&gt;The entire channel&lt;/a&gt; is worth watching once you&#39;ve gone through the introductory clip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simple Circling Hands&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The natural transition from standing practice is to start repetitive movements. In standing, you tune into internal rhythms that only become obvious because there is no external movement. Circling Hands is a great bridge because your external movements are simple enough that you can let the internal rhythms drive them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch as &lt;a title=&#34;Q&amp;amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; performs Circling Hands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most important thing you can get from this YouTube qigong video is the way his whole body opens and closes, pulsing from the center, outward.&amp;Acirc; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exploring Internal Flows&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the next video, &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt; explains how to activate the two main energy flows that run your body: Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth. He teaches two different exercises to highlight these flows. Like Paul&#39;s demonstration above, if you practice these exercises you will begin to feel the &#34;pulls&#34; through the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth pointing out that while you may or may not be able to feel what he&#39;s describing right away, every teacher I&#39;ve ever had insists that you need to develop the internal sensitivity to these subtle movements through a standing or sitting practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transitioning into More Movement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Each mode of qigong practice gives you access to something different. &#34;Quiet&#34; practices like standing qigong or sitting meditation allow you to develop your internal awareness with as little physical coordination as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving practices do two things: they develop rhythm and they challenge your ability to maintain internal focus because of the ever-changing external conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these next two videos, we&#39;re going to introduce more movement, first by adding weight-shifting and turning, then by looking at the qigong set with the most complicated external form: Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try this &#34;Rolling the Ball&#34; exercise to see if you can maintain some of the internal awareness primed in the earlier qigong videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this last video isn&#39;t designed to be instructional or a follow-along practice. Instead, I want you to watch it and see if you can pick up some of the things we&#39;ve looked at in the other YouTube qigong videos in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see internal continuity? Opening and closing? Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth flows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The secret to training your eyes to see more subtle movement patterns is to look at someone&#39;s movements, in this case Tai Chi master &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, and try to feel inside your own body what he must be doing to create those movements.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this post gives you some ideas about how to use YouTube qigong videos to improve your own practice. Got any favorites that I&#39;ve left out? Be sure to let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 09:22:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I sat down with Robert Tangora to talk about his upcoming book on Tai Chi Cloud Hands when he was in Boston in October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he discusses Tai Chi Cloud Hands, almost reverently, Robert explains it as a paradigm for understanding the complete art of Tai Chi, and also as a way to bring each practitioner closer to integration. The basic problem is that you have a spectrum of practices, from sitting, to standing, to moving, to fighting, that all feel very different and all develop different attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked Robert to talk about this integration problem and explain why he sees Cloud Hands as an essential part of well developed Tai Chi practice. Here are some highlights from the interview, with a link at the end to the entire video and full transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of this interview will also appear in the &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi: State of the Art&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-state-of-the-art/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi State of the Art 2012 ebook&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven&#39;t had a chance to weigh in on that topic yet, complete the survey &lt;a title=&#34;2012 Survey&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-state-of-the-art/2012-survey/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2376&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fsAN3HlNvrc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fsAN3HlNvrc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the introduction to &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/span&gt; from his website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://tangorataichi.com/Book%20Intro.pdf&#34;&gt;TangoraTaiChi.com&lt;/a&gt; (right click and &#34;save as&#34;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Cloud Hands?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you talk to a lot of people who have done Tai Chi a long time, they&#39;ll all say, &#34;Oh yeah, Cloud Hands.&#34; They may not have any idea why Cloud Hands seems really kind of special, but almost universally they go, &#34;Yeah, there&#39;s something there that&#39;s going on that I can&#39;t quite put my finger on it but I know it&#39;s there.&#34; And well, what&#39;s going on is it&#39;s this hidden relationship between the symmetries in what you&#39;re doing externally and internally.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On the relationship between health and meditation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;From a health standpoint, meditation is very important because it develops a lot of sensitivity to what&#39;s going on inside you. And if you want to be able to kind of fix something, you&#39;ve got to be able to feel it. If you can&#39;t feel it, you can&#39;t fix it. Well, most of us feel things because we have pain reactions rather than feeling things that aren&#39;t painful. Well, through meditation you actually learn to feel a lot of things that aren&#39;t pain reactions and you learn how those things end up being interrelated with pain reactions. And if you want to become really efficient at kind of healing yourself, or for that matter if you&#39;re doing some sort of healing of somebody else, you&#39;ve got to be able to distinguish those two.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On maximizing the health benefits by doing martial arts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The people I&#39;ve met who really have the health stuff of Tai Chi really well-developed were all very respectable martial arts... Those are the people who have that most developed.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On having a spectrum of different practices:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You have to have something that allows you to go from what you develop energetically while you&#39;re sitting and standing and take that into motion. Otherwise you tend to just jump into the form and the things you&#39;re doing internally in meditation practice are gone.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How Cloud Hands develops physical and energetic alignments:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeah there is physical aspects to it, like there is certain alignments you really need to kind of put in place, but there&#39;s also kind of some more energetic things that don&#39;t really necessarily have a real good physical counterpart. And it&#39;s kind of the first place where you really start kind of encountering that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, if I&#39;m like doing something on the left side of my body and it creates like a twist in a spiral like down to the ground. And I can reverse that, bring it up. Well, eventually this starts actually stimulating the Chi in my body. Just kind of start doing the same type of thing, but it does it actually probably at a different pace than my physical tissue because I can&#39;t actually make my physical tissue twist like this. But it helps induce it. So at some point it&#39;s physical, but it also has these other components energetically that it&#39;s starting to really develop.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What 90% of Tai Chi practitioners might be missing:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately everything kind of moves in these oblique ellipses and circles from your abdominal cavity...Well if you&#39;re doing both simultaneously, you start developing these kind of pulls and compression&#39;s that massage and loosen up your organs, and it begins to develop that. It&#39;s not that if you just relax and you stay really loose and you turn, you get some of that. You just don&#39;t get as much. And the place where, from a martial standpoint what happens is, you tend to be able to project power from certain angles, pretty efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s fairly efficient, it actually can be quite efficient at handling forces basically working more or less in a horizontal plane. But if I want to handle forces working in other dimensions, like vertically and stuff, I really have to have the capacity for my body to move in that direction and it&#39;d be integrated with what&#39;s happening in my legs and waist. So that&#39;s the other component, that&#39;s very important in the cross body training that probably 90% of the people doing Tai Chi they don&#39;t do it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;My favorite quote from the interview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you just practice form, there are so many things that distract you from listening to yourself.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora Tai Chi Cloud Hands Interview&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi-cloud-hands-interview/&#34;&gt;Check out the complete interview here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>