<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>kwa on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/kwa/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in kwa on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/kwa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Maintaining the Four Points in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2013 08:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; alt=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, the question of &#34;should I rotate my spine in Tai Chi&#34; has come up frequently and led to a lot of confusion with some of our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are told to maintain the &#34;Four Points&#34; - a sort of internal frame that runs between the shoulders and the hips, forming a box that keeps the spine from rotating or side bending while you practice Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people hear this rule and think, &#34;but the spine has joints that rotate and bend in more than one plane&#34; or &#34;show me any athletic movement that doesn&#39;t make use of the rotational movement of the spine to generate power.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you reconcile these common sense observations with a principle that seems to limit natural movement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s look at the developmental context in a few stages of learning Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Maintaining the Four Points for Beginners&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First of all, you need to appreciate the context for each question and observation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start learning Tai Chi, most people haven&#39;t spent a lot of time separating upper body and lower body movement or thinking about which one drives the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for beginners, &lt;strong&gt;holding the Four Points in place allows you to more easily steer the shoulders from the hips&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you practice at this level, without rotating the spine, you train out all the upper-body-led exaggeration in your movements. You begin to learn how to feel the &#34;power coming from the legs, being steered by the waist, and expressed in the hands,&#34; to paraphrase the Tai Chi Classics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t follow the rule of the Four Points at this level, you tend to retain upper body dominance, never finding proper folding in &lt;a title=&#34;Basic Training: Focus on Your Kwa Squat&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/&#34;&gt;the hip joints and kwa&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hitting Your Limits&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, at a certain point, holding the Four Points as an &lt;em&gt;external frame &lt;/em&gt;starts to limit your movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you watch this video on the components of Roll Back, or Lu, you will see, especially around 3:30, the way that twisting and rotation enhances the subtly, connection, and power of your movements.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/PL8TPEu3TWw?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you progress to interactive practices, the additional rotational power you can generate from micro movements in the spine will improve the quality of your response to an incoming force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to only turning from the hips, having the capacity to create rotation in the spine is like typing with all 26 letters, not just 14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What the Rotators Miss&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, you can see this in the above video to a degree, but I want to also point out one of the less obvious benefits of maintaining what looks like a more rigid frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You have to take into account the difference between bone and soft tissue.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons we focus on maintaining bony alignments, beyond developing coordination and healthy movement patterns that don&#39;t wear on the joints, is finding separate movement in the fascia and muscles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you let the soft tissues turn around the bones, you begin to loosen them. If your bones and tissues are always turning together, you miss deeper internal loosening of these layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, a movement that looks very rigid and square may actually contain spirals throughout the soft tissues, but this is not obvious from the outside unless you&#39;ve been trained to look for subtle signs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you make a rule like &#34;never break the external frame of the Four Points,&#34; you don&#39;t account for someone&#39;s coordination, sensitivity, or body development. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several layers to the process of cultivating unified spiral-driven movement, but a simple rule like that doesn&#39;t account for very different needs at different stages of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, &#34;always twist the spine&#34; as a rule will keep you from developing certain sensitivity and connection and shouldn&#39;t be treated as an absolute outside of the right context either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? How do you make sense of these kinds of rules and principles in your own practice? Has your sense of their meaning changed over time?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Song&#34; or Relaxation in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/09/song-or-relaxation-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2013 09:16:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/09/song-or-relaxation-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The meaning of relaxation in a Tai Chi context is often confused with the same kind of limp, collapsed, let-go feeling you get from flopping on to the couch after a long day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, there&#39;s a very different sense of &#34;song&#34; or relaxation in Tai Chi, which is at once easy and loose, but also energized and alert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his translator&#39;s introduction to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Mastering-Yang-Style-Taijiquan-Zhongwen/dp/1583941525/?tag=dankleiman&#34;&gt;Mastering Yang Style Taijiquan&lt;/a&gt;, Louis Swaim nails the nuance of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Through this book one encounters the terms &lt;em&gt;song&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;fang song&lt;/em&gt;. These are often translated as &#34;relaxed&#34; and &#34;relax.&#34; Etymologically the term &lt;em&gt;song&lt;/em&gt; is based on a character for &#34;long hair that hangs down&#34; -- that is, hair that is loosened and expanded, not &#34;drawn up.&#34; Therefore, &#34;loosened&#34; and &#34;loosen&#34; are more accurate renderings for &lt;em&gt;song&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;fang song&lt;/em&gt;. The phonetic element that gives the character &lt;em&gt;song&lt;/em&gt; its pronunciation means, by itself, &#34;a pine tree,&#34; which carries an associated imagery of &#34;longevity,&#34; much as evergreens are associated with ongoing vitality in the West. This may provide a clue to the Taijiquan usage of this term, which must not be confused with total relaxation, but is closer to an optimal state of the condition referred to as &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tonus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in English anatomical parlance; that is, the partial contraction of the musculature, which allows one to maintain equilibrium and upright posture. The aligned equilibrium this is prescribed in Taijiquan is associated with imagery of being &#34;suspended&#34; from the crown of the head. One can, therefore, draw upon the available imagery of both something that is loosened and hangs down, and that of the upright pine, whose limbs do not droop down, but are buoyant and lively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Add More Song to Your Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To help you get a sense for what it feels like to &#34;loosen and hang&#34; internally, I made this video, highlighting 3 key areas that must be released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sLkWM1n_1kA?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic Training: Focus on Your Kwa Squat</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2013 07:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every six months or so, one of our Senior Instructors at Brookline Tai Chi tells me that he&#39;s had an amazing revelation about how to do the kwa squat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kwa squat is one of the very first things we teach, he&#39;s been doing Tai Chi for 40 years, and he gets new insight into it all the time. Amazing, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tai Chi and Back Pain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the reasons we get so interested in this exercise is its power to relieve pressure on the spine and open up important joints of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, our teacher &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis Tai Chi Resources&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis-tai-chi-resources/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt; explains how Tai Chi works on the spine, including the effects of squatting, tucking, &lt;a title=&#34;My Favorite Breathing Hack&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/30/my-favorite-breathing-hack/&#34;&gt;breathing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;sinking your chi&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a title=&#34;Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/&#34;&gt;Bend the Bow&lt;/a&gt; techniques done in Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/OA6ao4UyiiA?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though there are many different ways to open the spine in Tai Chi, let&#39;s focus on one of the core: &lt;strong&gt;the kwa squat&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a saying in Tai Chi, which surely applies to all arts, that &#34;high level skill is just high level basics.&#34; The deeper you go with the fundamentals, the better you get. So let&#39;s revisit the basics of the kwa squat. Specifically, we&#39;ll look at how this leads to a healthier spine and integrates the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Kwa Squat&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first three levels of using the kwa will get you in the game for the more sophisticated variations you use in Tai Chi. They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Folding the kwa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bending and Stretching from the kwa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pump the kwa&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/gevaFsGiYg0?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we&#39;re not really a squatting culture in the West, most people have a steep motor-learning curve when they try their first kwa squat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our hips tend to be frozen and we&#39;ll jam into the knees to try to lower the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-946 aligncenter&#34; alt=&#34;Downward Phase of Squat&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/05/squat-down-300x215.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;215&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In a proper squat,  the hip joint (green dot) moves back and down, while the knee joint (red dot), rotates in place. You can also track the femur movement (white line). &lt;em&gt;The knee doesn&#39;t move forward in space.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get a feel for the basic version by placing your knees up against the seat of a chair. When you squat, the chair shouldn&#39;t move at all. If you press into the chair, you are pressing into your knees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you will probably feel like you&#39;re sticking your butt out. That&#39;s a good thing for this exercise and it will lead us to a key difference between a Tai Chi kwa squat and the kind of squat you would use to lift heavy weight, like in a deadlift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Tai Chi kwa squat, you keep the spine straight, so the pelvis hangs like an anchor from the bottom of the spine. One of the reasons this is done is to create more space in the lumbar spine. As your sensitivity and control increase in this exercise, you can even begin to use the pulsing of the kwa to create a gentle opening at the sacroiliac joint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; alt=&#34;source: Wikipedia&#34; src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/91/Sacroiliac_joint.svg/500px-Sacroiliac_joint.svg.png&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;188&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Opening the sacroiliac joint makes the connection between the legs and spine much stronger, increases overall flexibility in the hips, and makes your movements much smoother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process of developing this fine motor control, you need to pass through several levels of releasing and relaxing muscles and coordination. For more practice ideas, you might want to review these posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;How to Get More Flexible without Adding Stretching to Your Practice&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/06/how-to-get-more-flexible-without-adding-stretching-to-your-practice/&#34;&gt;How to Get More Flexible without Stretching&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Femur Bone Rhythm&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/femur-bone-rhythm/&#34;&gt;Femur Bone Rhythm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Hip Mobility&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/hip-mobility/&#34;&gt;Hip Mobility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Qigong Radio Episode 2: Developing Your Soft Tissue with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/29/qigong-radio-episode-2-developing-your-soft-tissue-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Developing Soft Tissue in the Internal Arts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you focus on developing this core skill, all the other qigong and Tai Chi movements that you learn are designed to multiply out the benefits. If you skip over the basics, though, the other movements just become fancy hand-waiving. Always revisit your basic training!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Use Your Kwa in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/23/learning-to-use-your-kwa-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 07:40:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/23/learning-to-use-your-kwa-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this &#34;office hours&#34; post, Nate asked me about kwa work in Tai Chi. Specifically, we were looking at movements where you squat in a front stance. The question is figuring out how low to go and why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tai Chi, you use your kwa to control your movements. At first, think of your kwa as simply the fold in your hip joint. In the following video, though, I explain how your understanding, and use, of the kwa changes as you learn to work deeper into the body.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3345&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/gevaFsGiYg0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/gevaFsGiYg0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your practice, you should be clear about which skill you are practicing. Learn how to do each of these three:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fold the kwa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bend and Stretch from the kwa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pump the kwa&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you progress through these different skills, your sense of how to articulate the kwa changes. In the next two videos, I go on to show Nate how to hollow his kwa, which allows him to squat lower and govern how low he goes while staying aligned and connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we look at how the hollowing action allows you to release excess tension and holding in the lower spine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Tutorial on Hollowing the Kwa&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/tutorial-on-hollowing-the-kwa/&#34;&gt;Read the full Inner Form Tutorial on hollowing the kwa here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>