<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bruce-frantzis on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/bruce-frantzis/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in bruce-frantzis on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/bruce-frantzis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Practice Advice from Master Feng Zhiqiang</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/09/26/tai-chi-practice-advice-from-master-feng-zhiqiang/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 14:44:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/09/26/tai-chi-practice-advice-from-master-feng-zhiqiang/</guid>
      <description>Feng Zhiqiang was a famous Tai Chi Master from Beijing who was a major influence on my teacher Bruce Frantzis. Master Feng did some teaching in the West as well and we are fortunate to have access to a transcript of a 2001 workshop he taught in the Bay Area (thanks to the folks at SilkReeler.com for making this transcript available and thanks to Igor for sending it my way!).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Sensations That Arise When You Are Developing Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 07:24:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</guid>
      <description>In this episode of Qigong Radio, I answer some questions about different sensations readers have been experiencing when they practice.
In the Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong Instruction Manual, Bruce Frantzis lays out important guidelines for what kinds of &#34;chi reactions&#34; to expect. I want to show you how to apply these guidelines to your practice.
 Expect Chi Reactions
Dragon and Tiger is a powerful tool for awakening your body on physical, energetic, emotional, mental and spiritual levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.
Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</guid>
      <description>After teaching thousands of people of all ages and physical abilities over the last eight years, it is clear to me that there is one technique in Tai Chi that is more powerful than all others.
My main teacher, Bruce Frantzis, introduced me to this technique and taught me how to use all its variations, under different conditions. He has encouraged all his instructors to pass along this technique because it is practically a lost art.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Eight Energies of Tai Chi and the Physical Attributes of Roll Back</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 13:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</guid>
      <description>As part of the Tai Chi Mastery Program, Bruce Frantzis recently published a report called &#34;The Eight Principles of Tai Chi Chuan.&#34; The report is full of detail about stages of training 8 different energies of Tai Chi, laid out in clear and straightforward language.
But I always have a problem with writing like this....
On the one hand, it is invaluable for anyone who wants to understand the bigger context of their Tai Chi practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing Your Internal State through Tai Chi Equipment Training</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/17/testing-your-internal-state-through-tai-chi-equipment-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 09:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/17/testing-your-internal-state-through-tai-chi-equipment-training/</guid>
      <description>One aspect of Tai Chi that tends to get overlooked is testing.
I don&#39;t mean testing for rank or belts.
I mean testing the smoothness of your nervous system that should be evolving as you go deeper into your practice.
In this video, Tai Chi Master Bruce Frantzis demonstrates an exceptional degree of smoothness. 
Even though he is demonstrating a Ba Gua rolling exercise, all of the internal arts aim to cultivate this degree of fluidity:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Calm Your Mind Through Movement</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 08:45:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</guid>
      <description>Movement can be a powerful tool for creating a calm mind, but only when you follow some very specific rules.
Tai Chi was designed with these specific movement rules because the goal is to take you from tense to relaxed and from relaxed to vital and strong.
When my Tai Chi teacher, Bruce Frantzis explains the learning progression for Tai Chi, he makes it clear that when your primary focus is on the mind, and your goal is to calm your mind, you must follow this progression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More of the Best Qigong on YouTube</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/09/more-of-the-best-qigong-on-youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2012 08:18:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/09/more-of-the-best-qigong-on-youtube/</guid>
      <description>My friend Jess makes a point of studying with as many different teachers as he can. His goal isn&#39;t to dabble in a lot of different styles or systems. He is faithful and dedicated to his main practice, but he knows that each time he gets exposed to a new system, he learns something about his own.
See if you can glean one new thing from each of these qigong videos from YouTube to refine and improve your practice today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Push Hands and The Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 07:19:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re hosting Bruce Frantzis for a Push Hands Intensive this week at Brookline Tai Chi. The training is being filmed and it will become the Push Hands module of the Tai Chi Mastery Program, due out later this year.
Here are my thoughts so far on how the Push Hands component fits in with what we did this past summer in Brighton:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Lessons from Qigong Instructor Trainings</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/14/16-lessons-from-qigong-instructor-trainings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2012 08:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/14/16-lessons-from-qigong-instructor-trainings/</guid>
      <description>This June, my qigong teacher Bruce Frantzis will be offering a two-week Dragon and Tiger Qigong instructor training on Maui. Over the past 10 years, I&#39;ve attended most of the instructor trainings that he has offered, as well as many weekends and week-long retreats.
Being in an intensive learning environment at these events is great for your personal practice.
If you&#39;re thinking about teaching this material, though, you have to be smart about how you approach these trainings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 09:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m sure you&#39;ve spent time looking around YouTube for qigong and tai chi videos. According to their website, people upload 24 hours of video to YouTube every minute! No doubt you&#39;ve seen some crazy stuff. So how do you sift through all of it and more importantly, are there any qigong videos on YouTube worth watching?
The good news is, of course there are. And I&#39;ve put together a list of 5 good ones to get you started.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Form Training Final Update</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 12:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m heading home to Boston tomorrow, but I&#39;ve already begun looking through my notes and thinking about what I will personally practice and what I&#39;ll be able to share with my students in classes this coming year. Here are some of my initial thoughts:

How Material is Woven together over a Month:
 Day to day we&#39;re looking at really small specific pieces but now going back through my notes, I can start to see different threads that run throughout the duration of the month.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update from the Beach</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>Week 3 wraps up and testing is right around the corner. What was Bruce&#39;s big message as we prepare for testing? Work your ass off and cram all night for the big test? Not quite. You might be surprised. Check it out:

A Lesson about Integration:
The biggest thing that Bruce is emphasizing in the last couple days of class is that with this stage of the training, a month long training, you need integration time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 of the Short Form Instructor Training</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 09:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s my Week 2 update. Some big milestones this week: group 1 finished the form and group 2 has been languishing in the purgatory that is holding static postures. Check it out:

Inner Form vs. Outer Form
 In the two groups, we&#39;re doing very different things. The group one just finished the form this week. So on Thursday after they finished it, we came in Friday, and it was a really interesting dividing line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am Learning at the Wu Tai Chi Instructor Training</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 01:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</guid>
      <description>We&#39;re a week into the Wu Tai Chi short form instructor training in Brighton, UK, with Lineage Holder Bruce Frantzis. So far we&#39;ve been completely rebuilding our forms, working on Tai Chi leg power, and exploring the meditative aspects of the art. Check it out:

On Rebuilding Your Form:
It&#39;s crazy when you come at these things, you&#39;re completely rebuilding your Tai Chi form. We&#39;re about two-thirds of the way through the form and it feels so different.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>