<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bruce-frantzis on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/bruce-frantzis/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in bruce-frantzis on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/bruce-frantzis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Practice Advice from Master Feng Zhiqiang</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/09/26/tai-chi-practice-advice-from-master-feng-zhiqiang/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 14:44:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/09/26/tai-chi-practice-advice-from-master-feng-zhiqiang/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Feng Zhiqiang was a famous Tai Chi Master from Beijing who was a major influence on my teacher &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;. Master Feng did some teaching in the West as well and we are fortunate to have access to a transcript of a 2001 workshop he taught in the Bay Area (thanks to the folks at SilkReeler.com for making &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.silkreeler.com/drupal/?q=node/24&#34;&gt;this transcript&lt;/a&gt; available and thanks to Igor for sending it my way!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here he is in 1986 performing a Chen Style Form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/gVtO7pod5hM?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2001 workshop, Master Feng gives some great advice about different dimensions of practicing Tai Chi and qigong. I think you&#39;ll find the advice relevant to your own practice. Throughout the interview Master Feng is humble about his incredible skill and what&#39;s more, you can really tell that he was still actively practicing and learning, not resting on his credentials as the Master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even here, when he&#39;s describing a training process, we learn that he&#39;s working on it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master Feng says, &#34;... Gentle practice is more effective than forceful practice. Lengthening is better than contracting. It&#39;s not just a simple matter of health, it&#39;s also a very good stretching exercise.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which his student replies, &#34;Some of us may have noticed Grandmaster Feng has much longer arms than the rest of us. That&#39;s a result of practicing lengthening. Thirty years ago when we took a picture together, I noticed in the photograph that Master Feng&#39;s arm is about one finger longer than mine.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The master always keeps working!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve pulled a series of quotes and questions and answers from the transcript that I found particularly helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Structure and Body Alignment for Tai Chi&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even when you are standing upright, your weight should only be on one leg. When you&#39;re standing you should be relaxed and have your weight shifting from one leg to the other, never stationary and fifty-fifty. But not too obvious, that looks too funny. Don&#39;t let it be visible to an observer, but you should shift your weight from one leg to the other. Same thing with the foot. When you are standing you should never tighten your foot, and you should also flex it gently. Never stay in one position. Practicing in a relaxed manner is better than tensing up.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Whole-Body Coordination and Power&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Curved line is better than straight line. Even when your limbs are lengthened, they should also be curved. The body is the same. It should never be too straight. There should always be a curve somewhere. The Taiji body has five bows [Verbal clarification from translator: as in &#34;bow&#34; and arrow]. One arm, the other arm &amp;mdash; two bows. One leg, the other leg, and your spine - your body. So, five bows. There is a Taiji saying that &#34;once the body has cultivated five bows, (and can express the spring-like power) there is no equal opponent under Heaven.&#34; [Demonstration] This is one bow as well. Curving the chest is also a bow. Only by practicing in a slow and lengthening manner, you can then cultivate the spring-like energy. Something with springiness is very strong. If you drop it, it will never break. But if you have something that is hard and brittle, when you drop it it will shatter. That&#39;s what the old martial arts masters would say. If your body has five bows and you have this spring-like power, you will have no equal opponent under Heaven. Practicing martial art, you should know the theory. Only by knowing the theory can you grasp the martial aspect of Taiji.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Uncontrollable Shaking during Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the Q&amp;amp;A section of the transcript, Master Feng gives some direct, and indirect, practice advice. The first question is about standing qigong. He is asked, &#34;Basically, how should we stand? Any tips on standing? Some students have experienced interesting phenomena like uncontrollable shaking, whether that&#39;s good or bad, and whether we should do anything about it.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master Feng starts off with what appears to be a very theoretical answer, but I found it to be a pretty accurate description of the &#34;interesting phenomena.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone, greetings. This is a good question. Standing posture is Wuji, [Translator note: as in &#34;ultimate nothing&#34;]. Standing posture is posture of Wuji. Wuji is the state before Heaven and Earth was formed, when everything was in the primordial soup, when yin and yang were not differentiated. Wuji is silence, not moving, is quiet, whereas Taiji, the name of our practice, is opposite. Even though it looks as if standing posture/standing meditation there&#39;s no movement, however inside, just like in the primordial soup, there&#39;s always something, there&#39;s always something moving. When the internal subtle movement suddenly reaches critical level, then there&#39;s a Big Bang. That&#39;s when the light stuff floats up and the heavy stuff sinks down. And those that floats up form the heaven, and things that condenses become the Earth. The Big Bang essentially causes Taiji to happen. Taiji is yin and yang, the interplay between yin and yang. Between the interplay of yin and yang, everything else in this world is born. Without Taiji there&#39;s nothing, there&#39;s not even us. Everything, all life forms. Plants, animals. Human being are at the top of the animal kingdom, we are spiritual beings. The relationship between Heaven, Human, and Earth is the three pillars of the universe. Basically, from Wuji, even though there&#39;s no apparent movement, there&#39;s always something happening internally. When the time is right, the universe is formed, and Taiji is born. Same thing when we&#39;re doing standing meditation. There&#39;s no apparent movement, but there&#39;s always a little subtle shift. And after you&#39;ve been doing it for a while you could generate so much energy in your body that you&#39;d just have to move, that&#39;s the time for you to start doing your form. Within Wuji, even though the external is without motion, inside there is the beating of the heart, the circulation of blood, the flowing of chi. So within the motionless external something is contained inside that is moving.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
He continues with a very detailed cosmological description of the process of moving from Wu Ji to Tai Chi and beyond, which I won&#39;t add here. But then he returns to a very practical tip. I bolded the parts I thought were especially important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s go back to the standing meditation and involuntary movement. Not everyone will experience it. Some people will experience different feelings, different sensations, when your qigong practice is up to a certain level. Movement is one of them. It&#39;s normal to move. &lt;strong&gt;However, do not seek movement for its own sake.&lt;/strong&gt; The movement is a side effect. What we want to do is keep our attention, our intention, within our DanTien, and let the movement be. If the movement continues without bothering you, that&#39;s fine. But if it gets bigger and bigger, then you should use your will power, your mind, to tell it &#34;look, just stop it; don&#39;t move.&#34; Usually that will take away or control the movement. However if the movement is so big that it&#39;s beyond your control, then it&#39;s time to stop. You should do the DanTien turning exercise, gathering all the Qi that is wandering about back into your DanTien, and stop doing QiGong. &lt;strong&gt;Some movements are actually good phenomena. However we should not seek the phenomena. We should just focus on practicing QiGong.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On Fitting Practice into Our Busy Lives&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, I love how he addressed the question about learning all these forms and exercises, but not having enough time each day to practice them. If you follow his rules for practicing on limited time, you&#39;ll definitely turn even a few minutes into high-quality practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we have limited time, what should we do on a daily basis? You should at least cover two things: One is qigong, as many movements as you can do, and then the 24-form. However if you don&#39;t even have time to cover those two things, what you can do is, put the 24 aside and concentrate on a subset of qigong exercises. And those examples he was showing us, &#34;Heaven open, Earth close,&#34; or &#34;Earth open, Heaven close,&#34; that&#39;s one. Or &#34;double hand open-close,&#34; that&#39;s another one. So if you do those, that&#39;s ok. But you need to do more than nine repetitions if you just want to do one thing. And he&#39;s suggesting a few hundred repetitions. At least a hundred times or two hundred times. He&#39;s saying that because qigong is the foundation, is the core of our practice, if you don&#39;t have time for anything else, then do the core. However, it&#39;s best that you try to put aside at least an hour a day to do qigong as well as the 24.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So there you have it, practice advice from a Master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, last spring, Master Feng passed away. You can read more about him &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/tai-chi/feng-zhi-qiang-death/&#34;&gt;in this tribute from Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Sensations That Arise When You Are Developing Chi</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 07:24:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/01/15/common-sensations-that-arise-when-you-are-developing-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, I answer some questions about different sensations readers have been experiencing when they practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dragon-and-tiger-medical-qigong/&#34;&gt;Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong&lt;/a&gt; Instruction Manual, Bruce Frantzis lays out important guidelines for what kinds of &#34;chi reactions&#34; to expect. I want to show you how to apply these guidelines to your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Expect Chi Reactions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dragon and Tiger is a powerful tool for awakening your body on physical, energetic, emotional, mental and spiritual levels. As you practice these movements and begin to move your body in ways that may be different for you, energy and fluids in your body are stirred up and begin to move more vigorously. At some point you may experience reactions that may seem either positive or negative to you. These are called chi reactions: the body&#39;s response to the effects of energy beginning to flow more freely through previously blocked places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These reactions may show up immediately, hours after practicing, or even a day or two later. Although many people will not begin to feel either negative or positive reactions without practicing a lot, others, particularly if they have done other forms of personal development work, may notice reactions almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Positive Chi Reactions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Positive reactions can range from feeling less pain and having more energy to being more centered, relaxed and comfortable with your body. Some people report that they sleep much better; others report greater flexibility and balance. You may also notice that you are calmer and have fewer mood swings. You may experience an overall reduction in stress and tension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A transformative effect that most people consider positive, is an increase in and awareness of sexual energy. This is entirely normal as it is the most fundamental energy in your body, and practice of Dragon and Tiger will increase sexual energy. Finally, a transformative effect that confuses many people is what we call &#34;good pain.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dragon and Tiger is designed to gradually work more and more deeply into your body, to release muscles and other tissues and joints that have been restricted or blocked. When an area of your body that has been frozen begins to loosen and realign, more energy moves through that area than you are used to. But if the energy cannot flow freely or fully, you may experience temporary pain in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese medical theory of the body holds that pain in an area is a sign that the energy there is not flowing freely. You feel &#34;bad&#34; pain when an area is newly injured or hurt. In general, &#34;good&#34; pains tend to be temporary (lasting from a minute to at most a couple of days) and are usually dull, rather than sharp. As you practice you will learn to recognize such pains as signs of progress. Treat them with great care and keep within the 40 to 50 percent rule when you have pain, illness or injury (see p. 7). Back off practicing and be sure to consult your healthcare provider if you begin experiencing either significant pain or pain that does not go away quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Negative Chi Reactions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As your body wakes up on various levels, it may do so the same way as when aroused from a deep slumber &amp;mdash;cranky, sore and confused. You may experience some negative chi reactions. These can range from relatively mild but confusing aches, nausea, light-headedness, tingles, fatigue, unsteadiness, body temperature shifts or mood changes to strong emotional releases and mood swings to unusual dreams or shifts in perception. You may also experience physical discharges, such as stronger body odors or more frequent bowel movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As blocked and stagnant energy moves or leaves the body, energetic memories that are associated with the problem, stored in either your energy channels or physical tissue can awaken and cause you to relive the underlying and often repressed causes of the problem&amp;mdash;especially if you have a severe condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might experience what doctors refer to as a &#34;healing crisis.&#34; The term refers to that time during healing when a patient&#39;s body temporarily feels worse before it feels better. For example, when the body burns out infections, the patient often has a high fever. When the fever breaks, the symptoms of the disease pass. The fever may cause the patient to feel terrible, until the stored toxins or blocked energy are released. Afterwards the individual feels better as the illness passes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these reactions are common to many natural forms of healing and are often a sign that your body is cleansing itself. Many people have a healing crisis when they fast or switch to a cleansing or vegetarian diet. The practice of Dragon and Tiger may often trigger such effects; they are fairly normal reactions. What is important to remember is that these reactions are temporary and usually pass when your body begins to rebalance itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you begin to experience strong or uncomfortable sensations, immediately sit down, put your hands on your belly and gently breathe with your belly to ground and center yourself. Such sensations will usually pass within minutes. Then suspend or reduce your practice for a while. Start again by following the 20 percent or 40 percent rule and very gently explore your body&#39;s reactions to these practices. Remember that you are not alone in such experiences; almost everyone who practices will experience some of these reactions at some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the symptoms are intense, pull back your practice to 30 percent or 40 percent of what you consider your normal practice and consult with your teacher. Remember to drink plenty of water. Water helps accelerate the release of toxins. Taking some vitamin C also helps that process. Make sure you rest after practicing. Be sure to consult a healthcare professional immediately if you have any symptoms that might be a sign of a medical or psychological problem.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Listen to the episode to find out how to apply this principles to rising energy, activating the lower tantien, and differentiating between nerve flow, blood flood, and normal physical movement.&lt;br /&gt;
[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/q3tlLKD4YdM?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you download or listen to the episode below, you might also want to check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/bend-bow-spinal-qigong&#34;&gt;the description of Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong on EnergyArts.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/classes/chi-gung-bend-bow-introduction-bend-bow-and-shoot-arrow-december-1-2-late-fall-session&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be sure to check out Eric&#39;s Bend the Bow workshop, December 1 and 2, 2012 at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 09:01:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After teaching thousands of people of all ages and physical abilities over the last eight years, it is clear to me that there is one technique in Tai Chi that is more powerful than all others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis Tai Chi Resources&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis-tai-chi-resources/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, introduced me to this technique and taught me how to use all its variations, under different conditions. He has encouraged all his instructors to pass along this technique because it is practically a lost art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just this week, he released &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/tai-chi/the-insiders-guide-to-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;The Insider&#39;s Guide to Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, where he describes Tai Chi&#39;s most powerful technique in detail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upon recognizing what your own qi feels like, you begin two separate phases that synergistically work with each other. The first is centered on your central nervous system. Having gained the experience of putting your mind (awareness) into your muscles, you now learn to put it into your nerves. Relaxing and releasing the nerves themselves enables you to recognize the constant buzz that runs through your entire nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are not aware of this ever-present stressful buzz because it has become so normal. This buzz is a sure sign that your nervous system is either beginning to rev up (like a car going from 0-60 miles per hour in a few seconds), or even worse, has been locked habitually into a constant rev. This rev or buzz is how stress seeps through and hardens into your body. You now focus on ways to re-soften this nervous buzz inside you and progressively relax and release it from your nerves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a growing capacity to relax, you move into the second phase. Here you want to release the more-subtle nervous buzz of blocked qi inside all your body&#39;s tissues. Progressively, step-by-step, you find and release the rev in your joints, blood flow, spinal system, internal organs and glands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each stage of releasing the rev from your bodily systems makes your body more awake. This takes you into more subtle and powerful experiences of what it means and feels like for your body to be fully alive.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The enlivening technology of Tai Chi -- not what is visible on the outside, but what you do on the inside, with your mind, your chi, and in your nervous system -- holds the potential to transform the way you feel throughout the day, every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time I get a clear hit of just how to release a new layer, or relax to a new level, it blows me away and makes me hope that you can find a way to experience it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Eight Energies of Tai Chi and the Physical Attributes of Roll Back</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 13:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/10/22/the-eight-energies-of-tai-chi-and-the-physical-attributes-of-roll-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;a title=&#34;Your Guide to the Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/your-guide-to-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/a&gt;, Bruce Frantzis recently published a report called &#34;The Eight Principles of Tai Chi Chuan.&#34; The report is full of detail about stages of training 8 different energies of Tai Chi, laid out in clear and straightforward language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I always have a problem with writing like this....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, it is invaluable for anyone who wants to understand the bigger context of their Tai Chi practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re not careful, though, you can fall into a Tai Chi trap (see below after the video).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Physical Attributes of Roll Back&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the report, Bruce details each of the different energies and one of the sections that jumped out at me was the chapter on &#34;Lu&#34; or &#34;Roll Back.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roll Back is Tai Chi&#39;s signature yielding or softening energy. Bruce lays out an excellent progression for training Roll Back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I demonstrate the five points he makes about the &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; aspects of Roll Back:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/PL8TPEu3TWw?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Tai Chi Trap&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, when you read the report, Bruce lays out the physical aspects of Roll Back, then the energetic ones. Once he explains the physical aspects, he says,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the early stages of learning Roll Back, your movements will be large and obvious, both in your joints and in your waist. Over time, however, as your physical movements become more refined and circular, they can become extremely small, so tiny, in fact, that they are virtually invisible to the eye of someone untrained in observing subtlety of movement.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;And here&#39;s the trap: you read about subtlety and refinement and energetics that seem superhuman and because you are a well-trained, sophisticated thinker, you choose to imagine that you can do the subtle version right away.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bruce just gave you a road map, but you think you&#39;re already at your destination because you can read the map and picture the destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that&#39;s not how a journey really works and that&#39;s not how growth occurs in your Tai Chi practice. Especially when it gets to the subtle energetics, you have to work your way into them slowly over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Big Road Map: The Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bruce is about to release a huge road map for a lifelong journey through Tai Chi. My biggest fear is that people will buy the map and fantasize about the destinations, but never actually begin the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who does want to go on that journey, though, I&#39;m getting ready to go with you and I&#39;d be happy to be your guide along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To get the rest of my guided tour of the Tai Chi Mastery Program&lt;/strong&gt; (including &#34;The Eight Energies of Tai Chi Chuan&#34; report from Bruce), &lt;a title=&#34;Your Guide to the Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/your-guide-to-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;visit this page and sign up&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bon Voyage!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing Your Internal State through Tai Chi Equipment Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/09/17/testing-your-internal-state-through-tai-chi-equipment-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 09:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/09/17/testing-your-internal-state-through-tai-chi-equipment-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One aspect of Tai Chi that tends to get overlooked is testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t mean testing for rank or belts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean testing the smoothness of your nervous system that should be evolving as you go deeper into your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this video, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Master Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt; demonstrates an exceptional degree of smoothness. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4164&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though he is demonstrating a Ba Gua rolling exercise, all of the internal arts aim to cultivate this degree of fluidity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/owK-odZ8e9s?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, watch how he changes speeds and the size of the ball. There are no gaps in his changes. He doesn&#39;t pause and think about what to do next. The smoothness he demonstrates goes beyond external choreography and reveals a seamlessly integrated nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developing this kind of fluidity is only possible with feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can set a baseline level of relaxation when you do &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;standing qigong&lt;/a&gt;, or the slow-motion flow of the solo form, but it will only take you so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go deeper, you need to interact....with other people, with external objects, and with the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch how these instructors from Brookline Tai Chi use &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi Equipment Training with Don Ethan Miller&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/08/27/tai-chi-equipment-training-with-don-ethan-miller/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Equipment Training&lt;/a&gt; to hone their sensitivity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_vMsAN5LFl4?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see the way that they respond to each other, before and after the equipment upgrades?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, compare that to the first video. Can you see where freeing yourself from any internal gaps would make you more responsive, alive, and able to handle external pressure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beautiful thing about internal practices like Tai Chi is that you are training your nervous system to better respond to external pressure, but every encounter with an external force is an opportunity for refining internal awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Calm Your Mind Through Movement</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 08:45:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/09/10/how-to-calm-your-mind-through-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/10/P10001922.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2313&#34; title=&#34;Repulse Monkey&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/10/P10001922-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tai Chi in Gloucester, MA&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Movement can be a powerful tool for creating a calm mind, but only when you follow some very specific rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi was designed with these specific movement rules because the goal is to take you from tense to relaxed and from relaxed to vital and strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my Tai Chi teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt; explains the learning progression for Tai Chi, he makes it clear that when your primary focus is on the mind, and your goal is to calm your mind, you must follow this progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relax Your Muscles and Your Mind&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
At the first stage, you go for the big obvious stuff. Most of us are more tuned into muscular contraction and mental tension than to constrictions in our soft tissues or jammed joints. Start with what you can feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you are learning basic exercises and a broad-stroke version of the Tai Chi form, focus on relaxing your muscles and begin to catch yourself in moments of mental tension. Learn to let go of each one as you move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By training yourself to find these moments in motion, you begin to make relaxation a habit that will follow you into daily activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Find Your Shape&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you go through the Tai Chi form for the first time, you are sketching the basic shape that will be filled in in detail later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, don&#39;t overstretch, don&#39;t contract too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn to feel basic alignments, like centering the weight in your feet as you shift and turn and squat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the cadence of the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By following these movement rules, you are building a physical container. The more unified this container becomes, the more you can run your mind through your body. Following all of the rhythms and flows of the form with your awareness leads to the same kind of letting go for your mind that we began to work in with the muscles in the first stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Layer By Layer&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you relax your mind and your body, you can go deeper. Your mind penetrates deeper into the space inside your body and as a result, your body is knit together in a stronger way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You learn to make deep internal connections that optimize how you move and how you respond to your surroundings. You have more energy.You can interact with your internal environment in a smoother way too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how relaxation leads to strength.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More of the Best Qigong on YouTube</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/04/09/more-of-the-best-qigong-on-youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2012 08:18:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/04/09/more-of-the-best-qigong-on-youtube/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My friend Jess makes a point of studying with as many different teachers as he can. His goal isn&#39;t to dabble in a lot of different styles or systems. He is faithful and dedicated to his main practice, but he knows that each time he gets exposed to a new system, he learns something about his own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See if you can glean one new thing from each of these qigong videos from YouTube to refine and improve your practice today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you enjoy these videos, you should also check out this article on &lt;a title=&#34;5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/&#34;&gt;5 Important YouTube Qigong Videos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3769&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Practice Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This video is from Taoist Meditation teacher Bruce Frantzis. He discusses the often-overlooked foundation of Taoist meditation: building a strong link between your mind and your body. When you do this, you can run energy through your system in a more stable way, enabling you to go further in your meditation practice. To me, this is a compelling reason to develop your qigong practice. What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;274&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/4MHPc24k0IY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/4MHPc24k0IY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;274&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Build Stability and Structure&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Part of what allows you to build a safe container for moving more and more energy is the actual structure of the movements. In this video, Energy Arts instructor Paul Cavel demonstrates the &lt;a title=&#34;The Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/15/the-marriage-of-heaven-and-earth-qigong/&#34;&gt;Marriage of Heaven and Earth Qigong&lt;/a&gt; with clear structure. Pay particular attention to the two main flows of the movement, Heaven-to-Earth and Center-to-Periphery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;274&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/9ZkMwzEsumQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/9ZkMwzEsumQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;274&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Follow Your Energy to Build Flow&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In this last video, which you&#39;ll have to go to YouTube to watch since I can&#39;t embed it, Tai Chi Grandmaster Feng Zhiqiang demonstrates a qigong set where you can see his main emphasis is &lt;strong&gt;feeling and following his own energy&lt;/strong&gt;. Once you&#39;ve trained your structure, doing this kind of practice makes the flows go much deeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you watch his qigong practice, here is an example of his Chen Style Tai Chi, so you know that he can manifest very clear structure and form (look at those legs!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fXRDwm0ioX8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fXRDwm0ioX8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, compare that to the qigong set &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-5X5pBx8nUE&#34;&gt;in this YouTube clip&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Push Hands and The Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 07:19:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re hosting Bruce Frantzis for a Push Hands Intensive this week at Brookline Tai Chi. The training is being filmed and it will become the Push Hands module of the Tai Chi Mastery Program, due out later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are my thoughts so far on how the Push Hands component fits in with what we did &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011/&#34;&gt;this past summer in Brighton&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0XaK4Gy7fDc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0XaK4Gy7fDc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16 Lessons from Qigong Instructor Trainings</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/14/16-lessons-from-qigong-instructor-trainings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2012 08:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/14/16-lessons-from-qigong-instructor-trainings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Class by Brookline Tai Chi, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/brookline_tai_chi/1829912115/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2231/1829912115_838e5ddd20_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Class&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;This June, my qigong teacher Bruce Frantzis will be offering &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/store/events/events/dragon-and-tiger-medical-qigong-instructor-training#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=932cfb54&#34;&gt;a two-week Dragon and Tiger Qigong instructor training&lt;/a&gt; on Maui. Over the past 10 years, I&#39;ve attended most of the instructor trainings that he has offered, as well as many weekends and week-long retreats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in an intensive learning environment at these events is great for your personal practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re thinking about teaching this material, though, you have to be smart about how you approach these trainings. While getting certified is an important step in the teaching process, too many people see certification as an end point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the&amp;Acirc;  lessons I&#39;ve learned about what you should do, before, during, and after the training.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3319&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. They are the single best opportunity to invest in your own practice long-term.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material you will be exposed to will continue to reveal itself through practice for several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;I don&#39;t really know how to describe it in normal language, because it&#39;s not the typical linear learning process that most of us are used to. Think of the entire experience as one big experiment in farming. Bruce will be giving you seeds at the training, and if you water them with regular practice, all kinds of interesting things will emerge later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The training is not an end point in your learning process.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are people at these events who pay their money, get their seeds, and then start to daydream about all the brightly colored vegetables&amp;Acirc;  that will grow from the seeds someday. The go home and put the shiny package of seeds on their shelf, telling all their friends about the great vegetables they&#39;ll harvest soon, and showing everyone their packet of seeds. Six months later, they all but forget about the packet on the shelf and have returned to their regular lives. The seeds never get planted. Nothing grows and more importantly, they miss the chance to be nourished by what they would have harvested if they had truly approached this as a farming opportunity. That&#39;s the problem with treating the training as an end point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Be the farmer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going in to the training, you want to prepare your soil as best you can. You want your soil to be well-tilled so that the seeds have a fertile place to grow. If you show up at the training and you spend all your time hacking away at fresh ground, trying to learn the movements, you&#39;re missing the real learning opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. The more you are &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;re-learning&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;, not just learning, the better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what your current level of practice, when you get to the training, you will break down and refine everything you already know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Pay attention to how you are learning in addition to what you are learning.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do this stage well, you will go home with a clear progression to follow for your future practice and your future teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;how to learn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; dimension is like plotting the rows in your fields. If you mark everything off well, then your plants are more likely to thrive. Most people don&#39;t do this. They get caught up in little details or go off on a weird practice tangent, fixated on one new feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you need to alternate between deep focus and feeling, and big picture thinking and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Bruce will teach something in a hour that I have easily turned into a seven-week course at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructor trainings are designed to be comprehensive, but in a compressed time frame, that means you&#39;ll have to go back later and work out the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Take notes after class.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do the right kind of note-taking, you can glean the structures of how the material is organized, which is incredibly useful when you start teaching. In these trainings, I prefer to take notes at the end of each teaching block, not during the flow of class. When you&#39;re there and you are hearing something for the first time, try to feel it in your body and practice it. Then, your note-taking at the end of the morning or afternoon session will be a reflection on something you&#39;ve already experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Look for patterns in your notes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start paying attention to the patterns in your notebook, you can also start to see how Bruce teaches each piece and then layers new ones in. He has a very clear rhythm of introducing new material, then letting people absorb it, then letting people struggle with it and practice. The Senior Instructors are great at pointing the way to this level of information too. The hard part is that you are there to learn and absorb it yourself, so you have to get used to paying attention to multiple levels at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Be in sponge-mode.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At these trainings, you&#39;ll feel things you&#39;ve never been able to connect with before. When that happens, try to absorb as much of the feeling as you can. Don&#39;t over think it, but get good practice reps in while you can still feel what it is ultimately supposed to feel like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Don&#39;t get addicted to the master&#39;s help.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People get stuck here, being able to feel new things that are actually well beyond their current level of practice. When you leave, you have what I call &#34;the Bruce hangover&#34; because as you go home and practice, it really doesn&#39;t feel like it did when you were in his field. That can be frustrating, but you learn over time that you can work through the material and arrive at real integration. People get hung up on the shortcut of having a master put something in their bodies though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. Start over at the beginning. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;When you go home, the best thing to do for your personal practice is to go back to the very first thing Bruce taught and day one and start practicing from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12. Keep&amp;Acirc;  up your personal practice beyond teaching hours.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing about the relationship between teaching and personal practice is that you need both and they have to be separate. You can&#39;t rely on teaching time to be practice time. In the past, when I slipped on really having a separate personal practice, my teaching would suffer and I would feel like crap. At the times when I could keep my own practice going, on top of teaching, the teaching would really blossom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13. Keep your personal practice out of the classroom.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t teach whatever you are interested in at the moment. I think that&#39;s kind of selfish and myopic. Why would a beginner benefit from something that you are practicing, 5, 10, or 20 years in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14. Don&#39;t teach anything you can&#39;t clearly see going on in someone else&#39;s body or that you can&#39;t demonstrate on command if they put their hands on yours.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, you shouldn&#39;t be teaching anything you&#39;re trying to figure out yourself. In the most extreme case, if you have to stop and think about choreography, you shouldn&#39;t be teaching choreography. If I have to fumble around to get my joints pulsing, or I can only do it every 3rd time, I have no business teaching it to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material that you should teach to other people is material that you&#39;ve learned and integrated and you really own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15. Don&#39;t overestimate what your students are ready for.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, I see new teachers overestimate the depth of what their students can learn anyway. Practically, everyone starts teaching beginners. When you start your first class after the training, you have to teach people the moves. This just means that you have to keep all the really cool stuff you learned at the training under you hat until you&#39;ve developed students who are ready for that material. As you develop them, you&#39;re developing too, so it all works out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16. Teach and you will harvest.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve taught 15-20 hours a week of classes and private lessons for the last 7 years and I have to say that my personal practice has grown in some pretty awesome dimensions that I didn&#39;t anticipate. The hard work of keeping teaching and practice separate and keeping them both going really does pay off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you&#39;re seriously considering going, you have six months &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/store/products/featured/dragon-and-tiger-book-dvd-poster-package#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=932cfb54&#34;&gt;to get ready&lt;/a&gt;. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 09:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure you&#39;ve spent time looking around YouTube for qigong and tai chi videos. According to their website, people upload 24 hours of video to YouTube &lt;em&gt;every minute&lt;/em&gt;! No doubt you&#39;ve seen some crazy stuff. So how do you sift through all of it and more importantly, are there any qigong videos on YouTube worth watching?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is, of course there are. And I&#39;ve put together a list of 5 good ones to get you started. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2522&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Practice with YouTube Qigong Videos&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you will see from the videos below, there is a blend of instructional content, guided practice, and demonstration. You have to get creative when you are borrowing from a source like online video to boost your practice. Sometimes you will just do a quick check-in. Sometimes you will sit and watch an entire lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&#39;t recommend trying to do your practice and darting back and forth to the computer at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the video has good audio guidance that can run in the background, great. Otherwise, just watch it once or twice and then go and practice. I&#39;ll try to point out key places in each video where you can see skilled practitioners demonstrating things they aren&#39;t necessarily talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This introduction to standing by Lam Kam Chuen is one of my favorite overviews of the practice. He talks a little bit about the background of the practice and gives just enough instruction to get you started. If you already have a standing practice, it&#39;s worth watching because you can revisit some of the overarching reasons to do this qigong method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/StandStillBeFit&#34;&gt;The entire channel&lt;/a&gt; is worth watching once you&#39;ve gone through the introductory clip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simple Circling Hands&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The natural transition from standing practice is to start repetitive movements. In standing, you tune into internal rhythms that only become obvious because there is no external movement. Circling Hands is a great bridge because your external movements are simple enough that you can let the internal rhythms drive them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch as &lt;a title=&#34;Q&amp;amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; performs Circling Hands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most important thing you can get from this YouTube qigong video is the way his whole body opens and closes, pulsing from the center, outward.&amp;Acirc; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exploring Internal Flows&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the next video, &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt; explains how to activate the two main energy flows that run your body: Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth. He teaches two different exercises to highlight these flows. Like Paul&#39;s demonstration above, if you practice these exercises you will begin to feel the &#34;pulls&#34; through the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth pointing out that while you may or may not be able to feel what he&#39;s describing right away, every teacher I&#39;ve ever had insists that you need to develop the internal sensitivity to these subtle movements through a standing or sitting practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transitioning into More Movement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Each mode of qigong practice gives you access to something different. &#34;Quiet&#34; practices like standing qigong or sitting meditation allow you to develop your internal awareness with as little physical coordination as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving practices do two things: they develop rhythm and they challenge your ability to maintain internal focus because of the ever-changing external conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these next two videos, we&#39;re going to introduce more movement, first by adding weight-shifting and turning, then by looking at the qigong set with the most complicated external form: Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try this &#34;Rolling the Ball&#34; exercise to see if you can maintain some of the internal awareness primed in the earlier qigong videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this last video isn&#39;t designed to be instructional or a follow-along practice. Instead, I want you to watch it and see if you can pick up some of the things we&#39;ve looked at in the other YouTube qigong videos in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see internal continuity? Opening and closing? Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth flows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The secret to training your eyes to see more subtle movement patterns is to look at someone&#39;s movements, in this case Tai Chi master &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, and try to feel inside your own body what he must be doing to create those movements.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this post gives you some ideas about how to use YouTube qigong videos to improve your own practice. Got any favorites that I&#39;ve left out? Be sure to let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Form Training Final Update</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 12:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m heading home to Boston tomorrow, but I&#39;ve already begun looking through my notes and thinking about what I will personally practice and what I&#39;ll be able to share with my students in classes this coming year. Here are some of my initial thoughts:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1827&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ZkLnAA8ejb8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ZkLnAA8ejb8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Material is Woven together over a Month:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Day to day we&#39;re looking at really small specific pieces but now going back through my notes, I can start to see different threads that run throughout the duration of the month. It&#39;s almost like you don&#39;t even notice some of the nuances as in the moment, but like we&#39;ll look at something about the legs in Tai Chi from the first day and then we came back to it four or five days later and then we look at it again, and when you actually line up the pieces side by side, what you start to see is that...versus looking at it from like sort of looking at a ball, you look at it from one side and then the next time you look at it from this angle, then you look at it from this angle. And by taking this kind of spherical approach to it, looking at different facets of the subject, you start to develop a sense for the whole. And it&#39;s not the progression that he always teaches and it&#39;s not linear. It&#39;s not one, two, three, four, five. It&#39;s look at it this way, look at it that way and it&#39;s sort of up to you to put the pieces together to create the whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Handling Stress on a Whole New Level&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;They&#39;re all are these layers to that and progressions that I&#39;ll be able to lay out for my students, but personally for me I think one of the most exciting ones that I&#39;ll be able to bring to people is some really specific technical information about burnout and stress and no, I mean, if you think about Tai Chi in general, that&#39;s kind of what it&#39;s known for. It&#39;s a relaxation practice and it looks calming in that way. Everybody&#39;s first impression of it is that it is gentle and relaxing, but we actually got in much deeper into the technical stuff and the form that actually makes the softness of Tai Chi really work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;s not always contrasted to the couch potato model of relaxation where we live in this culture where we think, okay just go, go, go, go, go 24/7 and when you want to relax, pass out on the couch in front of the TV. So we have these two extremes. Tai chi is sort of an antidote to stress. It works on relaxation but it&#39;s a little more complicated than that. It&#39;s not... relaxation isn&#39;t just a flop. Relaxation has to do much more with your capacity to put energy out and take energy in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there&#39;s some really interesting technical stuff in terms of being able to absorb and nourish the body that is really Tai Chi&#39;s strong suit that you&#39;re not going to get in this kind of fast paced go, go, go, very Yang, very revved up kind of mentality. Instead, Tai Chi has a way of building the nervous system and building the body up so that it can rest, absorb and regenerate and we looked at some really specific ways to highlight in the form to make sure that happens for people.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update from the Beach</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 3 wraps up and testing is right around the corner. What was Bruce&#39;s big message as we prepare for testing? Work your ass off and cram all night for the big test? Not quite. You might be surprised. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1823&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/BQcg7CR5F78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/BQcg7CR5F78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Lesson about Integration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing that Bruce is emphasizing in the last couple days of class is that with this stage of the training, a month long training, you need integration time. And we talk about this all the time in regular weekly classes. We talk about in a given practice session, whether it&#39;s an hour or 20 minutes or whatever, you always have this sort of startup time where you just get warmed up. And then from there you go into the work period, where you just kind of crank and crank and crank, and that&#39;s when your system is the most open. You can get a lot done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the biggest mistake people make is that they do that hard charge all the way to the end. The secret to all of these energy practices, to really get your energy to smoothed out and then get into your nervous system in the best possible way, is that you need to have integration. So, we talk about it all the time. That&#39;s how we try to do each practice session. So, to me, it&#39;s really cool to watch this month-long work and hear Bruce talk about that and emphasize that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Yesterday he talked a lot about what to do on the day off, in terms of even just mentally rehearsing the form, going through and trying to feel it through your body without doing the movements. So there&#39;s a lot of interesting stuff about mental rehearsal that we talked about, but also just to let it kind of soak into your system. And I find when students can recognize that integration phase as a legitimate part of the practice, then you take it to a whole deeper level, because you recognize rest as an important part of hard work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And I think there are a lot of ways that we&#39;ve lost that idea culturally and a lot of ideas of success and hard work don&#39;t really acknowledge the resting and integration phase as an important piece of it. So even though we&#39;ve come through intensive month-long training, as we&#39;re rounding into the final stretch, rest and integration and relaxation is a key piece to learning all this stuff. And to me that&#39;s very cool. So that&#39;s what we&#39;re up to this week.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 of the Short Form Instructor Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 09:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my Week 2 update. Some big milestones this week: group 1 finished the form and group 2 has been languishing in the purgatory that is holding static postures. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1816&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/FpsecDulvWc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/FpsecDulvWc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inner Form vs. Outer Form&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;In the two groups, we&#39;re doing very different things. The group one just finished the form this week. So on Thursday after they finished it, we came in Friday, and it was a really interesting dividing line. Bruce made the big distinction between, on the one hand, on Thursday we finished the shape and the form, that&#39;s sort of the container. He said, &#34;Now, everything that we&#39;re going to do has to do with internal content.&#34; So he made this distinction all the time. He talked about the bottle versus the wine you put inside it and we even have an article at Brookline Tai Chi that we put out from, I think, it&#39;s from 1989 Tai Chi Magazine. The title of the article is &#34;The Inner Form is the Key to Health.&#34; And in the article, Bruce talks about all the different internal content things that should be going on that to be Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And I find this working with beginners all the time is such a huge hurdle to get them over. Because people know Tai Chi by looks like in the outside, they see the shapes and the movements, and they see it flowing and graceful and relaxed, but it&#39;s really hard unless you&#39;re used to looking at it, to see what&#39;s going on inside. But Bruce always makes this big point, it actually what goes on inside that makes Tai Chi actually effective. It makes it not just choreography but it makes it work to improve your health, we&#39;re going to do meditation and martial arts. If you don&#39;t have the internal content, it&#39;s like driving a car without an engine. So it&#39;s interesting to hear him talk about for a group that&#39;s just finishing the container of the form. Now, to start to see what he started out with. And as far as internal content for them and how we&#39;re going to build that up. So that&#39;s a cool inflection point in the halfway point for the first group.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Finding Internal Stability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the second group we&#39;ve been holding postures. And so we&#39;ve gone through now, I think, eight of the postures and the form, and building out from twenty, twenty-five, thirty minutes. And this is one of my favorite methods - the posture holding and you see up here, look at some other posing here, you see me messing around with 30 minutes in one posture or something else like that, I&#39;ve always liked it in the standing practice. It was the thing that kind of, for me, made the difference of what&#39;s in the outside and &#34;Hey, if you stand still and start to just feel into the body, there&#39;s this whole internal landscape you can start to explore.&#34; And that was the thing that always got me excited about Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&#39;m very happy that we&#39;ve been going through and holding posture by posture. What it is about it, is that if you get into each posture and the form, each of them because of the physical constraints, higher twisting, one way twisting, the other way, whether the posture&#39;s more extended, or whether the posture is more condensed, all of these things add up to determine in a specific posture how you manifest the energy of that posture. And so by holding it, you start to feel those internal gears kind of click and lock together in a way that you just if you&#39;re always just going through the form doing whatever, you totally missed that aspect. Sometimes you noticed really where you&#39;re tense, where things are stuck. But once you get each one of these things, it has kind of like a threshold where it clicks in. And I&#39;ve always thought about it in terms of, &#34;Okay, I&#39;m going to hold this one for twenty, this one for thirty, this one longer, longer.&#34; But one of the key points that Bruce made was that once you hit a certain stability point for that posture, everything opens up and lights up. The pathways light up or this connection lights up that gives the posture a unique flavor. That&#39;s the key moment. And then you wanted to maintain that for as long as you can. And inevitably you lose it, you shrink out of it, you start to collapse a little bit, something gets off. And this is game of like, &#34;Okay, how do I connect to it?&#34; Reliably create that effective posture and then stabilize it. And once you can stabilize it for a long time, then you move into this thing where the quality, the posture becomes integrated into your form and to how you move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to me, I don&#39;t know, it&#39;s a fascinating process. Other people joke that the fastest way clear Tai Chi class and get everybody to flee out of the room is to just make them close their eyes and hold the posture. So it&#39;s definitely a matter of personal preference. But I mean it&#39;s really cool, that&#39;s what we&#39;ve been focusing on all week.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am Learning at the Wu Tai Chi Instructor Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 01:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re a week into the Wu Tai Chi short form instructor training in Brighton, UK, with Lineage Holder Bruce Frantzis. So far we&#39;ve been completely rebuilding our forms, working on Tai Chi leg power, and exploring the meditative aspects of the art. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2964&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HoXz88Vyxe0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HoXz88Vyxe0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Rebuilding Your Form:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s crazy when you come at these things, you&#39;re completely rebuilding your Tai Chi form. We&#39;re about two-thirds of the way through the form and it feels so different. When you&amp;Acirc;  run through the whole thing one time, you get up to what we&#39;ve done so far and it feels brand new, like a completely different moves. And then you get to the last thing we&#39;ve done, you come around to the last move that you finished and you go back to your old form and it has a totally different feeling.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Yin and Yang of Tai Chi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contrast is that the biggest thing that he took from the London trainings into the Tai Chi training was this idea. He talks about it in terms of Yin and Yang, in terms of soft and hard, or in the sitting practice, it&#39;s about how do you go deep inside the body. You find this internal space and then let go of anything you find that&#39;s stuck. But there&#39;s an interesting contrast, it&#39;s not just let go and relax and collapse because the quality of mind it takes is that you have to sort of go inside, find and hold your awareness on something and persist with this awareness. That&#39;s a stronger quality. So this is interesting, this is Yin and Yang blend of getting your mind onto something and holding it there, giving it shape and containing this feeling. But then the other side it to completely let go, completely relaxing. So that&#39;s the Yin and Yang of the dissolving process. And we&#39;ve expanded that idea where he&#39;s talking about the energies in the Tai Chi form, the way we working on Tai Chi, the forming energies to the form, that balance of finding it, holding it and adding this kind of consistent, persistent meditative awareness as you do Tai Chi, is mirrored in the sort of the Yang aspects of the Tai Chi form. And then that letting go, softening, releasing, relaxing and just completely not holding on anything is there&#39;s the Yin qualities to the form, that have that same thing. So through Peng, Lu, Ji and An, each one of those from a meditative point of view can figure into how you&#39;re doing, making your Tai Chi form a true meditation practice, not just relaxation practice. So there&#39;s really great stuff there.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>