<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>personal-practice on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/personal-practice/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in personal-practice on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/personal-practice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-4629&#34; alt=&#34;help-browser&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/05/help-browser-150x150.png&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend last night about &lt;a title=&#34;Guide to Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; and different &lt;a title=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;meditation traditions&lt;/a&gt; that we had both tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many different reasons, on any given day, that we sought out the practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To clear our heads of racing thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To more deeply relax the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explore layers of the mind and emotions that aren&#39;t so obvious during our normal busy days.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It seems like we had really similar reasons to practice, but I was left wondering if it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; similar when we practice. What are the sensations that tell you you&#39;re on the right track? It seems like we want to end up in the same place, but are we taking the same road to get there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p4r3&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p4r3&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p4r3;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p4r3&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;554&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { r7p4r3 = new WufooForm();r7p4r3.initialize(options);r7p4r3.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 Practice Partners You Should Avoid</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/10/17/4-practice-partners-you-should-avoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 08:29:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/10/17/4-practice-partners-you-should-avoid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The next time you go to class, watch out for these 4 practice partners. While they all start out with good intentions, if you hang out with them too much, you&#39;ll get sucked into their quirky habits and slow down your own progress. Don&#39;t say I didn&#39;t warn you!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2278&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Checklist Charlie&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Checklist Charlie is the tai chi student who is forever stuck in his own head. Every time he practices, instead of feeling his body, he recites a list of stuff he is supposed to be doing. For most people, &#34;soundtracking&#34; your way through the form is a legitimate learning phase, but Checklist Charlie is stuck there forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/eaJebVBzufY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/eaJebVBzufY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Intense Irene&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Intense Irene takes her practice way too far. At first, this is a good thing. She works hard and uncovers a lot of depth. Over time though, she goes too deeply into one thing and it distorts the rest of her practice, leaving her potentially injured, way too tense, and out of balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HAIzvee9Ga4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HAIzvee9Ga4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Workshop Wally&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Workshop Wally loves to collect pieces of his practice, like random pieces from a bunch of different puzzles. When he tries to fit them all together, it&#39;s a total disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GfKb18GTeoQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GfKb18GTeoQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Environmental Ernie&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;m not talking about your &#34;greenest&#34; student, I&#39;m talking about the one with no internal motivation to practice. Environmental Ernie relies on the external environment, fellow students, regular classes, instructor-led sessions, to do his practice. And I think that&#39;s fine! We can all learn from his laid-back ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ueAUIXDyVdE?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ueAUIXDyVdE?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Twice a Day</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 04:32:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So, I know I&#39;m writing this on vacation where the most pressing decision we make each day is whether to hike, kayak, or swim, but I&#39;m going to go ahead anyway and recommend that you practice twice a day. Here&#39;s why...&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1979&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/in5LGYtp8xw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/in5LGYtp8xw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Learned from a Month-Long Tai Chi Intensive&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After a month in England, practicing 10 hours a day at &lt;a title=&#34;Movement Arts&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011&#34;&gt;the Short Form Instructor Training&lt;/a&gt; this summer, I have a renewed appreciation for daily practice rhythm. At the training, there were three distinct types of training sessions we would go through each day. In the mornings, we would practice in our groups. Most of the day, from 10am to 5pm was reserved for class time with Bruce. In the evenings, we would be free to practice again, ideally training the pieces of what we did in class that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During class time, we would have ten or twenty minutes to practice each new thing that Bruce introduced. That&#39;s fine to get an initial hit of each piece, but that brief exposure isn&#39;t the same thing as locking it in to your system. You have to take it two steps further. First, you have to expand that twenty minutes into forty-five minutes or an hour in the evening sessions. Then, after you eat and sleep and feel rested, you have to revisit the same material in a lighter way the next morning, trying to let the new material flow into your regular morning practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you look at the three pieces of each training day, you had integration of the previous day first thing in the morning, then new material during the bulk of the day, and finally a chance to really work on the new material in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the clearest way to see how this rhythm worked was to watch people not follow it! When people would blow off the evening training session, you could tell that the material wasn&#39;t soaking into their system the next day. Likewise, if they worked hard on pieces in the morning session (which they should have done the night before), they didn&#39;t have enough energy to get the most of out class that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I&#39;m Learning Practicing Twice a Day on Vacation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Going on vacation and having the free time to test this out again, I&#39;m even more convinced that you can learn a lot about your own practice rhythm by spreading out practice sessions throughout your day. The most surprising insight from the training was: &lt;strong&gt;the morning practice sessions were related more to the work I did the day before than they were to the two sessions following on the same day.&lt;/strong&gt; In other words, Tuesday morning practice was the completion of the training I did on Monday, not the warm-up for the rest of the training I was about to do on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the bigger pattern I wanted to test on vacation and it seems to be working really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you realize what this means, right? It means that eating, sleeping, and letting things settle down is an important part of learning. Or in other words, rest and integration complete hard work. We tend to think of work as an on/off switch. We&#39;re either working hard or being lazy. The lesson here is that rest and integration are the real opposites of hard work and that hard work doesn&#39;t pay off until you&#39;ve integrated it. Pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other cool thing about making this connection has been that now I feel like I&#39;m in one long training session. I used to think &#34;I practiced Monday, missed Tuesday, and Wednesday through Friday I did a little bit....I suck&#34;. Now, though, I think about chaining sessions of work, rest, and integration together and it gives the process much more continuity. You get out of an all-or-nothing mindset about your practice. To me, that seems to be much closer to making your practice a real part of the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Leave me a comment below and tell me about your practice cycles. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personal Practice Journey</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/17/personal-practice-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 10:12:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/17/personal-practice-journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having the luxury of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011&#34;&gt;full month of training&lt;/a&gt; this summer has made me step back and reflect on my own personal practice over the last 13 years. I tried to put together some of what this process has been like for me and sum it up &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/about/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;m curious to know what you think. Have you gone through periods of practicing without a teacher? Have you had times where you&#39;ve made huge strides in your practice? What was that like? Did the fruits of that period last a long time? Use the comments section below and let me know what it was like for you (or shoot me an email, but other people are probably curious too!).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Breathing, Qigong, and Meditation Improve Quality of Life</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/20/how-breathing-qigong-and-meditation-improve-quality-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 08:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/20/how-breathing-qigong-and-meditation-improve-quality-of-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I asked my friend and fellow qigong practitioner Catherine Chenoweth to talk a little bit about her experience using qigong to manage a chronic health condition. Here&#39;s what she had to say:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1782&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/07/5349FC1E-3A30-461B-9D4C-EC402891879A0.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;margin: 5px;&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/07/5349FC1E-3A30-461B-9D4C-EC402891879A0.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;160&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; align=&#34;left&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I was released from the hospital in 1996, it was after three months, and with a diagnosis of LAM (Lymphangioleiomyomatosis), a rare, progressive, untreatable and often fatal lung disease. I asked a friend who was well versed in alternative treatments what I should do for my health, and his response, immediate and emphatic, was &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;You need to do qigong!&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I did. What started as an effort to do something proactive for my health turned into a life long passion and became an irreplaceable part of my life. I think one of the smartest things I ever did was to take an entire week course of breathing with Bruce Frantzis. One thing that is very clear when one really starts to lose their ability to breathe is how much we take breathing for granted. It may even seem like a silly thing to spend money on &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; an entire week learning how to breathe! But it is a subject that has a surprising amount of depth, and you learn quickly that many people have very poor breathing habits. To learn to breathe with the entirety of your lungs, not just the lower half of the lung as opposed to the chest, but with the sides and back of the lung as well, is something that can increase overall efficiency, something that is a must for people with progressive lung disease who want to maintain the best quality of life that they can. Not only will proper technique and practice affect your breathing, but it will spill over into areas such as stress reduction, pain reduction, and overall well being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, a balance of breathing, meditation, and qigong has been the key to maximizing my quality of life with a lung disease. The slow, gentle movements of qigong give me a way to exercise when my body is unable to do any type of western exercise, for example when faced with chronic lung collapses or after a surgery. To progress in qigong means to go deeper into layers of your body, learning to become sensitive to and to manipulate soft tissue, fluids, joints and energy. To progress in certain other forms of exercise often means doing more physically demanding, more aerobic, bigger, faster movements &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; all aspects that can be impossible goals for someone who is sick or disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I applaud anyone who takes the first steps toward taking charge of their health. In an increasingly busy and distracted society, it can seem like the last thing on anyone&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s list is to be healthy and take care of their bodies. Whether you have an illness, disease, or injury, or whether you are healthy and wish to maintain your health into old age, find some time in your life to learn some of these ancient practices, and find some time in your day to practice them. A simple breathing or qigong practice will allow you to connect with your body again, and the rewards are well worth the effort. Being through what I have been through has given me a unique perspective and a deep appreciation of the limits and possibilities of the human body. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s the only vessel you have to get you through this life. Care for it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DIY Home Practice Challenge</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 13:19:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/06/diy-home-practice-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the recent practice survey we conducted at Brookline Tai Chi and experiments I&#39;ve been running in online learning, it&#39;s become clearer and clearer to me that most people need some external motivation when they are learning a new skill. That&#39;s not a judgment about willpower and motivation, it actually says more about the way we are wired for survival. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1523&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In Z Health, we always talk about the way that the nervous system is at once the most plastic system -- it can adapt to lots of different changes -- and also the most stable. The stability of the nervous system is a good thing from a survival and energy management point of view -- it doesn&#39;t cost you a lot of cognitive energy to get through your day if you run on habit. In that sense, the plasticity of the nervous system -- your ability to change and learn new things -- has to deal with the inertia of stability in your nervous system. When we are trying to learn new behaviors and forge new habits, these two things can be at odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&#39;ve seen and heard from my tai chi students, is that a little bit of external motivation goes a long way to spark the small changes you need to make on a daily basis to put new behavior in place. Last week, one of my students said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was liberating to think that 5 minutes of tai chi practice meant I could make progress, because until I thought about it that way, I avoided practice, assuming it was going to take 30 minutes or more.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, if you look at some studies on mental rehearsal and brain function, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1580438,00.html&#34;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;, you start to see that the cognitive component of learning new skills can be practiced in a much easier way than devoting hours and hours of grueling practice -- time that very few people I work with have to spare anyway. The smarter you get about your practice, the better you&#39;ll get at getting good at new things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#39;s my DIY Home Practice Challenge for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drill down into your practice until you get to a small chunk you can practice in 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick the easiest time of day to devote to your practice -- what&#39;s the perfect scenario for practicing this skill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a recurring reminder in your calendar -- pick the medium that will be most accessible to get the reminder at the right time, i.e. on your desktop to interrupt your work, via email, or even text message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each day when you get the reminder, do your 5 minute practice, and then maybe take a minute or two to reflect on the success of what you just did or refine the scenario if necessary&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You will fail to build up this practice habit if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You pick too big a skill to work on, e.g. I want to become a ballerina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are vague about when you are going to do it, e.g. I will practice it daily&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don&#39;t get the reminder at the right time, e.g. I&#39;ll practice at noon each day, but my reminder comes in at 6pm&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I know those failures might sound obvious, and you should pick something pretty simple and obvious to begin with, but what I hope is that once you see the power in this simple approach, you&#39;ll start to tackle more complex and exciting skill building and begin to reflect on a lot of different experiences, in business, at work, in personal relationships, with the same desire to make incremental progress as you do with a hobby or healthy habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m always curious to hear how this goes for people, so send me an email or drop a comment below once you get set up and start hitting your daily targets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing Single Whip</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/02/standing-single-whip/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 08:38:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/02/standing-single-whip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every time I circle back to extended periods of posture-holding, I find all kinds of new layers in my practice. Lately, I&#39;ve been holding Single Whip. I was shooting some other videos and I thought, &#34;why not see what happens over those 30 minutes&#34;. I had a mic on, so whenever I changed focus or felt some big internal shift, I made a comment. The end result, condensed down to 3:30, includes minute markers for each of the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/V05FDZbMHo4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/V05FDZbMHo4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here&#39;s the same footage, except all 30 minutes are shown, sped up at 8x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/WALkgFQ9a2w?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/WALkgFQ9a2w?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi in Telluride</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/02/tai-chi-in-telluride/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 10:51:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/02/tai-chi-in-telluride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/QExDRp6pAjg?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/QExDRp6pAjg?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take Home One New Thing</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/03/24/take-home-one-new-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 10:32:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/03/24/take-home-one-new-thing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-825&#34; title=&#34;Telluride&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/03/P1000033-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hiking in Telluride&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m on vacation this week in Telluride, Colorado. Telluride nestled into a box canyon, with peaks jutting up all around it. Pretty amazing scenery and hiking around at 10,000 feet gives you plenty of time to think. Whenever I come to a place like this, I always play the game of &#34;What If I Lived Here&#34;, where I try to envision life as a local. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-730&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Compared to what I hear about some ski towns, by the way, Telluride has a nice mellow blend of local vibe and constant visitor turn over. But why is that game so interesting? What&#39;s so fascinating about picturing yourself living somewhere you don&#39;t?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#39;ve thought about it over the last few days, it seems pretty similar to a learning problem you have as a student, a professional development problem you face as a teacher, and even a business problem you have running a small business. The problem is this: &lt;em&gt;how does inspiration that comes from somewhere outside of your normal routine impact and integrate with what you go back to doing on a regular basis?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, can I take something away from these gorgeous mountains without feeling like I need to move here? Can I learn a new form or exercise without abandoning everything I&#39;ve learned before?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the obvious answer is, of course you can. But as I&#39;m sitting here watching the mountains in the distance fade into morning clouds, I feel like really knowing this place is going to take more than a couple of days. So that&#39;s the flip side: if I take a little piece away with me, is it going to mean anything?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Take Home When I Travel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just getting a taste of place may not be the same thing as knowing it like your own home town, but I think it can help you know your home better. The things that jump out at you when you&#39;re in a new place have certainly faded into the background when you&#39;re at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, we were talking to a pilot in a bar yesterday. Recently arrived from the Bay Area, he says his most pressing problem in Telluride is whether to ski, fish, or go to the airport everyday. The good news was, if he timed it right, he could do all three. While we joked about the laid back rhythm of life here, it got me thinking about rhythms at home. You become blind to them as you go about your day, but I&#39;ve learned from Tai Chi that if you can be aware of an internal rhythm as you go through it, it&#39;s energizing, not draining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, being out in the mountains, there are many more geographic features to appreciate, and you can be sure when I go home, I&#39;ll be looking at rivers and oceans, and ok, hills, a little differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I&#39;m trying to say that coming to a place that feels so different from home gives you fresh appreciation for home and is worth it for that alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Take Home When I Study With Someone New&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Learning qigong, martial arts, or fitness over the years, I&#39;ve been exposed to many teachers, styles, and philosophies of movement. At this point, whenever I study with someone new, I try to treat it just like a travel experience: I&#39;m not moving anywhere, but just seeing things from a fresh perspective helps me appreciate the trajectory of my own practice and highlights certain elements of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say &#34;at this point&#34; because I think there is a learning threshold for being able to take small pieces from different sources and make sense of them. If you are too early in your practice, this is not a good approach. See, the drive to &#34;move to Telluride&#34; is a drive to have an integrated experience and understanding of something. Just like moving from country to country or town to town would make it hard to answer &#34;where are you from&#34;, trying to throw together understanding of movement by adding bits and pieces from different sources right from the start doesn&#39;t make sense either. You need to have an integrated learning experience first, before you try to add new elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to movement, my intuition is that 3-5 years of learning in a coherent system gives you this foundation. Many of my favorite practitioners and teachers talk about &#34;forging&#34; your body, like making a sword. You need to devote time to a single approach to let the method work on you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But once you cross this threshold, learning from a new teacher can be just like traveling to a new place. I&#39;ve experienced this time and again in workshops or seminars. Someone will have a very clear way to present (talking in Tai Chi terms now), how to feel the arms driven by the legs -- it might happen in an external form I&#39;ve never trained before, but the principle behind the movement is translateable into what I already know. And so you can take on new facets of your practice, without dabbling. It&#39;s more like refining the trajectory you are already on. The path becomes clearer and more focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the degree that you have a foundation in an art (and here&#39;s where I think learning, teaching, and doing business are all similar), being exposed to new ideas will refine what you already do. But there&#39;s one final hurdle that you need to overcome to really make this work: &lt;strong&gt;You have to throw away more than you keep.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s an art to finding the right ratio of &#34;throwing away&#34; and &#34;keeping&#34;, but it boils down to this. If you can take home one new thing, each time you go to a workshop, observe someone else&#39;s class, or read a business book, that&#39;s a huge success. It&#39;s so tempting, when someone presents a compelling idea, to say, &#34;that&#39;s it, I&#39;m abandoning everything I&#39;ve learned before and doing it this way!&#34; But you can&#39;t do that. It&#39;s the very same urge you feel when you travel to someplace beautiful and say &#34;Ok, I&#39;m dropping everything and moving here!&#34;. What about 99% of your life that exists back home. Transforming it into a new life in a new place isn&#39;t so simple. Yes, the pull is there, but if you can &#34;throw away&#34; most of that desire and &#34;keep&#34; the core of it, you&#39;ll be fond of the new place you&#39;ve visited AND deepen your appreciation for where you are from. It&#39;s the same for learning, teaching, and business.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>