<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi-practice on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi-practice/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi-practice on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi-practice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Update on Quantity vs. Quality and the Struggle for Perfect Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/06/19/update-on-quantity-vs-quality-and-the-struggle-for-perfect-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2013 07:32:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/06/19/update-on-quantity-vs-quality-and-the-struggle-for-perfect-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few months ago we talked about &lt;a title=&#34;Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/&#34;&gt;the signs of progress in your qigong practice&lt;/a&gt;. For so many of us, the issue of &#34;progress&#34; is central to qigong or Tai Chi practice, since we are driven by the desire to get it right, to solve a problem like a health issue, or to reach an amorphous and elusive spiritual goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we completely abandoned the idea of outcomes and perfection in practice? Instead, what if you started each day with a &#34;doing&#34; mindset in your qigong practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take this example of a ceramics teacher from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Art-Fear-Observations-Rewards-Artmaking/dp/0961454733&#34;&gt;Art and Fear by David Bayles and Ted Orland&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://kk.org/cooltools/archives/000216&#34;&gt;In his review of the book&lt;/a&gt;, Kevin Kelly pulls this and many more excellent excerpts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The ceramics teacher announced on opening day that he was dividing the class into two groups. All those on the left side of the studio, he said, would be graded solely on the quantity of work they produced, all those on the right solely on its quality. His procedure was simple: on the final day of class he would bring in his bathroom scales and weigh the work of the &#34;quantity&#34; group: fifty pound of pots rated an &#34;A&#34;, forty pounds a &#34;B&#34;, and so on. Those being graded on &#34;quality&#34;, however, needed to produce only one pot -albeit a perfect one - to get an &#34;A&#34;. Well, came grading time and a curious fact emerged: the works of highest quality were all produced by the group being graded for quantity. It seems that while the &#34;quantity&#34; group was busily churning out piles of work - and learning from their mistakes - the &#34;quality&#34; group had sat theorizing about perfection, and in the end had little more to show for their efforts than grandiose theories and a pile of dead clay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What does your Tai Chi practice look like if you focus on building quantity? One of my favorite examples is from Chinese Wrestling expert John Wang. In this short documentary, he demonstrates Tree Hanging for building martial power (and maybe other important attributes?):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://youtu.be/wqnQj1Lx02Y&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Master Wang discusses technique and gives his student pointers, but when asked when the practice gets easier, he says, &#34;second year.&#34; That&#39;s a quantity mindset, to measure the progress of a daily practice by  year-over-year changes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you don&#39;t need to go out and tear the flesh from your arm for a full year to build a foundation for your practice (and he doesn&#39;t think many people will do it anymore anyway), but is there an element of your practice that can be measured in quantity, not quality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of whatever &#34;semester&#34; you are currently in, what component of your practice would you place on the bathroom scale? Where can you focus your time and effort to amass some serious practice skill?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, what high quality fruits will you be surprised with at the end of a quantity-driven period of practice?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 11:14:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft  wp-image-4644&#34; alt=&#34;HMS guide to Tai Chi&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/05/HMS-guide-to-Tai-Chi1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;120&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; In his new book, the Harvard Medical School Guide to Tai Chi, &lt;a title=&#34;Living between the Lab and the Classroom with Dr. Peter Wayne&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/&#34;&gt;Dr. Peter Wayne&lt;/a&gt; lays out the &#34;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; to help us understand the interface between traditional Tai Chi practice and the Western biomedical paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Research Director of the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, jointly based at Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, and the founder of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.treeoflifetaichi.com/instructors.html&#34;&gt;Tree of Life Tai Chi Center&lt;/a&gt;, Peter blends more than three decades of teaching experience with ongoing inquiry into what makes Tai Chi an effective medical intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, we explore the development of the 8 Active Ingredients and how help translate Tai Chi into a Western context&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi are:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awareness, Mindfulness, Focused Attention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intention, Belief, Expectation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic Structural Integration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active Relaxation of Mind and Body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aerobic Exercise, Musculoskeletal Strengthening, and Flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natural, Freer Breathing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Interaction and Community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embodied Spirituality, Philosophy, and Ritual&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I asked Peter to explain how he understands Tai Chi practice through these 8 ingredients and how they are related to each other. While there are many ways to explain what Tai Chi is, this framework has to explain Tai Chi to a Western medical audience, making each element of the practice related to biomedical and psychological principles rooted in evidence-based medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter tells us what was easy to convey and where the Tai Chi principles were more esoteric, but important to explain through the framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also makes the case for greater medical literacy amongst Tai Chi teachers and practitioners because, as Tai Chi research gets more sophisticated, the feedback loop between what gets studied and how Tai Chi is defined will get tighter and tighter. If you&#39;re concerned with the legacy of Tai Chi in the West, you need to be a part of this conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the podcast for all that and a great sense for Peter&#39;s insight, generosity, and caring as a practitioner and leader in the Tai Chi research field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Rhythms at Tai Chi Immersion Week </title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/23/practice-rhythms-at-tai-chi-immersion-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 11:16:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/23/practice-rhythms-at-tai-chi-immersion-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is my mid-week update from Tai Chi Immersion Week 2013 at &lt;a title=&#34;Brookline Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/brookline-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s pretty cool to see folks come from all over to train for a week, but you really have to have the right mind set to make the most of the format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See what I mean here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://youtu.be/tBOBhSljYNo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice, be sure to include a clear:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warm-up: &lt;/strong&gt;where you settle in and transition from the rest of your day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ramp-up:&lt;/strong&gt; where the real &#34;training&#34; happens and you work on specific attributes of your practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration period:&lt;/strong&gt; where you don&#39;t try to do anything new, but let the work from the ramp-up period settle down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buffer:&lt;/strong&gt; where, without making an abrupt shift, you transition back into the rest of your day.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Whether you practice for &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;20 minutes&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a title=&#34;Practice Twice a Day&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/&#34;&gt;twice a day for a week&lt;/a&gt;, if you look for these rhythms, you will build more energy and deepen your Tai Chi practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>