<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>health-month on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/health-month/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in health-month on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/health-month/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Health Month Wrap-Up</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/29/health-month-wrap-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 14:48:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/29/health-month-wrap-up/</guid>
      <description>As March comes to an end, I&#39;m wrapping up playing Health Month, an online game that helps you integrate new habits and change behavior. Here&#39;s my review of Health Month and a recap of what I experienced. I have to say, I don&#39;t think I really explored it to the fullest, but there were a couple of things I really liked about it and a couple of things I didn&#39;t connect with in the design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Rules Are Lame</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/07/my-rules-are-lame/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 08:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/07/my-rules-are-lame/</guid>
      <description>So, with one week of Health Month under my belt, I think one thing is clear: I picked some pretty lame rules for March! I mean, they&#39;re pretty plain and looking at some of the other options, I definitely could have picked something more interesting. I chose:
 Bring lunch to work 3x per week Track food at least 6x per week Exercise at least 5x per week

I picked those rules initially because I thought they would be easy to track and measure and because I had already been working on them in February.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signing the Contract</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/04/signing-the-contract/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 08:38:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/04/signing-the-contract/</guid>
      <description>Part of playing Health Month is signing a contract to commit to follow your rules....and I was really surprised when I did it! One of the things I&#39;m thinking about while playing is how this is different from simply tracking what you eat, when you work out, and even setting goals in other areas. I didn&#39;t think it was going to be a big deal to actually sign this commitment, but it was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March is Going to be Health Month</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/21/march-is-going-to-be-health-month/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2011 09:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/02/21/march-is-going-to-be-health-month/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m pretty excited to try this one out. Health Month is a behavior change game where you set rules to follow each month and do daily tracking, with rewards and penalties for how well you follow them. I&#39;m just digging into it, but so far it looks like you can choose &#34;do more of this&#34; or &#34;do less of that&#34;. I like the idea of limiting the scope of the goal to a month (what BJ Fogg calls a &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>