<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>spine on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/spine/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in spine on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/spine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 Update</title>
      <link>/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 09:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a quick update on what we&#39;ve been working on during Immersion Week 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/-KpibI0ZE9s?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m very impressed (and I say so in the video about 15 times!) with the way this group has patiently explored many different facets of the Swings and Spine Stretch without rushing ahead to try to fit seemingly contradictory pieces together conceptually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, they&#39;re doing a great job experiencing/exploring each different component on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice this way, you naturally come to integration points where the components gel in a way you couldn&#39;t have predicted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Moving Exercises: Immersion Week 2014</title>
      <link>/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 10:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m getting excited about &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Immersion Week at BTC next month&lt;/a&gt;, where we&#39;ll take another look at the Spine Stretch and the Three Swings. Another look? Like we&#39;ve done it before? Yes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it exciting to go back to the same qigong sets over and over again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So-called creative people understand better than most that there is nothing new under the sun. Working with boulders of granite, with empty stages, with blank paper, they are credited with making something out of nothing, but that isn&#39;t exactly what they do. All art is derived from what is in actuality a remarkably finite human experience. Whatever the medium, the creative person&#39;s task is to interpret an essentially unchanging reality, a dog-eared reality pondered by Homer and Mel Brooks and everyone in between. The artist succeeds if he or she can present something familiar from an unfamiliar angle.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rheta Grimsley Johnson&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This quote comes from a book about Charles Schulz, the creator of Peanuts. &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinkleon.com/2007/10/29/the-twelve-devices-of-peanuts/&#34;&gt;In this post&lt;/a&gt;, Austin Kleon breaks down the 12 familiar devices that Schulz used over and over again to tell different stories in his comic strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reusing the devices, Schulz at once created context for the reader to return to and at the same time set us up to be surprised by new insights, twists, and revelations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s try to do the same thing in our qigong practice, instead of letting familiar sets become stale and dead.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/86kIjmFf9_U?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Insight in Old Exercises&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In planning this year&#39;s event, here are the themes I hope to explore and &#34;discover.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the Spine Stretch&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How the movements reveal physical layers -- from superficial fascia to the deep muscles surrounding the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legwork that enhances your connection to the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difference between sinking chi and dissolving and the way this contrast will help you get more rooted (sinking) and penetrate deeper into the spine (dissolving).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finishing the spine stretch with a more integrated connection between the arms, legs, and spine and a sense of internal stillness.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
See, many of these qualities can be found in a standing practice or a complex moving form of Tai Chi, but the interesting question is how we can draw them out of the procedure of the Spine Stretch. I know they&#39;re in there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the Swings&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we release the arms throughout the swings series in a way that enhances the overall feeling of release and relaxation in the body?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How, given the degree of movement in the swings, can we tune into steady and continuous head-to-toe sinking or dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we use the rotational motion and rhythm of the Swings to refine our feeling of the Central Channel as an axis of movement?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the end of the series, can will come to rest in a way that feels loose, alive, and settled simultaneously?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I love the challenge of extending internal awareness into an active practice like the Swings. Even as the arms are flying up above the head, you have to learn to stay grounded and connected. The rhythm and timing become an anchor for your mind in a way that&#39;s hard to get even in a slow-motion Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Immersion Week: April 22-25&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We&#39;ll spend 2.5 hours a day on each topic for four days, April 22-25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be doing Swings in the morning and Spine Stretch in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This format lets us approach all of the exercises from many different angles: direct feeling with the mind (standing qigong), partner exercises to sensitize different body parts/capacities (twisting, loosening, sinking), and mini-exercises that allow us to feel key principles/pieces of each larger exercise (arm drops and swing, kwa squats, folds, and hinges).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both events will be held at Brookline Tai Chi and there is limited space. If you plan to attend, I encourage you to sign up by April 1 to ensure a space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Here are the details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you&#39;re coming in from out of town, consider extending your stay to refine your &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/long-form-spring-series/&#34;&gt;Long Form with Craig Barnes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maintaining the Four Points in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2013 08:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; alt=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, the question of &#34;should I rotate my spine in Tai Chi&#34; has come up frequently and led to a lot of confusion with some of our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are told to maintain the &#34;Four Points&#34; - a sort of internal frame that runs between the shoulders and the hips, forming a box that keeps the spine from rotating or side bending while you practice Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people hear this rule and think, &#34;but the spine has joints that rotate and bend in more than one plane&#34; or &#34;show me any athletic movement that doesn&#39;t make use of the rotational movement of the spine to generate power.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you reconcile these common sense observations with a principle that seems to limit natural movement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s look at the developmental context in a few stages of learning Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Maintaining the Four Points for Beginners&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First of all, you need to appreciate the context for each question and observation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start learning Tai Chi, most people haven&#39;t spent a lot of time separating upper body and lower body movement or thinking about which one drives the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for beginners, &lt;strong&gt;holding the Four Points in place allows you to more easily steer the shoulders from the hips&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you practice at this level, without rotating the spine, you train out all the upper-body-led exaggeration in your movements. You begin to learn how to feel the &#34;power coming from the legs, being steered by the waist, and expressed in the hands,&#34; to paraphrase the Tai Chi Classics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t follow the rule of the Four Points at this level, you tend to retain upper body dominance, never finding proper folding in &lt;a title=&#34;Basic Training: Focus on Your Kwa Squat&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/&#34;&gt;the hip joints and kwa&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hitting Your Limits&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, at a certain point, holding the Four Points as an &lt;em&gt;external frame &lt;/em&gt;starts to limit your movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you watch this video on the components of Roll Back, or Lu, you will see, especially around 3:30, the way that twisting and rotation enhances the subtly, connection, and power of your movements.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/PL8TPEu3TWw?rel=0&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you progress to interactive practices, the additional rotational power you can generate from micro movements in the spine will improve the quality of your response to an incoming force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to only turning from the hips, having the capacity to create rotation in the spine is like typing with all 26 letters, not just 14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What the Rotators Miss&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, you can see this in the above video to a degree, but I want to also point out one of the less obvious benefits of maintaining what looks like a more rigid frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You have to take into account the difference between bone and soft tissue.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons we focus on maintaining bony alignments, beyond developing coordination and healthy movement patterns that don&#39;t wear on the joints, is finding separate movement in the fascia and muscles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you let the soft tissues turn around the bones, you begin to loosen them. If your bones and tissues are always turning together, you miss deeper internal loosening of these layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, a movement that looks very rigid and square may actually contain spirals throughout the soft tissues, but this is not obvious from the outside unless you&#39;ve been trained to look for subtle signs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you make a rule like &#34;never break the external frame of the Four Points,&#34; you don&#39;t account for someone&#39;s coordination, sensitivity, or body development. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several layers to the process of cultivating unified spiral-driven movement, but a simple rule like that doesn&#39;t account for very different needs at different stages of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, &#34;always twist the spine&#34; as a rule will keep you from developing certain sensitivity and connection and shouldn&#39;t be treated as an absolute outside of the right context either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? How do you make sense of these kinds of rules and principles in your own practice? Has your sense of their meaning changed over time?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I Learned from Robert Tangora about Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>/2012/03/14/what-i-learned-from-robert-tangora-about-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/14/what-i-learned-from-robert-tangora-about-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, we hosted &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt; at Brookline Tai Chi for an introduction to Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong. Prior to the workshop, I had put together a few thoughts on what it feels like to work with the spine in Tai Chi and qigong. This weekend definitely helped me refine my sense for what Spinal Qigong can do, so I wanted to share some of those lessons with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3578&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/_1hMPWIbTiY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/_1hMPWIbTiY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundational practices I describe in the video prepare you to work with the more sophisticated connections you access in Bend the Bow. &lt;strong&gt;One of the main goals of spinal qigong is to link the arms and legs by connecting them to the spine.&lt;/strong&gt; By learning to use the spine as a bow that can store and release energy, you learn to move the arms and legs &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the spine, not just &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the spine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Targeting the Spine in Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We used an exercise very similar to the one Robert demonstrates at 4:00 in this video to begin to feel the way that the arms and legs connect to the spine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;410&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;410&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of qigong principles that apply to working with the spine, Robert made it very clear that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first level of any qigong practice is all about coordinating moving parts. You need to practice slowly and careful, with the goal of synchronizing the timing of the movements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once timing is there, you being to build internal connections, i.e. it becomes possible to have the sense of one part leading another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to develop a clear sense of how the big muscles of the back connect to the arms and legs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Through partner feedback, you can start to discern how the arms and legs &#34;pull&#34; on the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You refine how the limbs pull on the spine in order to balance the left and right side of the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your body is open enough, spinal qigong can give an incredibly balanced, whole-body feel to all your movement.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Since the workshop, I&#39;ve used this exercise as a daily warm-up and it has been spilling over into my Tai Chi practice nicely. Everything feels more linked together. I&#39;m working on a post right now about breathing and some of the conclusions are the same: once deep internal connections are in place, the circular nature of these movements opens you up continuously as you practice. That is a huge contrast from linear stretching, which feel like you&#39;re flicking a switch on and off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my biggest takeaway about Spinal Qigong (at the moment, of course!) is that you need to approach it like every other qigong exercise that is designed to open up your body, but there definitely are some unique experiences that come up working with the spine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>