<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>spine on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/spine/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in spine on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/spine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 Update</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 09:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s a quick update on what we&#39;ve been working on during Immersion Week 2014.

I&#39;m very impressed (and I say so in the video about 15 times!) with the way this group has patiently explored many different facets of the Swings and Spine Stretch without rushing ahead to try to fit seemingly contradictory pieces together conceptually.
Instead, they&#39;re doing a great job experiencing/exploring each different component on its own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Moving Exercises: Immersion Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 10:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m getting excited about Immersion Week at BTC next month, where we&#39;ll take another look at the Spine Stretch and the Three Swings. Another look? Like we&#39;ve done it before? Yes!
Why is it exciting to go back to the same qigong sets over and over again?
So-called creative people understand better than most that there is nothing new under the sun. Working with boulders of granite, with empty stages, with blank paper, they are credited with making something out of nothing, but that isn&#39;t exactly what they do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maintaining the Four Points in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2013 08:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/29/maintaining-the-four-points-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>Recently, the question of &#34;should I rotate my spine in Tai Chi&#34; has come up frequently and led to a lot of confusion with some of our students.
We are told to maintain the &#34;Four Points&#34; - a sort of internal frame that runs between the shoulders and the hips, forming a box that keeps the spine from rotating or side bending while you practice Tai Chi.
Some people hear this rule and think, &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I Learned from Robert Tangora about Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/14/what-i-learned-from-robert-tangora-about-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/14/what-i-learned-from-robert-tangora-about-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>Recently, we hosted Robert Tangora at Brookline Tai Chi for an introduction to Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong. Prior to the workshop, I had put together a few thoughts on what it feels like to work with the spine in Tai Chi and qigong. This weekend definitely helped me refine my sense for what Spinal Qigong can do, so I wanted to share some of those lessons with you.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>