<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>intrinsic-motivation on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/intrinsic-motivation/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in intrinsic-motivation on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/intrinsic-motivation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Intrinsic Practice Motivation</title>
      <link>/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 09:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Marden Hill Road Sunset II; Palermo, Maine by Jody Roberts, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/jroberts72/6003983172/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Marden Hill Road Sunset II; Palermo, Maine&#34; src=&#34;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6010/6003983172_fc0cfb3308_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For the last couple of years, I&#39;ve been teaching regular workshops in Farmington, Maine. When I went up again last week, I had a fascinating conversation with one of the students. She was telling me how the core group had been coming along and that other people have come in and out of practicing with them. She said, &#34;you know, it&#39;s not really for everyone.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don&#39;t know if that jumps out at you as a significant statement, but as a Tai Chi teacher, it&#39;s &lt;a title=&#34;Brookline Tai Chi has no &#34;Former Students&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34;&gt;something I&#39;ve been thinking about for years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this one casual statement, she was really saying that her motivation to practice now comes from inside of herself. Along with a small group of dedicated classmates, she gets everything she needs from the practice itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a remarkable attitude. Every day, we get bombarded by messages that tell us to buy something to become something or fit in with other people. To be able to have a practice that lives inside of you, that&#39;s validated by performing it for yourself, and grows because you feed it with energy and time, is really incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, we&#39;re going to talk about how you discover your intrinsic motivation to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>