<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-gates on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/energy-gates/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy-gates on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/energy-gates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 Update</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 09:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a quick update on what we&#39;ve been working on during Immersion Week 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/-KpibI0ZE9s?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m very impressed (and I say so in the video about 15 times!) with the way this group has patiently explored many different facets of the Swings and Spine Stretch without rushing ahead to try to fit seemingly contradictory pieces together conceptually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, they&#39;re doing a great job experiencing/exploring each different component on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice this way, you naturally come to integration points where the components gel in a way you couldn&#39;t have predicted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Moving Exercises: Immersion Week 2014</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 10:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m getting excited about &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Immersion Week at BTC next month&lt;/a&gt;, where we&#39;ll take another look at the Spine Stretch and the Three Swings. Another look? Like we&#39;ve done it before? Yes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it exciting to go back to the same qigong sets over and over again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So-called creative people understand better than most that there is nothing new under the sun. Working with boulders of granite, with empty stages, with blank paper, they are credited with making something out of nothing, but that isn&#39;t exactly what they do. All art is derived from what is in actuality a remarkably finite human experience. Whatever the medium, the creative person&#39;s task is to interpret an essentially unchanging reality, a dog-eared reality pondered by Homer and Mel Brooks and everyone in between. The artist succeeds if he or she can present something familiar from an unfamiliar angle.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rheta Grimsley Johnson&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This quote comes from a book about Charles Schulz, the creator of Peanuts. &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinkleon.com/2007/10/29/the-twelve-devices-of-peanuts/&#34;&gt;In this post&lt;/a&gt;, Austin Kleon breaks down the 12 familiar devices that Schulz used over and over again to tell different stories in his comic strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reusing the devices, Schulz at once created context for the reader to return to and at the same time set us up to be surprised by new insights, twists, and revelations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s try to do the same thing in our qigong practice, instead of letting familiar sets become stale and dead.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/86kIjmFf9_U?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Insight in Old Exercises&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In planning this year&#39;s event, here are the themes I hope to explore and &#34;discover.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the Spine Stretch&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How the movements reveal physical layers -- from superficial fascia to the deep muscles surrounding the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legwork that enhances your connection to the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difference between sinking chi and dissolving and the way this contrast will help you get more rooted (sinking) and penetrate deeper into the spine (dissolving).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finishing the spine stretch with a more integrated connection between the arms, legs, and spine and a sense of internal stillness.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
See, many of these qualities can be found in a standing practice or a complex moving form of Tai Chi, but the interesting question is how we can draw them out of the procedure of the Spine Stretch. I know they&#39;re in there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the Swings&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we release the arms throughout the swings series in a way that enhances the overall feeling of release and relaxation in the body?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How, given the degree of movement in the swings, can we tune into steady and continuous head-to-toe sinking or dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we use the rotational motion and rhythm of the Swings to refine our feeling of the Central Channel as an axis of movement?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the end of the series, can will come to rest in a way that feels loose, alive, and settled simultaneously?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I love the challenge of extending internal awareness into an active practice like the Swings. Even as the arms are flying up above the head, you have to learn to stay grounded and connected. The rhythm and timing become an anchor for your mind in a way that&#39;s hard to get even in a slow-motion Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Immersion Week: April 22-25&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We&#39;ll spend 2.5 hours a day on each topic for four days, April 22-25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be doing Swings in the morning and Spine Stretch in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This format lets us approach all of the exercises from many different angles: direct feeling with the mind (standing qigong), partner exercises to sensitize different body parts/capacities (twisting, loosening, sinking), and mini-exercises that allow us to feel key principles/pieces of each larger exercise (arm drops and swing, kwa squats, folds, and hinges).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both events will be held at Brookline Tai Chi and there is limited space. If you plan to attend, I encourage you to sign up by April 1 to ensure a space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Here are the details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you&#39;re coming in from out of town, consider extending your stay to refine your &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/long-form-spring-series/&#34;&gt;Long Form with Craig Barnes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 and the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Book</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 16:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m very excited to share some news about two big projects with you today: Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s annual Immersion Week and the publication of the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance as a physical book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/bATZ5_2SMno?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join me from Tuesday, April 22 - Friday, April 25 at Brookline Tai Chi in Boston for &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Energy Gates Moving Qigong Exercises&lt;/a&gt;. Times, cost, and registration details in the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance is now available for purchase on Amazon, but you can also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.createspace.com/4498724&#34;&gt;get your copy of the physical book directly from the publisher&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When to Follow a Practice Recipe and When to Reflect on Your Practice</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 09:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this video, we&#39;re talking about building up the skill of Outer Dissolving in your standing qigong practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start out, it pays to follow a recipe - a set of instructions that lead through a certain procedure physically, energetically, and with your mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are times you want to break away from the recipe and times you&#39;ll want to reflect on your experience verbally -- but there are good and bad ways to do both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/wv2eex86CCE?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting at the Crown of the Head</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/16/starting-at-the-crown-of-the-head/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 14:13:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/16/starting-at-the-crown-of-the-head/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4985&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong Workouts&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2014/01/StandingNoName-01-300x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you read &lt;a title=&#34;Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;last week&#39;s post on standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;the Energy Gates book&lt;/a&gt;, or better yet, you can stand comfortably &#34;just feeling&#34; for 15-20 minutes, you&#39;re probably ready to embark on the downward dissolving process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I want to help you get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recorded a guided practice mp3 to get you through the first workout in the Energy Gates series: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/AEcQ&#34;&gt;Feeling the Gate at the Crown of the Head&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, in this phase, you want each practice session to have a clear structure, so that you release stuck energy in a systematic way. Here is my advice from the last post on &#34;the form&#34; of an Energy Gates standing session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in week 1, it could look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Crown of the Head - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Body - 3 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But week 11 would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel from the Crown of the Head down to the Solar Plexus - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Solar Plexus - 8 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Rest of the Body - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In other words, you should spend a substantial amount of time on whatever gate is the &#34;gate of the week.&#34; However, your practice session should always start with settling, finish with gathering, and have an easy flow down to the &#34;gate of the week&#34; and then from the &#34;gate of the week&#34; down into the ground after the main focus time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll notice that as you go through the process of the gates, your standing time can go from 15-20 minutes during the first few weeks up to 45-60 minutes towards the end of the process. If you can only manage 15-20 minutes and slowly adding more feels like too much of a strain, I recommend that you stick with the feeling method and not worry about the gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you&#39;re just setting out on this process, you&#39;re probably thinking, &lt;strong&gt;&#34;how am I supposed to be relaxed, feel into my body, and become more sensitive to my chi if I have to remember all these details??&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is exactly why I created &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/AEcQ&#34;&gt;this follow-along audio practice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out and let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 09:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-2355 alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture.jpg&#34; width=&#34;159&#34; height=&#34;337&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you set out to develop your internal energy using standing postures, there are two main ways you can go about it: &lt;strong&gt;by feel or by form&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there will be a lot of overlap in these two broad approaches, like aligning your body with gravity without collapsing internally and progressively releasing and relaxing as you stand, but when it comes to the role of the mind, form and feel can be very different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Feeling Approach&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You stand &#34;by feel&#34; for a few different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a good period of feeling, taking stock, and getting comfortable is useful almost any time you do your standing practice. Because our initial orientation in standing is inward, and we&#39;re likely coming to it from a lot of outward-facing activity, taking 3, 5, or even 10 minutes to just stand and feel creates a nice buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve settled in to your practice, then any &#34;form&#34; work you do for the remainder of the standing session will be much more productive: you&#39;ll be quieter, more relaxed, and more tuned-in to your internal environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In fact, I recommend that you get to a comfortable baseline of just being able to settle, relax, and feel your body in a standing posture for 20 minutes before you move on to the form phase.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason to take the feeling approach is to fully appreciate the effects of your posture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;The posture pictured above is a neutral posture, also referred to as Wu Chi. As soon as you raise the arms or change the stance, the effect of the body position will begin to shape what you feel, physically and energetically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you pick a different posture, you automatically start doing a different form. You don&#39;t need to do anything special with the mind. Just feeling the new effects of a specific posture, compared to your Wu Chi baseline, can be enough to keep you occupied through much longer (2-hour!) standing sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, by taking the feeling approach, you can build your connection to the ground. As you stand, &lt;a title=&#34;3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;ask yourself these 3 questions&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Over time, you will become more rooted, relaxed, and connected&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moving into Standing Forms&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Once you have a solid baseline of feeling the body, you can begin to work on the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, most people are familiar with Tai Chi Forms or choreographed sequences in other martial arts, but what do we mean when we use the word &#34;form&#34; in this context?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t think of &#34;form&#34; as movements, but instead think of it as a procedure, then it starts to make more sense. And the value of having a procedure, or a repeatable process, is that you can begin to see how you&#39;re changing over time by performing it, both because you can use it as reference point and because doing it actually changes you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In standing, the form is going to be what you do with your awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here I want to warn you:&lt;/strong&gt; just like someone who follows the rote choreography of the Tai Chi form with no regard for softness, relaxation, and connection will be really stiff and awkward, if you follow the mind-forms without regard for the qualities you develop in the feeling approach, you will be stiff and awkward in your standing. You will just be going through a rigid mental checklist and the impact you will have on your energy and physical body will be limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you can introduce a pattern of progressively sinking the mind through the body, while you maintain relaxation, connection, and root, all of the qualities you began to develop in the feeling approach will be amplified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Your First Form: Downward Flow&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body, Bruce Frantzis teaches a standing qigong sequence that is designed to clear stagnant chi out of your energetic system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic process is a standing &#34;form&#34; where you begin at the crown of the head and move your mind downward through the body each time you practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the first level, an Energy Gates practice session is structured like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In (using the feeling method described above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downward Scan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stillness, Settling Again, or Storing Chi&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The more you practice Energy Gates, the more you will refine the Downward Scan piece. &lt;strong&gt;Specifically, you will go through stages of feeling your body to feeling your energy to sinking your energy and finally to dissolving your energy. &lt;/strong&gt;Bruce discusses each of these stages in depth &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;in the Energy Gates book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At each stage of this process, though, the form is the same. You start at the top and work your way down. Every time you go through the body this way, no matter at what layer, you are strengthening the downward current of energy, which has a powerful restorative effect over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often joke that the downward flow of chi in your body plays the same role as the downward flow of water in the plumbing system of your house. Not enough downward flow is a problem there, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Energy Gates Over Six Months&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you read the book or hear someone explain the Energy Gates process, it&#39;s easy to picture a whole bunch of dots all over the body that light up as you do your scan. In fact, learning to feel the gates themselves is a natural extension of just being able to feel the denser tissues of the body directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to tune the mind to a slightly different frequency, but all the time spent standing and feeling pays off here: you&#39;ve trained your mind to stay in one spot for extended periods without jumping around and without tensing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you set out to do a complete pass through all the gates, it roughly breaks down into a six-month project. There are 23 main places you&#39;ll want to work with and you could work with one per week (you can definitely spend longer on each gate, but this is just the basic formula). Here is the list from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/energy-gates-qigong&#34;&gt;the Energy Arts resource page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bai hui, or the crown of the head.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third eye, the eyes, the center of the ears and the temple. Also the four jaw points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where the tongue touches the roof of the mouth and the throat notch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The base of the skull and in between each of the cervical (neck) vertebrae down to the seventh cervical vertebra at the base of the neck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From where the tongue touches the roof of your mouth to the end of the breastbone, on a line about the width of your mouth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The four points of the shoulder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The elbows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The wrists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hands (all the points).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The joints where the ribs connect to the sternum, the spaces between the ribs, the joints where the ribs connect to the spine, the area between the shoulder blades and the spine. For women only: the gates of the breasts (directly behind the nipples).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The solar plexus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The whole of the belly, starting from the front and dissolving through the internal organs back to the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tantien and the mingmen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the points along the spine, from the occiput to the tailbone, paying special attention to the occiput, the seventh cervical vertebra, the vertebra in the center of the shoulder blades, the one at the base of the shoulder blades, mingmen and the tailbone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hip sockets, the pelvic bones, and the kwa (that is, the area inside the front crest of the hip bones).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The anus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The genitals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The perineum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The knees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ankles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The feet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Below the floor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Above the head.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, when you start working through the gates, the structure of your practice session will change from what we laid out earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in week 1, it could look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Crown of the Head - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Body - 3 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But week 11 would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel from the Crown of the Head down to the Solar Plexus - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Solar Plexus - 8 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Rest of the Body - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In other words, you should spend a substantial amount of time on whatever gate is the &#34;gate of the week.&#34; However, your practice session should always start with settling, finish with gathering, and have an easy flow down to the &#34;gate of the week&#34; and then from the &#34;gate of the week&#34; down into the ground after the main focus time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll notice that as you go through the process of the gates, your standing time can go from 15-20 minutes during the first few weeks up to 45-60 minutes towards the end of the process. If you can only manage 15-20 minutes and slowly adding more feels like too much of a strain, I recommend that you stick with the feeling method and not worry about the gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Is it Very Taoist?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here you might start to wonder about whether some of these guidelines for the form seem too rigid. How do you reconcile these recommendations with what you feel when you stand free-form?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And by the way, I&#39;m not saying that &#34;feeling&#34; is kindergarten and &#34;form&#34; is more advanced. In fact, you should cycle between periods of each as you practice over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guidelines and form serve a purpose. You need to work through the structure to develop certain things. Eventually, will you have a more intuitive feel for what you need and how much? Of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, though, Flannery O&#39;Connor captured the issue well, when she argued for a classical education: &#34;And if the student finds that this is not to his taste? Well, that is regrettable. Most regrettable. His taste should not be consulted; it is being formed.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However counter-intuitive it seems at first, the best feeling, the most relaxation, and the greatest internal stillness that I&#39;ve ever uncovered has come from the practice periods when I&#39;ve given over to a form to follow. Later on, I can bask in that energy and &#34;just feel&#34; and enjoy it, but to get there, it was a lot of little small, formal steps along the practice road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wherever you find yourself on the standing path now, I hope this helps orient you a little more. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates in Vancouver, BC, Spring 2014</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 17:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-4518 &#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong &#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/03/20130326-094857.jpg&#34; width=&#34;360&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Dan standing in New Mexico, not Vancouver (yet!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you live in or near Vancouver?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you willing to travel to refine your Energy Gates practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the behest of a few eager Vancouver locals, I wanted to reach out and see if any of our Northwest-oriented readers would be interested in a spring 2014 Energy Gates seminar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Date and exact location haven&#39;t been nailed down yet, but if there&#39;s enough demand, I would love to come out and do some Energy Gates with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/rz6mzho0i8y4y5/&#34;&gt;Already excited? Sign up here so we can explore it more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Energy Gates Seminar Topics&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are so many great Energy Gates subjects related to &lt;a title=&#34;3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;Case Study: Energy Gates Tune-Up&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/21/case-study-energy-gates-tune-up/&#34;&gt;Cloud Hands&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;The Challenge of the Three Swings&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/&#34;&gt;The Swings&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a title=&#34;Spinal Qigong Exercises&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/spinal-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;The Spine Stretch&lt;/a&gt;, but I&#39;d like to take the approach of &lt;strong&gt;answering the burning questions that always come up when you start working on Standing, Sinking and Dissolving,&lt;/strong&gt; like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a lot of tension around my low back (or knees), how do I adapt the posture so it&#39;s not painful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should I use the actual gates in my practice or focus on general sinking and dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is quite a struggle to constantly remind myself to slow down. How do I slow my mind down without causing mental tension?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#39;m starting to feel chi when I stand. What do I do with it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can&#39;t feel chi when I stand. What do I do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I integrate standing, breathing, sinking, and dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I sink the chi of one part of my body, does it go all the way down to the ground?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get too tense when I try to maintain my alignments as I stand. What should I do&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#39;m experiencing shaking, sweating, heat or other weird bodily sensations. Is that normal?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to get live, personal feedback and soak up all the good chi of intensive group practice, then come stand with us in Vancouver next year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill out the form below and I will in touch directly with you about the details. If we can get a big enough group together, we&#39;ll make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again to the folks who initiated this conversation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var rz6mzho0i8y4y5;(function(d, t) { var s = d.createElement(t), options = { &#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,  &#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#39;,  &#39;autoResize&#39;:true, &#39;height&#39;:&#39;403&#39;, &#39;async&#39;:true, &#39;host&#39;:&#39;wufoo.com&#39;, &#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,  &#39;ssl&#39;:true}; s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;; s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() { var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return; try { rz6mzho0i8y4y5 = new WufooForm();rz6mzho0i8y4y5.initialize(options);rz6mzho0i8y4y5.display(); } catch (e) {}}; var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr); })(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dragon and Tiger Exercises for Activating the Lower Tantien</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 07:32:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re borrowing a technique from Dragon and Tiger qigong to try and get a better sense of the lower tantien. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lower tantien (&#34;dan-tee-en&#34;) is the energetic center of your physical body, located just below your navel, on the central axis of the body. If you dropped a line down from the crown of the head, through the body, and out the bottom of the pelvis, it would pass through the lower tantien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because this center is so deep inside the body, it is hard to feel. When you do find the energetic center of your body, though, you learn to realign your posture around it, feeling full and supported in a completely different way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/-613On-w15U?list=UU4DJ7xUL-TWEBOgDp_ekI5Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this exercise, you want to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the palms, looking for the energetic sensation, as if you were pressing magnets together or pulling taffy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the energy get quiet once you stabilize the connection. Release, dissolve, and let go, without disconnecting the palms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat the first two steps, but with the palms facing the lower tantien.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, try to connect to this same internal alignment with the arms resting by your sides&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you find it, just hang out with the connection and don&#39;t try to do anything else!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 08:23:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3864&#34; title=&#34;Stake Standing&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/05/Stake-Standing-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong as Prep for Meditation&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the outside, standing qigong can look calm, peaceful and meditative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the inside, if you don&#39;t ask yourself these 3 essential questions, standing can be grueling. Your muscles ache, you tremble and sweat, and in burning discomfort you strain to see how much longer you must endure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&#39;t have to be torture, though, if you adopt the right mindset as you practice.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4015&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have learned many different standing qigong &lt;em&gt;techniques&lt;/em&gt; from my teacher &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, but when I practice what he&#39;s taught about &lt;em&gt;mindset&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; in standing qigong, I&#39;ve had some of my biggest breakthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summer 2011, at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011/&#34;&gt;Wu Style Short Form Instructor training&lt;/a&gt;, he emphasized the role of standing qigong in developing internal connections in Tai Chi practice. We did work on the particular energetic techniques of different Tai Chi postures, but the bigger lessons of &#34;what to watch for&#34; and &#34;what you want to experience&#34; have been even more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote about the challenges and payoffs of an intensive environment like this for &lt;a href=&#34;http://imos-journal.net/?p=3486&#34;&gt;Into Mountains, Over Streams&lt;/a&gt; when I returned. Specifically, I described the way standing helps you find internal stability in your form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p id=&#34;internal-source-marker_0.8767203545320106&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Tai Chi has many methods for tuning you in to the inner form. My personal favorite was holding standing postures. It can be grueling work on a physical level. Even when you adjust to the physical discomfort, standing still for extended periods of time forces you to confront your own internal environment. Nothing is moving on the outside, so your attention focuses on the inside.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Holding postures to open specific energy lines in the body is very much a science. We began that study by exploring nine of the postures from the short form, holding each one for twenty to thirty minutes. Throughout this process, I could feel everything from the surfaces of my body, down through the layers of twisted tissue. I became acutely aware of how my bones and joints were aligned. Eventually I got access to the specific flow pattern each posture is designed to highlight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I often describe the sensation of &#34;getting&#34; a posture as feeling your internal gears clicking. The posture gels in a way that you would never experience if you always just go through the form. Until you spend time in each posture, you miss a whole hidden side of internal connectedness. When we asked Master Frantzis how to systematically train these postures after the training was over, he recommended working on each posture for 2 months and then changing to the next one in the series. It&#39;s amazing to feel your insides shift and change over one twenty minute standing session, but coming back to a posture each day for two months gives you a completely different level of insight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Before the training, I had always thought about posture holding as a timed goal, like, &#34;Okay, I&#39;m going to hold this one for twenty, this one for thirty, this one longer, longer.&#34; One of the key points that Master Frantzis  made was that you should focus on the feeling of stability in each posture, not on the clock. Once you hit it for that place in the posture, everything opens up and becomes connected in a way that gives the posture a unique flavor. That&#39;s the key moment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Once everything clicks, a practitioner wants to maintain the moment for as long as they can. When you lose it; you shrink out of it; you start to collapse a little bit; something gets off.  This is game we play with each posture. How do you connect to it and reliably re-create that feeling again and again? That&#39;s the goal of the first stage of posture holding. After you reach this stage, you start to work of experiencing the same connections as you move into and out of this posture in your form. Eventually you can string the whole form together this way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Other people joke that the fastest way clear a room full of people who want to learn Tai Chi is to just make them close their eyes and hold a posture. It&#39;s definitely a matter of personal preference! To me, posture holding is a way to feel more connected and more integrated and really develop a feel for letting things come together without forcing them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Adopting the Right Mindset for Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;At first, searching for internal stability this way can be frustrating. Even once you&#39;ve gotten a sense for it, you can&#39;t always reproduce it reliably. However, if you ask yourself these three questions as you practice, you odds of getting there again and again will get much better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;As you stand, ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is gravity going through me? (Not getting stuck somewhere)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are my nerves relaxing and releasing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there warmth?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can ask yourself this question about any part of your body or everywhere at once. If you wash over yourself with this questions again and again as you stand, you will adopt the right alignment of your body, mind, and energy and increase your chances of finding internal stability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Do I Keep My Awareness for Jumping Around?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/09/how-do-i-keep-my-awareness-for-jumping-around/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 11:57:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/09/how-do-i-keep-my-awareness-for-jumping-around/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the major goals of standing qigong is to develop a strong downward flow that clears stagnant energy out of your system and strengthens your natural restorative abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you begin to work on this process, though,&amp;Acirc;  it&#39;s natural to wonder how strict you need to be able sticking with the downward flow and what to do if you start to notice other things happening in the body. Recently, I got this question via email that nails the exact issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I get distracted for a second or my attention bounces unconsciously to another part of the body, or I notice that my alignments begin to collapse -- basically when I lose the continuity of the scan -- should I start over from the top of the head or continue from where I left off?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3259&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my advice and a little more about how to think about the problem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/wLWZghoDbs8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/wLWZghoDbs8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Download a Guided Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can download a 20-minute guided practice session that leads you through stabilizing this flow, first in the arms, then in the body &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/01/Sinking-without-Jumping.m4a&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guided Practice Aides</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/04/guided-practice-aides/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 15:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/04/guided-practice-aides/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a round-up of guided practice aides I&#39;ve put together in various sections of the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else would help you with your current practice? Let me know &lt;a title=&#34;Submit a Practice Question&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/submit-a-practice-question/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3207&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To download the audio files below, right click and &#34;save as&#34;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Breathing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Use these basic principles as a guide for your breathing and standing practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_153&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=47617447&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/9d18c9bd/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=47617447&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_153&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/9d18c9bd/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=47617447&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=47617447&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Downloads:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Breathing_Practice_1.mp3&#34;&gt;20-Minute Guided Practice #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Expanded_Breathing_Practice.mp3&#34;&gt;20-Minute Guided Practice #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can progress through longer standing sessions with these guided practice mp3s or pick one on any given day that matches your practice goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Settling_In.mp3&#34;&gt;5-Minute Scan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Waking_Up_Feeling_Awareness.mp3&#34;&gt;10-Minute Softening Practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Sinking_Chi.mp3&#34;&gt;20-Minute Downward Flow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wu Tai Chi Short Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Let me help you pace yourself through 3 rounds of the short form with this video or the audio download below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_292&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=39309639&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/5cd5a24b/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=39309639&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_292&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/5cd5a24b/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=39309639&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=39309639&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/downloads/Short_Form_Three_Times.m4a&#34;&gt;Short Form 3x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Case Study: Energy Gates Tune-Up</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/21/case-study-energy-gates-tune-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 06:51:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/21/case-study-energy-gates-tune-up/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this case study, you&#39;ll see how Kevin improved his Cloud Hands and Swings through video feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you can &lt;a title=&#34;Guide to Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;follow a guided practice for the standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; portion of Energy Gates, doing a follow-along for the moving exercises doesn&#39;t really help you improve your practice, so feedback is key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going through the process of not only getting a correction, but watching yourself before and after, helps you internalize the new movement pattern. If you are just told to change the way you are moving, sometimes the new pattern is so different from what you are used to that you can&#39;t feel the difference, and the correction doesn&#39;t stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this series, I think you&#39;ll see how Kevin was able to integrate the feedback and improve his set a little bit with each video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nice work, Kevin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2968&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Setting a Baseline&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is the clip Kevin initially submitted, of standing, Cloud Hands, Swings, and Spine Stretch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/xzf3p4w8WBc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/xzf3p4w8WBc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my first round of feedback:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the head roll forward a little more, lengthening up the back of the neck to open the occiput and lengthen the entire spine -- i.e. drop the chin slightly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try a smaller stance so that you can focus on aligning the centers of each leg joint on top of each other (as opposed to a wider stance where you will feel the leg muscles activate on the outside after a longer standing session).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cloud Hands&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have a very clear line on the ascending side, from the pushing leg up through the arms -- this is good, but you might also want to develop the sinking side too -- the side you&#39;re shifting on to, by tracking the downward hand and feeling that as that hand goes down to the hip, you are simultaneously feeling down the weighted leg. When the hand finishes, you will have arrived in the foot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long term, there is a difference between rotating around the side channels, which you are doing well here, and rotating around the central axis. This is another place where, if you take a slightly smaller stance, you will be able to track the line from the crown of the head, down through the roof of the mouth and all the way down to the perineum as your turning axis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The kwa folding and leg alignments are great.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;First Swing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Same basic comment as Cloud Hands: great leg alignments, but the wider stance is going to keep you rotating around the side channels more than the center -- for a while you might want to try doing a first swing with no weight shift, with the feet much closer together, so that you can feel rotation around the center in a clearer way -- again, this is more of a variation that highlights a different element, rather than an absolute.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Second Swing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is tied to the size of the stance a little, I think, but you&#39;ve got some &#34;leg reach&#34; going on with the unweighted leg in the side position. If you pause the video in one of the side positions, you see the foot pretty far ahead of the shoulder -- ideally, you want to pull the leg back with the hip and shoulder, so they stay in vertical alignment. The big idea here is that the movement can create a twist through your entire skeletal structure and you move in and out of the side positions, which is what is happening now -- that activates a lot of soft tissue turning. The caveat is that it can also tax the leg joints. More than a caution, though, if you make the structural movement more compact, it directs the force vectors inward, to the internal organs, and so you start to activate different benefits internally. So try a smaller step.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Third Swing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third swing is hard!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice how your arms go all the way back into the shoulder joint at the top and kind of rest there for a beat? That also tends to extend the spine and creates a brief pause at the top. You want to stay just shy of that position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The other way to look at it is through the kwa pump. You need to let the closing of the kwa pull all the way down through your feet each time you transition from one &#34;up&#34; position to another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You&#39;ve got the basic shape, I just want to re-orient you to the internal pulls and flows a little bit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the very end, when the body stops, the arms should just fall.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Spine Stretch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Looking good on the way up. On the way down, I would encourage you to move less from the lower back. Basically, once you move above the height of the diaphragm or lowest ribs, there isn&#39;t really any lumbar movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another thing that will help is more of a kwa squat as you go, as opposed to folding at the kwa. This will put you in the legs more.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overall, great stuff. I&#39;m really impressed with how you&#39;ve worked on this material on your own!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First Refinements&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A week later, Kevin sent me a second video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/WPvN6ZmKC78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/WPvN6ZmKC78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see, based on the feedback, that we&#39;re still working on some common themes. He&#39;s made some little tweaks, but because of where he is in the learning progression, the stuff he will focus on now will take some time to get into the body and change with regular practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud Hands&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;Acirc; Try to &#34;sit&#34; into weighted leg more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emphasize the down more than the up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You&#39;re doing good, smooth turning.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;First Swing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solid&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Second Swing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch how foot creeps out as you go through your reps, you can see it sneak out a little at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to do more of a pulling back feeling for unweighted side so the foot stays under the hip more.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Third swing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the transition, drop into the squat to get under you arms instead of lifting -- this is the same timing issue we discussed in &lt;a title=&#34;Three Swings from Opening the Energy Gates Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/exercises/three-swings-from-opening-the-energy-gates-qigong/&#34;&gt;the webinar&lt;/a&gt;, where you have to drop the body before the arms fall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch how everything opens out from the kwa at the sides -- ideally, if there is a strong up and down, you won&#39;t see this, instead the legs will open and the arms will swing up in the same line.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nailing the Third Swing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fl0aVXmy0jk?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fl0aVXmy0jk?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, when Kevin sent me a new video, he had completely re-engineered his Third Swing. Now, he was clearly closing his body before the arms were dropping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve seen people struggle with this change for a long time and never quite find the right feel for the timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you if you can pick up from the video a few of the other changes Kevin was able to integrate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud Hands&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The upward arm is much softer -- to the point of making a small circle at the top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a much better connection to the downward hand and you can see the connection all the way down through the weighted leg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the future: start twisting into unweighted leg sooner to start downward pull -- think about the kwa on the unweighted leg, right at the moment you begin to reverse direction, you want to see if&amp;Acirc;  you can feel a winding into that leg&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;First Swing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the future: the shoulder&#39;s nests and chest need to hollow more -- this isn&#39;t necessarily related to the first swing, but it&#39;s apparent here. The goal is to feel the chest sliding down as the spine rises up.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Second Swing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&#39;s better pull back on leg, but it still creeps out to sides. The fix is in making a more distinct weight shift from one leg to the other in the middle position (when you work on this, you give up flow). As you shift into one leg, the other feels like it gets scooped up from the hip joint and you want to have it completely off the ground before you turn to the side.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Since Kevin sent me this last video, we&#39;ve had follow-up conversations about certain principles that he&#39;s ready to integrate into his practice, some of which isn&#39;t as easily teachable through video feedback. So, there certainly is a limit to what can be communicated this way. What I hope you will see, though, is just how much you can shape your practice with this kind of feedback and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swings Webinar Replay</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/12/swings-webinar-replay/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 08:15:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/12/swings-webinar-replay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a quick note to let you know that if you missed Sunday&#39;s webinar on the Three Swings from Opening the Energy Gates, you can check out a replay &lt;a title=&#34;Three Swings from Opening the Energy Gates Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/three-swings-from-opening-the-energy-gates-qigong/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Active Should I Be When Standing?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/08/how-active-should-i-be-when-standing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2011 15:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/08/how-active-should-i-be-when-standing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lately, I&#39;ve been trying to do some &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;sinking&lt;/a&gt; during standing qigong,&amp;Acirc;  in addition to other practices, like opening and closing, but I don&#39;t get the full calming effect of the sinking.&amp;Acirc;  This is a problem, because it gets a lot of energy moving and something this manifests as more anger than I would like. What should I do?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2832&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_291&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=97397467&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/16658fb/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=97397467&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_291&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/16658fb/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=97397467&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=97397467&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s The Best Way to Practice &#34;Sinking the Chest?&#34;</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/06/whats-the-best-way-to-practice-sinking-the-chest-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2011 16:01:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/06/whats-the-best-way-to-practice-sinking-the-chest-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sinking the chest while raising the spine is a key energetic alignment practiced in Tai Chi to facilitate a grounding, downward flow of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martial artists use it to develop their root and anyone who &#34;gets stuck in their head&#34; will find some relief employing this principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you have a good standing position to practice sinking the chest?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2967&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_290&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=75228179&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/4f03b919/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=75228179&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_290&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;288&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/4f03b919/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=75228179&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=75228179&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>