<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>brookline-tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/brookline-tai-chi/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in brookline-tai-chi on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/brookline-tai-chi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Gratitude for Immersive Learning</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 09:33:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/04/18/gratitude-for-immersive-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-5033&#34; alt=&#34;Thank_You&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2014/04/Thank_You-e1397827802683-242x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;242&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night I taught my last two weekly classes at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next month, I&#39;ll be diving into &lt;a href=&#34;http://launchacademy.com/&#34;&gt;a new intensive learning experience&lt;/a&gt;, building software applications and learning about the web from a depth I&#39;ve only poked at up until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I have some really cool stuff planned for Immersion Week too, so I&#39;m not quite done yet!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s going to be a big change for me.  I don&#39;t quite know what to make of shedding a professional identity that I&#39;ve held for almost 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I don&#39;t quite know what to say to the students I&#39;ve worked so closely with over all this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I think about what&#39;s coming, I recognize a pattern that I&#39;ve repeated many times in my life. On many occasions now, I&#39;ve been able to dive into a pool that I couldn&#39;t swim in at first, and then somehow, float.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 10 years teaching weekly classes at Brookline Tai Chi, I feel ready to swim in a new pool and in a strange way, I&#39;m excited to be really out of my element, because I know that with the right structure, in the right environment, I will float back up to the surface buoyed by new skills and new perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ten Years Ago at Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I still remember walking across the room, not making eye contract with anyone, just shuffling out into the lobby to wait for students to come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was just a couple of weeks into my job as the new director of Brookline Tai Chi, in the summer of 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after that, many of our lead instructors left the school and while I was in the process of training to teach, I found myself with close to 20 hours a week of classes, not the 3 to 5 I had expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that being thrust into such a high volume of classes created one of the best learning environments I could have hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every night I would have 3 different classes, sometimes 4 on the weekends. That meant that each hour I had to do a complete reset, with a fresh new group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students would come in from whatever they had done all day and I had to &#34;land&#34; them, make the feel comfortable, relaxed and slowly tune them inward to become more present. I watch this arc, from scattered and tired, to relaxed and focused happen over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process, I learned how to more artfully make that transition myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we would get &#34;to work&#34; - the middle 20 - 30 minutes of class. In the work phase we would go into a form or a principle and really train it. Once you&#39;ve opened up, relaxed repetition is much easier, and more meaningful to your nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the hour, we would do an easy practice where the goal wasn&#39;t to keep squeezing in more and more information, but rather to feel integration, letting things settle and come to rest so that your body could more easily absorbs the training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, everything would go quiet&amp;hellip;.and then I would start all over again with the next group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did that for the last ten years, so 3 x 5 x 44 x 10 or over 6,000 times. When you factor in workshops and personal practice time, I&#39;m confident that I&#39;ve paid attention to this work-rest-integration cycle for well over 10,000 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Supportive Learning Environment&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;m so grateful for the opportunity to have done this kind of learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to Brookline Tai Chi for its community and its structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to my teachers who gave me material to work on and also guided me through the meta layer of learning even more through teaching and sharing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful for all the students who were excited to learn with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m grateful to all of you reading this post who have indulged my sharing my teaching experiences on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even now, as I open a new chapter professionally, the combination of training, learning, and teaching will form the foundation for new endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve benefitted from my writing, podcasts, videos, or teaching in any form on this site, I want you to know that it&#39;s largely because of the opportunities I had to develop a teaching voice at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you will &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/thank-you-dan-retrospective-and-appeal-for-transition-contributions/&#34;&gt;consider supporting Brookline Tai Chi at this time&lt;/a&gt;, so that our learning community will continue to produce new teachers, who work hard to benefit all of us, and that as a group, we will always have a home base to return to for deep learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Moving Exercises: Immersion Week 2014</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2014 10:47:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2014/03/27/energy-gates-moving-exercises-immersion-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m getting excited about &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Immersion Week at BTC next month&lt;/a&gt;, where we&#39;ll take another look at the Spine Stretch and the Three Swings. Another look? Like we&#39;ve done it before? Yes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it exciting to go back to the same qigong sets over and over again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;So-called creative people understand better than most that there is nothing new under the sun. Working with boulders of granite, with empty stages, with blank paper, they are credited with making something out of nothing, but that isn&#39;t exactly what they do. All art is derived from what is in actuality a remarkably finite human experience. Whatever the medium, the creative person&#39;s task is to interpret an essentially unchanging reality, a dog-eared reality pondered by Homer and Mel Brooks and everyone in between. The artist succeeds if he or she can present something familiar from an unfamiliar angle.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rheta Grimsley Johnson&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This quote comes from a book about Charles Schulz, the creator of Peanuts. &lt;a href=&#34;http://austinkleon.com/2007/10/29/the-twelve-devices-of-peanuts/&#34;&gt;In this post&lt;/a&gt;, Austin Kleon breaks down the 12 familiar devices that Schulz used over and over again to tell different stories in his comic strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reusing the devices, Schulz at once created context for the reader to return to and at the same time set us up to be surprised by new insights, twists, and revelations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s try to do the same thing in our qigong practice, instead of letting familiar sets become stale and dead.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/86kIjmFf9_U?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Insight in Old Exercises&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In planning this year&#39;s event, here are the themes I hope to explore and &#34;discover.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the Spine Stretch&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How the movements reveal physical layers -- from superficial fascia to the deep muscles surrounding the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legwork that enhances your connection to the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difference between sinking chi and dissolving and the way this contrast will help you get more rooted (sinking) and penetrate deeper into the spine (dissolving).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finishing the spine stretch with a more integrated connection between the arms, legs, and spine and a sense of internal stillness.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
See, many of these qualities can be found in a standing practice or a complex moving form of Tai Chi, but the interesting question is how we can draw them out of the procedure of the Spine Stretch. I know they&#39;re in there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the Swings&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we release the arms throughout the swings series in a way that enhances the overall feeling of release and relaxation in the body?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How, given the degree of movement in the swings, can we tune into steady and continuous head-to-toe sinking or dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we use the rotational motion and rhythm of the Swings to refine our feeling of the Central Channel as an axis of movement?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the end of the series, can will come to rest in a way that feels loose, alive, and settled simultaneously?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I love the challenge of extending internal awareness into an active practice like the Swings. Even as the arms are flying up above the head, you have to learn to stay grounded and connected. The rhythm and timing become an anchor for your mind in a way that&#39;s hard to get even in a slow-motion Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Immersion Week: April 22-25&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We&#39;ll spend 2.5 hours a day on each topic for four days, April 22-25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be doing Swings in the morning and Spine Stretch in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This format lets us approach all of the exercises from many different angles: direct feeling with the mind (standing qigong), partner exercises to sensitize different body parts/capacities (twisting, loosening, sinking), and mini-exercises that allow us to feel key principles/pieces of each larger exercise (arm drops and swing, kwa squats, folds, and hinges).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both events will be held at Brookline Tai Chi and there is limited space. If you plan to attend, I encourage you to sign up by April 1 to ensure a space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Here are the details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you&#39;re coming in from out of town, consider extending your stay to refine your &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/long-form-spring-series/&#34;&gt;Long Form with Craig Barnes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Inner Form of Balance</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 09:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4807&#34; alt=&#34;Ocean Balance Rocks&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/08/iStock_000020131551XSmall-300x198.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;198&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When my first Tai Chi teacher, &lt;a title=&#34;Bruce Frantzis Tai Chi Resources&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/bruce-frantzis-tai-chi-resources/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, came back to the US forty years ago to spread the Tai Chi he learned in China, he found out that many basic Tai Chi concepts were not being taught, either because of communications issues or lack of knowledge. Only a fraction of the vast potential of the art was being shared. Bruce set out to teach &lt;em&gt;the Inner Form of Tai Chi&lt;/em&gt; and that&#39;s what I have studied for the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of endless forms and choreography, we dove into the inner workings &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi&#39;s Most Powerful Technique&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/11/06/tai-chi-most-powerful-technique/&#34;&gt;that make Tai Chi so powerful for restoring health &lt;/a&gt;and unlocking hidden internal energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Tai Chi is moving into a new phase of popular understanding in the West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Brookline Tai Chi, we are being approached more and more often by insurance companies, federal and state government agencies, and research universities to weigh in on what makes an effective Tai Chi balance training program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi is being brought into a medical context, but I worry that we will just repeat Tai Chi&#39;s last emergence onto the Western scene: as a watered-down shell of what it could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that reason, I have sought out another champion of the Inner Form approach to Tai Chi to help me share with you the real Tai Chi Way to Better Balance. Don Ethan Miller has practiced and taught Tai Chi for more than 40 years, won national titles in Tai Chi Push Hands and has, in my opinion, a unique, direct, and profound approach to Tai Chi education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re working together on the &lt;a title=&#34;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/better-balance/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/a&gt; and I wanted to share with you why I think Don&#39;s approach to teaching Tai Chi is going to be so useful for your own practice and for when you want to share Tai Chi with the people around you whose balance is failing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simple, Yet Profound&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The exercises in the program may seem simple at first. They are accessible to almost any level of physical fitness and balance. In fact, the exercises are precisely layered (more on that below) to allow almost anyone to regain their balance safely and gradually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&#39;s the thing. I have seen firsthand, watching Don teach these exercises to people who have done Tai Chi for 5, 10 or even 20 years, that if you, the experienced Tai Chi practitioner, approach the program with an open mind, you will reignite your stale or faltering Tai Chi practice. Seasoned practitioners will find depth in the simplest instructions here and marvel at the layers of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re anything like me, you&#39;ll be jealous of the beginners who take on this program, because they&#39;re getting the depth you had to search for years to find, going from teacher to teacher for bits and pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Feel, Then Do&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For those of you who are new to Tai Chi, chances are, if you wander into your local YMCA or church Tai Chi class, you&#39;ll be thrown into &#34;The Form.&#34; With a great teacher, the form will be presented alongside the principles (Inner Form!) that make the movements work. Too often, though, the principles are absent and you&#39;re just asked to follow along until you get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To us, especially if you have the urgent need to improve your balance, this is the long way around&amp;hellip;in the best-case scenario. At worst, you fumble around, get frustrated and quit. No benefit there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won&#39;t find a forms-based approach here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, follow this simple rule as you work through the exercises in the program: &lt;strong&gt;feel, then do&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a practically limitless space to feel into when you open up your inner world with Tai Chi. From &lt;a title=&#34;Wu Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/wu-chi/&#34;&gt;the very first exercise&lt;/a&gt;, you&#39;ll be asked to explore by feel. This is Tai Chi from the inside out. It&#39;s all about what you learn to feel. And feeling leads to moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After each exercise, you will also feel and reflect on what you&#39;ve just done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, Don is like a master chef. He&#39;s crafted a book of recipes for you here. All the ingredients are laid out. The directions are clear. You just need to put them together and then, enjoy the dish. Taste it. Savor it. And be satiated with the wonderful, nurturing meals you are cooking for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Layers of Progress&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you work through the levels in the program, you&#39;ll notice that the skills you build are layered one on top of the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you get comfortable on two legs, with no distractions. But what happens when you only have one leg to stand on? &lt;a title=&#34;Dragon Scans the Horizon&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dragon-scans-the-horizon/&#34;&gt;Or you add an arm motion and a head turn?&lt;/a&gt; Slowly, you will add layers, and each time, you will understand how the new layer makes you stronger, more stable, and more internally connected in accordance with key Tai Chi principles like Rooting and Central Equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the complexity of the exercises increase, so will your rate of discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see people burst out of classes all the time. They can&#39;t wait to bounce down the street or frolic in the park. It&#39;s kind of goofy when you their eyes light up like little kids again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s what I wish for you and hope we can share with the world about the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later this month, we will be releasing the first DVD and eBook in this program, but you can start working on Tai Chi balance training right now. &lt;a title=&#34;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/better-balance/&#34;&gt;Click here to learn more.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Obviously Tai Chi Improves Balance, But How Do You Explain It?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 14:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/07/09/obviously-tai-chi-improves-balance-but-how-do-you-explain-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4716&#34; alt=&#34;don + sue 2&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2013/07/don-+-sue-2-e1373377188614-261x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;261&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We often talk about the way Tai Chi can &lt;a title=&#34;The Transformational Power of Tai Chi Body Mechanics&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/07/the-transformational-power-of-tai-chi-body-mechanics/&#34;&gt;improve your physical health and mental and emotional well-being&lt;/a&gt; from the point of view of the practitioner. But not everyone out there is as familiar with practical ways to use Tai Chi to support their health and wellness goals as you may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later this year, I&#39;m thrilled to have the chance to share Tai Chi with physicians in a course at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hmscme.com/activelives/faculty&#34;&gt;Harvard Medical School&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s always exciting to be able to present a combination of research and practice to knowledgeable caregivers, especially because in this case, the focus of the course is on promoting healthy, active lifestyles to their patients. What do you think I should share with them? If you have suggestions for what I should cover, please leave a note in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the mean time, I&#39;d like to invite you into a conversation about &lt;em&gt;how we talk about the benefits of our practice.&lt;/em&gt; As Brookline Tai Chi has been working with the Department of Public Health and other senior care agencies to spread practical implementation of &lt;a title=&#34;Dr. Fuzhong Li&#39;s Tai Chi Research&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/dr-fuzhong-lis-tai-chi-research/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi falls prevention research&lt;/a&gt;, we find ourselves in a very different world, using new language and talking to new audiences about the benefits of Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent episode of Qigong Radio, Dr. Peter Wayne discussed the &lt;a title=&#34;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, a framework that he uses to define his Tai Chi research. We need more thoughtful ways like this to express the benefits of Tai Chi practice in an understandable way, without watering everything down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to keep the conversation moving in this direction, so I took the problem to one of my most eloquent teachers, Don Ethan Miller. As a result, Don and I have been working on a new program, called &lt;strong&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance&lt;/strong&gt;, which will be out later this summer. In The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance, we set out to refine the language around Tai Chi balance concepts and, more importantly, get at the essence of what makes Tai Chi so good for improving balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we would like you to join in the conversation. Please join us for a discussion of The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance on Thursday, July 18, from 12-1pm EST. We will explore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The essential elements of a Tai Chi balance training program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to make sure you include these balance exercises in every practice session, whether your goal is falls prevention, becoming more relaxed and centered,  or training for competition-level Push Hands &lt;em&gt;(the secret is that it can be the same training!)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to share Tai Chi balance training with friends and family -- without making them feel like they have to take on a serious practice to get real benefits.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p3p1&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p3p1&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p3p1;(function(d, t) { var s = d.createElement(t), options = { &#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,  &#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p3p1&#39;,  &#39;autoResize&#39;:true, &#39;height&#39;:&#39;728&#39;, &#39;async&#39;:true, &#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,  &#39;ssl&#39;:true}; s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;; s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() { var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return; try { r7p3p1 = new WufooForm();r7p3p1.initialize(options);r7p3p1.display(); } catch (e) {}}; var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr); })(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice Rhythms at Tai Chi Immersion Week </title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/04/23/practice-rhythms-at-tai-chi-immersion-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 11:16:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2013/04/23/practice-rhythms-at-tai-chi-immersion-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is my mid-week update from Tai Chi Immersion Week 2013 at &lt;a title=&#34;Brookline Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/brookline-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s pretty cool to see folks come from all over to train for a week, but you really have to have the right mind set to make the most of the format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See what I mean here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://youtu.be/tBOBhSljYNo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice, be sure to include a clear:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warm-up: &lt;/strong&gt;where you settle in and transition from the rest of your day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ramp-up:&lt;/strong&gt; where the real &#34;training&#34; happens and you work on specific attributes of your practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration period:&lt;/strong&gt; where you don&#39;t try to do anything new, but let the work from the ramp-up period settle down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buffer:&lt;/strong&gt; where, without making an abrupt shift, you transition back into the rest of your day.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Whether you practice for &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;20 minutes&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a title=&#34;Practice Twice a Day&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/01/practice-twice-a-day/&#34;&gt;twice a day for a week&lt;/a&gt;, if you look for these rhythms, you will build more energy and deepen your Tai Chi practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2012 12:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/11/12/bend-the-bow-spinal-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Eric Peters describes what it&#39;s like to work with the energy of the spine, using Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bend the Bow is an advanced qigong set that requires precise alignment and refined sensitivity, but it gives you access to a much deeper level of internal connection and coordination than standard ways of moving your body through space. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric performing Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/q3tlLKD4YdM?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you download or listen to the episode below, you might also want to check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/bend-bow-spinal-qigong&#34;&gt;the description of Bend the Bow Spinal Qigong on EnergyArts.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/classes/chi-gung-bend-bow-introduction-bend-bow-and-shoot-arrow-december-1-2-late-fall-session&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be sure to check out Eric&#39;s Bend the Bow workshop, December 1 and 2, 2012 at Brookline Tai Chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Cloud Hands Fall Workshop</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 17:31:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/07/23/tai-chi-cloud-hands-fall-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4081&#34; title=&#34;Robert Tangora Tai Chi Cloud Hands&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/07/DSC_0067-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are in the process of finalizing the details of a Tai Chi Cloud Hands workshop with Robert Tangora this fall in Boston, from October 26-28.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As preparation for the workshop, I will be teaching a fall course at Brookline Tai Chi, covering the basic mechanics of Cloud Hands, as well as the prep exercises from Robert&#39;s newly published book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m really looking forward to taking everyone at Brookline Tai Chi through these exercises and at the same time, working with members of the Inner Form coaching program to improve their Cloud Hands practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4080&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, I just shared a 25-minute follow-along practice mp3 with the Inner Form members, guiding them through a set of Cloud Hands prep exercises. This is the same kind of coaching I give people in live classes each week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more it amazes me just how many different ways we are able to refine and improve qigong and Tai Chi practice. Of course, people have been teaching themselves the basics from books for years, but I think we&#39;ve entered age where getting feedback and guidance remotely is getting much more sophisticated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, there are elements of the practice that will only be transmitted in person, but think of how much more we are able to share this way, through video, audio, email, and written discussion -- across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It amazes me that people continue to find this site, reach out, and connect with each other about something so personal, so individual, and so fundamental to their sense of well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And I&#39;m grateful that I get to share in that with all of you!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, ok, so back to the workshop announcement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&#39;re in Boston and you want to prep for Tai Chi Cloud Hands with Robert Tangora in October, be sure you&#39;re on &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/contact-us/chi-mail&#34;&gt;the Brookline Tai Chi mailing list&lt;/a&gt; when we announce the new course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you plan to come to Boston for the workshop, you should probably join &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/contact-us/chi-mail&#34;&gt;the BTC email list too&lt;/a&gt;, so you&#39;ll get all the details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&#39;re already a member of the Inner Form section of this site, be sure to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/forum/cloud-hands-challenge/prep-exercises-mp3/&#34;&gt;download your practice mp3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a Tai Chi practice (budding or established) and you&#39;re looking for other dedicated practitioners who will share ideas with you, give you feedback and motivate you to keep up your practice, you should join us in &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/&#34;&gt;the Inner Form section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Straight Lines, Circles, and Spheres</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/04/11/straight-lines-circles-and-spheres/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2012 07:53:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/04/11/straight-lines-circles-and-spheres/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most fascinating connections between your mind and your body is the way that the actual physical movements that you make affect your awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When your movements are linear and jerky, your mind stops and starts too, essentially gapping out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can move in a smooth circular way, your mind tends to stay calmer too. Or at least, you can calm your mind through circular movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next level of &#34;smooth&#34;, though, is spherical movement. That&#39;s the specialty of Gods Playing in the Clouds Qigong.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3791&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Next session, at Brookline Tai Chi, we will begin to work on Gods again. Here&#39;s what we&#39;ll be focusing on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/WLlgMDqFW4I?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/WLlgMDqFW4I?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prepare for this shift from Heaven and Earth to Gods, and more generally, unpack the concept of straight lines, circles, and spheres, &lt;strong&gt;I&#39;m holding a free online class on Thursday, April 19 from 12 to 1pm, EDT.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow and Stabilizing the Mind with Craig Barnes</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 08:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/28/flow-and-stabilizing-the-mind-with-craig-barnes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2203&#34; title=&#34;Craig Barnes doing Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-3-199x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Craig Barnes doing Dragon and Tiger Qigong&#34; width=&#34;199&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;Stability and flow seem to be at odds with each other. Stability can mean rigidity, or at least, it seems to conjure up something fixed, sturdy, and unmoving. Flow isn&#39;t any of those things. It&#39;s fluid and changing. So how does Energy Arts Senior Instructor Craig Barnes blend the two so seamlessly?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2191&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Recently, Craig taught a workshop about awakening energetic sensitivity, drawn from principles of Dragon and Tiger Qigong. We worked a lot on the opening of the set. The goal was to &#34;fill up your chi&#34; before you start doing the movements, so that the body is awake and engaged and each movement is more alive and more connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specific method for waking up your energetic sensitivity begins with refining awareness of your physical body. How do you move each part under conscious control, in a smooth circular way? Craig is very skilled at leading a group through a gradual progression that brings each new piece online and then weaves it together with the previous pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What impressed me more, though, was the way he included &#34;stability points&#34;, while maintaining the flow of the teaching, which was also what he was teaching people to do in their practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps &#34;stability point&#34; is the wrong term. Certainly this was a &#34;point&#34; in time in the flow of practice, but what Craig teaches, as far as stabilizing the mind, has a more diffuse quality than &#34;point&#34; conveys. You miss it if you focus on all the little details of body mechanics. If you treat the components of your practice like a checklist, you never become internally connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stability of the mind, when Craig expresses it, becomes the ground for your practice. A stable mind is like a table, set for a great meal. The specific exercises are the plates and bowls and cups that get filled up with delicious food, but you need to set the table for the meal to come together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-medium wp-image-2204&#34; title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Sword Fingers&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/09/Craig-DT-2-224x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Sword Fingers&#34; width=&#34;224&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Internalizing the paradox of stability and flow goes a step or two beyond &#34;setting the table&#34;, though. Dragon and Tiger is a great place to learn how to stabilize the mind in the flow of movements because, between each distinct movement pattern, there are transitional moves that you can repeat as much as you need to. In these transitions, it&#39;s much easier to return to stability, but you don&#39;t have to break the flow. You do something simple, like circle the arms back and forth around the waist, or pulse the hands in and out, which keeps up a smooth flow. Through the simple repetition, your mind can settle down again at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Dragon and Tiger is made for this kind of work, you can still go through this process in any qigong set, if you follow these rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start your practice with simple, repetitive movements that allow you to tune into the background or underlying stability of your mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tease out gradually bigger and bigger movements, without losing the stable ground feeling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work up into larger flow patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take soft landings throughout the set that return you to something simple and repetitive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For tai chi people: this is why a phrase like Grasp Sparrow&#39;s Tail is repeated a dozen times in a long form.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning Tai Chi for the First Time</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/08/learning-tai-chi-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2011 09:54:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/09/08/learning-tai-chi-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are about to start the Early Fall session at Brookline Tai Chi and I&#39;ve been thinking a lot about how to teach the introductory class. The challenge, when you learn tai chi for the first time, is all about mindset. I want to see if I can teach them &#34;how to learn tai chi&#34; as much as actually teaching tai chi. This might sound like a beginner-only problem, but I have a challenge for more experienced readers at the end of this post and I&#39;m wondering if you can keep up with my beginners on this one. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2095&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inner Form vs. Outer Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you first start learning tai chi, the obvious reference point is what you&#39;ve seen people doing in the parks. People often describe it as &#34;slow-motion karate&#34; or a graceful dance. Understand that these comparisons only really touch the surface of what tai chi can be. You are looking at the Outer Form when you describe the choreography. But the real good stuff in tai chi happens with the Inner Form. Here&#39;s what I mean:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0Djrh7HNuuI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;345&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0Djrh7HNuuI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Your First Tai Chi Class&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Every teacher makes an important decision during the first class: focus on the Outer Form or Inner Form? In some ways, this is the answer they are giving to the question, &#34;What is Tai Chi?&#34; You can either answer this by showing the Outer Form or trying to give your students a feel for the Inner Form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an Outer Form class, you will be shown as many movements as you can possibly handle in an hour. It will feel like a dance lesson and the instructor will be in the front of the room counting out steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an Inner Form class, you will be shown one or two (at the most) movements. You will be asked to feel different facets of the movement, sometimes focusing on the upper body, then the lower body, then an aspect like breathing. You will also look at how performing each movement affects your nervous system. Can you get more relaxed as you do the movement? Are you straining to achieve a certain shape? You will eventually be shown how each part moves and what the mind should be doing. To coordinate your intention and your body well, you need to perform a single movement again and again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most beginners get frustrated by all the repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tell you the truth, I never know which students will fall in love with this approach and which will run screaming in the other direction. I&#39;m fine with that, actually. Tai Chi is a very particular method and it takes the right attitude or even constitution to connect with it. I don&#39;t mean this in a judgmental way. It&#39;s much more like puzzle pieces. You have to fit together with the Tai Chi approach. I&#39;ve never seen anyone be successfully forced into a relaxation practice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Learn Tai Chi -- All Over Again&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So for the experienced practitioners, when was the last time you slowed down and did a practice session like the Inner Form class I just described above? Tonight, my beginners are going to spend an hour exploring the opening movement of the form. Can you still practice like that? Can you find that much depth in a single piece of your practice? Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Form Training Final Update</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 12:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/12/short-form-training-final-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m heading home to Boston tomorrow, but I&#39;ve already begun looking through my notes and thinking about what I will personally practice and what I&#39;ll be able to share with my students in classes this coming year. Here are some of my initial thoughts:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1827&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ZkLnAA8ejb8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ZkLnAA8ejb8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Material is Woven together over a Month:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Day to day we&#39;re looking at really small specific pieces but now going back through my notes, I can start to see different threads that run throughout the duration of the month. It&#39;s almost like you don&#39;t even notice some of the nuances as in the moment, but like we&#39;ll look at something about the legs in Tai Chi from the first day and then we came back to it four or five days later and then we look at it again, and when you actually line up the pieces side by side, what you start to see is that...versus looking at it from like sort of looking at a ball, you look at it from one side and then the next time you look at it from this angle, then you look at it from this angle. And by taking this kind of spherical approach to it, looking at different facets of the subject, you start to develop a sense for the whole. And it&#39;s not the progression that he always teaches and it&#39;s not linear. It&#39;s not one, two, three, four, five. It&#39;s look at it this way, look at it that way and it&#39;s sort of up to you to put the pieces together to create the whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Handling Stress on a Whole New Level&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;They&#39;re all are these layers to that and progressions that I&#39;ll be able to lay out for my students, but personally for me I think one of the most exciting ones that I&#39;ll be able to bring to people is some really specific technical information about burnout and stress and no, I mean, if you think about Tai Chi in general, that&#39;s kind of what it&#39;s known for. It&#39;s a relaxation practice and it looks calming in that way. Everybody&#39;s first impression of it is that it is gentle and relaxing, but we actually got in much deeper into the technical stuff and the form that actually makes the softness of Tai Chi really work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;s not always contrasted to the couch potato model of relaxation where we live in this culture where we think, okay just go, go, go, go, go 24/7 and when you want to relax, pass out on the couch in front of the TV. So we have these two extremes. Tai chi is sort of an antidote to stress. It works on relaxation but it&#39;s a little more complicated than that. It&#39;s not... relaxation isn&#39;t just a flop. Relaxation has to do much more with your capacity to put energy out and take energy in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there&#39;s some really interesting technical stuff in terms of being able to absorb and nourish the body that is really Tai Chi&#39;s strong suit that you&#39;re not going to get in this kind of fast paced go, go, go, very Yang, very revved up kind of mentality. Instead, Tai Chi has a way of building the nervous system and building the body up so that it can rest, absorb and regenerate and we looked at some really specific ways to highlight in the form to make sure that happens for people.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3 Update from the Beach</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/08/05/week-3-update-from-the-beach/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 3 wraps up and testing is right around the corner. What was Bruce&#39;s big message as we prepare for testing? Work your ass off and cram all night for the big test? Not quite. You might be surprised. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1823&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/BQcg7CR5F78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/BQcg7CR5F78?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Lesson about Integration:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest thing that Bruce is emphasizing in the last couple days of class is that with this stage of the training, a month long training, you need integration time. And we talk about this all the time in regular weekly classes. We talk about in a given practice session, whether it&#39;s an hour or 20 minutes or whatever, you always have this sort of startup time where you just get warmed up. And then from there you go into the work period, where you just kind of crank and crank and crank, and that&#39;s when your system is the most open. You can get a lot done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the biggest mistake people make is that they do that hard charge all the way to the end. The secret to all of these energy practices, to really get your energy to smoothed out and then get into your nervous system in the best possible way, is that you need to have integration. So, we talk about it all the time. That&#39;s how we try to do each practice session. So, to me, it&#39;s really cool to watch this month-long work and hear Bruce talk about that and emphasize that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Yesterday he talked a lot about what to do on the day off, in terms of even just mentally rehearsing the form, going through and trying to feel it through your body without doing the movements. So there&#39;s a lot of interesting stuff about mental rehearsal that we talked about, but also just to let it kind of soak into your system. And I find when students can recognize that integration phase as a legitimate part of the practice, then you take it to a whole deeper level, because you recognize rest as an important part of hard work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And I think there are a lot of ways that we&#39;ve lost that idea culturally and a lot of ideas of success and hard work don&#39;t really acknowledge the resting and integration phase as an important piece of it. So even though we&#39;ve come through intensive month-long training, as we&#39;re rounding into the final stretch, rest and integration and relaxation is a key piece to learning all this stuff. And to me that&#39;s very cool. So that&#39;s what we&#39;re up to this week.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2 of the Short Form Instructor Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 09:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/30/week-2-of-the-short-form-instructor-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my Week 2 update. Some big milestones this week: group 1 finished the form and group 2 has been languishing in the purgatory that is holding static postures. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1816&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/FpsecDulvWc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/FpsecDulvWc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inner Form vs. Outer Form&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;In the two groups, we&#39;re doing very different things. The group one just finished the form this week. So on Thursday after they finished it, we came in Friday, and it was a really interesting dividing line. Bruce made the big distinction between, on the one hand, on Thursday we finished the shape and the form, that&#39;s sort of the container. He said, &#34;Now, everything that we&#39;re going to do has to do with internal content.&#34; So he made this distinction all the time. He talked about the bottle versus the wine you put inside it and we even have an article at Brookline Tai Chi that we put out from, I think, it&#39;s from 1989 Tai Chi Magazine. The title of the article is &#34;The Inner Form is the Key to Health.&#34; And in the article, Bruce talks about all the different internal content things that should be going on that to be Tai Chi form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And I find this working with beginners all the time is such a huge hurdle to get them over. Because people know Tai Chi by looks like in the outside, they see the shapes and the movements, and they see it flowing and graceful and relaxed, but it&#39;s really hard unless you&#39;re used to looking at it, to see what&#39;s going on inside. But Bruce always makes this big point, it actually what goes on inside that makes Tai Chi actually effective. It makes it not just choreography but it makes it work to improve your health, we&#39;re going to do meditation and martial arts. If you don&#39;t have the internal content, it&#39;s like driving a car without an engine. So it&#39;s interesting to hear him talk about for a group that&#39;s just finishing the container of the form. Now, to start to see what he started out with. And as far as internal content for them and how we&#39;re going to build that up. So that&#39;s a cool inflection point in the halfway point for the first group.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Finding Internal Stability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the second group we&#39;ve been holding postures. And so we&#39;ve gone through now, I think, eight of the postures and the form, and building out from twenty, twenty-five, thirty minutes. And this is one of my favorite methods - the posture holding and you see up here, look at some other posing here, you see me messing around with 30 minutes in one posture or something else like that, I&#39;ve always liked it in the standing practice. It was the thing that kind of, for me, made the difference of what&#39;s in the outside and &#34;Hey, if you stand still and start to just feel into the body, there&#39;s this whole internal landscape you can start to explore.&#34; And that was the thing that always got me excited about Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&#39;m very happy that we&#39;ve been going through and holding posture by posture. What it is about it, is that if you get into each posture and the form, each of them because of the physical constraints, higher twisting, one way twisting, the other way, whether the posture&#39;s more extended, or whether the posture is more condensed, all of these things add up to determine in a specific posture how you manifest the energy of that posture. And so by holding it, you start to feel those internal gears kind of click and lock together in a way that you just if you&#39;re always just going through the form doing whatever, you totally missed that aspect. Sometimes you noticed really where you&#39;re tense, where things are stuck. But once you get each one of these things, it has kind of like a threshold where it clicks in. And I&#39;ve always thought about it in terms of, &#34;Okay, I&#39;m going to hold this one for twenty, this one for thirty, this one longer, longer.&#34; But one of the key points that Bruce made was that once you hit a certain stability point for that posture, everything opens up and lights up. The pathways light up or this connection lights up that gives the posture a unique flavor. That&#39;s the key moment. And then you wanted to maintain that for as long as you can. And inevitably you lose it, you shrink out of it, you start to collapse a little bit, something gets off. And this is game of like, &#34;Okay, how do I connect to it?&#34; Reliably create that effective posture and then stabilize it. And once you can stabilize it for a long time, then you move into this thing where the quality, the posture becomes integrated into your form and to how you move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to me, I don&#39;t know, it&#39;s a fascinating process. Other people joke that the fastest way clear Tai Chi class and get everybody to flee out of the room is to just make them close their eyes and hold the posture. So it&#39;s definitely a matter of personal preference. But I mean it&#39;s really cool, that&#39;s what we&#39;ve been focusing on all week.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I am Learning at the Wu Tai Chi Instructor Training</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 01:48:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/26/what-im-learning-at-the-wu-tai-chi-instructor-training-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re a week into the Wu Tai Chi short form instructor training in Brighton, UK, with Lineage Holder Bruce Frantzis. So far we&#39;ve been completely rebuilding our forms, working on Tai Chi leg power, and exploring the meditative aspects of the art. Check it out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2964&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HoXz88Vyxe0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/HoXz88Vyxe0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Rebuilding Your Form:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s crazy when you come at these things, you&#39;re completely rebuilding your Tai Chi form. We&#39;re about two-thirds of the way through the form and it feels so different. When you&amp;Acirc;  run through the whole thing one time, you get up to what we&#39;ve done so far and it feels brand new, like a completely different moves. And then you get to the last thing we&#39;ve done, you come around to the last move that you finished and you go back to your old form and it has a totally different feeling.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Yin and Yang of Tai Chi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The contrast is that the biggest thing that he took from the London trainings into the Tai Chi training was this idea. He talks about it in terms of Yin and Yang, in terms of soft and hard, or in the sitting practice, it&#39;s about how do you go deep inside the body. You find this internal space and then let go of anything you find that&#39;s stuck. But there&#39;s an interesting contrast, it&#39;s not just let go and relax and collapse because the quality of mind it takes is that you have to sort of go inside, find and hold your awareness on something and persist with this awareness. That&#39;s a stronger quality. So this is interesting, this is Yin and Yang blend of getting your mind onto something and holding it there, giving it shape and containing this feeling. But then the other side it to completely let go, completely relaxing. So that&#39;s the Yin and Yang of the dissolving process. And we&#39;ve expanded that idea where he&#39;s talking about the energies in the Tai Chi form, the way we working on Tai Chi, the forming energies to the form, that balance of finding it, holding it and adding this kind of consistent, persistent meditative awareness as you do Tai Chi, is mirrored in the sort of the Yang aspects of the Tai Chi form. And then that letting go, softening, releasing, relaxing and just completely not holding on anything is there&#39;s the Yin qualities to the form, that have that same thing. So through Peng, Lu, Ji and An, each one of those from a meditative point of view can figure into how you&#39;re doing, making your Tai Chi form a true meditation practice, not just relaxation practice. So there&#39;s really great stuff there.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Quiet Awareness with Lee Burkins</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/30/accessing-quiet-awareness-with-lee-burkins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1656&#34; title=&#34;Lee Burkins Ba Gua&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/ABG1-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lee Burkins Ba Gua&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In June, between sessions at Brookline Tai Chi and during master classes with Bruce Frantzis, a small group of students got a special treat. Energy Arts Senior Instructor Lee Burkins was in town to train with Bruce, and on one of the nights off, he offered a special evening course on a topic he calls &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/blog/special-evening-mini-topic-lee-burkins&#34;&gt;&#34;Investing in Loss&#34;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I love about studying with someone like Lee is that he&#39;s a  practitioner whose art has soaked so deeply into his bones, that it  practically oozes out of his DNA. Everything he teaches seems so  obviously and natural when he explains it, but you&#39;ve never thought about  it before and never accessed it so effortlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second time he&#39;s taught at Brookline Tai Chi. The first  time, a couple of years ago, he did the same thing with the&amp;Acirc;  Ba Gua  Single Palm Change. Lee took a group of people, most of whom had never  done Ba Gua, and got them gliding around the room, finding the Ba Gua  step, and eventually even spontaneously twisting and turning into the  Single Palm Change. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1651&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our topic this year seemed more esoteric at first, so I was wondering if he&#39;d be able to do the same thing. What  the heck is &#34;Quiet Awareness&#34; and how do you let that run your physical  body? You could see that with many other teachers, this could have been a  2-hour theoretical lecture. Not with Lee. He snuck up on us with really  clear and simple physical exercises, just letting go of tension and  posture through movements. We let ourselves swirl around and find a  sloshing, fluid, sense of internal space. Once people had settled down  into deeper internal awareness, he showed us how to shape an internal  sense of letting go into a solid physical structure and full, alive, and  responsive physical movement. Obviously this is all a little hard to  explain in writing....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funniest moment though, was after everyone began to really get  what he was driving at, he said, &#34;ok, ok, you&#39;re doing it, so let me  give you something to feed your thinking mind too.&#34; See, the bigger  point he was driving at was that Quiet Awareness is a different mode for  your mind to be in, and you need that to understand your body, your  mind, and your energy. The internal arts are all about accessing this  mode and manifesting it. The problem is, most of us are trained to use a  different mode of awareness, i.e. the thinking mind. As a masterful  teacher, he recognized that, and with the gentle humor he always uses in  teaching, he graciously gave our thinking minds something to chew on  too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Here&#39;s the model he shared:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Leaves on river by rstrawser, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/14696088@N04/1544960560/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2395/1544960560_9e4ba9f9f8_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Leaves on river&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lee took the classic Chinese medicine phrase, &#34;the mind moves the chi  and the chi moves the blood&#34; and formulated it as &#34;the Quiet Awareness  moves the chi and the chi moves the fluids inside the body and therefore  the body as well&#34;. To really get this concept, he explained it like the  current in a river. Think of a leaf floating along in the river. That&#39;s  your body. When the current changes, that&#39;s like the chi shifting. It  shifts direction (inward to outward, up to down), because your Quiet  Awareness shifts first. The interesting part is the lag time between  the change of the current and movement of the leaf. Your Quiet Awareness  turns over, the chi follows, and so does the leaf, but as you are learning  to tune into this process, you can feel the leaf moving along the old  current pattern, even as the current is going a different direction.  Those are the circular transitions you feel in your form.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I don&#39;t know if I quite captured what we did or what Lee was  aiming to teach, but if you ever do get a chance to work with him, take  it. He&#39;s a kind and generous teacher and the naturalness of his art form  that pours out is a real treasure. &lt;a href=&#34;http://coloradointernalarts.com/practitioners.htm&#34;&gt;Lee lives and teaches in Colorado&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In his own words: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I followed up with Lee to see if this recap came close to capturing what he was teaching. Here&#39;s how he describes the process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the mind&#39;s frequency to smoothly transition from  the&amp;Acirc; vibration&amp;Acirc; of the intellectual aspect to approach and begin to  connect with the vibration/frequency of the intuitive mind. Once you  &#39;experience&#39; this shift in frequency and are able to stay in this mode  (a posture of the mind), &#39;what is hidden will be revealed&#39;, ie, the  connection of the quiet awareness to the chi to the body (nerves,  fluids, and tissues).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>