<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>visual-training on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/visual-training/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in visual-training on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/visual-training/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Read Faster, Move Better</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Eyercize is a free, web-based reading pacer that turns any text into a speed reading exercise. But, you can do more than just read faster using Eyercize. You can actually improve how you move, if you follow these simple training guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3457&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Part of the reason I&#39;m so excited about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eyercize.com&#34;&gt;Eyercize&lt;/a&gt; is how easy it is to use. Check out this video demo where I show you how to turn any web page into a eye training exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/rHKcP476yjY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/rHKcP476yjY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the creators of Eyercize explain on their site, most people probably haven&#39;t trained their reading skills since they first learned to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading faster, using the method that Eyercize is built on, relies on three interdependent skills. Basically, you read in chunks of letters. As your eye moves across the line, it takes a snapshot of a group of letters, which your brain processes, and then you move on to a new chunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading speed is determined by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The size of the chunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How quickly you jump from chunk to chunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much you keep moving forward, without going back to re-read the same chunk again&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eyercize trains you to expand the size of the chunk, move faster to the next chunk, and not go back and re-read the same chunk over again by moving the highlighter along at a set speed.&amp;Acirc;  If you really want to understand the technical details, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eyercize.com/home/tools&#34;&gt;add Eyercize to your bookmarks&lt;/a&gt;, hop over to the Wikipedia page about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eye_movement_in_language_reading&#34;&gt;Eye Movements in Reading&lt;/a&gt;, and read through it in the Eyercize reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Role of the Eyes in Movement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Saccadic movement, the technical term for the eyes moving rapidly side to side, like you do in reading, is one of the main visual skills that your brain uses to get information about your surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are unaware of just how much spatial and positional information we take in, but your body adopts a postural response based on the quality of information your visual system feeds your brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-3477&#34; title=&#34;Postural strain can come from lack of visual stamina&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/02/shutterstock_18400546-300x199.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lack of visual stamina can lead to postural strain.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;199&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can think about it as another case of &#34;garbage in, garbage out&#34;, but I prefer the positive statement that if you give your nervous system the best possible information, you get the best performance out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more, I&#39;ve written about &lt;a title=&#34;The Strange Link between Eyes and Movement&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/30/the-strange-link-between-eyes-and-movement/&#34;&gt;the link between eyes and movement&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/&#34;&gt;how the eyes influence flexibility&lt;/a&gt; (at 4:00 in the video) , and &lt;a title=&#34;2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/&#34;&gt;how poor eye movement can lead to neck pain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, though, the most important thing to know is that there is actually a bio-feedback test you can use to tell if new information is &#34;good information&#34; or &#34;garbage&#34;. In this case, when we are using a tool like Eyercize, we will use a bio-feedback test to tell when we&#39;ve hit the limit of productive eye work. More isn&#39;t always better. Especially with visual training, you can easily do too much in one sitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one of many bio-feedback tests we use in Z Health to determine if we should keep training or take a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Test Range of Motion Before and After&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Range of motion, using something as simple as a toe-touch, can tell you a lot about the state of your nervous system. You can also use shoulder flexion (like I demonstrate &lt;a title=&#34;What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) or neck rotation, which is especially instructive if you notice one side is a lot tighter than the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all about the little indicators that the fight-or-flight response is kicking in. If your nervous system perceives threat, it reigns in range of motion. Just think of the protective gesture of the &#34;fetal position&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our premise for this bio-feedback test is that if range of motion increase, and you feel looser and more flexible after performing the reading exercises, you have a green light to continue. As soon as you notice a decrease in your range of motion, stop, rest, and do something to restore the balance, like I recommend below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get your baseline for your reading practice session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand up straight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bend forward and try to touch your toes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice how far you go and which muscles feel tight first&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You&#39;re going to perform exactly the same exercise after you do 1 minute of speed reading with the pacer. Then retest your range of motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Red Light, Green Light&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Did you notice a change before and after 1 minute of speed reading? If not, double your time and try it again. Repeat this process until you notice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any change in range of motion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Postural changes while you read, like slumping in your chair or craning your neck&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you can comfortably do 2-3 minutes of speed reading with no noticeable change in posture or pre- and post-testing, then you are ready to increase the variables in the reader. Those are all the controls along the left side of the Eyercize interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Balance Foveal Work with Peripheral Work&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eyercize trains one of your foveal vision skills. &#34;Foveal&#34; means you are using the retina to focus on something. The opposite skill set is peripheral vision, and you can use peripheral vision work to give yourself a break from too much focusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a really simple peripheral drill you can do right at your desk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring your arms up in front of you and touch your hands together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start wiggling your index finger on each hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slowly move your arms apart and out to the sides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As your hands move away from each other, keep wiggling your fingers, but look straight ahead -- here&#39;s where you activate your peripheral vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue to track your wiggling fingers using only your peripheral vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can move your hands up and down independently in your peripheral field, but be sure to keep your eyes straight ahead&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a couple of minutes of peripheral work should be a nice balance to intense focus work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use Eyercize with posture in mind, you&#39;ll see some great results in reading speed and your overall quality of movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2012 09:03:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my students says that in medical school they were taught how to explain their clinical observations in a way that made them sound more official. For example, if you see something once, you can say that &#34;in my experience...&#34; The second time you&#39;ve observed the same phenomenon, you can say that &#34;in case after case....&#34; Finally, if you&#39;re seeing something more than two times, you&#39;ve seen it &#34;in a series of cases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, last week, in case after case of neck-related pain and discomfort, the cause of the pain came down to one simple movement principle: substitution.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2949&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In this video, I explain how the nervous system bridges the gap between what you ask your body to do and performing that task by any means it can. Practically, this can result in the wrong body part moving for one that doesn&#39;t respond to the call of the nervous system, or &#34;substitution.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chronic substitution leads to pain, discomfort, and sets the stage for injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Specific Causes of Neck Pain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the case of neck pain, you&#39;ll often see under-performing eyes or stuck vertebrae force the neck into excess movement:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/KsBX4eHvtTo?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/KsBX4eHvtTo?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to avoid these causes of neck pain:&lt;/strong&gt; Tune up your eyes (&lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;try my free visual training course&lt;/a&gt;) and do a full-body movement inventory on a regular basis (&lt;a title=&#34;Recommended Products&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/products/&#34;&gt;check out the Z Health R-Phase set&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching the First &#34;Foundations of Relaxation&#34; Course</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/03/15/launching-the-first-foundations-of-relaxation-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 16:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/03/15/launching-the-first-foundations-of-relaxation-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m pretty excited about this: &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/courses/eyes-and-visual-training/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eyes and Visual Training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-714&#34; title=&#34;Floating Hot Dog&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/03/Hot-Dog-300x169.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;169&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s my new online course and the first in the Foundations of Relaxation Series I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As I&#39;ve been developing the course, I keep saying to myself, &#34;I wish everyone who comes to see me for pain relief or to learn tai chi did this first.&#34; In fact, that&#39;s how I developed the whole series. There are a few simple things that don&#39;t take a lot of oversight or feedback from an instructor that everyone can do to move better (meaning more gracefully and in less pain).&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-712&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m offering it at a pretty steep discount on what I plan to sell it for: $49 for now, instead of $97 (so snatch it up!). Plus, you get lifetime access to the material, so you can keep coming back to it and working on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a host of secondary reasons this is exciting too. One of them is that I&#39;m using Trainerfly, my web-based training app, to run the course. I&#39;m already using it with private clients and remotely teaching a tai chi group in Maine, but this is the first full course. I&#39;m sure I&#39;ll learn a ton by doing it, which is great, because I have a few other tai chi teachers interested in doing the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for updates on how it&#39;s going once people are in the system working with the course material!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>