<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>visual-training on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/visual-training/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in visual-training on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/visual-training/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Read Faster, Move Better</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</guid>
      <description>Eyercize is a free, web-based reading pacer that turns any text into a speed reading exercise. But, you can do more than just read faster using Eyercize. You can actually improve how you move, if you follow these simple training guidelines.
Part of the reason I&#39;m so excited about Eyercize is how easy it is to use. Check out this video demo where I show you how to turn any web page into a eye training exercise:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2012 09:03:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</guid>
      <description>One of my students says that in medical school they were taught how to explain their clinical observations in a way that made them sound more official. For example, if you see something once, you can say that &#34;in my experience...&#34; The second time you&#39;ve observed the same phenomenon, you can say that &#34;in case after case....&#34; Finally, if you&#39;re seeing something more than two times, you&#39;ve seen it &#34;in a series of cases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching the First &#34;Foundations of Relaxation&#34; Course</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/15/launching-the-first-foundations-of-relaxation-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 16:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/15/launching-the-first-foundations-of-relaxation-course/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m pretty excited about this: Eyes and Visual Training
It&#39;s my new online course and the first in the Foundations of Relaxation Series I wrote about here. As I&#39;ve been developing the course, I keep saying to myself, &#34;I wish everyone who comes to see me for pain relief or to learn tai chi did this first.&#34; In fact, that&#39;s how I developed the whole series. There are a few simple things that don&#39;t take a lot of oversight or feedback from an instructor that everyone can do to move better (meaning more gracefully and in less pain).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>