<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>movement-practice on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/categories/movement-practice/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in movement-practice on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/movement-practice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Intrinsic Practice Motivation</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 09:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</guid>
      <description>For the last couple of years, I&#39;ve been teaching regular workshops in Farmington, Maine. When I went up again last week, I had a fascinating conversation with one of the students. She was telling me how the core group had been coming along and that other people have come in and out of practicing with them. She said, &#34;you know, it&#39;s not really for everyone.&#34;
Now, I don&#39;t know if that jumps out at you as a significant statement, but as a Tai Chi teacher, it&#39;s something I&#39;ve been thinking about for years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 09:53:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>I get the question all the time, or at least it&#39;s always implied, &#34;When am I going to get it?&#34; Or, &#34;how do I know if I&#39;m getting good at this?&#34;
Now, let&#39;s unpack a little bit of what&#39;s behind this question and then I want to share some different ways that I think you can answer this question on your own, without even asking your teacher.
Practice Goals
I&#39;m on a training trip this weekend out in New Mexico with Robert Tangora.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Should I Practice Today?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/22/what-should-i-practice-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 09:25:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/22/what-should-i-practice-today/</guid>
      <description>If you&#39;ve learned many different meditation, qigong, breathing, and movement practices over the years, you may be faced with the problem of trying to decide what to practice each day.
In this episode of Qigong Radio, I&#39;ll show you a framework for thinking about your different modes of practice and show you the single most important goal of an energy arts practice, regardless of the mode or specific techniques.
Specifically, we&#39;ll look at:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Following Instructions</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/16/following-instructions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2012 07:32:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/16/following-instructions/</guid>
      <description>One thing that&#39;s been on my mind since Bruce was here teaching a Push Hands Intensive is what it means to follow instructions in your training. He basically laid out a year or longer curriculum during a week. What do you come away with? What should you practice? How do you reconcile &#34;downloading&#34; a whole curriculum at once vs. really upacking it and learning to use it over the next year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Difference Between Breathing in Yoga and Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/21/the-difference-between-breathing-in-yoga-and-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/21/the-difference-between-breathing-in-yoga-and-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>As Nate and I were discussing specific breathing challenges in qigong and Tai Chi, he started to explain the way he had learned to work with breathing and movement in his yoga training.
It&#39;s fascinating to compare strategies for working with the mind-body connection across different systems, and while this is by no means a definitive exploration of similarities and differences, I think you&#39;ll see that there are two distinct approaches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arm Swing And The Force Transmission Problem</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 08:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</guid>
      <description>One of your practice goals should be to be able to make sense of other people&#39;s movement patterns. Learning how to watch someone move, and see what&#39;s going on, is going to give you really valuable information that you can then apply to your own practice.
In the following video clip, I demonstrate two different gait patterns, with different arm swings. If you can start to see how the arm swing differs between the two, you&#39;ll start to gain some valuable insight into how to assess and correct your own movement imbalances.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turn the Legs to Turn the Body</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 09:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/</guid>
      <description>When you see a series of exercises, you can either look at what&#39;s common to all of them, or how they are different. In this video, I go through several variations of turning exercises, where I&#39;m using the connection between the legs and the spine to drive body movement.
Most people will look at the arms in each exercise and say, &#34;those are not the same movements&#34; and that&#39;s true, but they would be missing the most important part: how the legs turn the body.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read Faster, Move Better</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</guid>
      <description>Eyercize is a free, web-based reading pacer that turns any text into a speed reading exercise. But, you can do more than just read faster using Eyercize. You can actually improve how you move, if you follow these simple training guidelines.
Part of the reason I&#39;m so excited about Eyercize is how easy it is to use. Check out this video demo where I show you how to turn any web page into a eye training exercise:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Get More Flexible without Adding Stretching to Your Practice </title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/06/how-to-get-more-flexible-without-adding-stretching-to-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/06/how-to-get-more-flexible-without-adding-stretching-to-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>If you&#39;ve been reading this blog for a while, you know I love a challenging practice problem. One of our Inner Form members wrote to me and said, &#34;I need more flexibility, but I don&#39;t have time to add a whole other stretching routine to my current practice. What can I do?&#34;
I have good news if you&#39;ve been mulling over a similar practice problem. It all comes down to how you understand flexibility.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2012 09:03:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</guid>
      <description>One of my students says that in medical school they were taught how to explain their clinical observations in a way that made them sound more official. For example, if you see something once, you can say that &#34;in my experience...&#34; The second time you&#39;ve observed the same phenomenon, you can say that &#34;in case after case....&#34; Finally, if you&#39;re seeing something more than two times, you&#39;ve seen it &#34;in a series of cases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Absolutely Anything in 2012</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 09:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>At this time of year, you hear a lot about New Year&#39;s resolutions.
This year, I was happy to see a lot of people saying &#34;New Year&#39;s resolutions don&#39;t work.&#34; We all know that&#39;s true from personal experience, but these folks were referencing a growing understanding about how learning and skill-building take place. Most of what we now know about how the nervous system works flies in the face of changing through the strength of your willpower alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2011 08:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</guid>
      <description>Frozen shoulder is one of those terms that people accept with resignation and it seems like a plausible explanation...until you start to poke around in your own nervous system.
If you&#39;ve ever been told you have a frozen shoulder, I urge you to look a little bit beyond the (overly) simple mechanical explanation.
Obviously, I&#39;m not diagnosing your shoulder from a YouTube video, but I just want you to ask a few more questions and try these two experiments:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Z Health Exercises for Stiff Joints in the Morning</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2011 08:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</guid>
      <description>In just ten minutes of head-to-toe movement, you can get rid of stiff joints in the morning. What&#39;s the secret? There isn&#39;t one really...you just have to move every single joint. Z Health exercises for joint mobility give you an easy template to use to get this done, though.
Check out this example of head-to-toe joint mobility: 

The metronome-like quality of the music got me. Sorry! You know why I like metronomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Give the Gift of Better Movement</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/07/give-the-gift-of-better-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 08:38:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/07/give-the-gift-of-better-movement/</guid>
      <description>This year, why not persuade your friends and family to be a little healthier and move better?
I know that&#39;s always a tricky area to wade into, so&amp;Acirc; I&#39;ve picked out a few things below that will help anyone become better educated about movement and inspire them to act (or trick them into it, depending on how you look at it!).
Check them out:
The Perfect Shoe
If you ask me how many pairs of Vivo Barefoot shoes I own, I would ask you if you mean for just wearing around or for tai chi or for formal occasions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress Reduction Techniques That Work in 5 Minutes or Less</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</guid>
      <description>Even if you have cultivated a daily practice that takes you into deep relaxation, it&#39;s helpful to have a set of stress reduction techniques &#34;that work in 5 minutes or less.&#34;
You can pull these out during the day when you have a few minutes of downtime. If you are busy and really stressed out, these relaxation techniques can prevent your stress level from going through the roof.
Try them and let me know what you think.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>