<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>movement-practice on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/categories/movement-practice/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in movement-practice on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/categories/movement-practice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Intrinsic Practice Motivation</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 09:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/04/18/discovering-intrinsic-practice-motivation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Marden Hill Road Sunset II; Palermo, Maine by Jody Roberts, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/jroberts72/6003983172/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Marden Hill Road Sunset II; Palermo, Maine&#34; src=&#34;http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6010/6003983172_fc0cfb3308_n.jpg&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For the last couple of years, I&#39;ve been teaching regular workshops in Farmington, Maine. When I went up again last week, I had a fascinating conversation with one of the students. She was telling me how the core group had been coming along and that other people have come in and out of practicing with them. She said, &#34;you know, it&#39;s not really for everyone.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don&#39;t know if that jumps out at you as a significant statement, but as a Tai Chi teacher, it&#39;s &lt;a title=&#34;Brookline Tai Chi has no &#34;Former Students&#34;&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34;&gt;something I&#39;ve been thinking about for years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this one casual statement, she was really saying that her motivation to practice now comes from inside of herself. Along with a small group of dedicated classmates, she gets everything she needs from the practice itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a remarkable attitude. Every day, we get bombarded by messages that tell us to buy something to become something or fit in with other people. To be able to have a practice that lives inside of you, that&#39;s validated by performing it for yourself, and grows because you feed it with energy and time, is really incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, we&#39;re going to talk about how you discover your intrinsic motivation to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are You Making Progress in Your Practice?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 09:53:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/26/are-you-making-progress-in-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/03/20130326-094857.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;20130326-094857.jpg&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-full&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I get the question all the time, or at least it&#39;s always implied, &#34;When am I going to get it?&#34; Or, &#34;how do I know if I&#39;m getting good at this?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let&#39;s unpack a little bit of what&#39;s behind this question and then I want to share some different ways that I think you can answer this question on your own, without even asking your teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice Goals&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m on a training trip this weekend out in New Mexico with &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt;. Robert is teaching to six of us, twice a day, for two hours each session and the only agenda is giving personal feedback. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did I travel across the country for this? Isn&#39;t there enough to work on in my regular weekly practice? What do I hope to get out of it (besides revisiting all my favorite restaurants in Santa Fe)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The open-ended opportunity to get personal feedback was intriguing to me for two reasons: one was that I value Robert&#39;s input and have learned a ton whenever I&#39;ve studied with him. I figured there would be lots more to take in if the week was tailored to my practice needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second reason was the format. By having two shorter classes per day, we&#39;re going to have big chunks of practice time in the afternoon and evening. Being on the other side of the country, with fewer work responsibilities, I knew I could devote some solid practice time to integrating the small chunks of feedback I&#39;d be getting in each session. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this training format is to set up a rapid feedback loop where new input is balanced with integrative practice, twice a day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, it&#39;s hard to feel the loop. You go to class once, maybe twice a week, and you can get swept up in whatever the teacher leads you through. In our busy lives, it&#39;s hard to find time to do additional practice, especially when carving out time to commit to class may have been a challenge in the first place. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of you who read this site are in the reverse situation. You get occasional input from an instructor in person, or did years ago, but now you have to figure out how to upgrade your practice on your own. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, we&#39;re all often left wondering, &#34;how do I know if I&#39;m making progress?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Process vs. Outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people that I talk to come to Tai Chi and qigong for the way it makes them feel. Or I should say, keep coming back to it because of the way it feels. There&#39;s nothing competitive or achievement-oriented about having a daily renewal activity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to weight lifters, triathletes, or your friend who plays in a softball league, you might get left feeling like you&#39;ve got nothing to show for your practice. The benchmarks and fruits of your practice are harder to discern because the endeavor is largely process-driven. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I want to suggest that &#34;process vs. outcome&#34; is a distinction you don&#39;t need to make. Instead, do both: create outcomes to shoot for, then settle into the process and enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learn more when I set small, measurable goals in my practice and furthermore, I feel much more confident answering the question, &#34;am I getting better?&#34; when mini-goals are part of my training routine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Quantity or Quality&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what should you measure? &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/12/17/tai-chi-moving-for-better-balance-with-dr-fuzhong-li/&#34;&gt;Do you hook yourself up to a balance machine&lt;/a&gt;? Measure the number of squats you can do in an hour (hint: fewer is better!)? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applied to qigong and Tai Chi, quantifying starts to get ridiculous pretty quickly...and it&#39;s not the right way to go about it, if your only goal is to reach a certain number. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tracking Quality Over Time&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I wrote an article for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p5x7/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel&#39;s Inner Quest Journal&lt;/a&gt; explaining a tracking process I went through for a hundred days of spinal bowing. I would practice this one technique for 5 minutes a day and then record my experience in a spreadsheet. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My rule was that I wasn&#39;t going to spend a lot of time writing about what happened and I wasn&#39;t going to spend a lot of time reading what I had written. I could only look back every once in a while to look for patterns. I didn&#39;t want the reflection time to outweigh the actual practice time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just the act of recording revealed something surprising: the next day when I started out, I was more aware of what I had done the previous day (since I had verbalized it) and could return to certain themes, more than I would have otherwise. This one little act helped me build more momentum around one practice principle than I had experienced ever before in this timeframe. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting an Outward Goal to Find an Inward State&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the hundred-day spinal practice yielded such interesting results, I was on the lookout for a new way to bring structure to my practice. At Brookline Tai Chi, Don Miller was just beginning a Yiquan standing class and I caught the standing bug again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first class we talked about &#34;gates&#34; or practice thresholds that Yiquan Masters said held new insights and rewards when you passed through them. For standing postures, this was a time marker, 20 minutes, one hour, two hours. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been down that road before with standing qigong, and knocked on the one-hour gate, but never really traveled through it. This time, though, something inside me clicked, and I found deep motivation to start up again. I say this because just standing by the clock can be awful, and not productive at all. Normally, I think you should spend lots of time just standing naturally, and seeing how long it is when you feel like it&#39;s time to quit. That will teach you a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For whatever reason at this point in time, though, building up to longer standing periods just seemed like the thing I needed to do. I&#39;ve gone through periods like this in the past, naturally slowing down until a 5-minute form would take me 30 minutes, for example. I&#39;ve never been back to that and I don&#39;t know how it happened in the first place, but at the time, that&#39;s what my system needed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the standing experiment, the rule I set for myself was to find my natural threshold, then add one minute each day. So far, about 20 days in, this has felt like a good pace. For the first couple of weeks, I finished feeling like I wanted to do more. That&#39;s a good sign that I&#39;m not hitting internal resistance yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all goes well, I should be able to report back about the two-hour gate in the next couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I told Don what I was doing, he said, &#34;well that doesn&#39;t sound very Taoist.&#34; But here&#39;s the thing. Over the years I&#39;ve learned if you only rely on your internal compass, the way the Taoist sages seem to advise, you get fooled into quitting too soon, thinking it&#39;s the natural way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more I believe that you need to set up artificial structures, like my time experiment, to reveal your true limits and fluctuations. If I let my arms down the first time I get tired, I will never realize that adjusting the foot or opening the hip would send a surge of energy that would boost the arms, and I could go on for five more easy minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there a limit on the other side where  you unnaturally force it? Of course. But if you never run little experiments in your practice, you&#39;ll never know the difference. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, before you go off and set up an experiment for yourself, let me be clear, it&#39;s not just pushing through the number that&#39;s important. In fact, it&#39;s not really about pushing yourself at all. Instead, the structure of your practice creates a sort of backdrop for learning. When you return to the same scene each day, you pick up contrast and insight that you would miss otherwise. You set your natural internal fluctuations against the same practice conditions, so that you reveal new facets of the internal changes, not so that you beat the external number. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll try to give examples of different markers I discover along this current path as I go, and now that I&#39;ve told you about it, I guess I better keep moving!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Should I Practice Today?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/22/what-should-i-practice-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 09:25:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/22/what-should-i-practice-today/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve learned many different meditation, qigong, breathing, and movement practices over the years, you may be faced with the problem of trying to decide what to practice each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, I&#39;ll show you a framework for thinking about your different modes of practice and show you the single most important goal of an energy arts practice, regardless of the mode or specific techniques.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3918&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we&#39;ll look at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your spectrum of practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bill Ryan&#39;s helpful rule: your mind moves your chi and your chi moves your body and vice versa.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pros and cons of a sitting breathing practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to use light movement to prime chi flows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The benefits of looking for larger practice patterns.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In this episode, I also recommend that you check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Healing-Whole-Foods-Traditions-Nutrition/dp/1556434715/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1337691768&amp;amp;sr=1-1&#34;&gt;Healing with Whole Foods by Paul Pitchford&lt;/a&gt; if you want to learn more about seasonal practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks to everyone who has supported the Qigong Radio project by making a donation to our equipment upgrade fund. Because of your support, I decided to invest in new equipment, even though we didn&#39;t reach our goal of $1500. If you enjoyed the content, consider making a small donation to help me catch up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form action=&#34;https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr&#34; method=&#34;post&#34;&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;cmd&#34; value=&#34;_s-xclick&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;hidden&#34; name=&#34;hosted_button_id&#34; value=&#34;JM5L8XE2BBXM4&#34; /&gt; &lt;input type=&#34;image&#34; name=&#34;submit&#34; src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/btn/btn_donateCC_LG.gif&#34; alt=&#34;PayPal - The safer, easier way to pay online!&#34; /&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.paypalobjects.com/en_US/i/scr/pixel.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/form&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Following Instructions</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/16/following-instructions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2012 07:32:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/16/following-instructions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Following Instructions&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.staticflickr.com/34/70712598_54046afbdc_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;181&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;One thing that&#39;s been on my mind since &lt;a title=&#34;Push Hands and The Tai Chi Mastery Program&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/&#34;&gt;Bruce was here teaching a Push Hands Intensive&lt;/a&gt; is what it means to follow instructions in your training. He basically laid out a year or longer curriculum during a week. What do you come away with? What should you practice? How do you reconcile &#34;downloading&#34; a whole curriculum at once vs. really upacking it and learning to use it over the next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are interesting problems to have, right?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3812&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I discuss the psychology of following instructions in Episode 4 of Qigong Radio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And don&#39;t miss upcoming episodes, including one with Brookline Tai Chi founder and Energy Arts Senior Instructor Bill Ryan on developing your energetic sensitivity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listen Now:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Difference Between Breathing in Yoga and Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/21/the-difference-between-breathing-in-yoga-and-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/03/21/the-difference-between-breathing-in-yoga-and-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As Nate and I were discussing specific breathing challenges in qigong and Tai Chi, he started to explain the way he had learned to work with breathing and movement in his yoga training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s fascinating to compare strategies for working with the mind-body connection across different systems, and while this is by no means a definitive exploration of similarities and differences, I think you&#39;ll see that there are two distinct approaches.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3647&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/4LqqayxyCB4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/4LqqayxyCB4?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this difference make sense to you? How does it compare to other breathing/meditation/mindfulness practices you&#39;ve explored? Leave a comment and let us know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arm Swing And The Force Transmission Problem</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 08:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/22/arm-swing-and-the-force-transmission-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of your practice goals should be to be able to make sense of other people&#39;s movement patterns. Learning how to watch someone move, and see what&#39;s going on, is going to give you really valuable information that you can then apply to your own practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following video clip, I demonstrate two different gait patterns, with different arm swings. If you can start to see how the arm swing differs between the two, you&#39;ll start to gain some valuable insight into how to assess and correct your own movement imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the clip and then we&#39;ll look at some of the implications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3165&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/o7n2Fy3KGYI?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said at the beginning of the clip, your body adapts to postural changes instantaneously to find the most efficient way of dissipating force that comes into your skeletal structure. This principle was first explained to me by Dr. Eric Cobb, creator of &lt;a href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13500&#34;&gt;Z Health Performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you can see excessive (or deficient) movement in someone&#39;s whole-body pattern, you can pretty reliably draw the conclusion that they need some isolated movement tune-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But, the site of the abnormal movement is not the problem area.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always remember that principle. Was there something wrong with my left arm in the video clip? No, it started swinging more because the right arm was restricted. We changed the right arm and created excessive swing in the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there is a lot more to be said for how you begin to see the connections and determine what needs to move more or less to make the whole body move more efficiently. For now, though, I want you to try a little experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Field Test Your Ability to See&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a title=&#34;APR 092 by chiolachic, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/chio/2432915922/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3091/2432915922_d36e45be2a_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;APR 092&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Brookline Tai Chi is located at mile 23 of the Boston Marathon. People run up and down Beacon Street all day long. As we were working on our ability to see these patterns, a friend and I would sit on the front steps of Brookline Tai Chi to watch runners and walkers come and go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a good spot with lots of running traffic and look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Differences in swing between left and right arms from behind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How high each foot comes up behind the body -- can you see the sole of the shoe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Torso rotation -- is it more pronounced to one side?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excessive head movement in any particular direction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Stirring&#34; with the arm -- making a circle out to the side instead of coming straight back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;Loops&#34; in the lower leg -- circles instead of straight up and down movement&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The challenge with seeing these patterns is that we very easily integrate this information and experience is as &#34;someone running.&#34; We don&#39;t stop to consciously parse the different parts of their movement. For the most part, it&#39;s a good thing that we take in chunks of information, instead of individual pieces. Think of how daunting it would be to have to record each data point and consciously put it together. You&#39;d never make it down the street!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, if you want to really hone your ability to see, correct, and improve movement patterns, you have to train to break the patterns back down again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turn the Legs to Turn the Body</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 09:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/20/turn-the-legs-to-turn-the-body/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you see a series of exercises, you can either look at what&#39;s common to all of them, or how they are different. In this video, I go through several variations of turning exercises, where I&#39;m using the connection between the legs and the spine to drive body movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people will look at the arms in each exercise and say, &#34;those are not the same movements&#34; and that&#39;s true, but they would be missing the most important part: &lt;strong&gt;how the legs turn the body&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3517&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GoqiuidbvGM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GoqiuidbvGM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Same Motor, Different Attachments&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In order to really see what&#39;s going on in this video, you need to think of a motor that can be fitted with different attachments. In our kitchen, for example, we have a mixer that can blend food together, make dough, whisk, grind meat, or cut pasta. The motor is the same in each case, but for every special application, you attach a different tool to the end of the motor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you watch the video above, imagine that I am doing exactly the same thing. The legs and the waist are the motor and the angle of the turn, the arm movements, and the plane that force is expressed along are all the various attachments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[nonmember]Inner Form members, &lt;a title=&#34;Member Login&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/member-login/&#34;&gt;log in&lt;/a&gt; to read the full breakdown of the video and get your practice assignment.[/nonmember]&lt;br /&gt;
[ismember]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Psoas Connection&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The easiest way to start to develop this connection is to understand how the psoas muscles connect the legs to the spine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, these big muscles run from the upper part of your thigh and attach to each side of your spine. They work like a steering mechanism. If you want to rotate the spine to the right, the psoas on the right contracts, pulling your spine that way. To turn left, the right side relaxes and the left side contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the beginning of this mechanism in the first exercise in the video, the Peg Board drill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned the Peg Board drill from Z Health founder Dr. Eric Cobb. The Peg Board concept is that as one heel pushes down, the other rises up, as if it were pushed from below by a peg. So we imagine standing on a &#34;peg board&#34; to do this exercise. The goal is to find the connection from one leg into the spine and through the pelvis to the other leg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next exercises expands on the Peg Board by adding more turning (0:12). Here, I&#39;m letting the pull through the leg turn the hips. You start the Peg Board looking a little like Elvis, but here you try to smooth it out. Think of the alternative. When you see people turn from the shoulders or even the hips, the body is not as smoothly integrated. What we develop from the Peg Board exercise is having a clear, connected, swiveling base of support. The rest of the body can come along for the ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next (0:16), let the pivot go through the legs completely, to bring the hips around through a 180 degree arc. With this full pivot, you begin to perform something that looks very much like foundation training in many Northern Chinese martial arts. The &#34;bow stance&#34; or &#34;gong bu&#34; is a commonly trained posture and now you can see how it is used to develop whole-body turning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, you can see the evolution of the psoas connection into whole-body turning from this simple 4-part progression. Next, we need to look at the arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Planes of Force&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Watch the way the arms move&amp;Acirc;  through the various exercises in the video. You will see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forward force, as in the first punching exercise (0:18)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Horizontal force, as in the bagua cutting exercise (0:36)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vertical force, as in the double teacup exercise (1:26)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combinations of force vectors like Cloud Hands and Rolling the Ball (2:02)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The cool thing about the leg power you develop this way is that you can express opposite force vectors simultaneously or with a slight change in intention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the bagua coiling exercise (1:10) is usually looked at as a drilling out with the fingers. However, if you pay attention to the elbow on the way back in, you can turn it into a pulling exercise instead. A similar thing happens with the teacup exercise. There is a powerful elbow drop hidden in the falling arm, but most people emphasize the hand or wrist coming in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi Cloud Hands is the ultimate test of your ability not to fixate on one particular force vector. The way it is organized, you slip through the four basic energies of Peng, Lu, Ji, and An, doing them in pairs. You have to find a way to clearly express each one, and then effortlessly change to the next. In my view, this is why &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora thinks of Cloud Hands as the ultimate practice integrator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The best way to develop this connection is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to get the hang of the Peg Board drill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the action of the legs in the Peg Board drill take you through bigger and bigger turning ranges until you get to 180 degrees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick one of your favorite exercises that fits this paradigm (standing qigong doesn&#39;t count for this exercise!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale back the exercise so that it doesn&#39;t feel like you are &#34;doing anything&#34; with the arms (very light &lt;a title=&#34;Three Swings from Opening the Energy Gates Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/three-swings-from-opening-the-energy-gates-qigong/&#34;&gt;First Swing &lt;/a&gt;works well here)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slowly work back up into the full shape of the movement, until you are reasonably confident that you are not using your arms to do the motion, but instead the movement of the legs and waist&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[/ismember]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Read Faster, Move Better</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/08/read-faster-move-better/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Eyercize is a free, web-based reading pacer that turns any text into a speed reading exercise. But, you can do more than just read faster using Eyercize. You can actually improve how you move, if you follow these simple training guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3457&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Part of the reason I&#39;m so excited about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eyercize.com&#34;&gt;Eyercize&lt;/a&gt; is how easy it is to use. Check out this video demo where I show you how to turn any web page into a eye training exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/rHKcP476yjY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/rHKcP476yjY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the creators of Eyercize explain on their site, most people probably haven&#39;t trained their reading skills since they first learned to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading faster, using the method that Eyercize is built on, relies on three interdependent skills. Basically, you read in chunks of letters. As your eye moves across the line, it takes a snapshot of a group of letters, which your brain processes, and then you move on to a new chunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading speed is determined by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The size of the chunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How quickly you jump from chunk to chunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much you keep moving forward, without going back to re-read the same chunk again&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eyercize trains you to expand the size of the chunk, move faster to the next chunk, and not go back and re-read the same chunk over again by moving the highlighter along at a set speed.&amp;Acirc;  If you really want to understand the technical details, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eyercize.com/home/tools&#34;&gt;add Eyercize to your bookmarks&lt;/a&gt;, hop over to the Wikipedia page about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eye_movement_in_language_reading&#34;&gt;Eye Movements in Reading&lt;/a&gt;, and read through it in the Eyercize reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Role of the Eyes in Movement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Saccadic movement, the technical term for the eyes moving rapidly side to side, like you do in reading, is one of the main visual skills that your brain uses to get information about your surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are unaware of just how much spatial and positional information we take in, but your body adopts a postural response based on the quality of information your visual system feeds your brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-3477&#34; title=&#34;Postural strain can come from lack of visual stamina&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/02/shutterstock_18400546-300x199.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Lack of visual stamina can lead to postural strain.&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;199&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can think about it as another case of &#34;garbage in, garbage out&#34;, but I prefer the positive statement that if you give your nervous system the best possible information, you get the best performance out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more, I&#39;ve written about &lt;a title=&#34;The Strange Link between Eyes and Movement&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/03/30/the-strange-link-between-eyes-and-movement/&#34;&gt;the link between eyes and movement&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/&#34;&gt;how the eyes influence flexibility&lt;/a&gt; (at 4:00 in the video) , and &lt;a title=&#34;2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/&#34;&gt;how poor eye movement can lead to neck pain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, though, the most important thing to know is that there is actually a bio-feedback test you can use to tell if new information is &#34;good information&#34; or &#34;garbage&#34;. In this case, when we are using a tool like Eyercize, we will use a bio-feedback test to tell when we&#39;ve hit the limit of productive eye work. More isn&#39;t always better. Especially with visual training, you can easily do too much in one sitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one of many bio-feedback tests we use in Z Health to determine if we should keep training or take a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Test Range of Motion Before and After&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Range of motion, using something as simple as a toe-touch, can tell you a lot about the state of your nervous system. You can also use shoulder flexion (like I demonstrate &lt;a title=&#34;What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) or neck rotation, which is especially instructive if you notice one side is a lot tighter than the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all about the little indicators that the fight-or-flight response is kicking in. If your nervous system perceives threat, it reigns in range of motion. Just think of the protective gesture of the &#34;fetal position&#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our premise for this bio-feedback test is that if range of motion increase, and you feel looser and more flexible after performing the reading exercises, you have a green light to continue. As soon as you notice a decrease in your range of motion, stop, rest, and do something to restore the balance, like I recommend below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get your baseline for your reading practice session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand up straight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bend forward and try to touch your toes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice how far you go and which muscles feel tight first&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You&#39;re going to perform exactly the same exercise after you do 1 minute of speed reading with the pacer. Then retest your range of motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Red Light, Green Light&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Did you notice a change before and after 1 minute of speed reading? If not, double your time and try it again. Repeat this process until you notice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any change in range of motion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Postural changes while you read, like slumping in your chair or craning your neck&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you can comfortably do 2-3 minutes of speed reading with no noticeable change in posture or pre- and post-testing, then you are ready to increase the variables in the reader. Those are all the controls along the left side of the Eyercize interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Balance Foveal Work with Peripheral Work&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eyercize trains one of your foveal vision skills. &#34;Foveal&#34; means you are using the retina to focus on something. The opposite skill set is peripheral vision, and you can use peripheral vision work to give yourself a break from too much focusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a really simple peripheral drill you can do right at your desk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring your arms up in front of you and touch your hands together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start wiggling your index finger on each hand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slowly move your arms apart and out to the sides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As your hands move away from each other, keep wiggling your fingers, but look straight ahead -- here&#39;s where you activate your peripheral vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue to track your wiggling fingers using only your peripheral vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can move your hands up and down independently in your peripheral field, but be sure to keep your eyes straight ahead&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a couple of minutes of peripheral work should be a nice balance to intense focus work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you use Eyercize with posture in mind, you&#39;ll see some great results in reading speed and your overall quality of movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Get More Flexible without Adding Stretching to Your Practice </title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/06/how-to-get-more-flexible-without-adding-stretching-to-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/06/how-to-get-more-flexible-without-adding-stretching-to-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve been reading this blog for a while, you know I love a challenging practice problem. One of our Inner Form members wrote to me and said, &#34;I need more flexibility, but I don&#39;t have time to add a whole other stretching routine to my current practice. What can I do?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have good news if you&#39;ve been mulling over a similar practice problem. It all comes down to how you understand flexibility.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3403&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this quick practice video I shot the other morning. You&#39;ll see one way that I blend joint-by-joint mobility, qigong, and Cloud Hands:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/sazLaIUxpbY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/sazLaIUxpbY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Understand the Brakes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Most people think of flexibility as a fixed degree of stretch in your muscles. If you didn&#39;t have a chance to read my recent post on &lt;a title=&#34;What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/&#34;&gt;Frozen Shoulder&lt;/a&gt;, you should go back and check that out. The quick version is that your nervous system will throw the brakes on range of motion any time it perceives a threat to your safety. The problem is not with the particular muscle tissue. You actually have a communication problem going on with the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So you have to find a better way to talk to your nervous system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Z Health, we look at an information hierarchy that governs how your nervous system processes input. The most valuable information comes from the visual system, then your inner ear, and finally from the positional information it gets from where your joints are in space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to assess how your nervous system is integrating these three sources of information and work out the different ways that you are receiving conflicting reports. Confusing information results in the threat level going up and things like range of motion going down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He wrote me asking for a shortcut to flexibility and I&#39;m ready to write a novel about the nervous system. Sorry! Hang in there.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, there is a process you can go through to clear up all the different ways that your nervous system is confused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the flexibility issue specifically, the easiest thing to rule out at first is how all the joints are moving. You&#39;ve heard me say this before, but a head-to-toe scan, mobilizing each and every joint, takes less than 15 minutes, so there&#39;s no reason not to do it. What you&#39;ll discover are &#34;hidden stuck spots&#34; that were impeding range of motion through this whole nervous system confusion process. A joint-by-joint inventory clears them up, your nervous system is able to more smoothly integrate positional information, and as a result it releases the brakes, giving you more range of motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you progress, you work into more complicated positions, test bigger ranges of motion, play with different speeds and expand the range of safe, clean movement your body is comfortable with. In other words, your flexibility increases!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the &#34;morning mobility&#34; video again. &lt;em&gt;What you&#39;re seeing is how I&#39;ve learned to integrate the mobility drills that open me up the most into my warm-ups for Tai Chi practice, without spending tons of time on them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Tutorial on Hip Mobility&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/tutorial-on-hip-mobility/&#34;&gt;In this Inner Form tutorial, I answer Dara&#39;s question about hip flexibility specifically and teach a five-minute mobility practice that he can integrate into his regular Tai Chi practice.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 Subtle Causes of Neck Pain and How to Avoid Them</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2012 09:03:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/02/04/2-subtle-causes-of-neck-pain-and-how-to-avoid-them/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my students says that in medical school they were taught how to explain their clinical observations in a way that made them sound more official. For example, if you see something once, you can say that &#34;in my experience...&#34; The second time you&#39;ve observed the same phenomenon, you can say that &#34;in case after case....&#34; Finally, if you&#39;re seeing something more than two times, you&#39;ve seen it &#34;in a series of cases.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, last week, in case after case of neck-related pain and discomfort, the cause of the pain came down to one simple movement principle: substitution.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2949&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In this video, I explain how the nervous system bridges the gap between what you ask your body to do and performing that task by any means it can. Practically, this can result in the wrong body part moving for one that doesn&#39;t respond to the call of the nervous system, or &#34;substitution.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chronic substitution leads to pain, discomfort, and sets the stage for injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Specific Causes of Neck Pain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the case of neck pain, you&#39;ll often see under-performing eyes or stuck vertebrae force the neck into excess movement:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/KsBX4eHvtTo?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/KsBX4eHvtTo?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to avoid these causes of neck pain:&lt;/strong&gt; Tune up your eyes (&lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;try my free visual training course&lt;/a&gt;) and do a full-body movement inventory on a regular basis (&lt;a title=&#34;Recommended Products&#34; href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/products/&#34;&gt;check out the Z Health R-Phase set&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Absolutely Anything in 2012</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 09:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/04/how-to-learn-absolutely-anything-in-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Chess at Starbucks by radioflyer007, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/radioflyer007/4677003347/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://farm2.staticflickr.com/1304/4677003347_3bcb440632.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chess at Starbucks&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;205&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;At this time of year, you hear a lot about New Year&#39;s resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I was happy to see a lot of people saying &#34;New Year&#39;s resolutions don&#39;t work.&#34; We all know that&#39;s true from personal experience, but these folks were referencing a growing understanding about how learning and skill-building take place. Most of what we now know about how the nervous system works flies in the face of changing through the strength of your willpower alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I urge you to leave that mindset behind in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you should think about any changes, anything you want to learn, as slowing building a skill, with small steps you can practice, building like a snowball, until you&#39;re doing great new things without trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s how that works.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3160&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deliberate Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You often hear people say, &#34;practice makes perfect&#34;, but the reality is a little more complicated. One retort is &#34;practice makes permanent&#34;, which speaks to the way that your nervous system ingrains what you do over and over so that it becomes close to automatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you actually want to learn something new this year, you need get smart about how you build your new skills. The model that captures this the clearest is the deliberate practice model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deliberate practice has four components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need a framework for understanding what to practice -- this is where seeking out guidance from someone who has mastered that skill or taught others to do so is critical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to practice a very specific skill because you need a high degree of focus -- trying to juggle two or three new things at a time won&#39;t work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need immediate feedback on your practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to practice over and over and over again, a lot.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The irony for most of us is that we want to get better at something, so we just go out and do it. It&#39;s like trying to drive somewhere new without a map. You&#39;ll base your decisions, turn-by-turn, on old information about places you&#39;ve been before, which may work pretty well, but clearly won&#39;t get you there with the same directness as having a roadmap to guide you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, step one of any new deliberate practice endeavor that you seek out is to find the right map. Get good guidance, regular feedback, and keep practicing, biting off a little at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other thing you need to worry about, once you have the deliberate practice cycle down, is staying in a healthy &#34;learning zone&#34; as you take on new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recognizing Fight-or-Flight&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A natural part of trying to master any new skill is working beyond your current capacity. The problem is that pushing yourself too far into new territory will be counter-productive. When you exceed your limites, your body initiates the fight-or-flight response and you will no longer engage in productive learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the core Z Health training principles is learning to identify the onset of the stress response in any activity. When you recognize the signs of fight-or-flight, you learn to dial back your training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you may find:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your heart rate speeds up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your breathing gets heavy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your face becomes flushed or pale or alternates between them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your mouth dries up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You move toward the fetal position in subtle ways -- your shoulders hike up, your facial muscles contract, you draw your arms in to protect your body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You stop hearing what&#39;s going on around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You get &#34;tunnel vision&#34; and lose your peripheral field.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you experience these things, or more likely, when someone points out to you that they are happening or you realize it in hindsight, you know you&#39;ve exceeded your capacity to integrate new information in that moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the poise and relaxation that comes through smart, modulated training in this boxing clip. Obviously, boxing can be a brutal sport, but watch the way that this training is structured, to stretch him in different ways, testing his visual skills, playing with his threat level and capacity to integrated movement information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know that the training is done correctly because of how graceful and relaxed he is able to be under this kind of pressure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/2y5jB0uZOrM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/2y5jB0uZOrM?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you work through this process, probably without an army of coaches, camera crews, and fans, you&#39;ll have to look back on the experience and break down how things came together and what you could do to decrease the threat level next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one of my favorite examples of this is a college football coach who plays crowd noise over the loudspeaker during practice sessions. He wants his players to simulate game conditions as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the gradual increase in game-like threat levels as they learn new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the coach introduces a new play in the locker room. He maps it out for the players and they get the idea. Next, they head to the field without pads on and with no defense trying to stop them. Little by little, the coach can introduce new elements that demand concentration, and most importantly from our point of view, integration of new information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can control a situation so that you can selectively increase the amount of information -- visual, auditory, spatial, or physical -- that you need to integrate to master a skill, then you will be able to learn anything in a smooth, steady manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&#39;s it going to be in 2012?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a Frozen Shoulder Anyway?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2011 08:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/26/what-is-a-frozen-shoulder-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frozen shoulder is one of those terms that people accept with resignation and it seems like a plausible explanation...until you start to poke around in your own nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve ever been told you have a frozen shoulder, I urge you to look a little bit beyond the (overly) simple mechanical explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I&#39;m not diagnosing your shoulder from a YouTube video, but I just want you to ask a few more questions and try these two experiments:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2746&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ksccNw4hlsU?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do about a Frozen Shoulder&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you tried the experiments in the video and saw some changes in your shoulder movement, your best bet is to find someone who can assess your movement on a global (whole-body) level. This person, &lt;a title=&#34;Find a Z Health Trainer near you&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=1347&#34;&gt;like a certified Z Health instructor&lt;/a&gt;, for example, will be able to see what body parts are not moving when they should be and which ones are when they shouldn&#39;t be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can alleviate a lot of &#34;frozen&#34; anything in the body with this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&#39;t find an instructor near you, the next best thing is to begin a head-to-toe, full-body mobility program, &lt;strong&gt;focusing on everything else except your frozen shoulder &lt;/strong&gt;(&lt;a title=&#34;Z Health R-Phase Manual and DVD&#34; href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=13446&#34;&gt;the Z Health R-Phase series is the best way to go about this&lt;/a&gt;). The number one rule you need to follow is &#34;never move into pain.&#34; Instead, you will re-educate your body and all its moving pieces, taking the burden off the parts that are already working too hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fairly quickly (like, within a few good training sessions), you will see a change in how you move, 90% of the time. If you keep it up, you&#39;ll prevent further aggravation along these lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few more ideas if you&#39;re looking for other ways to &lt;a title=&#34;Get Moving&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/get-moving/&#34;&gt;GET MOVING&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Z Health Exercises for Stiff Joints in the Morning</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2011 08:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/19/z-health-exercises-for-stiff-joints-in-the-morning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In just ten minutes of head-to-toe movement, you can get rid of stiff joints in the morning. What&#39;s the secret? There isn&#39;t one really...you just have to move every single joint. Z Health exercises for joint mobility give you an easy template to use to get this done, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this example of head-to-toe joint mobility: &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2581&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jCUM8kZ-etY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/jCUM8kZ-etY?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The metronome-like quality of the music got me. Sorry! You know why I like &lt;a title=&#34;Metronome Mobility&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/14/metronome-mobility/&#34;&gt;metronomes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you do a mobility flow like this, with the goal of loosening up your stiff joints, especially first thing in the morning, you want to follow these movement principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Movement Rules for Getting Rid of Stiff Joints in the Morning:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move Every Joint with Precision&lt;/strong&gt;: In the video above, I started with the fingers and worked back toward the spine, then down through the lower body. Each Z Health exercise is designed to target a specific joint. As much as possible, the rest of the body remains still while you isolate an individual joint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build Towards Flow:&amp;Acirc;  &lt;/strong&gt;When you&#39;re mastering the movement of any one joint, you&#39;ll start with straight-line movement, then do circles, and then progress to more flowing figure-8&#39;s. It&#39;s important to work in that order, because the linear movement almost always reveals places where you haven&#39;t developed good conscious control. You never find these places if you skip to figure-8&#39;s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never Move Into Pain: &lt;/strong&gt;Especially if you feel stiff in the morning, you might confuse &#34;waking up&#34; with &#34;being in pain.&#34; Never take yourself into painful ranges of motion. Instead, as you loosen up, your range of motion will increase. It&#39;s not unusual to notice a difference between the first and the third repetition in this regard. Remember: &lt;em&gt;being in pain will not alleviate your stiff joints&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With a morning mobility warm-up like this, you&#39;ll find yourself looser,&amp;Acirc;  more tuned-in to your body and ready to get moving. I often use the discipline of moving each body part head-to-toe as a way to trick myself into practicing more in-depth work when I&#39;m not really in the right frame of mind. Have you ever done that? Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Give the Gift of Better Movement</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/07/give-the-gift-of-better-movement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 08:38:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/07/give-the-gift-of-better-movement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year, why not persuade your friends and family to be a little healthier and move better?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that&#39;s always a tricky area to wade into, so&amp;Acirc;  I&#39;ve picked out a few things below that will help anyone become better educated about movement and inspire them to act (or trick them into it, depending on how you look at it!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check them out:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2625&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Perfect Shoe&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you ask me how many pairs of Vivo Barefoot shoes I own, I would ask you if you mean for just wearing around or for tai chi or for formal occasions.&amp;Acirc;  I&#39;m only kind of kidding...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They send out pretty good deals on these shoes on a regular basis, but this is the first time I&#39;ve seen them throw in cool movement-related bonuses. There are two different deals right now, depending on which style of shoe you buy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance Package&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-full wp-image-2639&#34; title=&#34;performance package&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/12/performance-package.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;290&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A choice of VIVOBAREFOOT &#34;performance&#34; shoe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Born to Run&lt;/span&gt; hard cover by Christopher McDougall ( a book that will make you reconsider whether you want to wear shoes ever again!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Proprioception: Making Sense of Barefoot Running&lt;/span&gt; book by Lee Saxby (same guy who put &lt;a title=&#34;Running Rhythm&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/07/running-rhythm/&#34;&gt;these videos together&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn the Skill DVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free Shipping&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
They say that this package is valued at up to $200, but prices start at $102 with this offer, using the 40% holiday code &lt;strong&gt;VBPP&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How it Works:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a pair of Evo, Evo II, Neo, or Neo Trail to your shopping bag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;Acirc; Add the item &#34;Performance Holiday Package&#34; to your shopping bag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;Acirc; When both items are entered in your cart, enter promo code: &lt;strong&gt;VBPP&lt;/strong&gt; in the shopping bag to receive 40% off your complete holiday package.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Head over to &lt;a href=&#34;http://buy-ethicalfashion.at/DKleiman?CTY=4&amp;amp;CID=5474&#34;&gt;VivoBarefoot.com&lt;/a&gt; now and browse these styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lifestyle Package&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-full wp-image-2640&#34; title=&#34;lifestyle package&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/12/lifestyle-package.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;290&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A choice of VIVOBAREFOOT &#34;lifestyle&#34; shoe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pair of Stuffitts to hold your shoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Proprioception: Making Sense of Barefoot Running&lt;/span&gt; book by Lee Saxby&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn the Skill DVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free Shipping&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This package is valued at up to $210, but prices start at $102 with this offer, using the 40% holiday code &lt;strong&gt;VBLP&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How it Works:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a pair of Aqua, Kali, Mary Jane or Oak to your shopping bag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;Acirc; Add the item &#34;Lifestyle Holiday Package&#34; to your shopping bag&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;Acirc; When both items are entered in your cart, enter promo code: VBLP in the shopping bag to receive 40% off your complete holiday package.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Head over to &lt;a href=&#34;http://buy-ethicalfashion.at/DKleiman?CTY=4&amp;amp;CID=5474&#34;&gt;VivoBarefoot.com&lt;/a&gt; now and browse these styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;For the Keyboard Athlete in your life:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;BID=14857&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; src=&#34;http://www.zhealth.net/banners/KA-Affiliate-Banner-250x250.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Z Health Master Trainer Jen Waak has put together a really interesting &#34;training manual&#34; for the office athlete. Remember when Jen talked about &lt;a title=&#34;Kilimanjaro Made Easy&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/&#34;&gt;what she learned climbing Mount Kilimanjaro&lt;/a&gt;? Well, her big trek was an escape from the cubicle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, she&#39;s pulled that wisdom together in a guide to staying healthy when you&#39;re at your desk all day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I really like about her guide is the actual guide. She formatted it so it can stand upright on your desk for easy reference, like the picture on the left. Pretty clever!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zhealth.net/documents/computer-eyes-bonus.pdf&#34;&gt;Check out the sample chapter on &#34;visual hygiene&#34; or exercises you can do to mitigate eye strain from too much computer use.&lt;/a&gt; (right-click save PDF)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://edge.affiliateshop.com/public/AIDLink?AID=99991&amp;amp;amp;BID=14857&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to head over to the Z Health website where you can purchase the &#34;Keyboard Athlete&#39;s Guide to Pain Relief &amp;amp; Prevention.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Winter Energy Boost&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You know what it feels like to head into the darkest time of the year. It&#39;s fine to slow down and get quieter, but sometimes the winter blues can be a real energy drain. Why not perk up a little with a refreshing, invigorating qigong practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/store/products/featured/dragon-and-tiger-book-dvd-poster-package#a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=932cfb54&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dragon &lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-2660 alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/12/dragon-and-tiger-dvd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dragon and Tiger Medical Qigong&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; height=&#34;250&#34; /&gt;and Tiger Qigong&lt;/a&gt; is a simple set to learn and the whole point of the exercises is to clear away stagnant chi and rev up your circulation. Anyone can learn it and have fun with it at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you make take your practice seriously (if you read this blog regularly, I really hope you don&#39;t take it &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; seriously!), the person in your life who wants a casual introduction to qigong and something easy to practice with will really enjoy this DVD/book set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;border: 0pt none;&#34; src=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/affiliate/scripts/imp.php?a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;a_bid=932cfb54&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cool part about the way the set is packaged is that you&#39;ll get DVDs, a manual, and a wall chart. Energy Arts put a complete set of resources together for your home practice, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instruction on qigong warm-ups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move-by-move how-to on DVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-level practice sets to follow on DVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An illustrated manual with movement details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A wall chart you can use while you practice with key positions for each movement&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve been experimenting with what kind of resources work best for &#34;home study&#34; and I have to say that this combination will get you pretty close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For someone who has never done qigong before, this is a safe, high-quality, and valuable introduction to the practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/affiliate/scripts/imp.php?a_aid=dkleiman&amp;amp;amp;a_bid=932cfb54&#34;&gt;Click here to find out more.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Want More Ideas?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/lm/RGVK0M6WINWPP/dankleiman&#34;&gt;&#34;Movement Practice&#34; recommended reading list&lt;/a&gt; on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stress Reduction Techniques That Work in 5 Minutes or Less</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/05/stress-reduction-techniques-that-work-in-5-minutes-or-less/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you have cultivated a daily practice that takes you into deep relaxation, it&#39;s helpful to have a set of stress reduction techniques &#34;that work in 5 minutes or less.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can pull these out during the day when you have a few minutes of downtime. If you are busy and really stressed out, these relaxation techniques can prevent your stress level from going through the roof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try them and let me know what you think.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2540&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5 Minute Body Scan&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just a few minutes of trying to tune into your body, instead of being stuck in your head, can help reduce the weight of some of the stress you are feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-2355&#34; title=&#34;basic standing qigong posture&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture-141x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; width=&#34;141&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standing posture pictured, here, do a 5-minute downward body scan, starting at the top of the head and working your way down, feeling height-by-height until you reach your feet.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First, set your posture:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;place your feet hip-width apart, so your joints are aligned &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll feel the weight balanced evenly in each foot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lengthen the back of your neck, so the chin drops slightly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax your shoulders, as if the arms were slipping off the rib cage, to the left and right, not slouched forward or pulled back&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Next, settle in:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your breathing go smooth, so the turn-over from inhale to exhale feels natural and not forced&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Begin to scan:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bring your feeling awareness up to the crown of your head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;once you feel like you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve gathered your awareness to a single point, let your mind spread out through the crown of the head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;give in to gravity and let your mind drop down the body, height-by-height, feeling front, sides, and back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;let your mind rest lightly on any sensations you feel as you scan, checking in, without trying to do anything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work downward until you can feel your feet settle into the floor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more guidance on practicing this technique, check out &lt;a title=&#34;Settling in with Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/09/19/settling-in-with-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;this article on Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt; (with a free guided-practice mp3 download).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Metronome Mobility&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This exercise is great for coordination and control and it&#39;s just distracting enough to let your nervous system reset its stress level by the time you are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s use this Z Health shoulder circle as an example for the metronome exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowNetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashVars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allownetworking&#34; value=&#34;all&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed id=&#34;viddler_Trainerfly_125&#34; width=&#34;437&#34; height=&#34;287&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;//www.viddler.com/player/ca402b88/&#34; allowScriptAccess=&#34;always&#34; allowNetworking=&#34;all&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; flashVars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; allownetworking=&#34;all&#34; flashvars=&#34;f=1&amp;amp;openURL=62949995&amp;amp;autoplay=f&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;nologo=0&amp;amp;hd=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you feel comfortable performing the basic shoulder circle as in the video above, you&#39;ll need to set a metronome to 60 beats per minute. Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a baseline for one repetition at your &#34;normal&#34; speed. How many beats?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, perform a circle at half your normal speed, or 2x as many beats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat this process, slowing down each time until the movement gets too choppy to be a smooth circle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now repeat the process getting faster each time instead of slower&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you keep the rest of the body &#34;quiet&#34; -- you don&#39;t get any points for flailing around!&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating this process for hip circles, ankle circles, or even finger/wrist/hand circles will work too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of metronome mobility as a stress reduction technique is to draw your mind and away from the mental and emotional pressures that are causing stress in the first place. Moving your body at different speeds provides novelty for your nervous system, which helps achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tai Chi Short Form&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/11/Brush-Knee-200x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Brush Knee&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2539&#34; /&gt;When you do 5 minutes of tai chi, you have to change how you are practicing. You need to shift out of your normal &#34;training&#34; mindset, where you focus on little details, or work a principle over and over again until it clicks. That kind of deep practice mindset is great for 30 minutes or an hour of practice or more, but it&#39;s not going to do the trick in 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a 5 minute practice for stress reduction, you need to focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moving smoothly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making large, circular shapes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feeling the space around you, in your etheric field, not deep inside your body&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point, about putting your mind into your etheric field, might sound a little strange. What you are trying to do is clear the energetic layer around your body. Think of it as where you interface with the world. If you can sweep everything clean here, then the stress doesn&#39;t have the chance to soak into your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Got More Stress Reduction Techniques?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The thing that all these techniques have in common is that they are designed to recharge your nervous system through physical and energetic circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you accomplish this same goal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share your stress reduction techniques in the comments below.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>