<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>rooting on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/rooting/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in rooting on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/rooting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Tai Chi Rooting, Sinking, and More in Chicago</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/11/tai-chi-rooting-sinking-and-more-in-chicago/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 16:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/10/11/tai-chi-rooting-sinking-and-more-in-chicago/</guid>
      <description>Inspiration for Rooting and Lengthening in Chicago
On November 9, I&#39;ll be teaching a seminar for my friend Chris Cinnamon at Enso Tai Chi (registration details here).
This year we&#39;ll continue the &#34;Put More Chi in Your Tai Chi&#34; theme that we started last year by focusing on Tai Chi Rooting, Sinking Chi, Dissolving, and more.
The goal is to give everyone a clear sense of how nourishing it can be to find your root and feed it through solo exercises and interactive partner practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Inner Form of Balance</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 09:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/08/16/finding-the-inner-form-of-balance/</guid>
      <description>When my first Tai Chi teacher, Bruce Frantzis, came back to the US forty years ago to spread the Tai Chi he learned in China, he found out that many basic Tai Chi concepts were not being taught, either because of communications issues or lack of knowledge. Only a fraction of the vast potential of the art was being shared. Bruce set out to teach the Inner Form of Tai Chi and that&#39;s what I have studied for the last 15 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Course: Introduction to Rooting and Stability</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2013 07:36:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/08/02/new-course-introduction-to-rooting-and-stability/</guid>
      <description>If you listed to the recent Qigong Radio episode on Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Balance, you probably want more insight into how to put Tai Chi balance training to work in your practice.
Now you can start Tai Chi balance training with our new eBook, &#34;An Introduction to Rooting and Stability,&#34; where you will take the Tai Chi Way to re-gaining, one of life&#39;s simplest yet most essential treasures--the gift of balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Connection Between Rooting and Strength in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/26/the-connection-between-rooting-and-strength-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 08:42:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/07/26/the-connection-between-rooting-and-strength-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>In a recent post, we looked at 5 Ways to Build Strong Legs. When I posted the video to Youtube, someone replied:
I think nowadays there is a great misunderstanding of internal martial arts goals and methodology. The great issue is not to become strong but to become very weak!
Now, I think the commenter is kind of right, but misses a critical point, by simply reducing Tai Chi to the art of getting weaker and weaker.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Becoming a Giant Rooted Spring in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/14/becoming-a-giant-rooted-spring-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 09:22:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2012/05/14/becoming-a-giant-rooted-spring-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>When you relax into the turning of the waist and feel how it connects to the legs, you begin a process of rooting while moving that creates a dynamic and springy stability. Kind of a paradox, right?
You feel like a giant spring, anchored to the floor even though you&#39;re moving around, that is constantly being wound up and then released.
The key to cultivating this connection is how you relax through your turning, so let&#39;s start off by getting clear on what we mean when we say relaxation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>