<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>traditional-chinese-medicine on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/traditional-chinese-medicine/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in traditional-chinese-medicine on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/traditional-chinese-medicine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing Qigong Breathing Exercises -- Mp3</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 08:38:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/06/27/standing-qigong-breathing-exercises-mp3/</guid>
      <description>The biggest question people ask me about standing qigong, especially when they hear about the 2-hour project, is &#34;what do you do, just stand there?&#34;
There is actually a really delicate balance between &#34;doing&#34; and &#34;feeling&#34; when you stand. You learn lots of different techniques, like breathing, sinking, dissolving, and pulsing, but how you apply them internally when you are holding a static posture is a tricky topic.
If you rev your engine too much -- activating strong diaphragmatic breathing the entire time, for example -- then you miss the potential stillness in the posture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 11:14:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>In his new book, the Harvard Medical School Guide to Tai Chi, Dr. Peter Wayne lays out the &#34;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; to help us understand the interface between traditional Tai Chi practice and the Western biomedical paradigm.
As the Research Director of the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, jointly based at Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, and the founder of the Tree of Life Tai Chi Center, Peter blends more than three decades of teaching experience with ongoing inquiry into what makes Tai Chi an effective medical intervention.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>