<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>productivity on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/productivity/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in productivity on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Kilimanjaro Made Easy</title>
      <link>/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 10:05:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-2151&#34; title=&#34;Jen on Kilimanjaro&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2011/09/P1010499-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;Z-Health Master Trainer Jen Waak is a self-described &#34;recovering management consultant&#34;. These days, she helps other &#34;Keyboard Athletes&#34; improve and maintain their bodies and stay healthy even when they&#39;re stuck behind a desk all day. What surprised me about reading Jen&#39;s advice on &#34;what you should do at your desk&#34;, was that it sounded a lot like what she did last year to get ready for a climb up Mount Kilimanjaro.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1999&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here&#39;s what Jen had to say about her prep and training:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It was a year ago today that I left to climb Kilimanjaro. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m not a climber, I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t camp, and I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t like the cold. So why I thought this was a good idea I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll never know. I just knew it was something I needed to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I got over the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what have I done?&#34; stage, it was time to start figuring out what it would take to summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I started researching the trip, and here is what I learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;40% of climbers don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t make the summit, and the vast majority of the succumb to hypoxia (altitude sickness) since a summit of 19,340 feet means there is about half of the oxygen at the summit than there is at sea level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was going to be traveling ~60 very hilly miles on foot over 9 days. No one day was going to be the gotcha &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; instead it was going to be the accumulated miles that would wear down my body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being comfortable in your gear is critically important since what you have with you is, well, what you have with you. And there&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s nothing like getting blisters and only 59 more miles to go.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In a situation like this, it would be really easy to get freaked out and not know where to start. But, using a framework I call the Energy Bank, I was able to fairly easily come up with a extremely doable training plan that made summiting downright easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Energy Bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Energy Bank is this idea that we all have a finite amount of energy to get through the day, and everything we do during the day &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; everything &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; either adds to or depletes our bank balance: the lighting in the room, your breathing patterns, the horrible morning commute, your uncomfortable desk chair, and that grande burrito you had for lunch. It all has an impact. And just like a bank balance the higher the average balance, the larger the margin of error before going bankrupt. As you can imagine, a large margin of error will serve someone well when attempting one of the Seven Summits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my goal in preparing for Kilimanjaro was to get my Energy Bank Balance high enough so that the trip wouldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t run the balance down to zero &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; focusing specifically on what I would encounter on the trip that would be more likely to result in large withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training for the Climb&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Breathing:&lt;/strong&gt; I knew this was already a weak link for me - and given that it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s also the downfall of most climbers, this became my #1 priority. My first goal was to fix my breathing patterns at sea level during everyday activities. Once I had that mastered, I went on to practicing my breathing while in oxygen debt (as ultimately that was what I would encounter on Kilimanjaro). Since I live at sea level, I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t truly replicate the conditions on Kilimanjaro, but instead would sprint or run stairs and focus on my breathing during and after those activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision:&lt;/strong&gt; Another one of my weak links, I spent a great deal of time working on my visual skills. My depth perception isn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t great, which translates into me being tentative going down stairs. Since I had to travel 60 miles over hilly terrain, not being comfortable going up and down was going to be a BIG problem. So, I incorporated some basic convergence drills into my training so my eyes could re-learn to focus and my brain would re-learn depth perception. Like my breathing, first I worked on this during everyday activities, and then I moved on to working it into my running stairs, long hikes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Endurance:&lt;/strong&gt; Going and going over 9 days on rough terrain was something I didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have any experience in. Using the Energy Bank concept, I realized that if my body was already somewhat adapted to that it would be a lot easier. But, with a hectic schedule and living in the city, I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t exactly take off for 9 days to climb in the Cascades. Instead, I got the idea that if fatigued my legs the night before a long hike with either a run or stair session, that I would begin the adaptation process of going long distances on tired legs. So, I would either do a long stair session or a run one night and then the next morning go and hike 10+ miles with a 3,000 foot elevation gain (since that would most replicate the conditions I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d find on Kilimanjaro). I got in probably 3 or 4 of these back-to-back training sessions prior to Kilimanjaro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gear:&lt;/strong&gt; Remember that part where I said I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t climb or camp? Yeah, that meant that I had a buy and test a TON of gear for the trip. In the weeks leading up to the climb my week would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on a hike, discover I didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t have the right gear (either through blisters, sweating sunscreen into my eyes, or dealing with lots of bugs. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d come home and take notes on what worked and what didn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to REI and pick up what I was missing (and just cover my eyes while signing the credit card receipt)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on another hike and re-assess. Lather, rinse, repeat until I knew I had what I needed.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overkill? Maybe. But I had no blisters, no chafing, and at no point did I say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I wish I would have brought&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;Acirc;  Everything got tested on at least one 10+ mile hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recovery:&lt;/strong&gt; Early on in my physical training I got a bit ambitious and decided to run 4 miles down a mountain. That turned out to be one of the less bright things I could have done, as I couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t go up and down stairs for several days after that. But it also highlighted something I hadn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t considered &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; that I could get sore. A phone call to fellow Master Trainer and endurance athlete Shannon Mauck revealed the world of recovery drinks to me. Yet another thing for me to test &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I needed to find something that I both liked the taste of and that would agree with my system. (Turns out I really like Accelerade.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did it Work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d have to give the entire experiment an unqualified, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;hell, yeah.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;Acirc;  My training wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t extreme &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I did 6 long hikes and then a couple of hours of running, sprinting, and stairs per week. I worked on my breathing and vision for a few minutes a day, and made a point of incorporating that practice while on my long hikes. And the entire trip up the mountain was a piece of cake for me &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;Acirc; I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d get into camp each night with extra energy to burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The biggest surprise:&lt;/strong&gt; The mental shift in who I am. I grew up a really sick little kid, and had never considered myself an athlete. And now I had accomplished that thousands of people cannot each year. I had to redefine who I am, and now think of myself as an athlete. Because everything is a skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you liked the way she managed her mountain climbing training, you&#39;ll definitely be interested in her insight into bringing more energy into your daily life: &lt;a href=&#34;http://keyboardathletes.com/yourenergybank/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Increase Your Energy Bank Balance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pros and Cons of Automation</title>
      <link>/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 09:32:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Pro: My Car Broke Down and I Was Actually Happy about It&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I guess I need to explain that a little more. I wasn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; happy that it broke down. I was on the way to Maine to teach the &lt;a href=&#34;/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/&#34;&gt;tai chi group in Farmington&lt;/a&gt;, so that sucked. And it was the clutch the completely died, so I knew it was going to be a few dollars to repair. But that was actually part of the silver lining. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-661&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;See, a couple of years ago, I read about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iwillteachyoutoberich.com/blog/tip-6-use-gas-prices-to-become-your-own-hedge-fund/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ramit Sethi&#39;s strategy for hedging fuel costs&lt;/a&gt;. The theory goes, if you are paying for something that goes up and down over the course of a year, you should find a way to even out the costs. This makes sense from a paycheck point of view, right? You take home the same amount of money each week, so you&#39;ll be in more predictable shape if your expenses work the same way. I adapted that strategy to create a car savings account. Looking back we realized we spent roughly the same amount of money on car-related expenses year to year, but they almost always came in spikes when something went wrong. To smooth out the spikes, I took a monthly average of those annual expenses and started putting it away automatically into a savings account each month. Now, when something breaks down, the money is already sitting there and I don&#39;t have to sweat a disruptive spike in our monthly expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dog has his own account too, for &#34;random&#34; vet visits that actually happen on a pretty predictable basis. And I guess that&#39;s the bigger lesson here. Looking back year over year, you start to see some clear patterns for stuff like this, even though the clutch dying or the dog eating something awful seems like a random occurrence. So, if you automate savings around these &#34;random predictable&#34; expenses, you save yourself a huge headache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Con: I Want Automation Now&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I get the &#34;automation itch&#34; whenever I&#39;m starting a new project. The &#34;automation itch&#34; is the desire to put a system in place, which is ultimately a good thing, but it usually strikes prematurely. Getting the itch can be a major trap and I&#39;ve slowly learned to recognize that it usually takes more time to set up an automated system early in a project than it takes to execute something manually. The best advice I&#39;ve ever gotten here is &#34;do it manually until you don&#39;t have enough hours in the day.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went through this at Brookline Tai Chi with an online registration system for classes. In summer 2009, we added online registration and probably 1/3 of current students adopted it right away. What was striking was that close to 80% of new students took to the system. Those statistics are interesting, but probably more appropriate for a post about changing systems in a business....another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flash forward to last week. This session, we got back to back cases of students who couldn&#39;t register online because of their unique situations. That means we need to rebuild the system to fit their situation, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wrong. That was two cases out of how many? Let&#39;s say 200. 1% of registrations. Do you think we have time to do 1% by hand? Especially if you consider that doing 1% of registrations this way takes 10 minutes of admin time, compared to several hours of developer time to make the change, it&#39;s a no-brainer. Of course, there&#39;s one other important factor: systems changes always have to put the user experience front and center. &lt;strong&gt;It&#39;s never a good idea to argue to your customer that they should interact with your business a certain way because it&#39;s easier for some back-end reason&lt;/strong&gt;. In this case though, to the students involved it looked like we were making a special exception for them, which they appreciated. So it worked out all around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a year ago I would have panicked a little more about these two cases. Or I would have thought about how to tinker with the system first. This time though, my first thought was &#34;2 out of how many?&#34; and my second thought was how to create the best manual solution. Beware the automation itch!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning the Wheel</title>
      <link>/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2010 08:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Claude Hopkins, in &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Scientific Advertising&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Rapid stream ran by the writer&#39;s boyhood home. The stream turned a wooden wheel and the wheel ran a mill. Under that primitive method, all but a fraction of the streams&#39; potentiality went to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then someone applied scientific methods to that stream -- put in a turbine and dynamos. Now, with no more water, no more power, it runs a large manufacturing plant.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-470 alignleft&#34; title=&#34;falls&#34; src=&#34;/uploads/2010/12/4121005703_2898edb080_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt; I love the image of harnessing more power from natural resources through better systems. Obviously, we&#39;re still taking about making a small business really churn, not powering a city from a hydro-electric plant, but the lesson is clear. If you&#39;re not using good systems in your small business, you&#39;re wasting potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&#39;d like to have it both ways, because the other part of the image that is so striking to me is the miller with the old wooden wheel. Every movement education professional that I know is really a craftsperson at heart. I just know there&#39;s a balance, though, between your craft and your business supporting a lifestyle you&#39;d like to live. That&#39;s what we&#39;re striving to find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/d-kav/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DaveKav&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make the Most of Phase-Based Activities</title>
      <link>/2010/12/13/make-the-most-of-phase-based-activities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 13:29:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/13/make-the-most-of-phase-based-activities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out this talk from 37Signals co-founder Jason Fried at TEDx Midwest, specifically at 5:13 when he starts comparing sleep and work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/5XD2kNopsUs?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/5XD2kNopsUs?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It got me thinking about other &#34;phase-based&#34; activities, like Tai Chi or Qigong practice. Most productive practice happens when you can allow yourself to move through several stages of settling in and keep a continuous practice thread going for an hour or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last 6 years of running 3 hour-long classes back-to-back-to-back, multiple times per week, I&#39;ve gotten a pretty good feel for these phases. Now, not only do I feel different phases whenever I do my own practice, but because of all the class teaching, I have a feel for the same thing at a group level. Pretty cool benefit of 3,000+ hours of teaching!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you understand your own practice (or any creative endeavor) better if you use the phase model?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>