<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>productivity on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/tags/productivity/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in productivity on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Kilimanjaro Made Easy</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 10:05:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/09/15/kilimanjaro-made-easy/</guid>
      <description>Z-Health Master Trainer Jen Waak is a self-described &#34;recovering management consultant&#34;. These days, she helps other &#34;Keyboard Athletes&#34; improve and maintain their bodies and stay healthy even when they&#39;re stuck behind a desk all day. What surprised me about reading Jen&#39;s advice on &#34;what you should do at your desk&#34;, was that it sounded a lot like what she did last year to get ready for a climb up Mount Kilimanjaro.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pros and Cons of Automation</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 09:32:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2011/03/01/the-pros-and-cons-of-automation/</guid>
      <description>Pro: My Car Broke Down and I Was Actually Happy about It
I guess I need to explain that a little more. I wasn&#39;t really happy that it broke down. I was on the way to Maine to teach the tai chi group in Farmington, so that sucked. And it was the clutch the completely died, so I knew it was going to be a few dollars to repair. But that was actually part of the silver lining.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning the Wheel</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2010 08:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/14/turning-the-wheel/</guid>
      <description>Claude Hopkins, in Scientific Advertising:
A Rapid stream ran by the writer&#39;s boyhood home. The stream turned a wooden wheel and the wheel ran a mill. Under that primitive method, all but a fraction of the streams&#39; potentiality went to waste.
Then someone applied scientific methods to that stream -- put in a turbine and dynamos. Now, with no more water, no more power, it runs a large manufacturing plant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make the Most of Phase-Based Activities</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/13/make-the-most-of-phase-based-activities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 13:29:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/2010/12/13/make-the-most-of-phase-based-activities/</guid>
      <description>Check out this talk from 37Signals co-founder Jason Fried at TEDx Midwest, specifically at 5:13 when he starts comparing sleep and work:

It got me thinking about other &#34;phase-based&#34; activities, like Tai Chi or Qigong practice. Most productive practice happens when you can allow yourself to move through several stages of settling in and keep a continuous practice thread going for an hour or more.
Over the last 6 years of running 3 hour-long classes back-to-back-to-back, multiple times per week, I&#39;ve gotten a pretty good feel for these phases.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>