<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>state-of-the-art on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/state-of-the-art/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in state-of-the-art on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/state-of-the-art/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Yin and Yang of Learning and Teaching the Internal Arts</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/07/the-yin-and-yang-of-learning-and-teaching-the-internal-arts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2012 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/07/the-yin-and-yang-of-learning-and-teaching-the-internal-arts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a guest post from my friend and fellow instructor, Paul Cavel. I asked Paul to talk a little bit about his experience teaching all over Europe and what he&#39;s learned after nearly 20 years doing it. There are some great insights here about the internal energy arts that you can apply to your own practice, whether you teach or not. Take note when he talks about practice mindset!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3549&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1537&#34; title=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been traveling around Europe teaching internal arts in England, France, Germany and Greece since 1995, as well as training with my teacher almost every year in the United States since 1994. Through these experiences, I&#39;ve had the opportunity to meet people of many different backgrounds and observe how cultural influences can give them unique perspectives on most any subject, including their neigong training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, more than any cultural differences, I see that the real challenges come from the Western mindset being so radically different to the Eastern approach. I know for me, as a Westerner learning ancient Eastern arts, the initial hurdle was to figure out the methodology underlying the great content I was training, so I could see the bigger picture--the proverbial light at the end of the tunnel. There are 16 neigong, each with many, many layers of complexity, and dozens of forms to learn in any one system, so understanding how each can be integrated into the whole within the linear Western model for learning can be a bit tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students who achieve real and sustainable results from their practice are those who approach their training with patience, dedication and consistency. Perhaps most importantly, they have the willingness to work towards balance in all aspects of their being, rooting out weaknesses rather than only playing to their strengths--tenants consistent with an Eastern learning strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;East Meets West&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some people approach their practice as though they have &#34;been there, done that,&#34; but from an Eastern perspective, that would be completely missing the point. Instead, it&#39;s about the depth and range of your skill set and how you can apply it in every conceivable way--not just in your practice, but in life. The students who catch onto this style will, over time, automatically weave in mechanics that create flowing forms and circulate blood and chi more profoundly. These are the factors that influence health and well-being, and give the most experienced practitioners the ability to achieve seemingly superhuman results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find a tai chi class in almost every major city across the Western world, but few schools teach the deep internal content that underlies and powers up these forms as originally propagated in the East. Many schools have resorted to a linear teaching style to suit the average Westerner, but the Eastern approach has always been a circular progression: that is you learn a technique and practise it for awhile, developing your skill to the extent you can over several weeks to months. When you reach a plateau and your practice seems to stop evolving, you move on to other techniques, integrating everything you&#39;ve learned within your forms (qigong sets, tai chi styles or bagua palm changes). Later, you return to the original technique, once again singling out that thread and further refining it. Although, upon revisiting the technique, your increased awareness--in body, mind and chi--contributes to an upgrade in your overall understanding and execution of the technique. This circular learning process creates a multiplying, self-sustaining positive feedback loop in your practice and the results you can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Structure-Flow Continuum&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Most students approach their practice from one of two ends of the spectrum: either from the perspective of flow or structure. That is there are those who gravitate towards the integrity of the movement form (i.e. successful execution of component pieces that combine to create a physical form) and others who focus on the flow, or the overall quality of motion within any given form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the point of view of teaching the internal arts, it is helpful to know where a student&#39;s talent lies--either in flow or structure. Initially, using their natural ability, you can focus on that stream of information to help them gain some momentum. Once they gain some skill in that which comes easier for them, then a good teacher will use this momentum to redress the balance by focusing on exercises that will develop the opposite end of the continuum. This approach allows students to see the bigger picture with their talent being the driver of their success. As anyone who trains with an emphasis on internal power development knows, it is the balance between form and flow that is at the crux of all matters relating to how much benefit any one person will get from their practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life as a Traveling Teacher&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Teaching in different cultures for nearly two decades tuned me into the fact that, as a teacher, I cannot be attached to one style or method of presenting material as each culture, city, class, group or individual will have a slightly unique disposition. Although any given culture might be predisposed to start from a particular perspective, the magic of the internal arts is in the details and how they seamlessly integrate with all others. So there really is no starting line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circular progression of learning is about building up and breaking down component pieces in endless weaves and patterns, essentially looking at every possible angle to create a well-integrated, balanced form. This kind of assimilation is what allows students to overcome obstacles and achieve their goals, regardless of where they begin. From the perspective of teaching, I&#39;ve not found anything more rewarding than helping students come to this realization and take on a long-term outlook towards their training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1529&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/strong&gt; is a certified sports massage therapist, personal trainer and senior instructor of internal arts and Taoist meditation master Bruce Frantzis. Since 1987, Paul has studied the Energy Arts System in-depth, including qigong, tai chi, bagua zhang, Longevity Breathing therapy, qigong tui na energy healing and meditation. In 1995, with the encouragement of his teacher, he began offering an integrated health, fitness and stress-management solution to exercise and strengthen the body while releasing blockages -- in mind-body-energy -- that help people realize their true human potential. Find Paul blogging at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/&#34;&gt;www.CircleWalking.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Dilemma: What Do My Students Expect?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/29/teaching-dilemma-what-do-my-students-expect/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Feb 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/02/29/teaching-dilemma-what-do-my-students-expect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/groups/210896728949290/&#34;&gt;Insight Taiji Facebook group&lt;/a&gt;, we got into a fascinating discussion about the challenges of teaching and the different kinds of student expectations that come across as teachers. As much as this was framed as a teacher&#39;s dilemma, I felt that I came away with some lessons about how I set my own expectations as a student as well.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3535&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthony Court has been studying systems of health, healing, meditation and self-defense for over 41 years. He has taught and given workshops in Britain and Southern Ireland, and holds regular classes in Wales. Anthony started the discussion with this reflection:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s been on my mind over the last few years, and that has been the way that many new comers are going straight into more advanced forms and practices. I noticed this trend starting in the early nineties. I know I have been at these &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;Internal Arts&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; for quite some time now, but when I first started my Taiji and Qigong training with Erle (after six years with other teachers) including Professor Chee Soo (who&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s introduction to energy work, has always had such a profound effect on my practice), we practiced Yang Chen-fu for about six years, and only then started learning the Yang Lu-chan (in the old W.T.B.A. syllabus it was only commenced after gaining 3rd degree black belt level).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years people have dropped into my classes, which normally consist of one hour of Qigong followed by one hour of form (the emphasis is different in the self-defence classes) recently one student in his twenties said at the commencement of the Yang Chen-fu form&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar; &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Oh! I don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t do that form, I only do the advanced form.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; When I asked how many years he had been training he said &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Three&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. I then asked him to stand in &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;ward off left&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; posture and was able to push him off balance with one finger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not an isolated cases, people are coming to class, trying to do very small movements, expressing no yin or yang hand moments, and wiggling (for want of a better description) around a great deal. As for being able to defend them selves, forget it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that I have stated here is simply what I have witnessed over the last few years. It is not meant to be a reflection on any teacher, club or school or association. I simply think that basic training is somehow getting bypassed. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s the same with &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;push hands&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; and other practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 34 years of training, 3 years in the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;external&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; systems, and 31 in the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;Internal&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; my approach has changed considerably. To me now, as the French say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Less is more.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; The only forms practiced in my classes these days are Yang Chen-fu, Small San-sau and Taiji Sword and other weapons. All the focus is on the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;correct&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; feeling, and understanding of movements, understanding how to connect the tendons, and the connective tissue for the development of power and speed etc. How does everyone feel about the above? I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d be very interested in your comments and observations. Or is it just me?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Everything that Anthony was describing sounded familiar. I tend to see this mentality play out in a slightly different way, though. So I wrote back:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I know what you mean and I think it&#39;s part of a bigger cultural issue, maybe in the West in general, but definitely here in the States. The phrase that sums it up nicely for me is the &#34;20 year overnight success story.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or as I read someone describe it lately, &#34;other people only see your highlight reel.&#34; Meaning, they don&#39;t see all the day-to-day hard work that goes into practice, only the fruits of long practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, they see the results and think &#34;I want that&#34; but don&#39;t realize all the small steps that go into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only good news that I can see is in &#34;deliberate practice&#34; models of learning, from authors like Geoff Colvin and Malcolm Gladwell, where slow, incremental progress is being valued over flashy end results. I hope this kind of thinking continues and spreads in our culture!&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Rodney Owen, who organizes this group, also weighed in. &amp;Acirc; Rodney &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intaiji.com&#34;&gt;teaches in High Point, North Carolina&lt;/a&gt;, and writes &lt;a href=&#34;http://nagualtime.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;a blog on martial arts and mindfulness&lt;/a&gt;. He said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a different problem with new students. Most of my new students have an idea of Taiji that is common, but not what I teach. Often they expect some new age floating yoga, or a class on nothing but some soft slow form--only. I teach Taiji as a complete martial art and form is only a small part of the whole picture. I teach Chen style, but my approach is probably similar to yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see three distinct areas of Training that make up what I call proper Taiji: Qigong (including sitting meditation); Taiji form(s); and partner exercises. I don&#39;t have enough students to have separate beginner and advanced classes, but I give everyone an outline or curriculum to follow. I ask new students to only be concerned with sitting meditation, standing Qigong, one or two simple dynamic Qigongs, and the Four Energies Form (Peng, Lu, Gi, An) for the first three months or so. I do not place a lot of emphasis on learning form, and I insist there is no reason to be in a hurry. At the same time, I start teaching partner exercises--push hands, sticky hands, chi na, chi sau immediately--not a lot, but as an integral component of training right from the start. I also am a big proponent of Qigong and sitting meditation. For anyone who comes to me interested in &#34;Tai Chi for health&#34;, I have a Qigong/meditation only class, that is quite fun and powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ruler, or standard of achievement is mostly fang song--acquiring a state of sung. If the student can be sung, still do the short form, 20 minutes of standing, push hands, and chi na without tensing up, then he/she is ready to consider more advanced training. I also keep it simple. We have a short form--12 movement, and long form--48 movement; a set of dynamic Qigong; and partner exercises noted above. And that is more than enough for anyone--several years worth of training.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From Rodney&#39;s comment, you can see how clearly he sees the major practice milestones, e.g. maintaining &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;sung&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; through a practice session. The problem is that, compared to the funny arm-waving that most people equate with Tai Chi, the average person walking through his door has even less context for figuring out where to put that concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote back:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodney, one of my favorite teaching moments was with a private student who insisted on learning the forms. I tried again and again to introduce more fundamentals like standing or simple qigong. One day, after about 18 months, he looked at me and said, &#34;Can we just do Cloud Hands&#34;. Haha, victory!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this mentality really common too...and we just have to find a way to &#34;give them what they want in the hope that they&#39;ll want what they need&#34;. I definitely know teachers who disagree with this approach.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Then Kelly Whelan-Enns weighed in. Kelly has been training in the internal arts for 24 year and he currently teaches beginner&#39;s classes in Qigong and Baguazhang three times a week in Winnipeg, Manitoba. You can hear something that I think is common to just about every good teacher I&#39;ve ever met, a real love for training the basics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost 25 years in the internal arts and I am still amazed at how little time people want to put into the basics and &#39;master&#39; the advanced stuff. I have been lucky to find even 8 people in the last three years that keep coming back every class to repeat and repeat the basics. I have always had a love for basics, getting the feeling right. I feel privileged when a person comes to my classes with the same intent, to get the foundations right. I have MMA guys show up to my classes thinking they are going to learn a magic secret and cannot even get through 2mins of Zhan Zhuang. I never see them again. Not one MMA player ever becomes a regular.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Recently, I asked my teacher about this phenomenon. He said in China there was a very clear understanding that only 1 in 1,000 people really &#34;gets it.&#34; But, the other 999 still practiced and got something from the practice and the teacher taught them within their capacity. He said that the difference was that in the West, everyone came in with the fantasy that they were the 1/1000, but in China, people were happy with what they got from regular training, even though they knew they were in the 999/1000 group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My biggest hope, as we continue to educate each other, as teachers, students, and general public with a casual interest in tai chi, is that we create a context where there is room for people to participate in many different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to shift out of the mindset that being a hardcore martial artist, meditator, and health fanatic all rolled into one is the only genuine way to have Tai Chi in your life. When we make room for different levels of engagement and different roles for people to play in the Tai Chi community, we won&#39;t water down the tradition and the art will take a more sustainable, stable place in the West as a valuable cultural activity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Dr. Mark Cheng is Bringing Tai Chi to the Fitness Community, Part 2</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/25/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2012 08:11:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/25/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a title=&#34;How Dr. Mark Cheng is Bringing Tai Chi to the Fitness Community, Part 1&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/18/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-1/&#34;&gt;part 1 of this interview&lt;/a&gt;, we talked to Dr. Mark Cheng about how his background as an acupuncturist, martial artist, strength coach and PhD in Chinese Medicine has shaped his point of view about the broader subject of fitness and wellness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now he&#39;s going to explain his thinking behind developing a project, called Tai Cheng, which aims to introduce Tai Chi to a much larger fitness audience.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3225&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is Dr. Cheng&#39;s introduction to Tai Cheng:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/tCPrrsyP1-0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/tCPrrsyP1-0?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Cheng aims to synthesize his various perspectives and present Tai Chi in an accessible way to an American audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally the CEO of Beachbody had the idea to call the program Tai Cheng, as in Cheng of my last name &amp;eacute;&amp;bdquo;&amp;shy;. That didn&#39;t make sense to me, so I kept the spelling but changed the character &amp;amp; the concept. So, if you look at the pinyin C-H-E-N-G, and if you look at the logo, and if you understand Chinese, you&#39;ll be able to understand that the &amp;aelig;&amp;circ;character actually means &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;achievement&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; &amp;aelig;&amp;circ;&amp;aring;&amp;Scaron;&amp;Yuml; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;evolution&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;change&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; &amp;egrave;&amp;reg;&amp;Scaron;&amp;aelig;&amp;circ;. You know how Tai Chi &amp;aring;&amp;curren;&amp;ordf;&amp;aelig;&amp;yen;&amp;micro; literally means &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;supreme ultimate?&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Tai Cheng means &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the supreme change&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the supreme evolution.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not reinventing the wheel, as much as going back to what Tai Chi was supposed to be originally. From what one of my teachers said, Tai Chi at its inception was taught so that you understand that all the basics, all the fundamentals of movement, all of the baseline of skill that we&#39;re supposed to be laying is actually the secret to high performance. If you want to perform well, if you want to build skill, but you don&#39;t have that solid foundation, in Chinese, they say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;lian wu bu lian gong, dao lao yi chang kong&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; which means, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;if you train martial arts, but you don&#39;t establish a foundation of functional movement, as you get older you&#39;re left with nothing.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi is like a really well-cut diamond. I mean, to look at it from only one perspective, you&#39;re really robbing yourself of the richness of the experience. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m not saying that you have to fight or that you have to be into combative martial arts or that you have to be into some esoteric meditation or anything like that. If you don&#39;t come into Tai Chi with health issues you may not appreciate the restoratives that you&#39;re getting, and in that case instead of rehab, it&#39;s prehab. If you&#39;re coming to Tai Chi and you just enjoy this as a rejuvenative exercise, you may never care about the self-defense aspect of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what Tai Chi can be. It can improve how your body functions. It can re-center your spine. It can improve your posture. It can dramatically lower your stress levels by virtue of teaching you how to control probably the most necessary vital process and probably the only vital process that you can control volitionally, your breathing. It can heighten your awareness of tension in your own body. It can point out to you how your body reacts to stressors both physical as well as mental. Those things are very important for anyone wanting to get the most out of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lives are full of factors and stressors that can compromise optimum functionality. So I made sure that Tai Cheng began with a &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;neural reboot&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. Because neurologically or neuromuscularly, there&#39;s so many people who have neuromuscular systems that have gone afoul from hours and hours of sitting in spinal flexion or from funny exercise patterns or what have you. Let&#39;s take that whole system and reboot it and say, &#34;instead of trying to debug every little thing, let&#39;s just reboot the whole system and then give you a fresh start in movement.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the thing is that most Tai Chi products are taught out there in a monkey-see-monkey-do fashion. Emulate these movements. There&#39;s not a whole lot of explanation why and if you teach Tai Chi using the language of, &#34;Stroke Peacock&#39;s Tail&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;White Crane Cools Wings&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; or whatever, the average American is going to look at that with a certain degree of cynicism and go, &#34;Yeah, okay, do you want me to get crystals and incense too?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Tai Cheng, I wanted to be able to show people that this ancient training method holds a lot of relevance to their modern lives. You just need to be able to see it in a way that makes sense in terms of sports medicine, in terms of self defense, in terms of restoring the body, in terms of preparing you for high impact, interval training. And that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s my forte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I talk about in Tai Cheng is how you would be taught Tai Chi in its most traditional fashion. When you first roll in to find an old school Tai Chi master, the last thing that he has you do is the form. He or she I should say. The most essential part of Tai Chi training, as I&#39;ve been taught, are the ji ben gong or the basic training exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re taught from the most traditional standpoint of the basics, of the ji ben gong, what are you doing essentially? You&#39;re doing exactly what we&#39;re taught to do in terms of sports medicine, in terms of functional movement by people like Gray Cook, who say that you need to lay a huge platform of fundamental movement, a baseline of mobility and stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s the essence of what Tai Chi should be. What a lot of people are confusing for Tai Chi these days is just like, &#34;Okay, come follow me as I do this pre-choreographed form. This sequence of movements is all of Tai Chi.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; That&#39;s not Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, Tai Chi is a principle. As long as you understand the fundamentals of movement, you optimize your body for movement. And then, you understand ways of training those principles. Anything that you put in the machine comes out as Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Cheng project is designed to get these core concepts about what Tai Chi is, out to the widest possible audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted something that would not just be for the octogenarian, not just be for the young kid, not just be for the martial art insider, and not just for injury rehab people. I wanted something that no matter who you are, you&#39;ll be able to look at this and go like, &#34;Oh geez! This stuff is valuable to me!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the way in which I taught it, I think, is probably is going to be challenging for some people. Instead of trying to dump tons of movements and sequences on them at a time, which is how many are conditioned to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;learning&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;, I actually dial them back a lot. I wanted people to see that I&#39;m having them focus on the prerequisites movement rather than on advanced skillsets first. A lot of people think they&#39;ll buy an instructional DVD or DVD series because they want to just learn like a form or something cool and learn a lot at once. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m dialing people back, and saying, &#34;Look, you got tons of movements already. Let&#39;s see how solid your platform of movement is.&#34; So, that really was the big revolution in thinking that I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m hoping catches on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the points that I tried to convey to the CEO of Beachbody (the company that produces Tai Cheng) was that, let&#39;s say you got someone doing P90X, something pretty vigorous like that and they&#39;re doing maybe like a cardio kickboxing classes or Turbo Kick or what have you, or someone that&#39;s an MMA competitor. If your body&#39;s only used to exercising one way all the time, your muscular system adapts to that. So, it stops experiencing maximum benefit after a certain point. If all your workouts are pretty intense in terms of like high speed, high load, high intensity, you will burn yourself out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like the soil, if you farm only one crop on a plot of land all year round, you will strip that soil dead. It won&#39;t be able to support any another crops. With the field, when you rotate crops intelligently, you ensure the longevity of the soil. With your body, if you rotate different workouts schemes or if rotate different ways of training, you ensure the longevity of your body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in the first test group, we had one guy that was scheduled for a bilateral knee replacement, total knee replacement surgery. We had one woman who was drop-dead gorgeous, in rockstar shape who had been doing a lot of working out. We really had the whole gamut, and everybody reported improvement. We had one guy who was morbidly obese, and just walking from one side to the other side of the room, he would pant and start sweating. That guy that came in morbidly obese just ran his first marathon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gentleman who was scheduled for bilateral knee replacement, I think less than or maybe about half-way through the program pulled me aside to show me that he could climb up and down a flight of steps without limping along painfully step-by-step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, the woman who is in rockstar shape yet couldn&#39;t even do one proper pushup started cranking out strict pushups with higher &amp;amp; higher reps. The thing is regardless of what you come to the table with, Tai Cheng will make you perform better.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There is a valuable lesson here for all movement instructors. If you get a roomful of people with a huge range of abilities and you&#39;re going to get them started doing some Tai Chi practice, how do you frame it? How do you set the expectation for what people are going to experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I guess part of it comes back to being a medical professional. My bottom line is do no harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So more than anything else, I want people to be able to push the envelope but not tear it. So I want them to push the envelope with their movement. I want them to push the envelope of their capacity. I want them to push the envelope of their ability and both their mobility and their stability, but I also want them to do so in a way that they will feel worked but still have more energy in the tank if they need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t want anyone to ever feel like, &#34;I&#39;m so thrashed that all I can do is just lie here in a quivering heap.&#34; And conversely, I don&#39;t want anyone to feel like, &#34;I&#39;m bored out of my ass. I need to go do something mindless and fast and hyper.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&#39;ve got people that are expecting high volumes of movement and high intensity, the key is to instruct them and say, &#34;Look, I understand your expectations and your habits, but what I&#39;m trying to teach you to do is to pay attention to yourselves, to your body, to your movements, and to your performance in a far more attentive and productive manner. We have a society &amp;amp; a lifestyle that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s mostly based on distraction over concentration. If you look at children these days, their parents never taught them to focus in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have kids that are classified as this, that, and the other, or diagnosed as having different learning disorders or cognitive/developmental disorders. While there are certainly some disorders or diseases that are genuinely medical in their nature, a lot of them are really social in nature. That kid won&#39;t make eye contact? Okay. Well, as a parent, did you consistently reinforce the necessity for eye contact from a very young age or did you just kind of ignore that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a situation like the one I just described, that&#39;s not a medical thing. That&#39;s a social thing. So, to be able to teach people or re-socialize people in a way to say, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I&#39;d like you to slow down. I&#39;d like you to concentrate on your breath. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d like you to realize where the little bugs in your motor programming are and learn how to overcome them.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a deeper level of understanding that&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s coming in Tai Cheng. I&#39;m not saying you&#39;re not good enough, I&#39;m not saying that your output is not good enough, and I&#39;m not saying that your effort isn&#39;t good enough, but learn to refine. Learn to appreciate. Learn to drop the defensiveness, so you can continually and truly improve, truly move better, truly feel better, and truly train harder, longer, and more safely!&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you can see, the Tai Cheng project is at an interesting crossroads, bringing the traditional values of high performance martial training into a conversation with modern sports science and rehabilitative medicine. At the same time, Dr. Cheng is giving Tai Chi practitioners and other martial artists license to go out and test their training methods and practice principles in new arenas. It&#39;s going to be fun to see how Tai Cheng takes hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more about Dr. Cheng&#39;s work and this upcoming project, visit: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/taichengworkout&#34;&gt;www.facebook.com/taichengworkout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Dr. Mark Cheng is Bringing Tai Chi to the Fitness Community, Part 1</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/18/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2012 09:35:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/18/how-dr-mark-cheng-is-bringing-tai-chi-to-the-fitness-community-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/01/DrCheng.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3250&#34; title=&#34;DrCheng&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/01/DrCheng-179x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dr Mark Cheng performing Tai Chi&#34; width=&#34;179&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Dr. Mark Cheng compares learning Tai Chi to studying a well-cut diamond, and as you&#39;ll see in the following conversation, his background as an acupuncturist, martial artist, strength coach and PhD in Chinese Medicine actually allows him to look at the broader subject of fitness and wellness in the same multi-faceted way. With the depth and range he brings to teaching movement, it&#39;s no wonder that he&#39;s leading the way to introducing Tai Chi to a much larger fitness audience and in the process, asking all Tai Chi people to step back and take a fresh look at their art.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3179&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked about his upcoming project, called Tai Cheng, an introduction to Tai Chi and healthy movement coming out in 2012, as well as his journey through movement and martial arts, going all the way back to his first experience with Tai Chi at age 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Cheng&#39;s message is clear and ambitious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My deepest wish for Tai Cheng is that this takes off. Whether using Tai Chi as the vehicle or whether using functional movement as the vehicle, we need to be able to show the world and be able to teach the world to see that effective exercise is not just about sets and reps. It&#39;s not just about how much weight did you move. The focus of Tai Cheng is on the quality of your movement and how you feel at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, a good exercise program considers how you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re going to be in the long run. If you&#39;re training really hard now, you may look great after doing 90 days of high intensity training, but then your body may be so trashed from repetitive motion injury. Because of the pain, there could be so much cortisol going through your body that you&#39;re really fighting a losing battle against weight gain. So obviously situations like this aren&#39;t productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to show people that you&#39;ve got to be able to regulate stress. You&#39;ve got to be able to eat well and eat healthy, but also live healthy and make healthy choices as far as your own exercise. Seeing people make the leap in understanding that takes them just from sets &amp;amp; reps to seeing that quality of movement comes first would thrill me to no end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you read about his initial exposure to Tai Chi and his growing movement education, you&#39;ll see how several different intertwined threads have brought him to this project.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On his early training background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My first love has always been Chinese martial arts. I was fortunate enough to start before adulthood. My first exposure to Chinese martial arts was with my father, who studied Tai Chi with one of Cheng Man Ching&#39;s students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember the first time I saw my father practicing Tai Chi. It looked like the funniest thing to me. When you&#39;re a little kid and you watch someone moving in slow motion like that, you&#39;re just struggling to suppress the snickering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, my father heard me giggling and was like, &#34;Hey, you think this is funny, but this is really martial arts!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that thought sounded even funnier to me. So, then I totally lost it... You can imagine a little kid rolling around on the floor laughing his head off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my father goes, &#34;Okay, you don&#39;t realize that. Well, throw a punch right at me.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I was like, &#34;Oh, really? Okay!&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just teed off and with Shou Hui Pipa (Play the Pipa), he launched me and I remember it&#39;s like I didn&#39;t really feel anything. It wasn&#39;t like a hard joint lock, no pain. It&#39;s just that I threw a punch and next thing I knew, I was sailing through the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember thinking, &#34;Wow! This is sweet. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve got to learn this!&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; That was 30 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I came out to California to pursue my undergraduate degree, I was fortunate enough to study martial arts under several outstanding masters, from Prof. Daniel Lee to Shotokan Karate pioneer Tsutomu Ohshima. At a certain point, my interests in Chinese martial arts led right into Chinese medicine. I remember seeing my Shaolin teacher, Hong Li-rong, occasionally seeing patients on evenings that we had training classes. We would bow to start class, and then he&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;d turn the class over to one of the senior students for warmup while he would use his manual medicine skills to heal people. And as you know, a lot of the higher-level sifu are also, in addition to their martial skills, very renowned for their medical or healing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finishing my undergrad degree in East Asian Studies at UCLA, I did a short stint in import-export, realized I wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t doing what made me happy, and then went on to study acupuncture here in California. After graduation &amp;amp; earning board licensure, I apprenticed with one of Dr. Yu Da-Fang&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s disciples to study tui na (Chinese manual medicine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been specializing in Chinese manual medicine since then, which allowed me to meet the legendary Sifu Dan Inosanto, and he in turn introduced me to Pavel Tsatsouline, who is the founder of the RKC Kettlebell method. Pavel introduced me to Gray Cook, the founder of the FMS, or Functional Movement Systems. So Chinese medicine really brought me to three of my most important mentors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gray has been responsible for really revolutionizing my whole view of medicine and of patient care. Working with Gray has really given me a new motivation for going back and reviewing Tai Chi and reviewing traditional Chinese martial arts in general to see what gems are in the training.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you can see, this is a very traditional upbringing in the Chinese martial arts. At the same time, Dr. Cheng has also connected to people in the fitness world who also have a very complete paradigm for understanding movement and understanding the body. Now, he is holding these two paradigms and treating them in their own right, but also seeing differences and seeing crossover points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the ways I talk about it when my patients ask me or when my colleagues ask me, &#34;What&#39;s your direction? What are you all about? Why can&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t you define yourself professionally as one thing or the other?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My explanation is that it really goes back to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;What is Asian-American?&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have the luxury of coming from a culture that&#39;s very old with a lot of traditional, old, and powerful knowledge. But being that we are American, we have the freedom to look at what we have, what we come to the table with, in terms of our own culture, with a critical eye. We can look at the things that we bring to the table, and say that certain things may not stand the test of time in terms of laboratory validation. That freedom allows us to change, to evolve, and to improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we&#39;re also here in the States, we have access to so much information and so much openness, breadth of thought, and discovery. I think it would be a bigger travesty to not take advantage of that freedom to learn from the people that we have surrounding us who are just brilliant minds.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you look at the history of Tai Chi too, of course there were innovators and there was ongoing research. And people would come along and say, &#34;Let&#39;s take it one way or take it the other way.&#34; People err on the side of thinking that tradition is a static thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think one of the biggest mistakes is when you hear from people who say tradition is static. It&#39;s not, because if you look at the term &#34;mixed martial art&#34; you look at systems like Choy Lee Fut. By definition, that&#39;s an amalgam of three systems already. That&#39;s a mixed martial art. So, what&#39;s mixed? What&#39;s not mixed? I mean, these things have been mixed, and synthesized, and rethought, and reworked since time immemorial. It wasn&#39;t until we got dogmatic in saying that, &#34;No, no. It has to be this way.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In Part 2, Dr. Cheng will go into detail about how he chose a focus for his new project and how it aims to bring Tai Chi to a wide audience, especially people who have had little or no exposure to genuine Tai Chi. For more about Dr. Cheng&#39;s work and his upcoming Tai Cheng project, visit: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/taichengworkout&#34;&gt;www.facebook.com/taichengworkout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living between the Lab and the Classroom with Dr. Peter Wayne</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2012 09:50:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-3237&#34; title=&#34;PW Correction&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2012/01/PW-Correction.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;215&#34; height=&#34;197&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trained in Evolutionary Biology, Peter Wayne, Ph.D., has spent the last 12 years in medical research and more than 35 years studying and teaching Tai Chi. He now serves as Research Director for the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine jointly based at the Harvard Medical School and Brigham and Women&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Hospital, where a primary focus of his research is studying the clinical and physiological impacts of Tai Chi on health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to Peter about the unique opportunities and challenges of being both a Tai Chi teacher and a researcher and how these two different roles inform each other. He is currently working on a book about the same topic. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-3233&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little about your book&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book summarizes what the medical research community knows about the clinical health benefits of Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;for example, Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s impact on heart disease, balance, psychological well being, and overall quality of life. But it also tries to go a little further, exploring the biological mechanisms that may underlie why Tai Chi is effective for so many conditions. To do this, I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve organized the book around what I call &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the eight active ingredients of Tai Chi.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; The grouping of these ingredients reflect both what I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve learned is essential in Tai Chi from my many Tai Chi and qigong teachers, and also what I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve learned from our Tai Chi research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The concept of isolating active ingredients is common in other medical research. But does it really make sense to think of Tai Chi within this framework?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great question&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;..and I think absolutely so. Part of why I chose this language is to bend the ear of my medical colleagues&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;to try to communicate in their language. Even if we see positive clinical effects in Tai Chi trials, without plausible mechanisms&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; that is, being able to attribute clinical health effects to specific &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;active ingredients&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;, research results often have little traction in the medical community. Mechanisms are part of what we call the totality of evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, by using this language, we&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve been able to emphasize Tai Chi&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s richness&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;that it includes not just one active ingredient&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;but many&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;including those related to neuromuscular control, breathing, cognitive processes, etc. This may explain why it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s helpful for so diverse a set of health issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a teacher, thinking in terms of active ingredients has helped me shape a curriculum that tries to maximize the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;dosage&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; of essential tai chi principles in as short a period of time as is possible. This is key for teaching in clinical trials which are often constrained in length due to funding limitations; but also relevant to community-based classes where we want people to get a real taste of deep Tai Chi as quickly and efficiently as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living in the research world and the Tai Chi world at the same time allows Peter to apply lessons from one to the other. Here he explains how his scientific education influences the way he understands teaching Tai Chi:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My formal academic training was in evolutionary biology and ecological modeling, and my research for the first 15 years was with plants. So shifting to medical research 12 years ago was a big change for me. Consequently, I bring a somewhat unique perspective to the teams of medical researchers I work with. My training to think ecologically, in terms of systems, is more like Chinese Medicine in that it focuses on ecological interactions within the body&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;how systems interact to create a complex whole that is greater than the sum of its parts. In contrast, Western medicine has traditionally emphasized reductionist thinking, focusing on smaller and smaller parts, often at the cost of not seeing the whole person. Interestingly, systems biology is being increasingly appreciated in medicine, and Tai Chi research fits beautifully into this more ecological framework of health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you give an example?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;brvbar;,breathing is a really important element in our tai chi and qigong training. But there&#39;s no way you can substantially change your breathing without changing your posture and how you hold your structure. And your breathing deeply affects you nervous and cardiovascular system, and many aspects of your mood; it can be a great tool for focusing the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;monkey mind&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; and becoming more sensitive to the inner landscape of our body. And of course changes in all these processes feedback on how we move and socially respond and interact with others. All these processes are ecologically intertwined with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also still think it&#39;s useful to unpack the interconnected components&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;for example to teach breathing exercises on their own and to study the physiological impacts of breathing exercises, in isolation of the larger package of Tai Chi. As a teacher, focusing on individual components helps brings awareness to finer scale processes, and it helps make a clearer teaching intention. Also talking about the physiology of breathing in classes helps some students appreciate the work, and for the students, there can be a lot of power in knowing. Most of us like to be told why we are doing a given practice in a given way. It really helps if students are informed. It creates buy in. I really love building bridges between traditional practices and modern science for this reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally, what&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s it like for you teaching in a clinical trial compared to your community-based classes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In clinical trials, we are asking individuals to volunteer their time as a study participant so we can learn more about the health effects of Tai Chi. Often, these individuals have serious health conditions, and may not have chosen Tai Chi, or even heard of it, were it not for their doctor telling them about the trial. So many come to class not because they especially want to do tai chi, but because it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s a &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;tilde;new therapy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade; they are hopeful it might improve their health. So there is sometimes a bit more time devoted to easing them into the work and making them feel comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think in your classes, in my classes, everyday someone walks in, and it&#39;s like an energetic push-hands. How do you meet that person exactly where they are and make them feel comfortable. And sometimes it has to be with a joke, sometimes it has to be with empathic solemnness, sometimes it&#39;s with a little distance&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;some do not initially care for intimacy. And you just have to feel that out. The real challenge, of course, is when you try to feel it out with 30 different people at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoying the challenge of connecting with diverse populations, and find humor and science help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite moments in teaching new Tai Chi students, both in clinical trials and community-based classes, is introducing them to a qigong warm-up exercise called &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Washing yourself with qi from nature.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; This very simple exercise, done either standing or seated, is designed to gather in healing, rejuvenating, peaceful energy from nature and guide this energy through every cell of the body, starting at the crown of the head and down through the chest, shoulders, spine, all the internal organs, through the legs and feet. I ask participants&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34;not uncommonly older housewives and retired blue collar workers with little or no exposure to New Age practices --to imagine doing this while standing on a mountaintop, a beach, or wherever they feel they would be surrounded by nourishing energy. As they do the movement, I invite them to trust the energy to permeate and revitalize every cell of their body, while at the same time, tired sick energy is filter out and washed out through the soles of their feet into the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll abruptly stop, smile, and acknowledge with them how odd or weird this all sounds. They typically agree and we all laugh together. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ll then share with them some of the research my colleagues and I have done related to the placebo effect, that sheds light on the exercise we are learning, and more generally supports the Tai Chi principle that what you think and believe impacts your physiology and how you feel. Typically, I draw on the well-documented placebo effect in asthma patients. Briefly, asthma patients in placebo studies were recruited to participate under the guise of evaluating new asthma drugs. Wearing an air-tight breathing mask, first they were told they would be challenged with an airborne insult, for example, ragweed, but actually they were simply given saline sprayed into the air they inhaled. Just the suggestion of ragweed induced physiologically measurable asthmatic attacks in the majority of participants. Following this insult, they were then told they were being given a new asthma &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;rescue&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; medication, which again was saline, and most of those who had had the asthma attacks quickly recovered. A huge body of research now shows that this so-called placebo effect -- that is, that placebos can have a real therapeutic effect -- is true for nearly all medical interventions, including sugar pills, mock injections, even surgery, and for nearly all medical conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this brief interlude, I return back to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;washing yourself with qi from heavens&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and jokingly say &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;so as we wash with qi from heavens, you can go to your special place and imagine breathing in and bathing every cell in your body with healing energy, or you can breath in ragweed or other toxic substances. It&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s your choice!&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Learn more about Peter&#39;s school here at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.treeoflifetaichi.com/&#34;&gt;Tree of Life Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Man Who Did His Tai Chi Form 19,100 Times</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2011 07:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/28/the-man-who-did-his-tai-chi-form-19100-times/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;I got an email the other day that was a little bit different than the usual requests for lessons. It read:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;I learned the Short Form at Brookline Tai Chi under the tutelage of Bill Ryan back about 1996-1997. For seven years, I continued to do the short form three times every morning. Then for the past eight years or so, I have done the short form four times every morning.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;I keep a log of my centering practices, and have documentation that over the past 15 years, I have only missed doing my tai chi on three days, two when I was strapped down in hospital beds and unable to get up, and one day when I simply forgot to practice. (I practiced twice the next day.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Thus, I have done the short form now over 17,800 times.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;There were so many things that fascinated me about getting this email. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2966&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;First of all, it reinforced my belief that there&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s no such thing as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dankleiman.com/2010/12/01/brookline-tai-chi-has-no-former-students/&#34;&gt;&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;former student&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/a&gt;. As a teacher, this was a powerful reminder that you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t know the full extent of what you are giving your students and just how far they will take what they learn.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Then, consider this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He practices tai chi every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He practices several repetitions of the short form every time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He logs his practice every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;As you know from reading this blog, I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m a little obsessed with the idea of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;practice.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Clearly this man knew something about cultivating a practice. I wanted to know more about what motivated him to practice daily and record it with such diligence. So I asked him, but I wasn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t ready for the depth and thoughtfulness of his answer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-3105&#34; title=&#34;Sandy Davis&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/12/IMG_0518-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sandy Davis runs Resilience Works&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;It turns out, I was talking to &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;The Resilience Guy.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Sandy Davis runs a company called &lt;a href=&#34;http://resilienceworks.com/&#34;&gt;ResilienceWorks&lt;/a&gt;, dedicated to teaching people how to become more resilient, or as he puts it:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;CENTER&#34;&gt;&amp;Acirc; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-size: small;&#34;&gt;The more you invest wisely in your own vitality,&lt;br /&gt;
The more resilient you become, and&lt;br /&gt;
The easier it is to thrive.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Many of us come to movement arts like tai chi or qigong because of an innate desire to thrive, but Sandy has gone into great depth explaining the structures that make this process possible. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;He advocates for &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;Seven Simple Self-Care Structures&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; that make this possible:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Keep all your agreements.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Eat well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Sleep well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Have a daily centering practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Exercise aerobically on a regular basis.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Have a daily creative practice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Log your self-care results every day.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Now, when we talk about &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;practice&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; here, we often talk about 3 or 4 of these structures (mainly centering, exercise, and sleep). We often imply that a lot of what grabs you about something like tai chi is the creative expression you derive from continually refining it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;And certainly we talk about tracking your practice -- although I haven&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t yet met anyone else who has taken this habit to quite the same degree as Sandy -- he&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s missed three days of practice in the last 14 years, and he can prove it!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;So what is it about &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;keeping all your agreements&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; that adds to your store of energy? When I heard Sandy describe this particular structure, it broadened my sense of &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what builds your energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; and &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;what uses up your energy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; in a way I had never considered. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.resilienceworks.com/resiliencemanual&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Resilience Manual&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; , Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s guide to developing these structures, he writes:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;There is much satisfaction to be had in knowing that you are someone who can be relied upon to keep your word. By consistently walking your talk, &lt;strong&gt;you can acquire a deep-seated self-confidence in your ability to successfully follow through&lt;/strong&gt; on whatever you agree to undertake. This includes faithfully attending to your own foundational self-care habits, as well as to faithfully doing your chosen daily self-care practices.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Alternatively, there is much disappointment to be had in knowing that you are someone who routinely fails to follow through on your commitments. Whenever you fail to keep your word, whenever you fail to do what you promised, whenever you do 95% of what you said you would do and leave the last 5% unfinished, in all these instances, you experience a loss of self-respect. Each of these failures, whether obvious and public, or miniscule and private, generates a measure of personal disappointment and/or discouragement. &lt;strong&gt;Such breakdowns cost you valuable energy. They undermine your self-confidence. And they get in the way of deepening your resilience-readiness. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;What I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve highlighted in bold above should be familiar language when you think about your movement practice. You are either moving in a way that builds and integrates your coordination and your energy, or in a way that saps both and leads to dis-integration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Many of us have a gut feeling that how we cultivate a movement practice spills over into other dimensions of life, but I think Sandy has clearly articulated exactly how that works in the above passage. The lesson is that doing your movement practice won&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t make you a better person, but &lt;em&gt;it is a template for how to move toward more wholeness in other areas of your life&lt;/em&gt;. In Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s language, both structures feed your resilience-readiness and the store of resilience that you naturally draw energy from, no matter what situation you are facing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;The linchpin to all of this, from Sandy&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s point of view, is the seventh structure, or the meta-structure of logging the results of the other six structures on a daily basis. In &lt;em&gt;The Resilience Manual,&lt;/em&gt; he makes several compelling arguments for keeping a daily practice log both to gain perspective and to sustain accountability to yourself. For me, the most compelling reason is the deep satisfaction this seventh structure generates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;A week or so after our lesson, Sandy e-mailed me to make a correction to the number of times he has done the short form (hence the title of this post):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;FYI, I re-checked the numbers, and it turns out that I have actually done the short form more than 19,100 times. It will be a treat to pass the 20,000 mark. At my current rate of four times each day, that will take me another seven-plus months. But who&#39;s counting?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Think about how great that must feel to realize that you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;re actually a little closer to 20,000? And not because you can brag about a number, but because you know you&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve made a serious ongoing investment in your own well-being.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;Big thanks to Sandy for sharing his method with so much clarity and simplicity! His website has more information, including some useful free resources and more in-depth explanations of the daily self-care structures. Check them out here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://resilienceworks.com/download.asp&#34;&gt;ResilienceWorks.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #000000;&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oh, and we also agreed that Sandy should come in for a tune-up every 3,000 forms, not every 10,000 or 15,000!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 Different Ways to Think about Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/14/9-different-ways-to-think-about-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2011 08:00:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/12/14/9-different-ways-to-think-about-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi: State of the Art&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-state-of-the-art/&#34;&gt;State of the Art&lt;/a&gt; survey, I asked people to explain what drew them to Tai Chi initially and what keeps them interested. I was also curious to know more about what role, if any, Tai Chi plays in their physical health,&amp;Acirc;  mental/emotional wellbeing and spiritual development. Weighty stuff, I know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People came back with some surprising and great answers. Here are a few:&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2773&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;My primary interest was in chi gung. After trying tai chi, I was immediately interested. Now, experiencing how forming &amp;amp; filling variously shaped energetic containers with chi gung, pouring their contents into the tai chi form, the expansion that happens therein &amp;amp; how that further fills out the chi gung has hooked me. It&#39;s the most fascinating process I&#39;ve ever experienced, 10 fold, &amp;amp; it JUST KEEPS GOING! I&#39;ve barely even scratched the surface! - Jason Swinton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What keeps me interested? I love the form and practice, the complexity and ever increasing depth to which practice leads, the beneficial effects on my body, mind and emotions, the chi gung, the new things about my body and mind the practices teaches -- Chris Cinnamon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use tai chi to remain as flexible as possible and generally to be as healthy as possible. Also to increase energy. I find regular practice does smooth my emotions and generally after practice I feel balanced and calm so that is a big plus for me. - Jo Sawyers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It continues to allow me to deepen my understanding of myself, as well as improve &amp;amp; maintain my health &amp;amp; well being. - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imos-journal.net&#34;&gt;Anthony Guilbert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I enrolled with a young friend who was dying of cancer to support her and introduce her to something that would distract her and help her find some balance. I immediately felt the benefits for myself and recognized that all of us who feel the cultural pressure to give 110% at all times in every facet of life. No matter the details of our struggle, I saw that we all need to find the quiet, sill place inside us and to inhabit out bodies; a place where we&#39;re awake and focused, and can be restored. Otherwise, for me, and others I see moving through life, it&#39;s easy to go overboard to keep tempo with invented cultural demands and ignore the need for balance and inner strength. I know that I was simply wearing out my host body like a pair of replaceable shoes. Now, my practice of the form and appreciation for what it does, is like a banister to hold onto, no matter the level of expertise in the moves. Concurrently my interest in performing these subtle moves developed over centuries has increased. It&#39;s very valuable in my life. -Chris Radant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Better balance. More confidence. Stronger. Calmer mind. -&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.swimmingdragontaichi.com/&#34;&gt;Randy Moy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slowing down and really focusing on what you are learning and listening to how it feels in your body really tunes out a lot of noise generated by life in the &#34;real&#34; world. The quieter you get the more you hear. What could be better? -Carla Ross&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I practice Tai Chi following my morning meditation and it feels like both a completion and a beginning. I return to it occasionally during the day if I feel I am losing my balance. -Nancy Kleiman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a high pressure job so use Tai Chi in the evenings to relax/distance myself from work issues - also, balance and co-ordination are improving steadily - certainly feel calmer and more &#39;controlled&#39; (maybe in control of myself would be a better way of putting it) &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&#34; Tony Gibbons&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Tai Chi for you?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What hooked you about the practice initially? What is it that keeps you motivated? Share you thoughts in the comments or complete the&lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-state-of-the-art/2012-survey/&#34;&gt; Tai Chi: State of the Art 2012 survey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 09:22:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I sat down with Robert Tangora to talk about his upcoming book on Tai Chi Cloud Hands when he was in Boston in October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he discusses Tai Chi Cloud Hands, almost reverently, Robert explains it as a paradigm for understanding the complete art of Tai Chi, and also as a way to bring each practitioner closer to integration. The basic problem is that you have a spectrum of practices, from sitting, to standing, to moving, to fighting, that all feel very different and all develop different attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked Robert to talk about this integration problem and explain why he sees Cloud Hands as an essential part of well developed Tai Chi practice. Here are some highlights from the interview, with a link at the end to the entire video and full transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of this interview will also appear in the &lt;a title=&#34;Tai Chi: State of the Art&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-state-of-the-art/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi State of the Art 2012 ebook&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven&#39;t had a chance to weigh in on that topic yet, complete the survey &lt;a title=&#34;2012 Survey&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tai-chi-state-of-the-art/2012-survey/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2376&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fsAN3HlNvrc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/fsAN3HlNvrc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the introduction to &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The Internal Structure of Cloud Hands&lt;/span&gt; from his website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://tangorataichi.com/Book%20Intro.pdf&#34;&gt;TangoraTaiChi.com&lt;/a&gt; (right click and &#34;save as&#34;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Cloud Hands?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you talk to a lot of people who have done Tai Chi a long time, they&#39;ll all say, &#34;Oh yeah, Cloud Hands.&#34; They may not have any idea why Cloud Hands seems really kind of special, but almost universally they go, &#34;Yeah, there&#39;s something there that&#39;s going on that I can&#39;t quite put my finger on it but I know it&#39;s there.&#34; And well, what&#39;s going on is it&#39;s this hidden relationship between the symmetries in what you&#39;re doing externally and internally.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On the relationship between health and meditation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;From a health standpoint, meditation is very important because it develops a lot of sensitivity to what&#39;s going on inside you. And if you want to be able to kind of fix something, you&#39;ve got to be able to feel it. If you can&#39;t feel it, you can&#39;t fix it. Well, most of us feel things because we have pain reactions rather than feeling things that aren&#39;t painful. Well, through meditation you actually learn to feel a lot of things that aren&#39;t pain reactions and you learn how those things end up being interrelated with pain reactions. And if you want to become really efficient at kind of healing yourself, or for that matter if you&#39;re doing some sort of healing of somebody else, you&#39;ve got to be able to distinguish those two.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On maximizing the health benefits by doing martial arts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The people I&#39;ve met who really have the health stuff of Tai Chi really well-developed were all very respectable martial arts... Those are the people who have that most developed.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;On having a spectrum of different practices:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You have to have something that allows you to go from what you develop energetically while you&#39;re sitting and standing and take that into motion. Otherwise you tend to just jump into the form and the things you&#39;re doing internally in meditation practice are gone.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;How Cloud Hands develops physical and energetic alignments:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeah there is physical aspects to it, like there is certain alignments you really need to kind of put in place, but there&#39;s also kind of some more energetic things that don&#39;t really necessarily have a real good physical counterpart. And it&#39;s kind of the first place where you really start kind of encountering that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, if I&#39;m like doing something on the left side of my body and it creates like a twist in a spiral like down to the ground. And I can reverse that, bring it up. Well, eventually this starts actually stimulating the Chi in my body. Just kind of start doing the same type of thing, but it does it actually probably at a different pace than my physical tissue because I can&#39;t actually make my physical tissue twist like this. But it helps induce it. So at some point it&#39;s physical, but it also has these other components energetically that it&#39;s starting to really develop.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What 90% of Tai Chi practitioners might be missing:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately everything kind of moves in these oblique ellipses and circles from your abdominal cavity...Well if you&#39;re doing both simultaneously, you start developing these kind of pulls and compression&#39;s that massage and loosen up your organs, and it begins to develop that. It&#39;s not that if you just relax and you stay really loose and you turn, you get some of that. You just don&#39;t get as much. And the place where, from a martial standpoint what happens is, you tend to be able to project power from certain angles, pretty efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s fairly efficient, it actually can be quite efficient at handling forces basically working more or less in a horizontal plane. But if I want to handle forces working in other dimensions, like vertically and stuff, I really have to have the capacity for my body to move in that direction and it&#39;d be integrated with what&#39;s happening in my legs and waist. So that&#39;s the other component, that&#39;s very important in the cross body training that probably 90% of the people doing Tai Chi they don&#39;t do it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;My favorite quote from the interview:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you just practice form, there are so many things that distract you from listening to yourself.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora Tai Chi Cloud Hands Interview&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/robert-tangora-tai-chi-cloud-hands-interview/&#34;&gt;Check out the complete interview here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>