<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>running-a-school on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/running-a-school/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in running-a-school on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/running-a-school/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Student Practice Habits</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2011 08:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/30/decoding-student-practice-habits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Donkey Kong from Arcade-Musuem.com&#34; src=&#34;http://www.arcade-museum.com/images/118/1181242103213.png&#34; alt=&#34;The Donkey Kong Model of Learning&#34; height=&#34;256&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What the heck does Donkey Kong have to do with the practice habits of tai chi students? It turns out the ladders and platforms in the video game are a perfect model for understanding the ecosystem of students practice habits. Let me explain the survey design and then I&#39;ll share some really fascinating results about how people engage Brookline Tai Chi to develop their tai chi practice.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1494&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Survey Design&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Last week we conducted a small practice survey to try to get a more accurate picture of what students do outside of class. We sent out a request to participate to about 2000 people on our email list, and 30 completed the survey in detail. I then divided the 30 into 3 groups, to test the difference between two types of daily reminders and a weekly follow-up. The initial survey, sent on a Sunday, asked people about &#34;typical&#34; practice habits: frequency, duration, and content. I followed up on Friday with the same set of questions, but instead of asking what people &#34;typically&#34; practice, I asked them what they specifically practiced &#34;last week&#34;. In between the initial Sunday survey and the follow-up Friday survey, 1/3 of participants received a daily email that said &#34;Thanks again for volunteering to help us develop better practice tools for our tai chi community. I&#39;m going to send you a little practice reminder every day this week and ask you about it at the end of the week. So...take a few minutes today to do some practice!&#34;. Another third got a similar email, but it included a link to a one-question survey: &#34;what did you practice today?&#34; The last third only got the Sunday and Friday surveys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who Participated in the Survey&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, in this case, we actually know just about everyone who participated in the survey, but that&#39;s a good thing. We&#39;re not trying to run a randomized, controlled, double-blinded study. We&#39;re trying to gain deeper insight into our students&#39; experience and develop tools for them that makes the practice more rewarding. So who participated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people were relatively new to learning tai chi and chi gung&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people have been doing home practice for 15 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people attend classes 3-5 times per week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people don&#39;t live nearby the school or in Massachusetts (but they were tuned in enough to what we do to complete this survey, hmmm)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I was really excited to see that we got such a range of people interested in participating in this experience. It speaks to richness of our community that the request to &#34;help us develop better practice tools&#34; was embraced by people with so many different relationships to the school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the results started coming in, it looked to me that people fell into a few distinct categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Home Practicers vs. School Practicers vs. Blended Practice People&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skill Acquisition Mode vs. Practice Plateau Mode&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There was also a category of what I think of now as &#34;Super Practicers&#34;. Whereas most people reported on practice frequency as a number of days, these folks said &#34;daily&#34;. As I watched their survey results come in and read how they talked about their practice, it was clear that their practice is so ingrained into their lives, that practicing for them is just like eating or breathing. Surprisingly, the amount of time the Super Practicers reported varied from 10 minutes to 2 hours. It wasn&#39;t like the 10 minute Super Practicer was yearning to be in the 2 hour category, though. It was just that 10 minutes a day makes perfect sense for the role practice plays in their life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Skill Ladders and Practice Platforms&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ok, so here&#39;s where the Donkey Kong Model comes in. It was very clear that the students we surveyed fell into two different groups, which roughly matched up to how long they had been in their practice, but not completely. Some of the participants were actively engaged in learning new material, which is usually the choreography of a tai chi or chi gung set. The folks in this category who received daily email reminders to practice did more practice during the week than they thought they typically do. The folks in this category who only got the end-of-week follow-up did less practice than they reported initially.&lt;strong&gt; It seems clear from these results that when you are on the ladder of new skill acquisition, daily practice triggers help you get there faster.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, we have the people who are maintaining a regular, ongoing practice. For these folks, there was almost no change in reported practice, whether they received daily emails or the weekly survey. To these people, the reminders were more of an annoyance (they told me so!). The conclusion here isn&#39;t that the tool is not useful, it&#39;s that these folks don&#39;t need an external reminder to perform something that is internally motivated. More importantly, seeing very little change in the Practice Plateau group highlighted the impact of the daily reminders on the Skill Acquisition group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Donkey King Model is useful here, because over the course of your lifetime of practice, you don&#39;t just go through one Skill Acquisition Phase and one Practice Plateau. I like that image from the game of hanging out on a platform for a while, at a certain level of practice, before you embark on another climb up the skill ladder. From my own experience as a student and as a teacher, I think this is much more common. My intuition is that the daily reminder tool could be refined, if it&#39;s goal-specific enough, to be useful to anyone who is in a Skill Acquisition Phase, not just complete beginners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where Does Motivation Come From?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Where does motivation come from? I don&#39;t actually know for sure, but we learned some really interesting stuff about how people construct their practice. There seems to be a spectrum from internal to external sources of motivation. Again, this often correlated to how long people have been doing the practice, but not completely. Here&#39;s what I mean: when people first walk through the door to learn chi gung or tai chi, they need external motivation: they don&#39;t have the right information yet, they don&#39;t know what to practice, and they don&#39;t have any practice habits yet (for this art).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you climb one or two skill ladders, you start to feel the benefits of practice. You no longer practice &#34;because my doctor told me to&#34; or because &#34;I saw people doing it in the parks in China&#34;. Instead, the practice starts to satisfy you on some level. At this point, we see some branching. There are a small number of people who take one course and then go off and practice on their own forever. To me, they&#39;ve abandoned all of the external motivation we can provide, and made regular practice 100% internally driven. More often we see students who are happy to have the social support of classmates, a physical place to practice, and the guidance of an instructor -- all external motivators --- to keep their practice going. Many slot into this relationship with the school indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our instructors tells a funny story where a friend of hers, on hearing that she&#39;s been coming to classes for 15 years, said &#34;Don&#39;t you know it already?&#34; That&#39;s a perfect example of assuming that long term practice is one big skill ladder to climb. It&#39;s not. The practice plateaus along the way are not the same as the linear climb to skill acquisition and part of what a community like Brookline Tai Chi offers is not only external motivation, but external connection -- to people and a place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any progress we make developing practice tools for our students will have to consider all of these factors, internal and external motivators, phases of skill acquisition and even the satisfaction of practice plateaus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That brings me to the most surprising result in our survey. Many of the participants fell into the Super Practicer category, with extremely high internal motivation to practice, and in some cases no immediate geographic proximity to the school. By all appearances, this is the group who has moved on from everything we have to offer -- weekly classes, skill ladders, a space, people to practice with, instructor feedback . So why did so many of these folks respond to a request to develop practice tools for our community? In one sense, they appear to be the least connected to the day-to-day activities of the school and the least in need of help with practice, but they all responded to our request and gave a tremendous amount of insight into their practice habits. It&#39;s going to be a huge payoff for me when we finally figure out what makes these folks tick.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build Yourself a Pyramid</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/09/build-yourself-a-pyramid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2011 10:00:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/05/09/build-yourself-a-pyramid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not talking about a polygon with triangular faces or a marketing scam to rope your friends in. I&#39;m talking about The Pyramid Method, laid out by Cal Newport on his blog, &lt;a href=&#34;http://calnewport.com/blog/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Study Hacks&lt;/a&gt;. Newport tells the story of a friend of a friend&#39;s journey to becoming a professional hip-hop artist. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1262&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The key, he claims, was that the friend, Chris, followed the Pyramid Method -- named for the hip-hop club, The Pyramid, where he honed his craft. Chris went back to the Pyramid again and again and as he worked his way to becoming the undisputed champ of their weekly rap battles, he polished all the different facets of his hip-hop game. This is the essence of Newport&#39;s method. From the post where he tells Chris&#39;s story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Pyramid Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between the first two years after Chris&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s graduation, and the two years that followed our fateful phone call, couldn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t be starker. The key to his transformation was two-fold: (1) Chris focused his attention on improving his standing at a single venue; and (2) this venue provided clear metrics, so he could track his progress and use this to tweak his practice to be as effective as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I call this general technique the Pyramid Method. &lt;strong&gt;I claim that it&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s a powerful approach for anyone looking to transform an interest or natural talent into an expertise that cannot be ignored.&lt;/strong&gt; Regardless of the pursuit in question, if you want to take it someplace serious, follow Chris&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s example. This means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a single relevant venue to join at the entry level and work to increase your standing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure the venue offers clear metrics on your progress; use these metrics to guide your efforts to get better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forget all the other bullshit advice and mini-strategies people offer for getting ahead in your pursuit. If you can&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t master this one venue, then you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t yet deserve the world&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s respect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put your head down, and get it done.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As I read Newport&#39;s story, it dawned on me that the single biggest problem most teachers have getting better at teaching and building a student following along the way was that they were missing their Pyramid -- the one venue they could go again and again and get reliable feedback on their skills. I like Newport&#39;s tone and candid admission that there really isn&#39;t any glory in the Pyramid phase of honing your skills, but that&#39;s the big fat open secret to getting really good: you have to be there, doing it, all the time and adapting to feedback as you go. That&#39;s too boring for most people who think they deserve students because they&#39;ve been at their hobby for a long time. I&#39;m not going to go back down that road. I&#39;ve explored the psychological flip you need to make as a successful teacher &lt;a title=&#34;A Teacher&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Reality, Part 1&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;A Teacher&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Reality, Part 2&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a title=&#34;A Teacher&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s Reality, Part 3&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, let&#39;s talk about building a Pyramid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Brookline Tai Chi as The Pyramid&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If we break down the four parts of Newport&#39;s model, we can actually see how BTC is the perfect place for teachers to hone their skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 1. Pick a single relevant venue to join at the entry level and work to increase your standing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a budding tai chi teacher in our system, this is the most relevant venue in the country. Most of my teaching peers have to teacher introductory sessions to a handful of students over and over again, because they don&#39;t have a venue with the kind of structure we do at BTC. For the new teacher, there is a clear entry-level opportunity and as they build a following, there is a natural progression for them to go through, teaching more advanced material.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Make sure the venue offers clear metrics on your progress; use these metrics to guide your efforts to get better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one teaching metric at BTC that matters: retention. Again, with a small sample size, it&#39;s easy to have a half-dozen excuses for why this student or that student didn&#39;t come back. Once you start seeing 20 new students every 7 weeks, though, you see trends (these excuses continually add &#34;old students&#34; back into the mix too, by the way). If you&#39;re perceptive, and you get some outside feedback on your teaching, you can begin to tweak how you run classes and how you related to students so that they are engaged, happy, and interested in studying with you on an ongoing basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Forget all the other bullshit advice and mini-strategies people offer for getting ahead in your pursuit. If you can&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t master this one venue, then you don&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t yet deserve the world&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s respect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love this piece of advice in the Pyramid Method. The classic example I&#39;ve experienced with BTC is outreach teaching. We get a steady stream of calls from groups, classes, and health fairs, stuff like that, looking for instructors to come teach to a group. For a while I didn&#39;t turn these down, at first for the wrong reason. See, at first, I thought being responsive to these requests would be a great way to get new business. It doesn&#39;t work that way. Don&#39;t get me wrong, I really enjoy talking to the student who came from that one conference, two years later, but this isn&#39;t the way to drive new business.....in one sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, this is an area where the Pyramid Method drove me outside of my &#34;single venue&#34;. I was getting some experience taking beginners through our six month introductory course cycle and I felt comfortable with the seven week format of a single course, but I didn&#39;t really know how to teach a good introductory &lt;em&gt;hour&lt;/em&gt;. What happens in the first hour that makes people excited to continue with the practice? Even though I taught that intro hour 4 times every 7 weeks, I decided to look outside of BTC for a way to practice what I call &#34;teaching cold&#34;. Teaching cold is all about teaching the intro to people who are less convinced that tai chi was right for them than the people who had made an effort to come into the school. That&#39;s why, for a while, I continued to say yes to every outreach teaching request we got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put another way, I know a small percentage of people will embrace a ten year practice arc and feel a deep connection to their personal journey. You can&#39;t teach to these people and survive professionally. You have to feed their journey differently, but it&#39;s not the main driver of successful commercial teaching. A much larger percentage of people will feel good about themselves, make a social connection, and enjoy a recreational version of the practice. These are the folks that have to be convinced in one hour and these are the folks the school is built to serve initially. So, I had to go out and find them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are versions of this experiment that you can perform at every stage of the learning process. Changing the format, the audience, and the context helps you build different skills, but I can always plug them back into better teaching at BTC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Put your head down, and get it done.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love that he sums up in one line what is typically a 3-5 year journey for most beginning instructors. Most people get over the initial excitement of being asked to teach in 6-8 months. It&#39;s hard for them to comprehend that coming to the end of September-August school year is the first lap around the track. What I always find interesting, though, is that these same people have yoked themselves with a personal practice that unfolds on that longer timeline. Most of them are excellent practitioners who must have that long view of their own personal development. Why is it that developing commercial teaching skills look so different to them? I can tell you that the ability to change gears with students -- delivering the one hour class then turning around and diving in with ten year veteran students -- has given me the ability to do the same in my practice. I just wish more people would see cultivating their teaching practice as an extension of their personal practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Brookline Tai Chi Fulfills Five Core Human Drives</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/25/how-brookline-tai-chi-fulfills-five-core-human-drives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2011 10:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/25/how-brookline-tai-chi-fulfills-five-core-human-drives/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been on my mind a lot in the past month that Brookline Tai Chi is approaching its 20th anniversary. With a rough calculation, that also means that we are approaching having taught 10,000 students in that time span. I can&#39;t decide which one of those milestones is going to look better on the big banner out front. How about &#34;10,000 People Relaxed&#34;?&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-922&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of reaching these major institutional marks, I&#39;ve also been wondering about the underlying mechanisms that have given the school such an amazing run so far. Surely, with this longevity, there have to be elements of the Brookline Tai Chi experience that transcend any one individual teacher, staff member or student. Then I came across the concept of &lt;a href=&#34;http://book.personalmba.com/core-human-drives/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Core Human Drives, from the Personal MBA by Josh Kaufman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;evp-706dca57ff4f870c95b76810b39ea177-wrap&#34; class=&#34;evp-video-wrap&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;http://book.personalmba.com/evp/framework.php?div_id=evp-706dca57ff4f870c95b76810b39ea177&amp;amp;id=MDItMDUtY29yZS1odW1hbi1kcml2ZXMtMS5tNHY%3D&amp;amp;v=1303391994&amp;amp;profile=default&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
  _evpInit(&#39;MDItMDUtY29yZS1odW1hbi1kcml2ZXMtMS5tNHY=&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you look at the overarching structure of Brookline Tai Chi, you can start to see how a system is in place to fulfill all five of these drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Learn&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The most obvious place to begin is the drive to learn. As a school, that is our most clearly stated goal. People come to us out of curiosity to learn, motivated to master new skills, and get satisfaction by progressing through the curriculum, course-by-course. We have multiple levels in each subject area and so, when you look at our course offerings on paper, the learning progression is very clearly laid out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, we get students whose drive to learn is more refined, and doesn&#39;t map on to the structure of our curriculum. These students can self-regulate the drive to learn more than the average student, and you see them adapting the curriculum to their needs, instead of relying on the external structure of the curriculum. I always have fascinating discussions with them, and many argue for dropping the curriculum model altogether. Having seen a thousands of people interface with our curriculum structure, though, I try to show these students that they are the exception, not the rule, when it comes to needing external guidance in fulfilling the drive to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Defend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As tai chi becomes more well known in the West and the body of research that supports its health benefits grow, we see more and more students who come at their doctor&#39;s recommendation. You could call this the drive to defend, because these people have identified a long-range threat to their health and are taking preventative countermeasures. Students who come in &#34;because my doctor recommended it&#34; are kind of like teachers who just teach the material. If this is their only motivation, it&#39;s going to be a hollow experience. Nobody lasts very long when their sole reason for learning tai chi is someone else&#39;s prescription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we&#39;re going to talk about the drive to defend, you can&#39;t simply say &#34;tai chi will prevent X&#34; or &#34;improves Y&#34; any more than you can make someone enjoy a salad by saying &#34;eat your vegetables&#34;. However, when someone makes the turn to embracing a personal practice, the drive to defend is fulfilled on a different level. For these students, the practice becomes an indispensable part of maintaining their health and wellness because they learn to manage their own energy. This is a very personal process though, and any prescription from a doctor or PT to practice is only incidental to internalizing personal practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as BTC fostering this drive, at best we can be a place where new students see other people modeling this behavior. You can&#39;t tell someone to adopt tai chi as a self-care energy management tool, but you can certainly show them what it looks like by example. In fact, this is one of the intangibles that comes across with the best teachers on day one. Whether or not students realize it, to some degree they are attracted to the teacher&#39;s personal practice as it comes out in their personality, bearing, and energetic demeanor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Acquire&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Because we live in a culture that conditions us to buy stuff in an attempt to fulfill our deeper drives, I&#39;ve always thought the drive to acquire had a funny place at Brookline Tai Chi. It&#39;s there, but it&#39;s pretty refined when you compare it to the urge to buy a shiny piece of plastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, we have a sort of dual economy, with external and internal currency. It&#39;s not uncommon to hear &#34;what class are you in?&#34; or have students who get excited about being in the advanced classes by 2015. What&#39;s more interesting to me is the subtle statement of status when people practice openly at the school. Don&#39;t get me wrong, I don&#39;t think it&#39;s a bad thing at all. In fact, I think the message it sends is, &#34;I&#39;m confident and comfortable with what I know and I&#39;m getting my practice in because this is important to me.&#34; I just think it&#39;s worth identifying this as part of fulfilling the drive to acquire on some level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drive to acquire in the tai chi world also motivates you to acquire &#34;spring in your ligaments&#34; or a 45-minute standing practice. We try to present the practice accordingly, like a giant developmental jigsaw puzzle, part mystery to figure out, part collection of pieces to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Feel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From the first class, we try to center each class around developing a facet of feeling awareness. As you look down the developmental path at the school, &#34;feeling&#34; becomes more and more refined. In the beginning, it can be as simple as noticing the speed at which your body wants to perform the opening movement of the tai chi form. &#34;Slowness&#34; is the first quality people associate with the practice and even appreciating that can have a felt impact on the first day of class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More experienced practitioners describe the learning arc as an ongoing process of feeling into and exploring an &#34;internal landscape&#34;. Bruce Frantzis often describes learning Taoist energy and meditation practices as &#34;awakening internal senses&#34;. From this point of view, the more someone invests in their practice, the more they are engaged in a grand process of feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an institutional point of view, we have to facilitate this process so students can gradually go deeper, but you can never assume that on any given day, for any person, you know what they are feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a class recently, I was showing a group how to do an exercise, not from the point of view of stretching muscles, but by releasing their nerve. It&#39;s a much lighter, gentle approach, but the goal is to perform the same exercise that often feels like a tissue stretch. A few students in class connected with the new approach in a way that made the exercise more accessible than ever before. When we discussed this, though, a couple of people were adamant that the new approach did nothing for them. Instead of convincing them that they should, in fact, feel in new and amazing ways, I was comfortable with them not connecting with this approach. This upset them or at least surprised them, but in order to have people genuinely connect with internal sensations, you have to make room for big misses too. There would be something disingenuous about every single person having a cathartic energetic awakening every hour of every class. In fact, not only would encouraging this kind of experience be dishonest on our part, it&#39;s unhealthy for students to work with their own energy that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I meet more and more people who come in to BTC with &#34;qigong experience&#34;, who have only ever really had these big group &#34;experiences&#34; that are in fact more disassociation and escapist fantasy than healthy energy development. One of the things I like about the way Bruce has always presented the Taoist tradition that he teaches is that, to some degree, it is mundane. The emphasis on slow and steady progress, tethered to concrete physical feeling awareness, is actually very stabilizing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Drive to Bond&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I tend to think that community develops around the edges of practice. When you talk about people connecting to each other through shared experience, the structure at Brookline Tai Chi again plays an interesting role. The quality of the shared experience shifts over time, from external to internal, like all of the other drives we&#39;ve looked at so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, people bond of feeling confused, klutzy, and slightly uncomfortable learning new skills. Since we start all of our beginners together, they can relax about performing to the standards of more experienced students and feel comfortable when they see their classmates fumbling along beside them. As they progress into deeper internal territory, the exercises they do with their classmates are a little more intimate, but they&#39;ve also become comfortable around each other, so it works most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you talk about fulfilling the drive to bond in the classroom, though, you&#39;ve already skipped over several steps in the process that get you into the classroom in the first place. From someone&#39;s very first interaction with the school, the drive to bond is sitting on their shoulder, asking them questions like &#34;Can I see myself there?&#34; or &#34;Is this a place for people like me?&#34; or even &#34;Will there be people there I get along with and who will like me?&#34;. In subtle ways, we have to answer this question 100 times before someone is comfortable enough to do a partner exercise where the instructions are &#34;let go&#34;. The drive to bond constantly asks &#34;Can I trust this place?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, as the program director, as the person who often writes the marketing copy, I&#39;m constantly trying to answer this question. When I walk into the school, eye contact, smiling, and addressing people by name goes a long way to always reinforcing this trust. Showing people that 20 years and 10,000 students later, we have a process that works is another strong indicator. What amazes me is that the weight of the 20 years/10,000 people experience comes through in the first 5 minutes of class. People can tell that there is something solid here, and it puts them at ease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess my one candid admission for this post is that sometimes conveying all this trust, and facilitating this bond makes me uneasy, because sometimes it feels very one-sided. By developing a trusting bond with 200 students at a time, lots of people share personal things with me. I have teachers like this too, where I&#39;m on the other side of the relationship. Without a relationship like this, I don&#39;t think deep learning can take place, but my hesitation is that often, people confuse it for more of a two-way street than it really is. Nothing makes me happier than overhearing two students in serious conversation, and knowing that I&#39;m not the glue that holds their bond together. Community forms around the edges of practice, and the more I can extricate myself from the bonds of that practice over time, the healthier our community is.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 3</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 10:19:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/18/a-teachers-reality-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/stephenagregory/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft&#34; title=&#34;Dripping Faucet&#34; src=&#34;http://farm1.static.flickr.com/69/165377377_6e9eabae34_m.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image courtesy of StephenAGregory&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;So far in this series we&#39;ve been talking about adapting &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;your teaching style&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the structure of your teaching business&lt;/a&gt; to fit the needs of your students. Now I want to look at a trait that all of the best teachers I&#39;ve studied with share, which is a work capacity they can turn on like a fire hose. If your work capacity only comes out like water from a dripping faucet, you won&#39;t be able to be &#34;big enough&#34; to encompass all of your students and their varying needs.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-894&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Work Ethic Isn&#39;t Work Capacity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The first distinction I want to make here is between work ethic and work capacity. It&#39;s the difference between fire and water. Work ethic is a spark, the fire, that drives some of these teachers to be on the road 30 weeks a year, or fly half way around the world to learn from obscure masters. It&#39;s the drive that makes 14 hour days, 6 days seem like a worthwhile pursuit. But ultimately, it&#39;s not what makes these things possible. The spark initiates these crazy journeys, but along the way, work capacity gets built up. Work capacity is more like a habit, and when these guys get up in the morning to teach, it&#39;s like they turn on a faucet and get a steady stream of water to draw from all day long.  Again and again I watch my teaching mentors lead 5-8 hour workshops, continue teaching while every else takes a break for lunch, and then have 2-3 hours of meetings at the end of the day. Knowing them, there was probably a hour of personal practice going on before the teaching day began. So what is it that allows them to go for 12 or 14 hours when most of their students are worn out from the 5 hours of training in the middle?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Logging the Hours, Deliberately&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To say that they are used to teaching is a too simplistic. Yes, step one is to log the teaching hours. Any skill requires that you put in time. There are a couple more dimensions to building your work capacity and in this case we&#39;ll look at teaching for examples of what they are. I&#39;ve written about Geoff Colvin&#39;s deliberate practice model before &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, when I explained part of my motivation for building Trainerfly. Colvin outlines essential elements for getting better at any skill through practice.  When I look at my teaching mentors, they all follow this deliberate practice model in unique ways. Not only have they logged serious teaching hours, but they&#39;ve run the &#34;teaching chunks&#34; experiment, where you create feedback loops and reproduceable teaching moments that allow you to build a student base and your own work capacity simultaneously. Let&#39;s break their down approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bruce Frantzis&#39; Three City Model&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/bruces-frantzis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bruce&lt;/a&gt; has a prolific teaching record, spanning decades and many different format, from one-on-one lessons to workshops packed with 200 students, I think one of the most interesting models he&#39;s taught in is what I&#39;ll call the Three City Model. He did this in the Bay Area in the 1990&#39;s and in New Mexico before that. Some of his most successful certified instructors have also replicated this model. The basic strategy is to offer regular weekly classes in three locations that are near each other, but spread out. The distance criteria are that the locations are in distinct markets, but they are close enough to each other that really dedicated students could travel to any of the three sites to study more than once a week if they wanted. In the Bay Area, this was Berkeley, San Francisco, and Marin County. I&#39;ve contemplated this model in the Boston area, with sites in Cambridge, Boston, and Brookline, for example.  The geographic benefit is striking a balance between accessing a larger potential student base and catering to hard core students simultaneously. There is a financial benefit here too. You can weather the inevitable ups and downs in attendance at one site, because you have the other two.&amp;Acirc;  The benefit for the teacher, though, is that you can experiment with what you teach and how you present it. Separate sites give you the chance to have a more controlled experiment than if you just decided to try a new approach each week at a single site. You can watch two groups evolved over six months or a year and see if a better way to teach emerges on a lot of different levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dr. Eric Cobb, The Constant Presenter&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Whenever I attend a Z Health training, I&#39;m always impressed with the way &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zhealth.net/about-z-health&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Cobb&lt;/a&gt; shifts gears between group teaching and working one-on-one with clients before the seminar begins, during the breaks, and often at the end of the day. He does it as effortlessly as turning up the water pressure on a faucet. The flow is on from the moment he enters the room, cranked up for the group, then down to just the right volume for someone he&#39;s never worked with before and then back up for everyone at once.  I know the he spent years in clinical practice before he started teaching Z Health publicly, and you can see the fine-tuned empathy that comes from years of working one-on-one. There is also something very particular about his rapport with a group that feels like it&#39;s built on all the one-on-one relationships in the room.  When you look at his current teaching schedule, you see over 20-30 events a year, often in the same 3-4 topics. Some of these groups are only 10-12 people and some are capped at 50 attendees. He&#39;s also presented the core concepts of Z Health at professional gatherings, conferences and through the lens of group coaching. Once again, this is the deliberate practice model in action: take the same key concepts and present them in as many different venues as possible -- individual, small group, big group, written, recorded on video.  By teaching anywhere and to everyone, two very interesting things happen. The first is you hone your message and make it scalable (i.e. you know it so well, you know how to present just the right amount of it, from the right perspective, to the right people). The second is sort of a fortunate by-product and that is that you gradually recruit people who also believe in your message. I call that a by-product because most people assume they deserve to have a massive, faithful following as soon as they have an idea in their heads. The message from all of these teachers is exactly the opposite: if you get a big enough fire hose going for long enough, the faithful will follow. Lots of people have ideas. Untested, unhoned ideas are worthless. When you see Dr. Cobb tirelessly flying around the country to successfully build a business and nonchalantly acknowledging that he would likely keep that up for another 5 years to keep on building, you realize that building work capacity is the secret ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bill Ryan&#39;s Healing/Teaching Blend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the traits that all three of these teachers have in common is that they are all gifted hands-on healers. I can attest to this from being under their hands personally, but it was also a key tool they used for developing their businesses early on and growing a dedicated following of students. I&#39;m not sure anyone has blended the two with the intensity Bill Ryan did while he was building up Brookline Tai Chi in the 1990&#39;s, though.  On top of founding, running, and teaching daily at Brookline Tai Chi, Bill relied on private lessons and bodywork to keep the school running and cultivate a core of students at a punishing rate. When I trained with him to take over the operations of the school, he was in a quieter mode, but he would still be there from 10am-10pm almost every day. I&#39;m not sure I ever even saw him stop and eat in those 12 hours bursts...and this was when he was transitioning out. The bigger point here is not about keeping crazy work hours. The point is that by working intensely one-on-one and transitioning to group classes, the different skills each teaching scenario require begin to blend, and that&#39;s a good thing.  When Bill was training me to teach tai chi, we would practice how to give form corrections as hands-on adjustments. We would each start on opposite sides of the room and Bill would say &#34;I&#39;ll meet you in the middle.&#34; By the time I was fumbling through the second or third student, Bill would show up next to me, having corrected 9 or 10. He developed fast eyes and fast hands that could make meaningful corrections, largely due to the number of hours doing private bodywork. While I wasn&#39;t a trained bodyworker, he encouraged me to do as many private lessons as I could. He swore by them as a way to hone your teaching, just because you had more space and time to play with adjustments and get immediate feedback from students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Create Deliberate Practice Moments&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What I&#39;ve learned from these guys is that you create the opportunities to hone your teaching. I don&#39;t see where they are today and think &#34;I want to be up on stage teaching 150 people&#34;. I think about their process and how I can create the teaching moments to steadily grow my capacity.  Bruce likes to talk about the &#34;20 year overnight success&#34; when he&#39;s talking about learning tai chi, but as a teacher who now attracts hundreds of students to a single event, he&#39;s a model for this same approach in teaching. He often points out how this message doesn&#39;t really come across in our culture, unless you really look for it. He&#39;ll talk about a sports movie, with a little kid throwing the ball around in his backyard, who by the next scene is transformed into the World Series-winning major league pitcher. What&#39;s the message there? Hang on to a distant dream and it will magically happen? That&#39;s why I initially wanted to make the decision between work ethic and work capactiy.  The ethic, the idea, the spark -- that&#39;s important and necessary, but it&#39;s the inspiration. Each of these teachers has taken their unique inspiration or aspiration and slowly, over time, developed the capacity to steadily build toward that image. You need a slow, steady fuel to make that journey, more like a flowing river than a short burst of flame.&amp;Acirc;  So take any opportunity you can get to deliberately develop your work capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 2</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2011 14:33:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/11/a-teachers-reality-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; title=&#34;Broadway Bridge&#34; src=&#34;http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2571/3817456902_962b9e082a.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; of this series, we talked about the social nature of wanting to belong to something bigger than yourself as one possible drive for learning tai chi. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-868&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The social drive is a major aid teachers can rely on to build their base of students. Another one, that we&#39;ll discuss here is our habitual drive, i.e. we are creatures of habit. That can be a good thing when it comes to maintaining a student base, but it is also the first major hurdle you have to clear as a teacher when it comes to getting new students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Habitual Inertia&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For some reason, it&#39;s easier to see inertia in other people, and attribute it to laziness or stupidity, than it is to appreciate the forces of habit working on ourselves. I&#39;ve had many conversations with sullen teachers who moan about students not coming to class. Whenever I hear them complain, I always wonder this: &#34;What&#39;s getting in the way of you offering classes six days a week? You know, it would be a lot easier for people to come to class if there almost always was a class for them to come to.&#34; And of course, these failing teachers throw up a long list of reasons why they can&#39;t offer more classes. This is the part that always stumps me: For the most part, the very same reasons they give for not offering more classes are the same reasons that make it hard for people to come to a class when it&#39;s only offered once a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s damn hard for people to get out and do things on a regular basis. How many different activities like that do you participate in? Survey 10 friends and ask them. I&#39;m guessing it&#39;s not too many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s why whenever someone actually walks through the door at Brookline Tai Chi and is ready to try out a class, it&#39;s a huge gift. They&#39;ve overcome so many barriers -- they&#39;re breaking their current routine, our schedules match, they&#39;ve done research and are motivated to try something new.&amp;Acirc;  And here&#39;s the thing, how many of those steps can I do for them with an advertising campaign? The answer is, approximately half.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, inertia can go one of two ways. The inertia of your own daily routine can keep you from participating in something new, or it can be the glue that holds together the things you are actively engaged in. From the point of view of running a school, we want to use the glue-side of inertia to keep people engaged, but we also have to be vigilant about finding the cracks in a new student&#39;s inertia, and help them shift into new routines and habits. I don&#39;t pretend to be an expert at doing this, but I know that there are two sides to this change process, the structural and the inspirational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Structural and The Inspirational&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The structural and the inspirational support each other. When you come to your first class and feel relaxed and energized after an hour of tai chi, that&#39;s inspirational. If there are three more times that week when the class fits your schedule and you know you can come back, that&#39;s a structural, systemic fact of how the business runs, and it supports the inspirational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, if class met once a week, more often than not, something comes up to break the new pattern you are trying to establish. You have fun on week one, you start to see yourself doing tai chi after a couple of weeks, but then you have to miss a week, and you don&#39;t make time to practice, and slowly, the other pulls in your life exert themselves, and your chance to make tai chi a habit slips away. It&#39;s not like I see this happen once in a while, I see it happen 30-40% of the time with new students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, you need to find the blend of structures and routines that support the moments of inspiration that you are out to engineer. The most successful teachers I know have this blend working for them. When teachers fail to build a student following, it&#39;s often because they don&#39;t balance these elements well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why a Structuralist Teacher Fails&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Structuralist teachers say things like &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;this week we learn this move and next week we learn that move and in 10 years you will benefit from the practice because Tai Chi is hard&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. I hate this approach. It&#39;s dry and sounds like &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;eat your vegetables.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Do you think any of your students who fought through all their habitual inertia want to wind up in your class only to be hit over the head with a boring, drawn-out curriculum that&#39;s more lecture than doing? You might get off on that, and I guess your one or two other students will too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not that the Structurists actually want to bore their students into relaxation. It&#39;s that they&#39;ve lost sight of the students through the mountains of information they&#39;ve combed through, first as a practitioner, then in preparing to be a teacher. They can see a sequence of material, but they can&#39;t see the material from the student&#39;s point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structuralists of the more self-absorbed variety thrive around people with similar experience in the practice. When they can talk to someone who is at the same level, they are very clear and compelling. The problem is that they can&#39;t see what&#39;s going on outside of themselves, in their students, so they fall back on external structure to teach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structuralists with less experience face the problem of not being able to motivate or inspire students. They come across as dogmatic and hollow, because they haven&#39;t seen far enough down the developmental pathway to come back and tell new students about it. Instead, they rely on the external structure to string people along, because they are also in the early stages of that process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where the Inspirationalists Fall Apart&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, you might think the antidote to the Structuralist is to turn on the charm and engage students in the moment as much as possible. We&#39;ve seen the all-inspiration, all-the-time trip too, and this fails because students don&#39;t have the context to understand the process they are going through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is a forest-for-the-trees problem, the Inspirationalists get students scratching at the bark, feeling it, and experiencing it so much that the students don&#39;t even know it&#39;s a tree. They just happen upon whatever tree the Inspirationalist feels like exploring that day. I see this tendency in long-time practitioners who have become looser about what they do in their own practice. They forget what they went through to develop their practice, and now they think they can teach people without using any process at all. It just leaves students confused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Inspirationalists lose students because they don&#39;t provide enough context and a clear structured process for working through the material. I find this is a real shame because all of the good traditions have a clear developmental path. This is what has allowed them to thrive over centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really gets me about Inspirationalists, though, is that they burn out and fall apart much faster than the Structuralists. They can stoke a lot of excitement in their students in the moment, but they&#39;re inconsistent. Maybe the have a good month and they&#39;re on a roll, but can you count on them to teach through a full year or even six months? Usually, you can&#39;t even get 3-4 times a week out of them. It&#39;s a classic loud burst vs. slow boil mentality. To be a successful teacher, and build a stable following of students, you can&#39;t be the flash in the pan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Consistent Inspiration or Inspired Structuralism&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So that leaves us somewhere in between. The Structuralists have a steadiness and consistency that makes them reliably available to students. The Inspirationalists create a spark that shows students what&#39;s possible. If you really want to build a student base, you&#39;ve got to work on both levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My teaching mentor, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.billryanenergyarts.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bill Ryan&lt;/a&gt;, figured out how to make both of these levels work at the same time. He has an artful blend of structural and inspirational teaching. As Brookline Tai Chi evolved under Bill&#39;s guidance, a large, university-like curriculum emerged, but he didn&#39;t fall into the Structuralist trap. Instead, every hour of every class was an engineered opportunity to find one-on-one inspirational moments for students. People felt like the practice was tailored to their needs as they received personal corrections. This is how you use structure to set up inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill also used inspiration to infuse structure with meaning. He always provided a narrative for where you were in the developmental process. Working your way through a structured curriculum feels like going on a journey when you use Inspirationalist teaching to tell the a story about the process. Every step along the path becomes a brief scene in a larger adventure. In that way, you can sustain inspired teaching of weeks and months and years. Each hour of class feels like picking up your favorite novel &lt;em&gt;(because the book is about YOU)&lt;/em&gt; and diving back into the story. Personal practice becomes writing the next paragraph and over the years you can look back on whole chapters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, teaching or running a school isn&#39;t very different from your own personal practice. Every time you go to practice, you address the particular form of the practice, and the art in your practice is about finding the deeper internal connection alive inside the form. Form without connection is hollow and connection without form is meaningless. Teaching a group for an hour or shepherding a student body through another school year is the same process at the core, just applied to different scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(image courtesy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/nickweinrauch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;nickweinrauch&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Teacher&#39;s Reality, Part 1</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2011 10:42:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/04/a-teachers-reality-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, Energy Arts Instructor Jess O&#39;Brien was in town, &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/blog/five-elements-hsing-i&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;teaching at BTC&lt;/a&gt;. We got to spend some time together and talk about teaching, studying with different teachers, and trying to run a teaching business. One thing that we came back to again and again was how difficult it is to build up a student base. I think I know why.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-852&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;People are Lazy, Social, and Creatures of Habit&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, I know it sounds like a mean thing to say, but in the words of Stanford psychologist BJ Fogg, people are &#34;lazy, social, and creatures of habit.&#34; Rather than looking at this as a moral judgment, take it as a reality of the way we are wired to operate in the world. In fact, if you look at studies about willpower and motivation or start to research how our nervous system functions, you begin to see that these qualities are survival responses that drive efficient behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, I know plenty of teachers who love to take the moral high ground about how their students should behave, who, in fact, have no students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start to accept that habit drives lazy, social student behavior more than anything else, some interesting implications arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, people want to be a part of a school just as much as they want to learn the material. Brookline Tai Chi is almost 20 years old and people identify with the institution. I wrote about a &lt;a href=&#34;../2010/12/06/your-marketing-universe/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&#34;marketing universe&#34;&lt;/a&gt;, where students orbit the school at different levels, i.e. your hard core students or the ones that drift in and out. Brookline Tai Chi is a planet, exerting major gravitational pull for an entire community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the larger Energy Arts community, though, BTC is the exception, not the rule. So what does Jess do about this? He and his teaching partner Isaac have one night a week to teach. How can they create a feeling of belonging to a school? While they don&#39;t have a visible physical space as a symbol of their school, they can draw on other symbols. Whenever Jess comes to teach at BTC, he brings obscure articles about martial arts and usually has 3-4 rare martial arts books in tow. A self-described martial arts nerd, Jess can go on and on about history, theory, and training. This is huge. While students might not be able to say, &#34;I belong to a school with a physical address&#34;, they can certainly say, &#34;I belong to a tradition.&#34; Jess and Isaac both use language that points to a larger lineage. This goes a long way for making students feel like they belong to something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infusing the language you use with a bigger sense of a community or a tradition is one key step you can take. You will also need to tell a developmental story to your students, so they understand the larger process they are going through. We&#39;ll explore this more later in the series when we look at people who have mastered the blend of systematic offerings that feel fresh and new and inspired every time they teach them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s also worth point out that &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the language you use&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; doesn&#39;t just mean &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the language you use in the classroom&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. It&#39;s &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the language you use everywhere&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;, in print, on the web, in emails to students. Absent a physical space that people can belong to, or even to support it, you need language that also triggers this sense of belonging. At Brookline Tai Chi, our space is an asset because it&#39;s such a clear symbol for people, but I think you can create other symbols (for less than $10,000/month!) that do the same thing. When I talked to Jess about it, I encouraged him to capture the way he talks about martial arts. If he can make everything around the classes sound and feel the same way, people will be eager to participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sense of belonging we are talking about here points to the &#34;social&#34; nature of people. Having a physical space for people to train touches on the &#34;habitual&#34; part as well. In the next post in this series, we&#39;ll look at how you create a teaching space that balances the need for consistency with the need to inspire students every single time they come to class.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>