<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi-chuan on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi-chuan/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi-chuan on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/tai-chi-chuan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 11:14:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>In his new book, the Harvard Medical School Guide to Tai Chi, Dr. Peter Wayne lays out the &#34;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; to help us understand the interface between traditional Tai Chi practice and the Western biomedical paradigm.
As the Research Director of the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, jointly based at Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, and the founder of the Tree of Life Tai Chi Center, Peter blends more than three decades of teaching experience with ongoing inquiry into what makes Tai Chi an effective medical intervention.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend last night about standing qigong and different meditation traditions that we had both tried.
When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoid Bad Tai Chi Posture</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/14/avoid-bad-tai-chi-posture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 17:12:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/14/avoid-bad-tai-chi-posture/</guid>
      <description>Tai Chi has the potential to solve many common posture-related problems, but only if you follow the correct Tai Chi principles.
Specifically, you want to pay attention to the body alignments that unify the arms, legs, and spine, creating effortless openness throughout the skeletal system.
In Tai Chi, the way you hold your neck and head and release the pelvis into the legs are the exact opposite of what those of us who sit all day do.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>