<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tai-chi-chuan on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi-chuan/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in tai-chi-chuan on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/tai-chi-chuan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2013 11:14:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/30/the-8-active-ingredients-of-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft  wp-image-4644&#34; alt=&#34;HMS guide to Tai Chi&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/05/HMS-guide-to-Tai-Chi1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;120&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; In his new book, the Harvard Medical School Guide to Tai Chi, &lt;a title=&#34;Living between the Lab and the Classroom with Dr. Peter Wayne&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/01/11/living-between-the-lab-and-the-classroom-with-dr-peter-wayne/&#34;&gt;Dr. Peter Wayne&lt;/a&gt; lays out the &#34;8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi&#34; to help us understand the interface between traditional Tai Chi practice and the Western biomedical paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Research Director of the Osher Center for Integrative Medicine, jointly based at Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, and the founder of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.treeoflifetaichi.com/instructors.html&#34;&gt;Tree of Life Tai Chi Center&lt;/a&gt;, Peter blends more than three decades of teaching experience with ongoing inquiry into what makes Tai Chi an effective medical intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this episode of Qigong Radio, we explore the development of the 8 Active Ingredients and how help translate Tai Chi into a Western context&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 8 Active Ingredients of Tai Chi are:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awareness, Mindfulness, Focused Attention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intention, Belief, Expectation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic Structural Integration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active Relaxation of Mind and Body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aerobic Exercise, Musculoskeletal Strengthening, and Flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natural, Freer Breathing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Interaction and Community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embodied Spirituality, Philosophy, and Ritual&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I asked Peter to explain how he understands Tai Chi practice through these 8 ingredients and how they are related to each other. While there are many ways to explain what Tai Chi is, this framework has to explain Tai Chi to a Western medical audience, making each element of the practice related to biomedical and psychological principles rooted in evidence-based medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter tells us what was easy to convey and where the Tai Chi principles were more esoteric, but important to explain through the framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also makes the case for greater medical literacy amongst Tai Chi teachers and practitioners because, as Tai Chi research gets more sophisticated, the feedback loop between what gets studied and how Tai Chi is defined will get tighter and tighter. If you&#39;re concerned with the legacy of Tai Chi in the West, you need to be a part of this conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the podcast for all that and a great sense for Peter&#39;s insight, generosity, and caring as a practitioner and leader in the Tai Chi research field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poll: What Does It Feel Like When You Meditate?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 09:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/24/poll-what-does-it-feel-like-when-you-meditate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-4629&#34; alt=&#34;help-browser&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/05/help-browser-150x150.png&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; height=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend last night about &lt;a title=&#34;Guide to Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/exercises/guide-to-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;standing qigong&lt;/a&gt; and different &lt;a title=&#34;3 Layers of Neigong Practice and Taoist Meditation with Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/01/29/3-layers-of-neigong-practice-and-taoist-meditation-with-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;meditation traditions&lt;/a&gt; that we had both tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say &#34;meditation&#34; in this context, we were including all practices like breathing for relaxation, Tai Chi, qigong, and sitting practices too. Part of what I&#39;d like to hear from you (see below) is how you define &#34;meditation&#34; in a way that&#39;s practical and part of your everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many different reasons, on any given day, that we sought out the practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To clear our heads of racing thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To more deeply relax the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To explore layers of the mind and emotions that aren&#39;t so obvious during our normal busy days.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It seems like we had really similar reasons to practice, but I was left wondering if it &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; similar when we practice. What are the sensations that tell you you&#39;re on the right track? It seems like we want to end up in the same place, but are we taking the same road to get there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-r7p4r3&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/r7p4r3&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var r7p4r3;(function(d, t) {&lt;br /&gt;
var s = d.createElement(t), options = {&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;r7p4r3&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;autoResize&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;height&#39;:&#39;554&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;async&#39;:true,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,&lt;br /&gt;
&#39;ssl&#39;:true};&lt;br /&gt;
s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;;&lt;br /&gt;
s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() {&lt;br /&gt;
var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return;&lt;br /&gt;
try { r7p4r3 = new WufooForm();r7p4r3.initialize(options);r7p4r3.display(); } catch (e) {}};&lt;br /&gt;
var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr);&lt;br /&gt;
})(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoid Bad Tai Chi Posture</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/14/avoid-bad-tai-chi-posture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2013 17:12:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/05/14/avoid-bad-tai-chi-posture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tai Chi has the potential to solve many common posture-related problems, but only if you follow &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/02/10/the-how-what-and-why-of-tai-chi-practice/&#34;&gt;the correct Tai Chi principles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, you want to pay attention to the body alignments that unify the arms, legs, and spine, creating effortless openness throughout the skeletal system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tai Chi, the way you hold your neck and head and release the pelvis into the legs are the exact opposite of what those of us who sit all day do. This is good news if you want to change your posture, but tough, because you probably spend lots of time in detrimental sitting positions each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the key postural elements of Tai Chi that rectify:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stiff Necks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eye Strain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compressed Lower Spine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unstable or Weak Legs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
http://youtu.be/4XskxdZbKyY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the video, you need to constantly avoid collapsed spinal posture and find length in every movement. Obviously this can be a big challenge when you are first learning Tai Chi. Your focus initially should be on learning the movements and separately working on the fundamentals, &lt;a title=&#34;Basic Training: Focus on Your Kwa Squat&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/03/11/basic-training-focus-on-your-kwa-squat/&#34;&gt;especially leg alignments and kwa squats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the movement patterns become more comfortable, you can integrate healthy alignment principles, initially ignoring the details of the moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For more experienced practitioners:&lt;/strong&gt; All of the details of the movements should &lt;em&gt;enhance&lt;/em&gt; the way Tai Chi opens the body by more precisely loosening the soft tissue, expanding the joints, bringing spring to the ligaments, and relaxing the nervous system. If you find that &#34;getting it right&#34; ever sends you away from feeling looser, stronger, and more relaxed, something&#39;s off about your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>