<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Page on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>https://dankleiman.com/page/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Page on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 09:19:08 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Lesson 1: Crown of the Head</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/lesson-1-crown-of-the-head</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 09:19:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/lesson-1-crown-of-the-head</guid>
      <description>Download Lesson 1: Crown of the Head here.
(right click to save)
In your first workout, give yourself plenty of time to settle in.
We&#39;ll use the crown of the head as an anchor point in future workouts as well: each time you stand, you&#39;ll return to this point as a way to focus the mind, gather your energy, and start the process of scanning down through the body.
Each week, I will send you a new workout via email.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Standing Qigong as a Gateway to Meditative Stillness</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/the-power-of-standing-qigong-as-a-gateway-to-meditative-stillness</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2014 22:53:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/the-power-of-standing-qigong-as-a-gateway-to-meditative-stillness</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Complete Energy Gates Dissolving Series</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/the-complete-energy-gates-dissolving-series</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2014 22:04:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/the-complete-energy-gates-dissolving-series</guid>
      <description>The easiest way to work through the Energy Gates Dissolving Series - like having a teacher by your side the whole time!
Over the next 21 weeks, you will do a complete pass through all of the major Energy Gates of your body.
Week-by-week, as you clear the gates, you will find new space inside the body, release bound or stuck chi, and realign the twists, kinks, and compressions that warp the body -- physically and energetically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Standing Qigong as a Gateway to Meditative Stillness</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/the-power-of-standing-qigong-as-a-gateway-to-meditative-stillness</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 14:17:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/the-power-of-standing-qigong-as-a-gateway-to-meditative-stillness</guid>
      <description>Qigong instructor Dan Kleiman practices Standing Qigong to relax his body and mind and strengthen the flow of chi throughout his energy system.
--- Free Practice Resources Available, See Details Below ---
Standing Qigong is a gentle, yet powerful way to cultivate your internal energy. From the ancient Chinese point of view, an abundance of internal energy, that circulates cleanly throughout your body, leads to a vibrant life.
When you practice Standing Qigong, you:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Start Your Standing Meditation Practice Now</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/start-your-standing-meditation-practice-now</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 13:26:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/start-your-standing-meditation-practice-now</guid>
      <description>Basic Standing Qigong Posture
Congratulations on starting your standing meditation practice!
As you can see from the picture on the right, &#34;standing&#34; is easy. Just begin in a relaxed, arms-by-the-sides posture, with your eyes closed.
Pay attention to these 3 important postural points:
 Unlock the knees and hips. Let the weight fall into the arches of each foot, not back to the heels. Relax the chest and muscles of the face and breath smoothly, without a lot of force or effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates Dissolving Series</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 14:59:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series</guid>
      <description>Before you begin the process of dissolving the Energy Gates, you should read Bruce Frantzis&#39; Energy Gates book or get instruction on basic standing alignment from an Energy Arts Instructor.
I also recommend that you can stand comfortably for 15-20 minutes using one of the following methods:
 Just Feeling Scanning and Sinking Asking these 3 Questions

Dissolving the Gates
When you set out to do a complete pass through all the gates, it roughly breaks down into a six-month project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Five Keys to Taoist Energy Arts</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/the-five-keys-to-taoist-energy-arts</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 15:54:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/the-five-keys-to-taoist-energy-arts</guid>
      <description>Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel recently released his &#34;Five Keys to the Taoist Energy Arts.&#34; If I had to put together a complete foundational program for learning qigong or Tai Chi, this is exactly what I&#39;d include.
What&#39;s inside the Five Keys:
 Breathing Energy Work Standing Meditation Smooth Circular Movement.

In short, all the foundations for a great qigong program!
As you know from many episodes of Qigong Radio, I turn to Paul whenever I want a clear and structured explanation of a dimension of my practice (check out these episodes on body development and meditation).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Set</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-set</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 15:51:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-set</guid>
      <description>Join Tai Chi Master-Instructor Don Ethan Miller in a ground-breaking new program to increase your physical stability and overall well-being: The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance DVD and eBook Set.

Each exercise and key Tai Chi concept is explained in detail and organized in a safe, easy-to-follow progression of levels.
By practicing the 3 Levels of Tai Chi Balance Training, you will soon embody the Tai Chi principles of Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Yin-Yang Balance, through such ancient exercises as:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance eBook</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-ebook</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 15:49:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-ebook</guid>
      <description>Join Tai Chi Master-Instructor Don Ethan Miller in a ground-breaking new program to increase your physical stability and overall well-being: The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance eBook.

Each exercise and key Tai Chi concept is explained in detail and organized in a safe, easy-to-follow progression of levels.
By practicing the 3 Levels of Tai Chi Balance Training, you will soon embody the Tai Chi principles of Rooting, Central Equilibrium, and Yin-Yang Balance, through such ancient exercises as:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dragon and Tiger Online Course</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/dragon-and-tiger-online-course</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 15:46:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/dragon-and-tiger-online-course</guid>
      <description>I recommend Dragon and Tiger Qigong for anyone who is looking for a core qigong set to anchor their daily practice. Here&#39;s why:



Learning to circulate the energy that runs your physical body will make you more relaxed and healthier, while giving you a calming boost of energy that carries you through your day.
Update: My first teacher and Energy Arts Senior Instructor Bill Ryan now teaches this material as an online course.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paul Cavel&#39;s Inner Quest Journal</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/paul-cavels-inner-quest-journal</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 15:44:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/paul-cavels-inner-quest-journal</guid>
      <description>Each month, Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel publishes a newsletter packed full of articles about neigong, qigong, Tai Chi, and Ba Gua.If you want to deeply understand the philosophy underlying your practice, you&#39;ll love his Inner Quest Journal.
Each issue includes:
 Articles, interviews and/or podcasts on nei gong energy arts, I Ching arts and Tao meditation The supporting roles of nature, nutrition and community, such as coverage of Five Element Theory, to boost practice results Taoist creation, cosmology and I Ching studies East meets West perspectives on specific injuries, including examining prevention and healing protocols Article contributions from experienced internal energy arts and meditation instructors Inspiring personal stories Your personal questions answered by Paul</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Tai Chi Rooting</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/introduction-to-tai-chi-rooting</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 15:42:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/introduction-to-tai-chi-rooting</guid>
      <description>In &#34;An Introduction to Rooting and Stability,&#34; you will be introduced to the ancient Chinese method for gaining, or re-gaining, one of life&#39;s simplest yet most essential treasures--the gift of balance.
These Tai Chi Balance Exercises by themselves form a beginning program that will produce a noticeable improvement in your sense of being grounded, or connected to the earth, centrally stabilized around a vertical axis, and able to change visual orientation while remaining balanced.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Springy Knees in Tai Chi</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/springy-knees-in-tai-chi</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2013 13:22:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/springy-knees-in-tai-chi</guid>
      <description>If you remember the original Star Wars&amp;reg; movie it is probably easy to remember the &amp;lsquo;droid C3PO and his strange gait. This android lacked the proper joint arrangement to move in a proper way, which made his walk seem stiff and difficult. But while his spine seemed stiff his knees worked quite well. The reason for this seeming anomaly is that the proper functioning of the knee is critical to effective movement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Will a Fall Cost You?</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/what-will-a-fall-cost-you</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 18:32:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/what-will-a-fall-cost-you</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Qigong Exercises to Open the Spine</title>
      <link>https://dankleiman.com/qigong-exercises-to-open-the-spine</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 16:41:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dankleiman.com/qigong-exercises-to-open-the-spine</guid>
      <description>People fall. The fall might be caused by a slip or trip or even an inner ear imbalance. Normally when we think someone falling we think of either the elderly or very young children still finding their balance. But according to the World Health Organization (WHO) falls are much more of a problem for all ages than most people realize. The organization said:
 &amp;middot; Nearly half a million people globally die from falls each year.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>