<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>energy-management on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/energy-management/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in energy-management on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/energy-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Run on Empty</title>
      <link>/2011/08/01/dont-run-on-empty/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2011 08:02:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/01/dont-run-on-empty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Steve Prefontaine in the 5000m preliminary heat of the US Olympic time trials, July 6, 1972, Hayward Field, Eugene Oregon by The Happy Rower, on Flickr&#34; href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/thehappyrower/5831042252/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; src=&#34;http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3601/5831042252_142150c2ed_z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Steve Prefontaine in the 5000m preliminary heat of the US Olympic time trials, July 6, 1972, Hayward Field, Eugene Oregon&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;485&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;Nobody moves through life with exactly the same amount of energy. Do you know how much you have to draw on? Do you know how to replenish your reserves? &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1709&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In chi gung, the energetic reserves you are born with are called your &#34;pre-birth chi&#34;. What you cultivate as you go through life, using practices like chi gung,&amp;Acirc;  is called &#34;post-birth chi&#34;. You use the combination of what you are born with and what you develop to run your body and your mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;But the science of energy development (chi gung) is not just about how much juice you can put out in a short sprint. Work and rest are two sides of the same coin and chi gung will actually help you get better at resting as well. We don&#39;t usually pride ourselves on being good at resting, but wouldn&#39;t you like to feel more refreshed when you wake up in the morning? Or get over a cold in 1 day instead of 3? Or be ready to take on your next big creative project after a few weeks off instead of a few months? When you rest better, you can sprint again SOONER as well as FASTER.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;So the next time you look around and see other people sprinting past you in life, don&#39;t strain to catch up to their speed. Instead, go deeper into your own work/rest cycle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>