<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>online-learning on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/online-learning/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in online-learning on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/online-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>5 YouTube Qigong Videos You Can Actually Learn From</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 09:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/11/28/youtube-qigong-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure you&#39;ve spent time looking around YouTube for qigong and tai chi videos. According to their website, people upload 24 hours of video to YouTube &lt;em&gt;every minute&lt;/em&gt;! No doubt you&#39;ve seen some crazy stuff. So how do you sift through all of it and more importantly, are there any qigong videos on YouTube worth watching?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is, of course there are. And I&#39;ve put together a list of 5 good ones to get you started. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-2522&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to Practice with YouTube Qigong Videos&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As you will see from the videos below, there is a blend of instructional content, guided practice, and demonstration. You have to get creative when you are borrowing from a source like online video to boost your practice. Sometimes you will just do a quick check-in. Sometimes you will sit and watch an entire lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&#39;t recommend trying to do your practice and darting back and forth to the computer at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the video has good audio guidance that can run in the background, great. Otherwise, just watch it once or twice and then go and practice. I&#39;ll try to point out key places in each video where you can see skilled practitioners demonstrating things they aren&#39;t necessarily talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This introduction to standing by Lam Kam Chuen is one of my favorite overviews of the practice. He talks a little bit about the background of the practice and gives just enough instruction to get you started. If you already have a standing practice, it&#39;s worth watching because you can revisit some of the overarching reasons to do this qigong method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/y07FauHYlmg?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/StandStillBeFit&#34;&gt;The entire channel&lt;/a&gt; is worth watching once you&#39;ve gone through the introductory clip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Simple Circling Hands&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The natural transition from standing practice is to start repetitive movements. In standing, you tune into internal rhythms that only become obvious because there is no external movement. Circling Hands is a great bridge because your external movements are simple enough that you can let the internal rhythms drive them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch as &lt;a title=&#34;Q&amp;amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/&#34;&gt;Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; performs Circling Hands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/GJvhji8vxLQ?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most important thing you can get from this YouTube qigong video is the way his whole body opens and closes, pulsing from the center, outward.&amp;Acirc; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exploring Internal Flows&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the next video, &lt;a title=&#34;Robert Tangora on the Importance of Integration in Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/07/robert-tangora-on-the-importance-of-integration-in-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Robert Tangora&lt;/a&gt; explains how to activate the two main energy flows that run your body: Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth. He teaches two different exercises to highlight these flows. Like Paul&#39;s demonstration above, if you practice these exercises you will begin to feel the &#34;pulls&#34; through the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s worth pointing out that while you may or may not be able to feel what he&#39;s describing right away, every teacher I&#39;ve ever had insists that you need to develop the internal sensitivity to these subtle movements through a standing or sitting practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/CAIep8SOpLw?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transitioning into More Movement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Each mode of qigong practice gives you access to something different. &#34;Quiet&#34; practices like standing qigong or sitting meditation allow you to develop your internal awareness with as little physical coordination as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving practices do two things: they develop rhythm and they challenge your ability to maintain internal focus because of the ever-changing external conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these next two videos, we&#39;re going to introduce more movement, first by adding weight-shifting and turning, then by looking at the qigong set with the most complicated external form: Tai Chi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try this &#34;Rolling the Ball&#34; exercise to see if you can maintain some of the internal awareness primed in the earlier qigong videos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/X8TNCbMwig8?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this last video isn&#39;t designed to be instructional or a follow-along practice. Instead, I want you to watch it and see if you can pick up some of the things we&#39;ve looked at in the other YouTube qigong videos in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see internal continuity? Opening and closing? Center-to-Periphery and Heaven-to-Earth flows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The secret to training your eyes to see more subtle movement patterns is to look at someone&#39;s movements, in this case Tai Chi master &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taichimaster.com/&#34;&gt;Bruce Frantzis&lt;/a&gt;, and try to feel inside your own body what he must be doing to create those movements.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/ocHe6dbR4ig?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this post gives you some ideas about how to use YouTube qigong videos to improve your own practice. Got any favorites that I&#39;ve left out? Be sure to let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30 Day Better Breathing Challenge</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 10:17:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/07/04/30-day-better-breathing-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&#39;ve been talking a lot about two things, &lt;a title=&#34;Follow the 20-20-20 Rule for Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/21/follow-the-20-20-20-rule-for-better-breathing/&#34;&gt;improving your breathing&lt;/a&gt; to give you a &lt;a title=&#34;Disrupt the Stress Cycle with Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/26/disrupt-the-stress-cycle-with-better-breathing/&#34;&gt;major energy/relaxation boost&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a title=&#34;Building Better Practice Tools&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/05/16/building-better-practice-tools/&#34;&gt;developing tools&lt;/a&gt; that help you &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/?p=1494&#34;&gt;follow-through on your home practice&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve even created an online course with all the information you need to cultivate better breathing habits: &lt;a title=&#34;Better Breathing&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/courses/better-breathing/&#34;&gt;Better Breathing&lt;/a&gt;. The biggest lesson we learned as we talked to BTC students&amp;Acirc;  was that the best time to use reminders to trigger your practice was when you were invested in learning a new skill.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1510&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; When you&#39;re going through a period of sustained practice, integrating stuff you&#39;ve learned before, you need external tools less. However, when you shift back into learning mode and set a specific training goal, getting extra, regular motivation from an outside source can push you over the line from wanting to learn something to ingraining it as a habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to cultivate better breathing habits is a great example of skill building that benefits from extra stimulation. As I explain in the breathing course, there is a clear threshold with your breathing practice that you need to cross to make a lasting impact on your habits. In one sense, the secret to mastering better breathing habits is just putting in the time. The steps along the path to better breathing aren&#39;t always exciting or immediately gratifying, but crossing the breathing threshold puts you into a different world where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;each breath feels deep and nourishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your insides feel smooth and relaxed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you radiate a sense of well-being and easy-to-sustain energy throughout your day&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These are the kinds of things you only notice once you&#39;ve had them and lost them. The biggest challenge of cultivating these qualities is that you can&#39;t do it in one single act of will power. You need sustained, regular practice to take you over the threshold. The good news is that you can leverage external tools, instead of just will power, to carry you over the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&#39;s why I&#39;ve created the 30 Day Breathing Challenge. If you want to hit a new depth of practice in the next month, I will give you the tools to get there. For a limited time, I&#39;m giving away my online breathing course (normally $29), for free. All you have to do is sign-up for the 30-Day Challenge using the form below. I will send you daily practice reminders and weekly video instruction drawn from the course. In 30 days, you&#39;re going to see a major shift in your personal practice. Ready?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://eepurl.com/xORb&#34;&gt;Sign up for the 30 Day Challenge here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gods Playing in the Clouds at Brookline Tai Chi</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/20/gods-playing-in-the-clouds-at-brookline-tai-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2011 08:09:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/20/gods-playing-in-the-clouds-at-brookline-tai-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re running a little experiment at Brookline Tai Chi to see if providing students with practice reminders, &lt;em&gt;ahead of time&lt;/em&gt;, will make them more comfortable starting the Gods Playing in the Clouds chi gung class this summer. &lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1589&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/blog/new-summer-gods-playing-clouds-chi-gung-dan-kleiman&#34;&gt;Read about the course here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/whzHtISshho?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;349&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/whzHtISshho?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set is made up of six, repetitive spherical movements and I think, if students have a chance to practice the basic shapes before the class starts, they will be much more comfortable and ready to learn the nuances of the internal work that goes into these basic shapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve created a basic instructional series to help students get ready and I hope they will use it as a reference point once the course begins to clear up any choreography confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll see!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A with Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 12:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/06/09/energy-arts-senior-instructor-paul-cavel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-1529&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_Bagua-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Paul Cavel is an Energy Arts Senior Instructor based in London. He teaches regular weekly classes there, but he&#39;s also been traveling all over the UK and Europe for years teaching workshops, including annual week-long retreats in Crete. I talked to Paul a little bit about his background in Tai Chi, neigong, and Ba Gua and asked him for some practice advice for a group of students who just completed a series at BTC on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little bit about how you got started studying these arts. Who were some of your first influential teachers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After a motorcycle accident in 1986, I started studying Yang style tai chi to heal my injuries. When the teacher left, the class naturally gravitated towards the Water method neigong practices as taught by my main teacher, Bruce Frantzis. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve been hooked ever since.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-1528&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over the last 30 years, Bruce has taught in so many different places and formats. When and how did you first start studying with him?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first encounter with Bruce was in a London seminar on the spiraling energy body. Of course, that material really opened my eyes to what qigong could do! When I subsequently lived with Bruce some years later in 1994-1995, my passion for bagua was ignited in his weekly classes. I got in by the skin of my teeth as one of the last students he let into the class&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Since you&#39;ve studied with Bruce, have you had other influential teachers? Have you studied complementary arts that you bring into your teaching?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve attended the odd seminar with a reputable Chinese master or two, including a couple of months of early morning training in the park with a master in California. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve also attended events hosted by the Tai Chi Union of Great Britain where several teachers offer workshops. I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;ve picked up the odd tidbit here and there from these courses. However, my direction is a product of Bruce&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;s mentoring and the desire to follow the tenants of the genuine Water tradition as passed down by him. Bruce is my one and only teacher.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-1537  alignright&#34; title=&#34;Paul_Cavel_SPC&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/06/Paul_Cavel_SPC1-225x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Paul and Energy Arts Instructor Peter Jenkins&#34; width=&#34;225&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell me a little bit about your teaching. Do you run regular classes? Workshops? Who are your students?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I teach full-time and offer various teaching formats, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Weekly classes and seminars in Kentish Town, London&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weekend seminars in England and Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weeklong retreats in Greece and Germany&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corporate training and executive coaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private and small group lessons&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I have students from all walks of life who practise for a wide variety of reasons. Some are looking for a system to maintain health and wellness while others are professionals who want an edge and/or a means for releasing stress. I also see many Energy Arts instructors who want to prepare for certification trainings or upgrade their practice and understanding of the material.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the three most important points that you would like other instructors to know about regarding your practice or your teaching or your business?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; My practice and my teaching are neigong-based. That is I focus on the strands of neigong that develop the body, chi and mind, and then integrate that material into Circle Walking, bagua, tai chi and meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;m based in North London where I offer my full programme. The seminar series and retreats I teach in Europe are designed with a particular focus in mind to help students develop that particular aspect of practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I offer a lot of hands-on personal corrections, partner exercises and component practice sets with a systematic, progressive focus. My aim is to help students solidify their foundation and integrate the deeper aspects of neigong that ultimately intertwine to create the more complex movement forms of bagua and tai chi.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Some of my students have just finished a series on the Marriage of Heaven and Earth, where they learned to open and close the joints of the arms and legs. How should they continue to work on this practice on their own?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have opened up the pulse, the next step is to balance your  system. This is normally done through Circling Hands Qigong, an easy,  repetitive motion that allows the mind to focus on the content rather  that the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through practice of Circling Hands Qigong, the process is simple:  compare the pulse in the joint on the left side to the corresponding  joint on the right side of your body, and make them the same. This is  done by reducing the joint with the larger range to that of the joint  with the smaller range. Go through all the pairs, e.g. hands, feet,  elbows and knees. Next, compare each pair to all other pairs, e.g. hands  to feet, elbows to knees, shoulders to hips, and equalise any  imbalances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reducing your range of motion to the joint with the smallest range, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dramatically soften the pulse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Release the nervous system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deepen the pulse in the joints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link the pulsing of the joints into one unified lattice, thereby amplifying the positive effects of the pulse.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For more from Paul on the art of pulsing, check out this two-part series,&amp;Acirc;  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/1469/pulsing-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.circlewalking.com/1501/pulsing-bagua-zhang/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Posted from Trainerfly: Launching an Online Course</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2011 10:36:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/04/21/cross-posted-from-trainerfly-launching-an-online-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/2011/04/11/how-i-launched-my-first-online-course/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this post from the Trainerfly blog&lt;/a&gt;. I talk to teachers and trainers all the time who want move beyond their live events, but the number of steps it takes, and the technology required to make it work seem overwhelming. Hopefully, I&#39;ve made a little dent in that perception!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching the First &#34;Foundations of Relaxation&#34; Course</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/03/15/launching-the-first-foundations-of-relaxation-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 16:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/03/15/launching-the-first-foundations-of-relaxation-course/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m pretty excited about this: &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/courses/eyes-and-visual-training/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eyes and Visual Training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-714&#34; title=&#34;Floating Hot Dog&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/03/Hot-Dog-300x169.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;169&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s my new online course and the first in the Foundations of Relaxation Series I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. As I&#39;ve been developing the course, I keep saying to myself, &#34;I wish everyone who comes to see me for pain relief or to learn tai chi did this first.&#34; In fact, that&#39;s how I developed the whole series. There are a few simple things that don&#39;t take a lot of oversight or feedback from an instructor that everyone can do to move better (meaning more gracefully and in less pain).&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-712&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m offering it at a pretty steep discount on what I plan to sell it for: $49 for now, instead of $97 (so snatch it up!). Plus, you get lifetime access to the material, so you can keep coming back to it and working on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a host of secondary reasons this is exciting too. One of them is that I&#39;m using Trainerfly, my web-based training app, to run the course. I&#39;m already using it with private clients and remotely teaching a tai chi group in Maine, but this is the first full course. I&#39;m sure I&#39;ll learn a ton by doing it, which is great, because I have a few other tai chi teachers interested in doing the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for updates on how it&#39;s going once people are in the system working with the course material!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Feedback from Trainerfly Beta</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2011 08:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/02/20/user-feedback-from-trainerfly-beta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/estimmel/&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-633&#34; title=&#34;megaphone&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/02/megaphone.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;megaphone by estimmel&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;180&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Over the last month or so, I&#39;ve gotten &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/&#34;&gt;Trainerfly&lt;/a&gt; out into people&#39;s hands and I&#39;ve been learning some really interesting lessons. I think it was easy for me to get wrapped up in how I&#39;ve evolved it as a tool in my business over the last two years and lose perspective on how other people might be trying to add it into their business from scratch, with none of that prior history.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-632&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Extra Layers&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you integrate a new business tool, you have a question of layers. In other words, if this is how I normally get something done, will the new tool add new layers of work, or remove them? And if it adds more work, is there another benefit that justifies the additional work. I got some strong feedback in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was amazingly clarifying for me to see the places where extra layers were not justified. Really specifically, the product is not strong enough right now to replace one-on-one communication if a trainer is using an email/youtube/spreadsheet system to get information to their clients. Why did I think I could compete with mature products from Google and Microsoft? Hahaha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if the communication issue is about hitting many people at different times with the same basic information, I think I have a winning solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Class, Deconstructed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The biggest thing that has been bugging me in the last 12-18 months on my own personal teaching front is summed up nicely by saying: &#34;teaching is a product that is consumed as it is produced&#34;. A little tear runs down my cheek at the end of every class, because I know that what happened in the last hour is lost forever in the ether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so maybe that&#39;s a little dramatic, but it bothers me that there&#39;s not a better way to preserve the moment, and from a business point of view, earn more money from it. Can you image a furniture maker who crafts single-use chairs? As soon as someone stands up, the chair disappears?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m starting to see a solution to this problem, though. It&#39;s not going to be hooking up 15 different cameras around the school and recording every single thing that happens. Instead, I&#39;m starting the process of extracting key ingredients from class, and transforming them into a touchstones that students can come back to again and again to further their practice outside of that elusive produce-and-consume teaching moment. There&#39;s a lot more to say about this strategy, and I&#39;m really excited about refining those tools. They will look really different than a traditional class -- you have to trade the interactive spontaneity of a good class, for structures that create reproduceable learning and practice moments for students.&amp;Acirc;  I think I know what that means....stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing the &#34;Foundations of Relaxation&#34; Series</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2011 07:48:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/02/15/introducing-the-foundations-of-relaxation-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a tai chi teacher and movement coach, I get to meet a lot of people who want to relax, slow down and have more energy for the things they love to do in life.  But there&#39;s a very common misconception that I encounter and I think it leads people to spend too much time chasing the wrong things when it comes to a relaxation practice.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-606&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Hopefully, this series will begin to clarify what the best way to start a relaxation practice is and how to most efficiently get the results you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the big mistake: people think that lots of hand-waving choreography, preferably done in a pristine setting, often to calming music, is the best way to become more relaxed. They&#39;re wrong. It&#39;s the best way to have a temporary escape from 24/7 habits that are creating more stress in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that you can change these underlying habits. Even though they are pre-conscious, you can learn to recognize them, test them, and alter them. And I can show you how that all works. This series will save you a lot of time and money to seeking me out in person, or wasting time on the wrong things with another qualified instructor. You can make major progress on your own, if you focus on three areas that I&#39;ll tell you about below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am putting together home-study courses for each of these areas, because they are subjects where you can make progress on your own, without the close guidance of an instructor, once you have the right information and a good practice system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can boost your energy, save a lot of discomfort, and begin the process of moving through life more gracefully, if you focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You See&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-610&#34; title=&#34;Your Picture May Be Fuzzy&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/02/TV-Snow-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Your Picture May Be Fuzzy&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How you see the world may be a little distorted. The eyes, or more accurately, vision governs how you interpret the physical space around you and how you respond to it (i.e. your posture and balance) way more than most people realize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we think of &#34;seeing&#34; something, we see it or we don&#39;t. Vision is a much more comprehensive, integrative act. In other words, seeing is what your eyes do mechanically, but vision is how your brain interprets the world coming at you. And your body reacts to that interpretation constantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these reactions and relationships are rooted in evolutionary survival mechanics, buried deep in your pre-conscious mind. But don&#39;t worry, there are some really clear ways to test how your body and eyes are working together and demonstrate clearly when the picture is fuzzy, even if you don&#39;t realize it right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest benefit of improving your visual skills is that, when your brain gets more information, it can react more efficiently. A small eye movement will replace a big body movement and simply put, to get from A to B will take less energy, so you&#39;ll have more energy to spend on something else or you&#39;ll get there faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 6-week course, you&#39;ll learn how to systematically test and observe what your body is doing subconsciously and improve how your brain interprets visual information. As your visual skills improve, your body will literally recalibrate how it moves through space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You Breathe&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-611&#34; title=&#34;Try Breathing through a Straw&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/02/Snorkel-201x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Try Breathing through a Straw&#34; width=&#34;201&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next area that I wish every single person would work on before they come see me is their breathing. Poor breathing dramatically reduces your energy level, encourages you to stay stressed out, and even impacts your mood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t believe me? Try walking around for the rest of your day today breathing only out of a straw. See how much energy you have for even the simplest things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a cultural level, our largely sedentary lifestyle has a direct impact on our breathing mechanism. See, good breathing is all about fully activating the diaphragm, creating a vacuum effect that fills the lungs and simultaneously pressurizes the abdomen, massaging the internal organs. In slumped seated posture, you limit the movement of the diaphragm. And no, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;good posture&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; with shoulders back and chest up doesn&#39;t fix the breathing problem. In fact, the way most people hold &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;good posture&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; makes the breathing problem worse --- they are trying to fill the lungs by expanding the chest to create more volume. Not only is this less effective than diaphragmatic breathing, but it actually mimics hyperventilation and triggers a stress response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to break the stress cycle and give yourself an internal tune up, is to learn the proper way to breath with the diaphragm and develop a consistent practice. Information alone doesn&#39;t do you any good...you have to be smart about making new habits. In the course, I will teach you how to do both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How You Walk&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-612&#34; title=&#34;Bricks&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/02/bricks-300x229.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bricks&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;229&#34; /&gt;When you teach movement 3-4 hours a day, you get to see a lot of different people&#39;s ingrained movement patterns and there are some striking common themes. Most people who want to learn tai chi, for example, begin by moving in exactly the opposite way prescribed by the Tai Chi Classics. In the Classics it says &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the movements should start in the feet, be powered by the legs, steered by the waist and expressed in the hands.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Instead, everything is about leading from the upper body, with little to no connection to the legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it&#39;s no coincidence that there is an abundance of back pain, knee injuries and general inability move around freely in our culture, right? Right......&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say it all starts in the feet. Try walking around with heavy bricks as feet and see how that feels. Maybe you feel a pinch in your hip right away, or a tug on the back. Maybe you&#39;re lucky enough to feel a crick all the way up in your neck. Lucky indeed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;feet&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; course, I will teach you how to open your feet again, even if you think your feet are too flat to work right or your hips are too stiff. &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;But I have these little plastic things that I put in my shoes....&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; Ok, if I told you to wear a full-body cast for the rest of your life because your aches and pains mean all those parts weren&#39;t supposed to be moving around, would you take me up on that offer? I&#39;m not knocking some foot support, but if you&#39;ve read this far, I think you know that I&#39;m focused on helping you change movement habits to have more energy and less pain. Immobile feet are part of a movement habit....and re-mobilizing the tiny little bones in your feet is an important new project for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll learn how to re-awaken the feet with self-massage and mobility exercises that will have you moving lighter, faster, and with a better bounce in your step. Just like the other courses in this series, everything is laid out in a 6-week format that blends learning new concepts gradually with systematic follow-up practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my teachers, Dr. Eric Cobb always says, &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;the body you have is the one you&#39;ve earned through how you move.&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; In these courses, I will teach you how to move differently in order to feel differently. Most people will never realize the degree to which their pre-conscious patterns are impacting how they go through their day, but you&#39;ll be tuned in to a whole different set of signs that will help you: cultivate more energy, move with more ease, and have less pain.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epic Meaning, Sheep Knuckles, and The Institute for the Future</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2011 09:30:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2011/01/03/epic-meaning-sheep-knuckles-and-the-institute-for-the-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-531&#34; title=&#34;gaming superpowers&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2011/01/gaming-superpowers-300x207.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;207&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jane McGonigal gives a fascinating talk about the &#34;superpowers&#34; cultivated by the game-playing masses (more than 500 million with another billion coming up in the next decade!). Obviously we all have the image of the gamer locked in his mother&#39;s basement, endlessly pawing away at an electronic reward system, like a hamster. McGonigal&#39;s takeaway is a little different though.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-528&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She emphasizes the motivation, inspiration, and social purpose built into game play. I think that&#39;s an interesting take. When I talked to an early pioneer of these games, he said that &#34;we knew they were addictive from the beginning&#34;, but it sounded like the dirty little secret that no one wanted to admit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I think the interesting question is whether the virtues of gaming (along the lines of motivation and engagement) can be transferred to real world activity without the addictive over-use that leads to unhealthy, sedentary life. Maybe as technology comes out of the basement and into the palm of your hand more readily, this is becoming a more reasonable goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, her talk is definitely worth watching (oh, and the sheep knuckles tie back nicely into Herodotus for a lesson on real world gaming!):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; width=&#34;446&#34; height=&#34;326&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowScriptAccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;wmode&#34; value=&#34;transparent&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;bgColor&#34; value=&#34;#ffffff&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;flashvars&#34; value=&#34;vu=http://video.ted.com/talks/dynamic/JaneMcGonigal_2010-medium.flv&amp;amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/JaneMcGonigal-2010.embed_thumbnail.jpg&amp;amp;vw=432&amp;amp;vh=240&amp;amp;ap=0&amp;amp;ti=799&amp;amp;introDuration=15330&amp;amp;adDuration=4000&amp;amp;postAdDuration=830&amp;amp;adKeys=talk=jane_mcgonigal_gaming_can_make_a_better_world;year=2010;theme=what_s_next_in_tech;theme=the_rise_of_collaboration;theme=a_taste_of_ted2010;theme=design_like_you_give_a_damn;theme=art_unusual;theme=media_that_matters;event=TED2010;&amp;amp;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;bgcolor&#34; value=&#34;#ffffff&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;446&#34; height=&#34;326&#34; src=&#34;http://video.ted.com/assets/player/swf/EmbedPlayer.swf&#34; flashvars=&#34;vu=http://video.ted.com/talks/dynamic/JaneMcGonigal_2010-medium.flv&amp;amp;su=http://images.ted.com/images/ted/tedindex/embed-posters/JaneMcGonigal-2010.embed_thumbnail.jpg&amp;amp;vw=432&amp;amp;vh=240&amp;amp;ap=0&amp;amp;ti=799&amp;amp;introDuration=15330&amp;amp;adDuration=4000&amp;amp;postAdDuration=830&amp;amp;adKeys=talk=jane_mcgonigal_gaming_can_make_a_better_world;year=2010;theme=what_s_next_in_tech;theme=the_rise_of_collaboration;theme=a_taste_of_ted2010;theme=design_like_you_give_a_damn;theme=art_unusual;theme=media_that_matters;event=TED2010;&amp;amp;preAdTag=tconf.ted/embed;tile=1;sz=512x288;&#34; bgcolor=&#34;#ffffff&#34; wmode=&#34;transparent&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Business Thought Experiment</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 19:35:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/29/hybrid-business-thought-experiment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m working strictly on a hunch here, but I think there&#39;s a connection between the sentiment I tried to express &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/03/technology-and-all-that-heavenly-glory/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; about not getting lost in the bells and whistles of technology, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://techcrunch.com/2010/12/24/hybrid-startup/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; about &#34;hybrid businesses&#34;.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-501&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One Foot in the Virtual World, One Foot in the Real World&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to&amp;Acirc;  the author, Glenn Kelman, a hybrid business has &#34;one foot in the virtual world and one foot in the real world.&#34; However, &#34;this isn&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;trade;t&amp;Acirc; the old &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;clicks-and-mortar&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; concept from the 1990s,  which put web glitter on an old-school business, building Walmart.com  for Walmart. A hybrid business is built entirely from scratch, to be  innovative in its online technology and its real-world operations.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m trying to envision how to adapt &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brooklinetaichi.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt; to the hybrid model or see how &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trainerfly&lt;/a&gt; fundamentally addresses this shift.&amp;Acirc;  Here are some thoughts along those lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right now, BTC is definitely in the &#34;clicks and mortar&#34; mindset. The purpose of the website is to tell people about classes and when they take place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trainerfly could fall into the same trap by simply mirroring the live training sessions, as a &#34;back-up copy&#34; of what happened in real life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some of the more interesting possibilities I&#39;ve been exploring with Trainerfly and online learning have allowed me to open up live teaching &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;to people outside of my usual geographic reach&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The value proposition for trainers and their clients might be better in a hybrid.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Impact on Your Value Proposition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last point deserves some illustration: think of the last time you or a friend joined a gym and got &#34;free&#34; personal training sessions with your new membership. If it&#39;s been a while, maybe you go through some exercises with the trainer and work out a plan. Great. But now here comes the awkward part. They offer you a $300 option or a $1,000 option. Everyone goes into high pressure mode, you squirm out, and the trainer loses another sale.&amp;Acirc;  Clearly, if high-pressure sales are involved, there&#39;s a dissonance between what you need and what the trainer is trying to offer you. Is there a middle-ground that works for both of you? I&#39;m guessing that if the trainer&#39;s only option is live training, then the answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sales terms, closing the sale came down to offering you an &#34;A or B offer&#34;, but the trainer had the wrong &#34;A or B&#34;. Both missed your real need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a hybrid live and online training model, I don&#39;t see how the trainer in this example (I don&#39;t know which side of the interchange you&#39;re likely to be on, probably both at some point), could offer much variety in terms of their &#34;A or B offer&#34;. The choice was only between more or fewer session, not a different type of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that&#39;s from a marketing and sales point of view. What about an educational point of view?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Shifting Your Teaching Model&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The shift toward a hybrid business model is critically important for independent movement educators. We are constrained by one major factor: our limited teaching time. The problem is that you develop a body of knowledge that is vastly bigger than the mechanism for sharing it, one-on-one time with a client. Your students/clients can&#39;t absorb everything you put out in a live training session, but what if the hybrid model makes your knowledge more easily digestible? What if you can share all the information you&#39;ve refined a little bit at a time, in a way that decouples the actual sharing from your live time with clients? I think the hybrid model lies in that direction....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading Kelman&#39;s article, I&#39;m more and more convinced that this is the way to go for movement educators. I&#39;ve already tried to articulate what I&#39;ll now think of as &#34;hybrid strategies&#34; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com/earn-an-extra-10000-this-year/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a related note, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/29/become-an-enterprise-of-one/&#34;&gt;&#34;Enterprise of One&#34; &lt;/a&gt;theory here. It&#39;s the crumbling barriers of entry to business technology that are making all of this possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Video for Tai Chi Group</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2010 09:17:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/12/17/new-video-for-tai-chi-group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a sneak peek at some online learning support I&#39;m doing with a Tai Chi group in Farmington, Maine. I went up a couple weeks ago to teach an afternoon workshop and this was the practice set we did by the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workshop participants also have access to a private Q&amp;amp;A forum, so as they practice between now and the next live training, I can give them feedback. I&#39;ll probably add some new videos as we go to answer any questions that come up. I also think it will be a useful way to pre-load content for the next workshop, i.e., if I can get them to learn some basic choreography before I arrive, we can spend our time focusing on refinements or more subtle internal principles that are best learned by feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the clip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; classid=&#34;clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000&#34; codebase=&#34;http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;src&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/yu9gAYbhZi4?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; /&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;embed width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/yu9gAYbhZi4?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; allowFullScreen=&#34;true&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can you teach movement online?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/19/can-you-teach-movement-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 15:44:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/19/can-you-teach-movement-online/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2010/11/18/learn-qigong-online/&#34;&gt;a recent post&lt;/a&gt;, I asked the question &#34;Can you learn qigong (or any movement art) online?&#34; The answer was a big fat qualified &#34;yes.&#34; I think there is a limited role that online resources can play in your movement education --- even though movement is something best learned through live human interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So the question for you, as a movement coach, is not whether or not you can teach online, the question is &#34;what is the appropriate way to use online resources in my movement education business?&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that the primary use is not to replace your live teaching, but to reinforce it. Whatever you teach in the classroom, your students will need to see 10 more times before it sinks in. With such limited live time with your students, why not get the next best approximation in front of them as soon as you can. Throw up a video, or a written explanation, and let them reflect on the in-class experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a secondary benefit here of course, for your business.&amp;Acirc;  Most likely, spending 2 or 3 or 4 hours a week with a student in person is on the high side. Do you see a student for an hour a week? How many hours a week do they need to be exposed to material to &#34;get it&#34;? If you can create a copy of your live training session online, to one degree or another, then their exposure to the material goes up, but your training time with them stays the same. &lt;strong&gt;You&#39;re multiplying your time. You&#39;re multiplying value for your client.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of topic I&#39;m explore much more on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trainerfly.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trainerfly&lt;/a&gt; blog. Trainerfly is a tool designed to solve exactly this kind of problem and help you, as a movement coach, grow a business that expands you teaching reach and makes the most of your limited live training time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learn Qigong Online?</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/18/learn-qigong-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 06:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/18/learn-qigong-online/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Can you learn qigong, or any movement art, online? This is a burning question for me right now. My immediate reaction is &#34;NO!&#34;. However, I believe there is a significant role for supplemental online material in the overall learning process, even for movement arts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s why it&#39;s a bad idea to learn movement online:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning movement is a kinesthetic experience, not a visual one -- you have to feel where you are in space and you certainly can&#39;t get that from staring at a screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need feedback -- when you are learning something new, you need refinement and guidance, usually hands-on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some things need to be felt on another person -- we get into this all the time with more subtle qigong principles and there is no way around feeling what&#39;s going on in the instructor&#39;s body to learn what you are trying to do in your own&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Those are my big 3 &#34;No way!&#34; reasons you can&#39;t learn qigong online. Or I should say, the reason why online learning shouldn&#39;t be your sole way of learning this stuff. Let&#39;s look at it from a different point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assuming you have some in-person feedback, at some time, can online resources supplement your movement education? Absolutely!&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here&#39;s why:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need practice. If you really want to &#34;get it&#34; you need to practice more outside of class time with an instructor than in class time. So, will a double-check of something you already learned help keep you on track? Yup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say you don&#39;t have regular access to an instructor. Are there certain things that you can begin to work on so that when you do meet up, you&#39;ll make the most of your time? Uh huh.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So, I think you can see, while I doubt how effective it is to learn movement exclusively online, I&#39;m in favor of online resources for movement education that support live training. I think there are novel uses for prep to maximize in-person time and follow-up to keep personal practice on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Moodle, I&#39;ve been developing an online qigong program with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.relaxationmeditation.co.uk/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Energy Arts Senior Instructor Paul Cavel&lt;/a&gt; and we&#39;ll be rolling out a version for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brooklinetaichi.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt; in the coming months. Paul developed the course material initially to keep his workshop students on track between seminars. We&#39;re going to use some of the same content to help people interested in starting at BTC get a jump start before new classes roll around.&amp;Acirc;  Of course, you&#39;ll hear more about how this all goes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ba Gua Program Product Launch</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/11/ba-gua-program-product-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 06:46:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/11/ba-gua-program-product-launch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been working with the team at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Energy Arts&lt;/a&gt; on various projects, but mainly in the capacity as a community coordinator. Currently, my focus is on helping them get a new community discussion forum off the ground, but I also had the chance to participate in the launch of their new Ba Gua Mastery Program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ba Gua Mastery Program is a home-study program with information on circle-walking for meditation and martial arts. They&#39;ve drawn from a live instructor training Bruce taught in 2009, and turned out CDs, DVDs, print manuals...the whole works! It&#39;s been a monumental effort and in the future I&#39;ll be discussing how we&#39;re going to blend live teaching with all these materials at BTC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now though, I want to talk about their launch strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks, they&#39;ve been building interest by sending out related content without trying to sell the program directly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-290&#34; title=&#34;offer&#34; src=&#34;dankleiman.github.io/uploads/2010/11/offer.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;478&#34; height=&#34;589&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a screen capture from one of the launch pages on their website.&amp;Acirc;  They&#39;ve added to it as they released new content, so I&#39;ve got back and highlighted what they put out in what order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first piece was a video of Bruce talking about his different Ba Gua teachers in China. On the video page, they included a &#34;pre-launch notification&#34; email list sign-up. In a follow-up email, they reported that over 2000 people opted-in to that list. Not bad, considering that all of the launch copy says they&#39;ll only be selling 250 copies of the program!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second piece was an interview I conducted with Bruce and Richard Taubinger, who is overseeing the launch. We discussed more of the details of the practice itself and why people should be interested in ba gua as an art. I&#39;m not sure about email sign-ups or interest in the interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the most direct approach, they gave away some sample material from the product itself, just before the launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure how long this page will be up for, but here is the launch page itself: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/bagua-mastery-program-launch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.energyarts.com/offer/bagua-mastery-program-launch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I really like how they gradually, but persistently built interest in the launch, drawing from a list they&#39;ve spent considerable time growing and finally putting just enough urgency around buying (only 250 copies!) that they will hopefully convince the right people to act on it. We&#39;ll see!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trainerfly Backstory: The Practice Problem</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 08:05:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2010/11/08/trainerfly-backstory-the-practice-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure I&#39;m not alone here. Teachers in all disciples, if they need their students to practice to learn what they are teaching, will relate. I don&#39;t know if &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;movement educators&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; have it worse because people tend to think of all movement as &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;working out&amp;acirc;&amp;euro; -- something you go and do, not an art you have to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, one of my favorite concepts when you are talking about getting really good at something is called &amp;acirc;&amp;euro;&amp;oelig;deliberate practice&amp;acirc;&amp;euro;. Geoff Colvin, explains the elements of deliberate practice in &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;Talent is Overrated&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2006/10/30/8391794/index.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Here&#39;s a summary article he wrote on CNNMoney.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to implement deliberate practice strategies has been a major shift in how I train myself and that&#39;s another story entirely. As a professional movement educator, though, I had another problem: I most of my clients for one hour a week. Maybe if I&#39;m lucky we meet in a group class setting for 3 or 4 hours a week. How can I extend a practice model to them that involves hours of practice repetition, constant feedback, goal setting, and ever-evolving mental models of the practice in such a short amount of face-to-face time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to make the deliberate practice model work, I had to decide how to spend the precious little in-person time with my clients and inspire them to cover as many of the other elements as possible outside of our one-on-one time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which would you choose? Endless repetition? Refined feedback? Goal setting? Mental models?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, it turns out to be a blend. They need to lay the foundation between sessions for refinement by getting their reps in. We can talk goal setting any time, but lots of it comes down to an emotional understanding of where they want to be that is finally sharpened face-to-face. There is an initial hump when I start to work with someone where the conceptual framework for training needs to be established, but the mental models evolve based on what they experience through practice and what other resources I can send their way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you can see where I&#39;m heading at this point. In order to make the most of one-on-one time in person, and give my clients the best possible movement education, I needed to separate out the pieces of the whole training pie that could be automated, or at least frozen in time through asynchronous communication tools (haha, fancy term for things like email and blogs!). Later, I&#39;ll explain how I began to sift through what could be leveraged and what needed to be face-to-face, but the problem started to be clearer when I realized I would have to make this distinction: &lt;em&gt;can I share this later or do I need to address it face-to-face.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>