<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>push-hands on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/dankleiman.github.io/tags/push-hands/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in push-hands on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/dankleiman.github.io/tags/push-hands/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 07:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I asked you about stressful situations and many of you shared your responses to &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p6q5/&#34;&gt;the Most Stressful Interaction of Your Week.&lt;/a&gt; Thank you for taking the time to respond. I hope the guided practice sessions I sent you in return helped bring some relaxation into your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I want to dive into some of the themes of those interactions and show you how Tai Chi, specifically the two-person interactive practices called Push Hands, trains you to respond to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as I was explaining this concept to a friend, I had to clarify, when your boss gets on your nerves this week, I&#39;m not saying you need to do Tai Chi together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is true that, when you train these interactive practices on a regular basis, the distinction between being present in a Tai Chi exercise and being present in any other interaction you have throughout your day starts to disappear.&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4217&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An Alternative to Fight or Flight&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Often, we grapple with our pre-conscious responses to external threats. Ironically, as Robert Sapolsky explains in detail in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Why-Zebras-Dont-Ulcers-Third/dp/0805073698&#34;&gt;Why Zebra&#39;s Don&#39;t Get Ulcers&lt;/a&gt;, our mental projections of the severity of the threat cause the same physiological response as an actual physical threat, but often, it turns out that there really was no threat at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when you prepare for a big meeting and you feel like you are walking into a room full of people who don&#39;t want to hear from you, you go through the same hormonal and chemical response internally as you would if those same people started hitting you with the chairs in the room. But you do it in &lt;em&gt;anticipation&lt;/em&gt; of the threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or if you get a letter from an ex, you put it aside until you have the time and energy to deal with it. The letter grows into a project and you have to get ready to open it with an elaborate ritual. But what if it turns out it&#39;s only a bill that you deal with easily?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you learn quickly in the interactive practices of Tai Chi is that how you respond to the threat is everything.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you tense up? Run away? Or is there another possibility?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch this example of how your response determines the outcome of the situation, regardless of what the other person is trying to do to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/dbt1nC9jypI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These same lessons apply to dealing with your fuming boss or a stubborn elderly relative:  when there is force coming at you, don&#39;t add more force to it, but don&#39;t shrink from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Push Hands trains you to listen to the other person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Listening Leads to Resolution&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You might think &#34;listening&#34; to another person means observing when they take a breath so you can start talking again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in an intense or stressful situation, the most important thing might seem to be to get your point across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, if you just lob opinions back and forth, you&#39;re diminishing the possibility of real resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you &#34;listen&#34; in Tai Chi, you&#39;re setting the stage for actual energetic resolution, which means both physical and emotional.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/vSc44Hm0ews&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this video, you see the problem you run into if you or the other person simply insists on forcing things to be a certain way. Sooner or later a bigger, stronger force is going to come along and you won&#39;t have your way afterall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when someone in your family announces major life changes or you and a colleague disagree about who was responsible for a piece of work, ask yourself how much you want to hold on and push for your agenda or whether there is a way to see the situation through, to a new kind of resolution where new possibilities will emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, one important thing to note here is that this does not mean you cave in to every little bit of pressure around you. We saw that in the first video. That&#39;s collapse and not the response we want to instill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge is, can you stay flexible and connected at the same time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you find out, the more Tai Chi that you do, is that there are some direct ways to train yourself to respond this way and you begin to feel the effects in all areas of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what was &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p6q5/&#34;&gt;your most stressful interaction this week&lt;/a&gt;? And how will you use it to bring about resolution?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Desire Pain as a Tai Chi Exercise</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/10/01/learning-to-desire-pain-as-a-tai-chi-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 12:41:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/10/01/learning-to-desire-pain-as-a-tai-chi-exercise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In response to &lt;a title=&#34;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/24/transforming-conflict-with-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, many of you sent me stories of situations where you were forced into a tense encounter and you had to draw on your practice to get you through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After, you feel relief and you can move on, but sometimes the idea slips through that, &#34;hey, I&#39;m a little better able to handle this kind of thing because of the way I faced it.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if you actually started to seek out challenging encounters because you sensed their transformative effect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is exactly what psychologists Phil Stutz and Barry Michels teach in their book, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thetoolsbook.com/&#34;&gt;The Tools,&lt;/a&gt; and it has some surprising Tai Chi parallels.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;more-4205&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Watch this short video clip about &#34;The Reversal of Desire&#34; which is their technique for facing pain that will move you out of your comfort zone and into new growth:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/kWZaQgDeHYM?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, by itself, this is a fascinating idea, that you seek out pain as transformation. But as we discussed in the podcast, I want you to go beyond ideas and into practical, physical manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s what&#39;s so exciting about your Tai Chi practice. It&#39;s not a metaphor for transformation. You&#39;re playing with the very material that will shift and change through practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How the Reversal of Desire is like an Interactive Tai Chi Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The steps that the authors teach in their tool are very similar to the physical experience you have in Tai Chi when you neutralize your own fear response and move towards the resolution of a confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s how the tool works just like Tai Chi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, you call out to the pain, you face it. In Tai Chi, the first stage of the encounter is face-to-face and the first hurdle you have to overcome is your impulse to &#34;freeze up&#34; in response to the threat. The connection here is that you literally experience this freezing in the front of your body, like &#34;a deer frozen in the headlights&#34;. Either you activate the front with enough sensitivity to pass to the second step, or you revert to the fear response, which plays out in a yin or yang way: you collapse or you tense up. The tool is similarly training your sensitivity and priming you to move into the encounter.&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, you move through a cloud of pain. They want you to feel it all around you. In the Tai Chi encounter, you do something similar. You have to let the other person&#39;s energy move through you (rooting) or past you (neutralizing). In both cases, step two you are completely enveloped by the energy of the threat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the final step of the tool, you visualize being spit out by the cloud of pain and you feel it at your back. In your Tai Chi response, once you can feel your back engaged, loose, flexible, and connected to your root, you have pretty much resolved the incoming threat and your best response arises.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In both cases, stepping up to the encounter without running away and letting it wash through your system, allows you to come out the other side, engaged, connected, and ultimately stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, you are training to allow the most natural response to arise, something you most likely hadn&#39;t planned, ruminated on, or conceived of, but that emerges because of the interaction. You get to a new place, because you have grappled with pain you would have otherwise fled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other tools in the book address different dimensions of the question, &#34;how do I turn my challenges into courage, compassion, and creativity?&#34; There certainly are more parallels to Tai Chi to explore. What sets &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thetoolsbook.com/&#34;&gt;The Tools&lt;/a&gt; apart is the emphasis on teaching exercises that you have to practice over and over again to build new responses. They are not after theoretical understanding, they want to cultivate an embodied response. Sound familiar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are some of the encounters you&#39;ve had lately where your practice either did or did not factor in to how you resolved the situation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/q7p6q5/&#34;&gt;Please take this anonymous, two-minute survey, so that we can how we talk about the potential for Tai Chi to transform conflict. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Push Hands and The Tai Chi Mastery Program</title>
      <link>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2012 07:19:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dankleiman.github.io/2012/03/28/push-hands-and-the-tai-chi-mastery-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re hosting Bruce Frantzis for a Push Hands Intensive this week at Brookline Tai Chi. The training is being filmed and it will become the Push Hands module of the Tai Chi Mastery Program, due out later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are my thoughts so far on how the Push Hands component fits in with what we did &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/tag/wsfit2011/&#34;&gt;this past summer in Brighton&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34;&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;movie&#34; value=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0XaK4Gy7fDc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowFullScreen&#34; value=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&#34;allowscriptaccess&#34; value=&#34;always&#34;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/v/0XaK4Gy7fDc?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0&#34; type=&#34;application/x-shockwave-flash&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; allowscriptaccess=&#34;always&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>