<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>wordpress on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>/tags/wordpress/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in wordpress on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/wordpress/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile-izing Wordpress and Moodle</title>
      <link>/2010/11/15/mobile-izing-wordpress-and-moodle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 14:16:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/15/mobile-izing-wordpress-and-moodle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time today upgrading the site and my phone so that I would have better mobile access to the site on my phone and so that you can too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what I ended up doing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding the &lt;a href=&#34;http://mobilepress.co.za/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MobilePress&lt;/a&gt; plugin to DanKleiman.com, so that the site adapts to your mobile browser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing the Wordpress app on my Droid, so that I can update the site from my phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.moodle.org/en/Moodle_for_Mobiles&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Moodle for Mobiles&lt;/a&gt;, which is &#34;is designed to work with mobile phones in Japan&#34;. Is that why it failed? I couldn&#39;t get the php to run cleanly.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Overall, I think this was a good step forward, except for the Moodle situation. It looks like there are several different native apps for mobile devices that are or are becoming available. That&#39;s good. I don&#39;t know if I&#39;ll have to modify the site to accommodate them or what. Depending on how I migrate current clients of mine over to Trainerfly, I may or may not look into this further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading a site update!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Mobile</title>
      <link>/2010/11/15/going-mobile/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 14:05:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/15/going-mobile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a test post from my phone. I just installed a Wordpress app for Android. I&#39;m also working on upgrading the blog and the noodle site for easy mobile access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: It looks like it picked up the post tags from my phone, but it missed the category. Also have to edit the post author through the site. But you don&#39;t really care about that, do you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;;-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>