<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>qigong on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/qigong/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in qigong on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://dankleiman.com/tags/qigong/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathing Techniques: Am I Doing it Right?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/06/breathing-techniques-am-i-doing-it-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 11:52:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/06/breathing-techniques-am-i-doing-it-right/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently received this breathing question and I thought it was worth sharing with everyone here as a post. (Don&#39;t forget, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/ask-me-anything/&#34;&gt;you can send me your practice questions&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m really confused! I took a Yang Style Tai Chi course and at the end of the class we would do Qigong. He said &#34;We will do diaphragmatic breathing. As you breath in draw the navel into the spine, as you exhale release and let the belly relax but don&#39;t collapse.&#34; What kind of breathing is this and what is the correct breathing for my qigong practice? Is this wrong?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is a great question. There are many, many different breathing methods, so it can be really hard to discern what any one practice is doing and how it fits in a larger practice context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, most of these techniques break down into big categories that are easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most breathing practices are designed to hit one or more of these areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effecient Gas Exchange&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internal Massage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energetic Activation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meditation/Working with the Mind&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Effecient Gas Exchange&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you breath well, in terms of moving gases in and out of the lungs, you can improve everything from your mood to your physical performance and focus, presence, and concetration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the most basic level, all breathing practices should make you a better breather in terms of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the correct muscles (diaphragm, intercostals)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reducing strain/effort in breathing at rest&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This &#34;Wall Exercise&#34; is one of my favorites for learning to feel the correct movement of the lungs/ribs during effecient breathing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oqsXcDA53YU&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;420&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal Massage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you hear &#34;diaphragmatic breathing,&#34; as in the initial question, at least in a Tai Chi/qigong context, it will often go beyond the simple effeciency model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to use the location of the diaphragm -- above the middle internal organs -- and its movement -- pumping up and down -- to actually massage the internal organs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you inhale, it creates a pressurization in the abdominal cavity. On the exhale, this pressure is released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternating compression and release creates massage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, the instructions are designed &lt;em&gt;to increase the massaging effect&lt;/em&gt;: &#34;As you breath in draw the navel into the spine, as you exhale release and let the belly relax but don&#39;t collapse.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a variation of a type of breathing practice called &#34;Reverse Breathing.&#34; When you do this kind of work, increasing internal pressures deliberately, you want to watch for your face turning red, the neck feeling tight, or a sense in your head of too much pressure. All of these are signs you need to back off and return to Natural Breathing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Energetic Activation and Working with the Mind&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we extend this process of using the breath to enliven the inside of the body, eventually we will cross over from physical activation to energetic activation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, breathing techniques can be a part of &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2013/02/25/dragon-and-tiger-exercises-for-activating-the-lower-tantien/&#34;&gt;awakening the lower tantien&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, you will use the sense of movement from the breathing mechanisms (diaphragm pumping up and down) and pressure changes in the abdominal cavity to wake up more and more feeling sensation until you fill a still center-point deep in the pit of the abdomen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I always recommend that you dial back the deliberate action of conscious breathing, letting it go quiet instead. This is how you open up the space to working more directly with your energy and the mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you can start to feel the lower tantien, you may notice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tantien emerging as your clear center of gravity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pulsing in sync with the rhythm of the breath.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your mind shifting to the tantien, or as is sometimes said, &#34;you start to see from the lower tantien.&#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sense of gathering energy into the lower tantien, especially if you have a period of quiet, non-intention at the end of your practice.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hopefully, these big categories will help you navigate the different types of breathing practices that you will encounter. No matter how you practice, it&#39;s always a good idea to finish with quiet, natural breathing so that you smooth out your nervous system. This will stay with you 24 hours a day if you set up a nice easy rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Returning to an Old, Familiar Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 09:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s easy to get caught in a linear, progress-oriented way of thinking about your practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&#39;s new? What can I learn next? Am I improving...all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get so caught up in doing it right and refining every little detail that you can lose sight of the what&#39;s really great about practice in the first place...the restoration, integration, and feeling of wholeness you can walk away with each time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Return to a Familiar Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
What if, instead of trying to always master something new, you went back to a practice you hadn&#39;t done in a while?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if that felt the same way it feels to see an old friend? Or visit a place you hadn&#39;t been in a long time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s an old friend I guess I&#39;d like you to meet (part of me was hoping this would be buried in YouTube&#39;s archives, never to surface again. Oh well!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I wanted to see what it looked like from the outside to hold a posture for an extended period of time. In this video, I&#39;m holding the final posture of Tai Chi&#39;s Single Whip for 25 minute...but it&#39;s sped up so you can really see the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/WALkgFQ9a2w&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; width=&#34;560&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s awful, right? You can see all the collapsing and poor breathing as I struggle through the duration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait. Why did I want to share this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oh, right, because every time I&#39;ve returned to this practice since that time, six months, a year, three years later, I can settle back into some of the practice grooves I established back then.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you return to an energetic practice like Standing Qigong, try not to just replicate the outward shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The feel of the posture (or movement) -- heavy, light, twisting, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The energetic pattern that defines the practice -- sinking, rising, absorbing, projecting, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The mind, the body, and the energetic pattern slotting into alignment, not immediately, but over a few minutes or several repetitions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This last piece, the alignment, is critical. Part of the challenge of remembering an old practice is that you remember what it felt like &lt;em&gt;at the end&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, you&#39;re settling in to it, so you have to keep the end in mind, but patiently wait for the pieces to slot together again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, this waiting, and the eventual alignment, returning to a familiar place, is what is truly restorative and energizing about this method of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Return is the movement of the Tao.&lt;br /&gt;
Yielding is the way of the Tao.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things are born of being.&lt;br /&gt;
Being is born of non-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: right;&#34;&gt;- Tao Te Ching, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/lao-tzu/works/tao-te-ching/te.htm&#34;&gt;Chapter 40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 Update</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 09:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a quick update on what we&#39;ve been working on during Immersion Week 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/-KpibI0ZE9s?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m very impressed (and I say so in the video about 15 times!) with the way this group has patiently explored many different facets of the Swings and Spine Stretch without rushing ahead to try to fit seemingly contradictory pieces together conceptually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, they&#39;re doing a great job experiencing/exploring each different component on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you practice this way, you naturally come to integration points where the components gel in a way you couldn&#39;t have predicted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaxing Your Feet to Find Your Root</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/10/relaxing-your-feet-to-find-your-root/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 08:44:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/10/relaxing-your-feet-to-find-your-root/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you settle into your practice each day, you should always give yourself a couple of minutes to just feel and see where your body, your energy, and your awareness are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one sense, each practice session is about bringing the rhythms of each of those into harmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s why Tai Chi and qigong can be so powerfully restorative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you take a couple of minutes to just &#34;settle in,&#34; you&#39;ll discover several possible things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your overall energy level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What feels active and open.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What feels stuck or sluggish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specific body parts that are calling out, in good or bad ways.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finding New Space in the Feet&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The other day, I was settling in to practice and the soles of the feet really stood out (sorry!) from everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the toes were hanging from the feet in a way that reminded me of this famous photo of workers having lunch on the beam of the Empire State building. Weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.afterimagegallery.com/nytconstructionworkers.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter&#34; alt=&#34;nytconstructionworkers&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2014/04/nytconstructionworkers-300x274.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;274&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what I think was going on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My ankles were relaxed, allowing the balls of the feet to connect to the ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The spaces between the toes opened up, allowing the individual toes to release.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could feel each toe &#34;hanging&#34; and connecting the ground too.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And why was that like the workers on the beam?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more I stood and moved with this feeling, the more the ball of the foot -- the beam -- became a support structure I could sink into. The more I sunk into the ball of the foot, the more the toes -- all the workers up there on the beam -- relaxed and let go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, and this is the part that would freak me out if I were ever anywhere near the top of the Empire State building, &lt;strong&gt;the more I relaxed the more it felt like there was infinite space for my feet to relax down into&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn&#39;t that what&#39;s so amazing about the photo? The way that the workers are so relaxed and grounded, but they&#39;re dangling over hundreds of feet of empty space?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating Your Own Big Sensations from Tiny Spaces&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, I don&#39;t want you to go try to reproduce this sensation. Remember, I didn&#39;t set out to do it either. There is a way to practice that makes it more likely that you will have similar experiences, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The more time I&#39;ve spent getting familiar with interior space, through &lt;a title=&#34;Energy Gates Dissolving Series&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt;, the more these spaces have opened up. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trick is to go in with the goal of feeling, not necessarily &#34;opening&#34; or &#34;releasing&#34; or &#34;sinking.&#34; Those are all techniques that evolve from feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you feel, then as the structure, space, and relationships between areas of the body become more familiar, and your overall intention of sinking or rising meld with the well-mapped areas, experiences like this one just seem to pour out from deep inside the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you bumped into anything like this in your own practice? I&#39;m always curious to hear!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embrace the Cold to Feel Your Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/07/embrace-the-cold-to-feel-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 08:48:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/07/embrace-the-cold-to-feel-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2014/03/iStock_000034767246Small-291x300.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Winter tree in the mountains&#34; width=&#34;291&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-5018&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s been such a cold winter in the Northeastern US this year, that even Niagara Falls has frozen over. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every night, students come in to class shivering, that is, once they&#39;ve resolved to venture out in the cold and the dark. And many haven&#39;t even been up for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I want to tell you about an important practice lesson you can learn from all this cold. You will develop a better feel for the chi of your etheric body and stay warmer in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, when you step out into frigid temperatures, your reaction is to tense up, contract your body, and shiver to keep warm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should do the opposite. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a short qigong practice you can use to relax, warm-up, and even improve your sensitivity to the energy that runs your physical body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embrace the Cold&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand, with your arms by your sides, legs relaxed and weight balanced through the feet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the cold air around you and how it&#39;s making contact with your body, through all your layers of clothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice any reaction to contract or withdraw.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gently, from the outer edges of the body, expand to meet the cold, reversing the tendency to tense up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the contact between your body and the cold air around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With time, expand the mind into the space around the body, feeling out into the cold, as if you were sensing for temperature. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when we tell people to extend their minds beyond their bodies, that can often seem strange, esoteric, or even impossible, but we do this naturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt someone walk up behind you? Can you feel the heat without touching the fire? I hope so!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to sense the chi in your etheric field requires the same kind of sensory activation that you use for many mundane activities. When you embrace this winter&#39;s cold, you have another great opportunity to enhance your senses and expand your awareness of chi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 and the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Book</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 16:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m very excited to share some news about two big projects with you today: Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s annual Immersion Week and the publication of the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance as a physical book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/bATZ5_2SMno?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join me from Tuesday, April 22 - Friday, April 25 at Brookline Tai Chi in Boston for &lt;a href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org/immersion-week-2014-energy-gates-moving-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;Energy Gates Moving Qigong Exercises&lt;/a&gt;. Times, cost, and registration details in the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance is now available for purchase on Amazon, but you can also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.createspace.com/4498724&#34;&gt;get your copy of the physical book directly from the publisher&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When to Follow a Practice Recipe and When to Reflect on Your Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 09:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this video, we&#39;re talking about building up the skill of Outer Dissolving in your standing qigong practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start out, it pays to follow a recipe - a set of instructions that lead through a certain procedure physically, energetically, and with your mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are times you want to break away from the recipe and times you&#39;ll want to reflect on your experience verbally -- but there are good and bad ways to do both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/wv2eex86CCE?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice, Stress, and Building Outward Connections</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 11:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&#34;At some point, don&#39;t we have to ask ourselves, &#34;Aren&#39;t I healthy enough?&#34;  Don&#39;t I need to work on &#34;waking up&#34;, on manifesting kindness and patience, and being other oriented?&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s from a conversation we&#39;ve been having in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/inner-form/&#34;&gt;Inner Form discussion&lt;/a&gt; group and it got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be learning to cultivate your chi to heal old injuries or for the inner experience of meditative exploration, but at some point, shouldn&#39;t your practice extend into the world around you, to the people in your life, and your work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&#39;m often in favor of letting these connections emerge naturally, but the comment above and this TED talk on stress are pushing me to make &#34;practicing in the world&#34; a little more explicit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making Stress Your Friend&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Stanford health psychologist Kelly McGonigal gives a great talk on transforming your relationship to stress. And it could save your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the video description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stress. It makes your heart pound, your breathing quicken and your forehead sweat. But while stress has been made into a public health enemy, new research suggests that stress may only be bad for you if you believe that to be the case.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RcGyVTAoXEU?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practicing in the World&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From this perspective, &lt;strong&gt;cultivating your internal energy is not about getting some horrible disease out of your system.&lt;/strong&gt; It&#39;s a way to process, digest, and to grow from what&#39;s useful while shedding what&#39;s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice homework this week: you know what it&#39;s like to find a special, quiet place to practice to &lt;a href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;build your chi&lt;/a&gt;, but what about your next interaction with another person as the best place to practice? Can you pause, hold the mind the same way when you do in your practice and let the encounter unfold the same way the qigong mind allows chi to resolve itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might draw some inspiration from &lt;a title=&#34;Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/&#34;&gt;Push Hands&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a title=&#34;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/24/transforming-conflict-with-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Tai Chi-style conflict resolution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Recipe for Rewarding Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/30/the-recipe-for-rewarding-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 09:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/30/the-recipe-for-rewarding-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4998&#34; alt=&#34;Mixing all the elements of a good qigong practice.&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2014/01/iStock_000019067988Small-200x300.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&#34;Is it better to structure your practice to stay with one energy gate, such as the crown, until you feel some dissolving happening there, or should you just keep moving through the gates week by week moving onto another gate?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent questions like this one keep pouring in. Thank you for sharing your practice experiences with me. I know other folks who read the blog really appreciate it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love hearing from you guys, especially when your questions are grounded in exploration, practice and thoughtful reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check this next one out too. I don&#39;t think I&#39;ve ever articulated the process of sinking chi as clearly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#34;I&#39;m basically aiming to keep my attention on each section of my body as I go down until I feel it has gone sung and has the sense that&#39;s its as relaxed as I&#39;m capable of - as well as the sensation that it has filled with qi (like the sponge analogy). Then I try to feel the leading edge of that fullness until it seeps down to the next section. Does this sound like I&#39;m sinking or dissolving? Or am I somewhere in between perhaps?&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you see the common thread in both of these questions? &lt;strong&gt;Both of these questions are about &#34;practice recipes.&#34;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice Recipes for Skill Acquisition&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I&#39;ve been reading about learning models a little more lately and I wanted to share the Dreyfus Model of Skill Acquisition with you. If you have the time, these slides give a great overview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&#34;border: 1px solid #CCC; border-width: 1px 1px 0; margin-bottom: 5px; max-width: 100%;&#34; src=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/3462945&#34; height=&#34;356&#34; width=&#34;427&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a title=&#34;Dreyfus Model Of Skills Acquisition&#34; href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/cynthiajoffrion/dreyfus-model-of-skills-acquisition&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dreyfus Model Of Skills Acquisition&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/cynthiajoffrion&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;cynthia joffrion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The big takeaway is that any time you are building a new skill, it helps to block everything else out and use a set of context-free rules to hone the skill....or in other words, follow a recipe!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Did you notice that experts fall back on rules, recipes, and analysis when things get too complex too?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice recipes help you separate signal from noise, what&#39;s important from what&#39;s irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the five stages in this model, you&#39;ll notice that at a certain point rules are replaced by patterns, then by decisions and intuition. As skills become ingrained, we subconsciously integrate more information than could possibly be explained and reduced to binary rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practice Recipes in Standing Qigong&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To apply this model to our standing practice, we need to adopt a novice mindset every time we practice a new way of standing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start out by asking yourself, &#34;if I want to build this skill, what rules should I follow?&#34; Practicing this way will give you &lt;strong&gt;focus and freedom&lt;/strong&gt;: you won&#39;t worry about a million different things and you&#39;ll be able to give your energy over to one or two simple tasks.&lt;br /&gt;
So if we return to the initial question and think about recipes, what do you notice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is it better to structure your practice to stay with one energy gate, such as the crown, until you feel some dissolving happening there, or should you just keep moving through the gates week by week moving onto another gate?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;This question is equivalent to saying, &#34;I like my bread a little crispier and browner, I think I&#39;m going to leave it in the over for a few more minutes.&#34; The recipe says 25 minutes, but you&#39;re making a choice to leave it in for 30. And that&#39;s fine!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;The person who asked this question is right on the edge of following the recipe to the letter and exploring, improvising and practicing &#34;to taste.&#34; I&#39;ve worked with a lot of people who don&#39;t play this edge enough. Either they lock themselves rigidly into a form or always go by feel. I don&#39;t think either of those is a good choice.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instead, you should run through the recipe many times, to really understand the steps and start to see the potential for variation&lt;/strong&gt;, like &#34;I could stay at this gate longer and feel more going on.&#34; Then, when you&#39;ve found a place to go deeper, break away from the recipe and really explore.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;In this case, any of gate, if it&#39;s a really productive area for you, could be a 2-week, 3-week, or month-long project.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;In the &lt;a title=&#34;Energy Gates Dissolving Series&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;Standing Dissolving Series&lt;/a&gt;, I&#39;m giving you weekly recipes to follow and taking you through a whole process, which you could also look at as one 6-month-long recipe to follow.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My recommendation in this case is to follow the recipe until you feel confident and comfortable without it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 style=&#34;margin-bottom: 5px;&#34;&gt;Deeply Ingrained Recipes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Re-read the second question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m basically aiming to keep my attention on each section of my body as I go down until I feel it has gone sung and has the sense that&#39;s its as relaxed as I&#39;m capable of - as well as the sensation that it has filled with qi (like the sponge analogy). Then I try to feel the leading edge of that fullness until it seeps down to the next section. Does this sound like I&#39;m sinking or dissolving? Or am I somewhere in between perhaps?&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In addition to being a great description of &lt;a title=&#34;Sinking Your Mind through Your Body&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/03/sinking-your-mind-through-your-body/&#34;&gt;sinking chi&lt;/a&gt;, I want you to notice that it&#39;s also an interesting blend of a clearly structured recipe, but also something that&#39;s done completely by feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get to this stage with a particular skill, where you&#39;re feeling your way through it in a consistent pattern instead of thinking it through like a list of instructions, you&#39;re ready to layer new skills on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this case, instead of following the leading edge and the seeping sensation, you tune in more to the energy &#34;behind&#34; the area that&#39;s releasing, without leaving that area. Hanging out here, with a listening attitude, sensing what unfolds next, will lead you into dissolving.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/standing-qigong-question/&#34;&gt;Do you have a Standing Qigong practice question? Ask me here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dissolving, Breathing, Structure, and Stillness: Follow-Up Q&amp;A</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/23/dissolving-breathing-structure-and-stillness-follow-up-qa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 08:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/23/dissolving-breathing-structure-and-stillness-follow-up-qa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34; id=&#34;docs-internal-guid-38f4178b-bf43-c313-f159-173b20fcce07&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-4992&#34; alt=&#34;Stillness of a Mountain Lake&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2014/01/iStock_000013351742Small-300x170.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;170&#34; /&gt;Thanks to everyone who reached out with questions about the first standing audio practice in the Energy Gates Dissolving series.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I want to share some of the questions with you here. Please let me know if you have any follow-up questions or comments or think there is anything the needs clarification. Hopefully we can approach this series together as an ongoing learning process!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#39;s the Difference between Outer Dissolving, Downward Dissolving, and Sinking?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This first question is a clarification about 3 different types of standing practices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;She asks,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;So we are getting acquainted with the the gates in this series in the context of downward dissolving, not outer dissolving.  Is that correct?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I also have a question about the progression of the standing practice.  Just for the sake of having the big picture, it would be useful to understand when to transition one&#39; practice from each stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;From sinking to downward dissolving&lt;br /&gt;
From downward dissolving to awareness of energy gates&lt;br /&gt;
From awareness to energy gates to outer dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Is this the correct sequence and what are the markers that you are ready to move into the next phase?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I like the way she lays out the stages, around sinking, awareness, and dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Technically, dissolving a general area and working on a specific gate are both methods of outer dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;As far as deciding which to know or knowing where you are at, these stages of practice are cyclical. You&#39;ll get to a point on any given day or go through periods of practice where one way of standing may call to you more than another.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;In this series, I&#39;m going to be emphasizing awareness of the gates with the hope that it turns into dissolving the gates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;In my experience there is a tendency to try to force the dissolving process to happen based on the concept, so I try to encourage people to discover the process more naturally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If you rest your mind in one area of the body and hold that area in your awareness with the intent to let go (paradox!), then naturally the energy that&#39;s binding it will begin to release. The release goes through phases with &#34;ice&#34;, &#34;water&#34; and &#34;gas&#34; being good landmarks for recognizing and talking about those phases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Does the Weight Fall through the Feet?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Here&#39;s an alignment question that gets a little confusing when you compare the standing we&#39;re doing to other practices where we play with varying the pressure in the feet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The only question I have is regarding letting the weight fall to the center of the feet (rather than the heel).  I understand how this is appropriate for the dissolving part of this standing.  But since, in Dragon and Tiger, Vol.2, pg. 24, Bruce talks about the Shi mian point causing energy to descend down the body, I was wondering if the weight should be more on the heel during the latter part of this standing when we do more of the sinking chi than the dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This is an interesting case where we look at several layers of the body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Yes, it&#39;s true that shifting ball to heel helps get energy going up and down. In this case, though, we&#39;re working on a slightly different set of structural alignments, where we want the OVERALL feeling of weight falling through the structure of the pelvis, legs, and feet to be the primary goal. Eventually, these two different techniques are layered on top of each other, even though they seem to be at odds right now - that&#39;s a common qigong experience!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Should I Breath during Standing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I received several questions about breathing - natural breathing, reverse breathing, breathing connected to energy flows, etc. To this list I would also add any techniques like lengthening, pulsing, twisting - generally anything you would do along pathways, with soft tissues, or joints.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The short answer is: at this point in the process, don&#39;t focus on any of that stuff!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If we break it down a little more, you will want to go through all of these techniques, and more. But here&#39;s the thing: there&#39;s a tradeoff between a specific focus, like your breath, and the overall container that you create by &#34;holding&#34; the posture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;It&#39;s always felt like two different volume knobs. If you turn up the volume on your breathing, at a certain point, you&#39;ll drown out your sensitivity to other things. On the other hand, if you get just the right volume on the breath, you&#39;ll find a harmony with the mind and your feel for the whole posture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;When you do practice a specific neigong element like breathing or lengthening or pulsing, work it for a few minutes, then stop. And feel. And see if what you&#39;ve set up is primed to go on its own and, with minimal effort, integrate with the whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Techniques for Closing the Practice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Another student asked about methods for closing the practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;You referred to &#39;gathering&#39; . Can you describe that? Is that just maintaining the form at the end of a practice session and feeling the energy?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
At the end of your practice session, especially if you&#39;ve done a &#34;form&#34; like a downward scan, you want to reserve at least a minute or two (sometimes 5 or 10) to just let the inside of your body and your energy go quiet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;There are specific techniques for storing chi in the lower tantien, and we&#39;ll get to those later, but at the very least, you want to create a layer of quiet between the activity of your practice and whatever you go about doing once you finish the practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The best part of adding this buffer in at the end: &lt;strong&gt;you begin to recognize stillness at other times during the &#34;active&#34; phase of your standing session.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the key to really good dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your Questions and Next Steps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Hopefully you found these questions helpful. Was there anything else you were wondering about during your standing practice?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If so, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/standing-qigong-question/&#34;&gt;drop me a line here&lt;/a&gt; and I do my best to answer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If you missed this first workout on the Crown of the Head and want to get started with the standing series, you can &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/AEcQ&#34;&gt;download it directly here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Ready for the next audio? &lt;a href=&#34;https://gumroad.com/l/YSOn&#34;&gt;Download it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Also, &lt;a title=&#34;Energy Gates Dissolving Series&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/energy-gates-dissolving-series/&#34;&gt;check back with this page&lt;/a&gt; where I will be adding a new workout each week. I recommend you do them in order if you decide to take on the dissolving process as part of your practice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 09:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-2355 alignleft&#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2011/10/basic-standing-posture.jpg&#34; width=&#34;159&#34; height=&#34;337&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you set out to develop your internal energy using standing postures, there are two main ways you can go about it: &lt;strong&gt;by feel or by form&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there will be a lot of overlap in these two broad approaches, like aligning your body with gravity without collapsing internally and progressively releasing and relaxing as you stand, but when it comes to the role of the mind, form and feel can be very different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Feeling Approach&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You stand &#34;by feel&#34; for a few different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a good period of feeling, taking stock, and getting comfortable is useful almost any time you do your standing practice. Because our initial orientation in standing is inward, and we&#39;re likely coming to it from a lot of outward-facing activity, taking 3, 5, or even 10 minutes to just stand and feel creates a nice buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve settled in to your practice, then any &#34;form&#34; work you do for the remainder of the standing session will be much more productive: you&#39;ll be quieter, more relaxed, and more tuned-in to your internal environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In fact, I recommend that you get to a comfortable baseline of just being able to settle, relax, and feel your body in a standing posture for 20 minutes before you move on to the form phase.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason to take the feeling approach is to fully appreciate the effects of your posture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;The posture pictured above is a neutral posture, also referred to as Wu Chi. As soon as you raise the arms or change the stance, the effect of the body position will begin to shape what you feel, physically and energetically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you pick a different posture, you automatically start doing a different form. You don&#39;t need to do anything special with the mind. Just feeling the new effects of a specific posture, compared to your Wu Chi baseline, can be enough to keep you occupied through much longer (2-hour!) standing sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, by taking the feeling approach, you can build your connection to the ground. As you stand, &lt;a title=&#34;3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;ask yourself these 3 questions&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Over time, you will become more rooted, relaxed, and connected&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moving into Standing Forms&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Once you have a solid baseline of feeling the body, you can begin to work on the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, most people are familiar with Tai Chi Forms or choreographed sequences in other martial arts, but what do we mean when we use the word &#34;form&#34; in this context?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t think of &#34;form&#34; as movements, but instead think of it as a procedure, then it starts to make more sense. And the value of having a procedure, or a repeatable process, is that you can begin to see how you&#39;re changing over time by performing it, both because you can use it as reference point and because doing it actually changes you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In standing, the form is going to be what you do with your awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here I want to warn you:&lt;/strong&gt; just like someone who follows the rote choreography of the Tai Chi form with no regard for softness, relaxation, and connection will be really stiff and awkward, if you follow the mind-forms without regard for the qualities you develop in the feeling approach, you will be stiff and awkward in your standing. You will just be going through a rigid mental checklist and the impact you will have on your energy and physical body will be limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you can introduce a pattern of progressively sinking the mind through the body, while you maintain relaxation, connection, and root, all of the qualities you began to develop in the feeling approach will be amplified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Your First Form: Downward Flow&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In Opening the Energy Gates of Your Body, Bruce Frantzis teaches a standing qigong sequence that is designed to clear stagnant chi out of your energetic system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic process is a standing &#34;form&#34; where you begin at the crown of the head and move your mind downward through the body each time you practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the first level, an Energy Gates practice session is structured like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In (using the feeling method described above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downward Scan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stillness, Settling Again, or Storing Chi&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The more you practice Energy Gates, the more you will refine the Downward Scan piece. &lt;strong&gt;Specifically, you will go through stages of feeling your body to feeling your energy to sinking your energy and finally to dissolving your energy. &lt;/strong&gt;Bruce discusses each of these stages in depth &lt;a title=&#34;Opening the Energy Gates by Bruce Frantzis is The Most Important Qigong Book To Have in Your Library&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/10/31/opening-the-energy-gates-by-bruce-frantzis-is-the-most-important-qigong-book-to-have-in-your-library/&#34;&gt;in the Energy Gates book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At each stage of this process, though, the form is the same. You start at the top and work your way down. Every time you go through the body this way, no matter at what layer, you are strengthening the downward current of energy, which has a powerful restorative effect over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often joke that the downward flow of chi in your body plays the same role as the downward flow of water in the plumbing system of your house. Not enough downward flow is a problem there, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Energy Gates Over Six Months&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When you read the book or hear someone explain the Energy Gates process, it&#39;s easy to picture a whole bunch of dots all over the body that light up as you do your scan. In fact, learning to feel the gates themselves is a natural extension of just being able to feel the denser tissues of the body directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to tune the mind to a slightly different frequency, but all the time spent standing and feeling pays off here: you&#39;ve trained your mind to stay in one spot for extended periods without jumping around and without tensing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you set out to do a complete pass through all the gates, it roughly breaks down into a six-month project. There are 23 main places you&#39;ll want to work with and you could work with one per week (you can definitely spend longer on each gate, but this is just the basic formula). Here is the list from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.energyarts.com/energy-gates-qigong&#34;&gt;the Energy Arts resource page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bai hui, or the crown of the head.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third eye, the eyes, the center of the ears and the temple. Also the four jaw points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where the tongue touches the roof of the mouth and the throat notch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The base of the skull and in between each of the cervical (neck) vertebrae down to the seventh cervical vertebra at the base of the neck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From where the tongue touches the roof of your mouth to the end of the breastbone, on a line about the width of your mouth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The four points of the shoulder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The elbows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The wrists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hands (all the points).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The joints where the ribs connect to the sternum, the spaces between the ribs, the joints where the ribs connect to the spine, the area between the shoulder blades and the spine. For women only: the gates of the breasts (directly behind the nipples).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The solar plexus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The whole of the belly, starting from the front and dissolving through the internal organs back to the spine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tantien and the mingmen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the points along the spine, from the occiput to the tailbone, paying special attention to the occiput, the seventh cervical vertebra, the vertebra in the center of the shoulder blades, the one at the base of the shoulder blades, mingmen and the tailbone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hip sockets, the pelvic bones, and the kwa (that is, the area inside the front crest of the hip bones).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The anus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The genitals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The perineum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The knees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ankles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The feet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Below the floor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Above the head.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, when you start working through the gates, the structure of your practice session will change from what we laid out earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in week 1, it could look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Crown of the Head - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Body - 3 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But week 11 would look something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Settle In  - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel from the Crown of the Head down to the Solar Plexus - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel the Solar Plexus - 8 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scan Down through the Rest of the Body - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storing Chi - 2 minutes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In other words, you should spend a substantial amount of time on whatever gate is the &#34;gate of the week.&#34; However, your practice session should always start with settling, finish with gathering, and have an easy flow down to the &#34;gate of the week&#34; and then from the &#34;gate of the week&#34; down into the ground after the main focus time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll notice that as you go through the process of the gates, your standing time can go from 15-20 minutes during the first few weeks up to 45-60 minutes towards the end of the process. If you can only manage 15-20 minutes and slowly adding more feels like too much of a strain, I recommend that you stick with the feeling method and not worry about the gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Is it Very Taoist?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here you might start to wonder about whether some of these guidelines for the form seem too rigid. How do you reconcile these recommendations with what you feel when you stand free-form?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And by the way, I&#39;m not saying that &#34;feeling&#34; is kindergarten and &#34;form&#34; is more advanced. In fact, you should cycle between periods of each as you practice over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guidelines and form serve a purpose. You need to work through the structure to develop certain things. Eventually, will you have a more intuitive feel for what you need and how much? Of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, though, Flannery O&#39;Connor captured the issue well, when she argued for a classical education: &#34;And if the student finds that this is not to his taste? Well, that is regrettable. Most regrettable. His taste should not be consulted; it is being formed.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However counter-intuitive it seems at first, the best feeling, the most relaxation, and the greatest internal stillness that I&#39;ve ever uncovered has come from the practice periods when I&#39;ve given over to a form to follow. Later on, I can bask in that energy and &#34;just feel&#34; and enjoy it, but to get there, it was a lot of little small, formal steps along the practice road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wherever you find yourself on the standing path now, I hope this helps orient you a little more. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outer Dissolving and The Role of the Mind in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/30/outer-dissolving-and-the-role-of-the-mind-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 10:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/30/outer-dissolving-and-the-role-of-the-mind-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Next month, we&#39;ll be starting a new Energy Gates course at &lt;a title=&#34;Brookline Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://brooklinetaichi.org&#34;&gt;Brookline Tai Chi&lt;/a&gt;, focused on Outer Dissolving and working through the Gates of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you work on dissolving the gates, you will inevitably be fighting the urge to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;visualize instead of feel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#34;chase&#34; energetic releases, untethered from the physical body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wonder if you are really feeling anything at all&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In this episode of Qigong Radio, I&#39;ll give my recommendations for avoiding these pitfalls and for &lt;strong&gt;setting up the conditions for actual energetic resolution&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ll indulge me, I&#39;ll even share one of my favorite passages from Moby Dick and tell you why I think it&#39;s a perfect description of standing qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[powerpress]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can also subscribe to Qigong Radio via:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://feeds.feedburner.com/QigongRadioWithDanKleiman&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/qigong-radio-with-dan-kleiman/id513000469&#34;&gt;iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Itch to Move Your Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 08:48:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We tend to think about our energy level like the money we have in the bank. You wake up in the morning, look in your energetic wallet and say, &#34;I&#39;ve got a lot of energy today&#34; or &#34;Man, I need 7 cups of coffee.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, to put it another way, thanks to this New Yorker cartoon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.condenaststore.com/-sp/If-we-re-all-just-energy-then-why-don-t-I-have-any-New-Yorker-Cartoon-Prints_i8481061_.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;aligncenter  wp-image-4975&#34; alt=&#34;If we&#39;re all just energy, then why don&#39;t I have any?&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/12/Screen-Shot-2013-12-20-at-8.14.34-AM.png&#34; width=&#34;577&#34; height=&#34;445&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In qigong, we think about &#34;having energy&#34; a little bit differently. Often, it&#39;s not just how much or how little, but &lt;strong&gt;how well is your energy circulating?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good energetic circulation gives you a feeling of &#34;more,&#34; while stagnant or stuck energy feels draining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is such a different concept than most of us have, I&#39;ve often wondered about where these two ideas came from and where these two ways of seeing the world split. In this post, I&#39;m not going to give you a deeply researched exploration of the origins of the Taoist understanding of the world. I&#39;ll let &lt;a title=&#34;Straight Lines, Circles, and Spheres&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/04/11/straight-lines-circles-and-spheres/&#34;&gt;our practices&lt;/a&gt; stand as of evidence of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I want to share with you some of the writings of 20th century Western philosopher Hans Jonas. He wrote about the phenomenology of life and in his descriptions of biological processes, we get a really interesting connection to what many qigong practitioners come to realize: &lt;strong&gt;we have a fundamental need to circulate chi.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;The Phenomenon of Life&lt;/span&gt;, Jonas is trying to reconcile the simplest forms of life with higher thought and our human experience of the mind. He tries to place them on a continuum and asks which one is for the sake of the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whatever the answer, one aspect of the ascending scale is that in its stages the &#34;mirroring&#34; of the world becomes ever more distinct and self-rewarding, beginning with the most obscure sensation somewhere on the lowest rungs of animality, even with the most elementary stimulation of organic irritability as such, in which somehow already otherness, world, and object are germinally &#34;experienced,&#34; that is, made subjective, and responded to (p.3).&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My personal theory on the origins of qigong is that those early Taoists went exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They sat or stood in postures and listened, both inside themselves and to the natural world. &lt;strong&gt;As they got quieter and more perceptive, the heard the echoes of Jonas&#39; &#34;most obscure sensation.&#34;&lt;/strong&gt; The irritability that Jonas describes set them up against the world outside and framed their inner worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That irritability is the same itch you feel when you know you need to get your chi moving, circulating through you and passing back and forth between you, the natural world around you and the other people you interact with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things are flowing, in and out, up and down, towards and away, we feel good: &lt;strong&gt;connected to something outside ourselves but at the same time internally unified and integrated.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like eating, breathing, and sleeping, circulating energy is a natural cycle that we can refine, enhance, and enjoy, but we need to pay attention to it on an ongoing, continuous basis to be healthy and feel whole.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates in Vancouver, BC, Spring 2014</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 17:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;size-full wp-image-4518 &#34; alt=&#34;Standing Qigong &#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2013/03/20130326-094857.jpg&#34; width=&#34;360&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt; Dan standing in New Mexico, not Vancouver (yet!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you live in or near Vancouver?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you willing to travel to refine your Energy Gates practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the behest of a few eager Vancouver locals, I wanted to reach out and see if any of our Northwest-oriented readers would be interested in a spring 2014 Energy Gates seminar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Date and exact location haven&#39;t been nailed down yet, but if there&#39;s enough demand, I would love to come out and do some Energy Gates with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/rz6mzho0i8y4y5/&#34;&gt;Already excited? Sign up here so we can explore it more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Energy Gates Seminar Topics&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are so many great Energy Gates subjects related to &lt;a title=&#34;3 Essential Questions to Ask Yourself During Standing Qigong&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/02/3-essential-questions-to-ask-yourself-during-standing-qigong/&#34;&gt;Standing Qigong&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;Case Study: Energy Gates Tune-Up&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/12/21/case-study-energy-gates-tune-up/&#34;&gt;Cloud Hands&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&#34;The Challenge of the Three Swings&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/11/16/the-challenge-of-the-three-swings/&#34;&gt;The Swings&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a title=&#34;Spinal Qigong Exercises&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/spinal-qigong-exercises/&#34;&gt;The Spine Stretch&lt;/a&gt;, but I&#39;d like to take the approach of &lt;strong&gt;answering the burning questions that always come up when you start working on Standing, Sinking and Dissolving,&lt;/strong&gt; like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a lot of tension around my low back (or knees), how do I adapt the posture so it&#39;s not painful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should I use the actual gates in my practice or focus on general sinking and dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is quite a struggle to constantly remind myself to slow down. How do I slow my mind down without causing mental tension?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#39;m starting to feel chi when I stand. What do I do with it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can&#39;t feel chi when I stand. What do I do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I integrate standing, breathing, sinking, and dissolving?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I sink the chi of one part of my body, does it go all the way down to the ground?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get too tense when I try to maintain my alignments as I stand. What should I do&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#39;m experiencing shaking, sweating, heat or other weird bodily sensations. Is that normal?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you want to get live, personal feedback and soak up all the good chi of intensive group practice, then come stand with us in Vancouver next year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill out the form below and I will in touch directly with you about the details. If we can get a big enough group together, we&#39;ll make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again to the folks who initiated this conversation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wufoo-rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#34;&gt;Fill out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://dankleiman.wufoo.com/forms/rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#34;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
var rz6mzho0i8y4y5;(function(d, t) { var s = d.createElement(t), options = { &#39;userName&#39;:&#39;dankleiman&#39;,  &#39;formHash&#39;:&#39;rz6mzho0i8y4y5&#39;,  &#39;autoResize&#39;:true, &#39;height&#39;:&#39;403&#39;, &#39;async&#39;:true, &#39;host&#39;:&#39;wufoo.com&#39;, &#39;header&#39;:&#39;show&#39;,  &#39;ssl&#39;:true}; s.src = (&#39;https:&#39; == d.location.protocol ? &#39;https://&#39; : &#39;http://&#39;) + &#39;wufoo.com/scripts/embed/form.js&#39;; s.onload = s.onreadystatechange = function() { var rs = this.readyState; if (rs) if (rs != &#39;complete&#39;) if (rs != &#39;loaded&#39;) return; try { rz6mzho0i8y4y5 = new WufooForm();rz6mzho0i8y4y5.initialize(options);rz6mzho0i8y4y5.display(); } catch (e) {}}; var scr = d.getElementsByTagName(t)[0], par = scr.parentNode; par.insertBefore(s, scr); })(document, &#39;script&#39;);&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Yin and Yang of Problem Solving</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/08/the-yin-and-yang-of-problem-solving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 09:46:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/08/the-yin-and-yang-of-problem-solving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-full wp-image-3831&#34; alt=&#34;following instructions&#34; src=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/uploads/2012/04/following-instructions.jpg&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; height=&#34;181&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;You know how you can be banging your head against a wall, trying to figure something out?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you sleep on it, take a shower, or go for a walk and suddenly a solution pops into your head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why this happens or how it works? So have I...and I don&#39;t know HOW it works, but I do know that we are practicing the exact same skill in qigong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s look at how it works in qigong, why you might be missing it, and how you can begin to recognize some of the same signs in other areas of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;20 Repetitions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
People often ask why we do qigong sets in certain numbers. Whenever I&#39;ve heard Bruce Frantzis answer that question, he tells a story about these elaborate experiments they run in the Taoist monasteries, over generations, with control groups and varying repetitions, to see what the optimal number of repetitions for each exercise is. I always feel bad for the monks who spent their lives doing a few too many of each exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think there&#39;s another reason to do somewhere around 20 reps of each exercises (in a typical qigong set). I tried to explain &lt;a title=&#34;Repetition as Rhythm: Why Do 20 Reps?&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2011/04/28/repetition-as-rhythm-why-do-20-reps/&#34;&gt;how each group of reps feels to me in this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this context, what I want you to start to look for is the moment when, after a certain number of repetitionss, you cross a threshold where internal rhythms can take over. Your directed, intentional mind can flip from &#34;doing&#34; to &#34;following.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In those moments when the solution to your problem finally dawns on you, don&#39;t you feel the same way? Your mind is open and the solution comes in. You&#39;re not bearing down on the problem with intention (and tension) the same way when you were trying to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tension and Relaxation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now, if these really are parallel processes, some interesting connections emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like you need a balance of doing and not doing, of tension and relaxation, or, as we&#39;ve been trained to think in qigong, yin and yang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For problem solving, most people focus on the yang moment of structure and intention, the active phase of &#34;working to solve the problem.&#34; Then, when we figure it out in the shower, &#34;out of nowhere,&#34; we beat ourselves up for not seeing it, or think we&#39;re stupid because now the solution is so obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But qigong teaches us that the yang phase is necessary to set up the yin phase. You have the prime the process actively before you can relax into the passive phase where a solution can emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often have you approached a problem with the intention to solve it, then equally valued and created the space, time, and distance to let the yin phase of problem solving happen? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we trained to let this happen the same way we train dissolving and sense our bodies, energies, and minds in qigong? &lt;em&gt;I know I could personally use more of this kind of practice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some more ideas on problem solving and letting solutions come to you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The True Value of Your Qigong Practice&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/07/30/the-true-value-of-your-qigong-practice/&#34;&gt;Tony Schwartz on Ennobling Rest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Neutralizing Stressful Interactions with Tai Chi Push Hands&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/10/08/neutralizing-stressful-interactions-with-tai-chi-push-hands/&#34;&gt;Pushing Hands to find a Third Solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Transforming Conflict with Tai Chi&#34; href=&#34;http://dankleiman.com/2012/09/24/transforming-conflict-with-tai-chi/&#34;&gt;Honing Your Tai Chi Listening Skills in Everyday Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>