<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>qigong on Dan Kleiman</title>
    <link>http://dankleiman.com/tags/qigong/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in qigong on Dan Kleiman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="/tags/qigong/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathing Techniques: Am I Doing it Right?</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/06/breathing-techniques-am-i-doing-it-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 11:52:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/06/breathing-techniques-am-i-doing-it-right/</guid>
      <description>I recently received this breathing question and I thought it was worth sharing with everyone here as a post. (Don&#39;t forget, you can send me your practice questions!)
I&#39;m really confused! I took a Yang Style Tai Chi course and at the end of the class we would do Qigong. He said &#34;We will do diaphragmatic breathing. As you breath in draw the navel into the spine, as you exhale release and let the belly relax but don&#39;t collapse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Returning to an Old, Familiar Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 09:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/05/02/returning-to-an-old-familiar-practice/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s easy to get caught in a linear, progress-oriented way of thinking about your practice.
What&#39;s new? What can I learn next? Am I improving...all the time.
You get so caught up in doing it right and refining every little detail that you can lose sight of the what&#39;s really great about practice in the first place...the restoration, integration, and feeling of wholeness you can walk away with each time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 Update</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 09:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/25/immersion-week-2014-update/</guid>
      <description>Here&#39;s a quick update on what we&#39;ve been working on during Immersion Week 2014.

I&#39;m very impressed (and I say so in the video about 15 times!) with the way this group has patiently explored many different facets of the Swings and Spine Stretch without rushing ahead to try to fit seemingly contradictory pieces together conceptually.
Instead, they&#39;re doing a great job experiencing/exploring each different component on its own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaxing Your Feet to Find Your Root</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/10/relaxing-your-feet-to-find-your-root/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 08:44:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/04/10/relaxing-your-feet-to-find-your-root/</guid>
      <description>When you settle into your practice each day, you should always give yourself a couple of minutes to just feel and see where your body, your energy, and your awareness are.
In one sense, each practice session is about bringing the rhythms of each of those into harmony.
That&#39;s why Tai Chi and qigong can be so powerfully restorative.
So, if you take a couple of minutes to just &#34;settle in,&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embrace the Cold to Feel Your Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/07/embrace-the-cold-to-feel-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 08:48:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/03/07/embrace-the-cold-to-feel-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s been such a cold winter in the Northeastern US this year, that even Niagara Falls has frozen over. Every night, students come in to class shivering, that is, once they&#39;ve resolved to venture out in the cold and the dark. And many haven&#39;t even been up for that.
Today I want to tell you about an important practice lesson you can learn from all this cold. You will develop a better feel for the chi of your etheric body and stay warmer in the process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immersion Week 2014 and the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance Book</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2014 16:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/27/immersion-week-2014-and-the-tai-chi-way-to-better-balance-book/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m very excited to share some news about two big projects with you today: Brookline Tai Chi&#39;s annual Immersion Week and the publication of the Tai Chi Way to Better Balance as a physical book.

Join me from Tuesday, April 22 - Friday, April 25 at Brookline Tai Chi in Boston for Energy Gates Moving Qigong Exercises. Times, cost, and registration details in the link.
The Tai Chi Way to Better Balance is now available for purchase on Amazon, but you can also get your copy of the physical book directly from the publisher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When to Follow a Practice Recipe and When to Reflect on Your Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 09:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/19/when-to-follow-a-practice-recipe-and-when-to-reflect-on-your-practice/</guid>
      <description>In this video, we&#39;re talking about building up the skill of Outer Dissolving in your standing qigong practice.
When you start out, it pays to follow a recipe - a set of instructions that lead through a certain procedure physically, energetically, and with your mind. However, there are times you want to break away from the recipe and times you&#39;ll want to reflect on your experience verbally -- but there are good and bad ways to do both.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice, Stress, and Building Outward Connections</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 11:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/02/06/practice-stress-and-building-outward-connections/</guid>
      <description>&#34;At some point, don&#39;t we have to ask ourselves, &#34;Aren&#39;t I healthy enough?&#34; Don&#39;t I need to work on &#34;waking up&#34;, on manifesting kindness and patience, and being other oriented?&#34;
That&#39;s from a conversation we&#39;ve been having in the Inner Form discussion group and it got me thinking.
You might be learning to cultivate your chi to heal old injuries or for the inner experience of meditative exploration, but at some point, shouldn&#39;t your practice extend into the world around you, to the people in your life, and your work?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Recipe for Rewarding Practice</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/30/the-recipe-for-rewarding-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 09:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/30/the-recipe-for-rewarding-practice/</guid>
      <description>&#34;Is it better to structure your practice to stay with one energy gate, such as the crown, until you feel some dissolving happening there, or should you just keep moving through the gates week by week moving onto another gate?&#34;
Excellent questions like this one keep pouring in. Thank you for sharing your practice experiences with me. I know other folks who read the blog really appreciate it too.
I love hearing from you guys, especially when your questions are grounded in exploration, practice and thoughtful reflection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dissolving, Breathing, Structure, and Stillness: Follow-Up Q&amp;A</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/23/dissolving-breathing-structure-and-stillness-follow-up-qa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 08:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/23/dissolving-breathing-structure-and-stillness-follow-up-qa/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to everyone who reached out with questions about the first standing audio practice in the Energy Gates Dissolving series.
I want to share some of the questions with you here. Please let me know if you have any follow-up questions or comments or think there is anything the needs clarification. Hopefully we can approach this series together as an ongoing learning process!
What&#39;s the Difference between Outer Dissolving, Downward Dissolving, and Sinking?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Form Versus Feel in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2014 09:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2014/01/09/form-versus-feel-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>When you set out to develop your internal energy using standing postures, there are two main ways you can go about it: by feel or by form.
Now, there will be a lot of overlap in these two broad approaches, like aligning your body with gravity without collapsing internally and progressively releasing and relaxing as you stand, but when it comes to the role of the mind, form and feel can be very different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outer Dissolving and The Role of the Mind in Standing Qigong</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/30/outer-dissolving-and-the-role-of-the-mind-in-standing-qigong/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 10:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/30/outer-dissolving-and-the-role-of-the-mind-in-standing-qigong/</guid>
      <description>Next month, we&#39;ll be starting a new Energy Gates course at Brookline Tai Chi, focused on Outer Dissolving and working through the Gates of the body.
When you work on dissolving the gates, you will inevitably be fighting the urge to:
 visualize instead of feel &#34;chase&#34; energetic releases, untethered from the physical body wonder if you are really feeling anything at all

In this episode of Qigong Radio, I&#39;ll give my recommendations for avoiding these pitfalls and for setting up the conditions for actual energetic resolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Itch to Move Your Chi</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2013 08:48:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/20/the-itch-to-move-your-chi/</guid>
      <description>We tend to think about our energy level like the money we have in the bank. You wake up in the morning, look in your energetic wallet and say, &#34;I&#39;ve got a lot of energy today&#34; or &#34;Man, I need 7 cups of coffee.&#34;
Or, to put it another way, thanks to this New Yorker cartoon:

In qigong, we think about &#34;having energy&#34; a little bit differently. Often, it&#39;s not just how much or how little, but how well is your energy circulating?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Gates in Vancouver, BC, Spring 2014</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 17:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/12/12/energy-gates-in-vancouver-bc-spring-2014/</guid>
      <description>Dan standing in New Mexico, not Vancouver (yet!).
Do you live in or near Vancouver?
Are you willing to travel to refine your Energy Gates practice?
At the behest of a few eager Vancouver locals, I wanted to reach out and see if any of our Northwest-oriented readers would be interested in a spring 2014 Energy Gates seminar.
Date and exact location haven&#39;t been nailed down yet, but if there&#39;s enough demand, I would love to come out and do some Energy Gates with you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Yin and Yang of Problem Solving</title>
      <link>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/08/the-yin-and-yang-of-problem-solving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 09:46:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://dankleiman.com/2013/11/08/the-yin-and-yang-of-problem-solving/</guid>
      <description>You know how you can be banging your head against a wall, trying to figure something out?
Then, you sleep on it, take a shower, or go for a walk and suddenly a solution pops into your head.
Have you ever wondered why this happens or how it works? So have I...and I don&#39;t know HOW it works, but I do know that we are practicing the exact same skill in qigong.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>